Genesis

2 Thus the heavens and the earth and all their army came to their completion. 2 And by the seventh day God came to the completion of his work that he had made, and he proceeded to rest on the seventh day from all his work that he had made. 3 And God proceeded to bless the seventh day and make it sacred, because on it he has been resting from all his work that God has created for the purpose of making.

4 This is a history of the heavens and the earth in the time of their being created, in the day that Jehovah God made earth and heaven.

5 Now there was as yet no bush of the field found in the earth and no vegetation of the field was as yet sprouting, because Jehovah God had not made it rain upon the earth and there was no man to cultivate the ground. 6 But a mist would go up from the earth and it watered the entire surface of the ground.

7 And Jehovah God proceeded to form the man out of dust from the ground and to blow into his nostrils the breath of life, and the man came to be a living soul. 8 Further, Jehovah God planted a garden in E′den, toward the east, and there he put the man whom he had formed. 9 Thus Jehovah God made to grow out of the ground every tree desirable to one’s sight and good for food and also the tree of life in the middle of the garden and the tree of the knowledge of good and bad.

10 Now there was a river issuing out of E′den to water the garden, and from there it began to be parted and it became, as it were, four heads. 11 The first one’s name is Pi′shon; it is the one encircling the entire land of Hav′i·lah, where there is gold. 12 And the gold of that land is good. There also are the bdellium gum and the onyx stone. 13 And the name of the second river is Gi′hon; it is the one encircling the entire land of Cush. 14 And the name of the third river is Hid′de·kel; it is the one going to the east of As·syr′i·a. And the fourth river is the Eu·phra′tes.

15 And Jehovah God proceeded to take the man and settle him in the garden of E′den to cultivate it and to take care of it. 16 And Jehovah God also laid this command upon the man: “From every tree of the garden you may eat to satisfaction. 17 But as for the tree of the knowledge of good and bad you must not eat from it, for in the day you eat from it you will positively die.”

18 And Jehovah God went on to say: “It is not good for the man to continue by himself. I am going to make a helper for him, as a complement of him.” 19 Now Jehovah God was forming from the ground every wild beast of the field and every flying creature of the heavens, and he began bringing them to the man to see what he would call each one; and whatever the man would call it, each living soul, that was its name. 20 So the man was calling the names of all the domestic animals and of the flying creatures of the heavens and of every wild beast of the field, but for man there was found no helper as a complement of him. 21 Hence Jehovah God had a deep sleep fall upon the man and, while he was sleeping, he took one of his ribs and then closed up the flesh over its place. 22 And Jehovah God proceeded to build the rib that he had taken from the man into a woman and to bring her to the man.

23 Then the man said:

“This is at last bone of my bones

And flesh of my flesh.

This one will be called Woman,

Because from man this one was taken.”

24 That is why a man will leave his father and his mother and he must stick to his wife and they must become one flesh. 25 And both of them continued to be naked, the man and his wife, and yet they did not become ashamed.

Genesis

10 And this is the history of Noah’s sons, Shem, Ham and Ja′pheth.

Now sons began to be born to them after the deluge. 2 The sons of Ja′pheth were Go′mer and Ma′gog and Ma′da·i and Ja′van and Tu′bal and Me′shech and Ti′ras.

3 And the sons of Go′mer were Ash′ke·naz and Ri′phath and To·gar′mah.

4 And the sons of Ja′van were E·li′shah and Tar′shish, Kit′tim and Do′da·nim.

5 From these the population of the isles of the nations was spread about in their lands, each according to its tongue, according to their families, by their nations.

6 And the sons of Ham were Cush and Miz′ra·im and Put and Ca′naan.

7 And the sons of Cush were Se′ba and Hav′i·lah and Sab′tah and Ra′a·mah and Sab′te·ca.

And the sons of Ra′a·mah were She′ba and De′dan.

8 And Cush became father to Nim′rod. He made the start in becoming a mighty one in the earth. 9 He displayed himself a mighty hunter in opposition to Jehovah. That is why there is a saying: “Just like Nim′rod a mighty hunter in opposition to Jehovah.” 10 And the beginning of his kingdom came to be Ba′bel and E′rech and Ac′cad and Cal′neh, in the land of Shi′nar. 11 Out of that land he went forth into As·syr′i·a and set himself to building Nin′e·veh and Re·ho′both-Ir and Ca′lah 12 and Re′sen between Nin′e·veh and Ca′lah: this is the great city.

13 And Miz′ra·im became father to Lu′dim and An′a·mim and Le·ha′bim and Naph·tu′him 14 and Path·ru′sim and Cas·lu′him (from among whom the Phi·lis′tines went forth) and Caph′to·rim.

15 And Ca′naan became father to Si′don his firstborn and Heth 16 and the Jeb′u·site and the Am′or·ite and the Gir′ga·shite 17 and the Hi′vite and the Ark′ite and the Si′nite 18 and the Ar′vad·ite and the Zem′a·rite and the Ha′math·ite; and afterward the families of the Ca′naan·ite were scattered. 19 So the boundary of the Ca′naan·ite came to be from Si′don as far as Ge′rar, near Ga′za, as far as Sod′om and Go·mor′rah and Ad′mah and Ze·boi′im, near La′sha. 20 These were the sons of Ham according to their families, according to their tongues, in their lands, by their nations.

21 And to Shem, the forefather of all the sons of E′ber, the brother of Ja′pheth the oldest, there was also progeny born. 22 The sons of Shem were E′lam and As′shur and Ar·pach′shad and Lud and A′ram.

23 And the sons of A′ram were Uz and Hul and Ge′ther and Mash.

24 And Ar·pach′shad became father to She′lah, and She′lah became father to E′ber.

25 And to E′ber there were two sons born. The name of the one was Pe′leg, because in his days the earth was divided; and the name of his brother was Jok′tan.

26 And Jok′tan became father to Al·mo′dad and She′leph and Ha·zar·ma′veth and Je′rah 27 and Ha·do′ram and U′zal and Dik′lah 28 and O′bal and A·bim′a·el and She′ba 29 and O′phir and Hav′i·lah and Jo′bab; all these were the sons of Jok′tan.

30 And their place of dwelling came to extend from Me′sha as far as Se′phar, the mountainous region of the East.

31 These were the sons of Shem according to their families, according to their tongues, in their lands, according to their nations.

32 These were the families of the sons of Noah according to their family descents, by their nations, and from these the nations were spread about in the earth after the deluge.

Genesis

11 Now all the earth continued to be of one language and of one set of words. 2 And it came about that in their journeying eastward they eventually discovered a valley plain in the land of Shi′nar, and they took up dwelling there. 3 And they began to say, each one to the other: “Come on! Let us make bricks and bake them with a burning process.” So brick served as stone for them, but bitumen served as mortar for them. 4 They now said: “Come on! Let us build ourselves a city and also a tower with its top in the heavens, and let us make a celebrated name for ourselves, for fear we may be scattered over all the surface of the earth.”

5 And Jehovah proceeded to go down to see the city and the tower that the sons of men had built. 6 After that Jehovah said: “Look! They are one people and there is one language for them all, and this is what they start to do. Why, now there is nothing that they may have in mind to do that will be unattainable for them. 7 Come now! Let us go down and there confuse their language that they may not listen to one another’s language.” 8 Accordingly Jehovah scattered them from there over all the surface of the earth, and they gradually left off building the city. 9 That is why its name was called Ba′bel, because there Jehovah had confused the language of all the earth, and Jehovah had scattered them from there over all the surface of the earth.

10 This is the history of Shem.

Shem was a hundred years old when he became father to Ar·pach′shad two years after the deluge. 11 And after his fathering Ar·pach′shad Shem continued to live five hundred years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters.

12 And Ar·pach′shad lived thirty-five years. Then he became father to She′lah. 13 And after his fathering She′lah Ar·pach′shad continued to live four hundred and three years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters.

14 And She′lah lived thirty years. Then he became father to E′ber. 15 And after his fathering E′ber She′lah continued to live four hundred and three years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters.

16 And E′ber lived on for thirty-four years. Then he became father to Pe′leg. 17 And after his fathering Pe′leg E′ber continued to live four hundred and thirty years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters.

18 And Pe′leg lived on for thirty years. Then he became father to Re′u. 19 And after his fathering Re′u Pe′leg continued to live two hundred and nine years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters.

20 And Re′u lived on for thirty-two years. Then he became father to Se′rug. 21 And after his fathering Se′rug Re′u continued to live two hundred and seven years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters.

22 And Se′rug lived on for thirty years. Then he became father to Na′hor. 23 And after his fathering Na′hor Se′rug continued to live two hundred years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters.

24 And Na′hor lived on for twenty-nine years. Then he became father to Te′rah. 25 And after his fathering Te′rah Na′hor continued to live a hundred and nineteen years. Meanwhile he became father to sons and daughters.

26 And Te′rah lived on for seventy years, after which he became father to A′bram, Na′hor and Ha′ran.

27 And this is the history of Te′rah.

Te′rah became father to A′bram, Na′hor and Ha′ran; and Ha′ran became father to Lot. 28 Later Ha′ran died while in company with Te′rah his father in the land of his birth, in Ur of the Chal·de′ans. 29 And A′bram and Na′hor proceeded to take wives for themselves. The name of A′bram’s wife was Sar′ai, while the name of Na′hor’s wife was Mil′cah, the daughter of Ha′ran, the father of Mil′cah and father of Is′cah. 30 But Sar′ai continued to be barren; she had no child.

31 After that Te′rah took A′bram his son and Lot, the son of Ha′ran, his grandson, and Sar′ai his daughter-in-law, the wife of A′bram his son, and they went with him out of Ur of the Chal·de′ans to go to the land of Ca′naan. In time they came to Ha′ran and took up dwelling there. 32 And the days of Te′rah came to be two hundred and five years. Then Te′rah died in Ha′ran.

Genesis

13 Following that A′bram went up out of Egypt, he and his wife and all that he had, and Lot with him, to the Neg′eb. 2 And A′bram was heavily stocked with herds and silver and gold. 3 And he made his way from encampment to encampment out of the Neg′eb and to Beth′el, to the place where his tent had been at first between Beth′el and A′i, 4 to the place of the altar that he had made there originally; and A′bram proceeded to call there on the name of Jehovah.

5 Now Lot, who was going along with A′bram, also owned sheep and cattle and tents. 6 So the land did not allow for them to dwell all together, because their goods had become many and they were not able to dwell all together. 7 And a quarrel arose between the herders of A′bram’s livestock and the herders of Lot’s livestock; and at that time the Ca′naan·ite and the Per′iz·zite were dwelling in the land. 8 Hence A′bram said to Lot: “Please, do not let any quarreling continue between me and you and between my herdsmen and your herdsmen, for we men are brothers. 9 Is not the whole land available to you? Please, separate from me. If you go to the left, then I will go to the right; but if you go to the right, then I will go to the left.” 10 So Lot raised his eyes and saw the whole District of the Jordan, that all of it was a well-watered region before Jehovah brought Sod′om and Go·mor′rah to ruin, like the garden of Jehovah, like the land of Egypt as far as Zo′ar. 11 Then Lot chose for himself the whole District of the Jordan, and Lot moved his camp to the east. So they separated the one from the other. 12 A′bram dwelt in the land of Ca′naan, but Lot dwelt among the cities of the District. Finally he pitched tent near Sod′om. 13 And the men of Sod′om were bad and were gross sinners against Jehovah.

14 And Jehovah said to A′bram after Lot had separated from him: “Raise your eyes, please, and look from the place where you are, northward and southward and eastward and westward, 15 because all the land at which you are looking, to you and to your seed I am going to give it until time indefinite. 16 And I will constitute your seed like the dust particles of the earth, so that, if a man could be able to count the dust particles of the earth, then your seed could be numbered. 17 Get up, go about in the land through its length and through its breadth, because to you I am going to give it.” 18 So A′bram continued to live in tents. Later on he came and dwelt among the big trees of Mam′re, which are in He′bron; and there he proceeded to build an altar to Jehovah.

Genesis

16 Now Sar′ai, A′bram’s wife, had borne him no children; but she had an Egyptian maidservant and her name was Ha′gar. 2 Hence Sar′ai said to A′bram: “Please now! Jehovah has shut me off from bearing children. Please, have relations with my maidservant. Perhaps I may get children from her.” So A′bram listened to the voice of Sar′ai. 3 Then Sar′ai, A′bram’s wife, took Ha′gar, her Egyptian maidservant, at the end of ten years of A′bram’s dwelling in the land of Ca′naan, and gave her to A′bram her husband as his wife. 4 Accordingly he had relations with Ha′gar, and she became pregnant. When she became aware that she was pregnant, then her mistress began to be despised in her eyes.

5 At this Sar′ai said to A′bram: “The violence done me be upon you. I myself gave my maidservant over to your bosom, and she became aware that she was pregnant, and I began to be despised in her eyes. May Jehovah judge between me and you.” 6 So A′bram said to Sar′ai: “Look! Your maidservant is at your disposal. Do to her what is good in your eyes.” Then Sar′ai began to humiliate her so that she ran away from her.

7 Later Jehovah’s angel found her at a fountain of waters in the wilderness, at the fountain on the way to Shur. 8 And he began to say: “Ha′gar, maidservant of Sar′ai, just where have you come from and where are you going?” To this she said: “Why, from Sar′ai my mistress I am running away.” 9 And Jehovah’s angel went on to say to her: “Return to your mistress and humble yourself under her hand.” 10 Then Jehovah’s angel said to her: “I shall greatly multiply your seed, so that it will not be numbered for multitude.” 11 Further Jehovah’s angel added to her: “Here you are pregnant, and you shall give birth to a son and must call his name Ish′ma·el; for Jehovah has heard your affliction. 12 As for him, he will become a zebra of a man. His hand will be against everyone, and the hand of everyone will be against him; and before the face of all his brothers he will tabernacle.”

13 Then she began to call the name of Jehovah, who was speaking to her: “You are a God of sight,” for she said: “Have I here actually looked upon him who sees me?” 14 That is why the well was called Be′er-la′hai-roi. Here it is between Ka′desh and Be′red. 15 Later on Ha′gar bore to A′bram a son and A′bram called the name of his son whom Ha′gar bore Ish′ma·el. 16 And A′bram was eighty-six years old at Ha′gar’s bearing Ish′ma·el to A′bram.

Genesis

18 Afterward Jehovah appeared to him among the big trees of Mam′re, while he was sitting at the entrance of the tent about the heat of the day. 2 When he raised his eyes, then he looked and there three men were standing some distance from him. When he caught sight of them he began running to meet them from the entrance of the tent and proceeded to bow down to the earth. 3 Then he said: “Jehovah, if, now, I have found favor in your eyes, please do not pass by your servant. 4 Let a little water be taken, please, and YOU must have YOUR feet washed. Then recline under the tree. 5 And let me get a piece of bread, and refresh YOUR hearts. Following that, YOU can pass on, because that is why YOU have passed this way to YOUR servant.” At this they said: “All right. You may do just as you have spoken.”

6 So Abraham went hurrying to the tent to Sarah and said: “Hurry! Get three seah measures of fine flour, knead the dough and make round cakes.” 7 Next Abraham ran to the herd and proceeded to get a tender and good young bull and to give it to the attendant, and he went hurrying to get it ready. 8 He then took butter and milk and the young bull that he had got ready and set it before them. Then he himself kept standing by them under the tree as they were eating.

9 They now said to him: “Where is Sarah your wife?” To this he said: “Here in the tent!” 10 So he continued: “I am surely going to return to you next year at this time, and, look! Sarah your wife will have a son.” Now Sarah was listening at the tent entrance, and it was behind the man. 11 And Abraham and Sarah were old, being advanced in years. Sarah had stopped having menstruation. 12 Hence Sarah began to laugh inside herself, saying: “After I am worn out, shall I really have pleasure, my lord being old besides?” 13 Then Jehovah said to Abraham: “Why was it that Sarah laughed, saying, ‘Shall I really and truly give birth although I have become old?’ 14 Is anything too extraordinary for Jehovah? At the appointed time I shall return to you, next year at this time, and Sarah will have a son.” 15 But Sarah began to deny it, saying: “I did not laugh!” For she was afraid. At this he said: “No! but you did laugh.”

16 Later the men got up from there and looked down toward Sod′om, and Abraham was walking with them to escort them. 17 And Jehovah said: “Am I keeping covered from Abraham what I am doing? 18 Why, Abraham is surely going to become a nation great and mighty, and all the nations of the earth must bless themselves by means of him. 19 For I have become acquainted with him in order that he may command his sons and his household after him so that they shall keep Jehovah’s way to do righteousness and judgment; in order that Jehovah may certainly bring upon Abraham what he has spoken about him.”

20 Consequently Jehovah said: “The cry of complaint about Sod′om and Go·mor′rah, yes, it is loud, and their sin, yes, it is very heavy. 21 I am quite determined to go down that I may see whether they act altogether according to the outcry over it that has come to me, and, if not, I can get to know it.”

22 At this point the men turned from there and got on their way to Sod′om; but as for Jehovah, he was still standing before Abraham. 23 Then Abraham approached and began to say: “Will you really sweep away the righteous with the wicked? 24 Suppose there are fifty righteous men in the midst of the city. Will you, then, sweep them away and not pardon the place for the sake of the fifty righteous who are inside it? 25 It is unthinkable of you that you are acting in this manner to put to death the righteous man with the wicked one so that it has to occur with the righteous man as it does with the wicked! It is unthinkable of you. Is the Judge of all the earth not going to do what is right?” 26 Then Jehovah said: “If I shall find in Sod′om fifty righteous men in the midst of the city I will pardon the whole place on their account.” 27 But Abraham went on to answer and say: “Please, here I have taken upon myself to speak to Jehovah, whereas I am dust and ashes. 28 Suppose the fifty righteous should be lacking five. Will you for the five bring the whole city to ruin?” To this he said: “I shall not bring it to ruin if I find there forty-five.”

29 But yet again he spoke further to him and said: “Suppose forty are found there.” In turn he said: “I shall not do it on account of the forty.” 30 But he continued: “May Jehovah, please, not grow hot with anger, but let me go on speaking: Suppose thirty are found there.” In turn he said: “I shall not do it if I find thirty there.” 31 But he continued on: “Please, here I have taken upon myself to speak to Jehovah: Suppose twenty are found there.” In turn he said: “I shall not bring it to ruin on account of the twenty.” 32 Finally he said: “May Jehovah, please, not grow hot with anger, but let me speak just this once: Suppose ten are found there.” In turn he said: “I shall not bring it to ruin on account of the ten.” 33 Then Jehovah went his way when he had finished speaking to Abraham, and Abraham returned to his place.

Genesis

19 Now the two angels arrived at Sod′om by evening, and Lot was sitting in the gate of Sod′om. When Lot caught sight of them, then he got up to meet them and bowed down with his face to the earth. 2 And he proceeded to say: “Please, now, my lords, turn aside, please, into the house of YOUR servant and stay overnight and have YOUR feet washed. Then YOU must get up early and travel on YOUR way.” To this they said: “No, but in the public square is where we shall stay overnight.” 3 But he was very insistent with them, so that they turned aside to him and came into his house. Then he made a feast for them, and he baked unfermented cakes, and they went to eating.

4 Before they could lie down, the men of the city, the men of Sod′om, surrounded the house, from boy to old man, all the people in one mob. 5 And they kept calling out to Lot and saying to him: “Where are the men who came in to you tonight? Bring them out to us that we may have intercourse with them.”

6 Finally Lot went out to them to the entrance, but he shut the door behind him. 7 Then he said: “Please, my brothers, do not act badly. 8 Please, here I have two daughters who have never had intercourse with a man. Please, let me bring them out to YOU. Then do to them as is good in YOUR eyes. Only to these men do not do a thing, because that is why they have come under the shadow of my roof.” 9 At this they said: “Stand back there!” And they added: “This lone man came here to reside as an alien and yet he would actually play the judge. Now we are going to do worse to you than to them.” And they came pressing heavily in on the man, on Lot, and were getting near to break in the door. 10 So the men thrust out their hands and brought Lot in to them, into the house, and they shut the door. 11 But they struck with blindness the men who were at the entrance of the house, from the least to the greatest, so that they were wearing themselves out trying to find the entrance.

12 Then the men said to Lot: “Do you have anyone else here? Son-in-law and your sons and your daughters and all who are yours in the city, bring out of the place! 13 For we are bringing this place to ruin, because the outcry against them has grown loud before Jehovah, so that Jehovah sent us to bring the city to ruin.” 14 Hence Lot went on out and began to speak to his sons-in-law who were to take his daughters, and he kept on saying: “Get up! Get out of this place, because Jehovah is bringing the city to ruin!” But in the eyes of his sons-in-law he seemed like a man who was joking.

15 However, when the dawn ascended, then the angels became urgent with Lot, saying: “Get up! Take your wife and your two daughters who are found here, for fear you may be swept away in the error of the city!” 16 When he kept lingering, then in the compassion of Jehovah upon him, the men seized hold of his hand and of the hand of his wife and of the hands of his two daughters and they proceeded to bring him out and to station him outside the city. 17 And it came about that, as soon as they had brought them forth to the outskirts, he began to say: “Escape for your soul! Do not look behind you and do not stand still in all the District! Escape to the mountainous region for fear you may be swept away!”

18 Then Lot said to them: “Not that, please, Jehovah! 19 Please, now, your servant has found favor in your eyes so that you are magnifying your loving-kindness, which you have exercised with me to preserve my soul alive, but I—I am not able to escape to the mountainous region for fear calamity may keep close to me and I certainly die. 20 Please, now, this city is nearby to flee there and it is a small thing. May I, please, escape there—is it not a small thing?—and my soul will live on.” 21 So he said to him: “Here I do show you consideration to this extent also, by my not overthrowing the city of which you have spoken. 22 Hurry! Escape there, because I am not able to do a thing until your arriving there!” That is why he called the name of the city Zo′ar.

23 The sun had gone forth over the land when Lot arrived at Zo′ar. 24 Then Jehovah made it rain sulphur and fire from Jehovah, from the heavens, upon Sod′om and upon Go·mor′rah. 25 So he went ahead overthrowing these cities, even the entire District and all the inhabitants of the cities and the plants of the ground. 26 And his wife began to look around from behind him, and she became a pillar of salt.

27 Now Abraham made his way early in the morning to the place where he had stood before Jehovah. 28 Then he looked down toward Sod′om and Go·mor′rah and toward all the land of the District and saw a sight. Why, here thick smoke ascended from the land like the thick smoke of a kiln! 29 And it came about that when God brought the cities of the District to ruin God kept Abraham in mind in that he took steps to send Lot out of the midst of the overthrow when overthrowing the cities among which Lot had been dwelling.

30 Later Lot went up from Zo′ar and began dwelling in the mountainous region, and his two daughters along with him, because he got afraid of dwelling in Zo′ar. So he began dwelling in a cave, he and his two daughters. 31 And the firstborn proceeded to say to the younger woman: “Our father is old and there is not a man in the land to have relations with us according to the way of the whole earth. 32 Come, let us give our father wine to drink and let us lie down with him and preserve offspring from our father.”

33 So they kept giving their father wine to drink during that night; then the firstborn went in and lay down with her father, but he did not know when she lay down and when she got up. 34 And it came about on the next day that the firstborn then said to the younger: “Here I lay down with my father last night. Let us give him wine to drink tonight also. Then you go in, lie down with him, and let us preserve offspring from our father.” 35 So they repeatedly gave their father wine to drink during that night also; then the younger got up and lay down with him, but he did not know when she lay down and when she got up. 36 And both the daughters of Lot became pregnant from their father. 37 In time the firstborn became mother to a son and called his name Mo′ab. He is the father of Mo′ab, to this day. 38 As for the younger, she too gave birth to a son and then called his name Ben-am′mi. He is the father of the sons of Am′mon, to this day.

Genesis

23 And Sarah’s life got to be a hundred and twenty-seven years long. They were the years of Sarah’s life. 2 So Sarah died in Kir′i·ath-ar′ba, that is to say, He′bron, in the land of Ca′naan, and Abraham came in to bewail Sarah and to weep over her. 3 Then Abraham got up from before his dead and proceeded to speak to the sons of Heth, saying: 4 “An alien resident and settler I am among YOU. Give me the possession of a burial place among YOU that I may bury my dead out of my sight.” 5 At this the sons of Heth answered Abraham, saying to him: 6 “Hear us, my lord. A chieftain of God you are in the midst of us. In the choicest of our burial places bury your dead. None of us will hold back his burial place from you to prevent burying your dead.”

7 Thereupon Abraham got up and bowed down to the natives, to the sons of Heth, 8 and spoke with them, saying: “If YOUR souls agree to bury my dead out of my sight, listen to me and urge E′phron the son of Zo′har for me, 9 that he may give me the cave of Mach·pe′lah, which is his, which is at the extremity of his field. For the full amount of silver let him give it to me in the midst of YOU for the possession of a burial place.”

10 As it was, E′phron was sitting among the sons of Heth. So E′phron the Hit′tite answered Abraham in the hearing of the sons of Heth with all those entering the gate of his city, saying: 11 “No, my lord! Listen to me. The field I do give to you, and the cave that is in it to you I do give it. Before the eyes of the sons of my people I do give it to you. Bury your dead.” 12 At that Abraham bowed down before the natives 13 and spoke to E′phron in the hearing of the natives, saying: “Only if you—no, listen to me! I will give you the amount of silver for the field. Take it from me, that I may bury my dead there.”

14 Then E′phron answered Abraham, saying to him: 15 “My lord, listen to me. A land plot worth four hundred silver shekels, what is that between me and you? So bury your dead.” 16 Accordingly Abraham listened to E′phron, and Abraham weighed out to E′phron the amount of silver that he had spoken in the hearing of the sons of Heth, four hundred silver shekels current with the merchants. 17 Thus the field of E′phron that was in Mach·pe′lah, which is in front of Mam′re, the field and the cave that was in it and all the trees that were in the field, which were within all its boundaries round about, became confirmed 18 to Abraham as his purchased property before the eyes of the sons of Heth among all those entering the gate of his city. 19 And after that Abraham buried Sarah his wife in the cave of the field of Mach·pe′lah in front of Mam′re, that is to say, He′bron, in the land of Ca′naan. 20 Thus the field and the cave that was in it became confirmed to Abraham for the possession of a burial place at the hands of the sons of Heth.

Genesis

24 Now Abraham was old, advanced in years; and Jehovah had blessed Abraham in everything. 2 Hence Abraham said to his servant, the oldest one of his household, who was managing all he had: “Put your hand, please, under my thigh, 3 as I must have you swear by Jehovah, the God of the heavens and the God of the earth, that you will not take a wife for my son from the daughters of the Ca′naan·ites in among whom I am dwelling, 4 but you will go to my country and to my relatives, and you will certainly take a wife for my son, for Isaac.”

5 However, the servant said to him: “What if the woman does not wish to come with me to this land? Must I be sure to return your son to the land from where you went out?” 6 At this Abraham said to him: “Be on your guard that you do not return my son there. 7 Jehovah the God of the heavens, who took me from my father’s house and from the land of my relatives and who spoke to me and who swore to me, saying, ‘To your seed I am going to give this land,’ he will send his angel ahead of you, and you will certainly take a wife for my son from there. 8 But if the woman should not wish to come with you, you also will have become free from this oath you gave me. Only you must not return my son there.” 9 With that the servant put his hand under the thigh of Abraham his master and swore to him concerning this matter.

10 So the servant took ten camels from the camels of his master and proceeded to go with every sort of good thing of his master’s in his hand. Then he rose and got on his way to Mes·o·po·ta′mi·a to the city of Na′hor. 11 Eventually he had the camels kneel down outside the city at a well of water about evening time, about the time that the women who draw water were accustomed to go out. 12 And he went on to say: “Jehovah the God of my master Abraham, cause it to happen, please, before me this day and perform loving-kindness with my master Abraham. 13 Here I am stationed at a fountain of water, and the daughters of the men of the city are coming out to draw water. 14 What must occur is that the young woman to whom I shall say, ‘Let your water jar down, please, that I may take a drink,’ and who will indeed say, ‘Take a drink, and I shall also water your camels,’ this is the one you must assign to your servant, to Isaac; and by this let me know that you have performed loyal love with my master.”

15 Well, it came about that before he had finished speaking, why, here coming out was Re·bek′ah, who had been born to Be·thu′el the son of Mil′cah the wife of Na′hor, Abraham’s brother, and her water jar was upon her shoulder. 16 Now the young woman was very attractive in appearance, a virgin, and no man had had sexual intercourse with her; and she made her way down to the fountain and began to fill her water jar and then came up. 17 At once the servant ran to meet her and said: “Give me, please, a little sip of water from your jar.” 18 In turn she said: “Drink, my lord.” With that she quickly lowered her jar upon her hand and gave him a drink. 19 When she was finished giving him a drink, then she said: “For your camels too I shall draw water until they are done drinking.” 20 So she quickly emptied her jar into the drinking trough and ran yet again and again to the well to draw water, and kept drawing for all his camels. 21 All the while the man was gazing at her in wonder, keeping silent to know whether Jehovah had made his trip successful or not.

22 Consequently it came about that, when the camels had finished drinking, then the man took a gold nose ring of a half shekel in weight and two bracelets for her hands, ten shekels of gold was their weight, 23 and he went on to say: “Whose daughter are you? Tell me, please. Is there any room at the house of your father for us to spend the night?” 24 At that she said to him: “I am the daughter of Be·thu′el the son of Mil′cah, whom she bore to Na′hor.” 25 And she said further to him: “There is both straw and much fodder with us, also a place to spend the night.” 26 And the man proceeded to bow down and prostrate himself before Jehovah 27 and say: “Blessed be Jehovah the God of my master Abraham, who has not left his loving-kindness and his trustworthiness toward my master. I being on the way, Jehovah has led me to the house of the brothers of my master.”

28 And the young woman went running and telling the household of her mother about these things. 29 Now Re·bek′ah had a brother and his name was La′ban. So La′ban went running to the man who was outside at the fountain. 30 And it came about that on seeing the nose ring and the bracelets on the hands of his sister and on hearing the words of Re·bek′ah his sister, saying: “This is the way the man spoke to me,” then he came to the man and there he was, standing by the camels at the fountain. 31 At once he said: “Come, you blessed one of Jehovah. Why do you keep standing out here, when I myself have made the house ready and room for the camels?” 32 With that the man came on into the house, and he went unharnessing the camels and giving straw and fodder to the camels and water to wash his feet and the feet of the men who were with him. 33 Then something to eat was set before him, but he said: “I shall not eat until I have spoken about my matters.” Hence he said: “Speak!”

34 Then he went on to say: “I am Abraham’s servant. 35 And Jehovah has blessed my master very much in that he goes on making him greater and giving him sheep and cattle and silver and gold and menservants and maidservants and camels and asses. 36 Further, Sarah the wife of my master bore a son to my master after her growing old; and he will give him everything he has. 37 So my master made me swear, saying, ‘You must not take a wife for my son from the daughters of the Ca′naan·ites in whose land I am dwelling. 38 No, but you will go to the house of my father and to my family and you must take a wife for my son.’ 39 But I said to my master, ‘What if the woman will not come with me?’ 40 Then he said to me, ‘Jehovah, before whom I have walked, will send his angel with you and will certainly give success to your way; and you must take a wife for my son from my family and from the house of my father. 41 At that time you will be cleared of obligation to me by oath when you get to my family, and if they will not give her to you, then you shall become free of obligation to me by oath.’

42 “When I got to the fountain today, then I said, ‘Jehovah the God of my master Abraham, if you are really giving success to my way on which I am going, 43 here I am stationed at a fountain of water. What must occur is that the maiden coming out to draw water to whom I shall actually say: “Please, let me drink a little water from your jar,” 44 and who will indeed say to me: “Both you take a drink, and I shall also draw water for your camels,” she is the woman whom Jehovah has assigned for the son of my master.’

45 “Before I was finished speaking in my heart, why, there was Re·bek′ah coming out, with her jar upon her shoulder; and she made her way down to the fountain and began to draw water. Then I said to her, ‘Give me a drink, please.’ 46 So she quickly lowered her jar from off her and said, ‘Take a drink, and I shall also water your camels.’ Then I took a drink, and she also watered the camels. 47 After that I asked her and said, ‘Whose daughter are you?’ to which she said, ‘The daughter of Be·thu′el the son of Na′hor, whom Mil′cah bore to him.’ Accordingly I put the nose ring on her nostril and the bracelets on her hands. 48 And I proceeded to bow down and prostrate myself before Jehovah and bless Jehovah the God of my master Abraham, who had led me in the true way to take the daughter of the brother of my master for his son. 49 And now if YOU are actually exercising loving-kindness and trustworthiness toward my master, tell me; but if not, tell me, that I may turn to the right hand or to the left.”

50 Then La′ban and Be·thu′el answered and said: “From Jehovah this thing has issued. We are unable to speak bad or good to you. 51 Here is Re·bek′ah before you. Take her and go, and let her become a wife to the son of your master, just as Jehovah has spoken.” 52 And it came about that when Abraham’s servant had heard their words, he at once prostrated himself on the earth before Jehovah. 53 And the servant began to bring out articles of silver and articles of gold and garments and to give them to Re·bek′ah; and he gave choice things to her brother and to her mother. 54 After that they ate and drank, he and the men who were with him, and they spent the night there and got up in the morning.

Then he said: “SEND me off to my master.” 55 To this her brother and her mother said: “Let the young woman stay with us at least ten days. Afterward she can go.” 56 But he said to them: “Do not detain me, seeing that Jehovah has given success to my way. Send me off, that I may go to my master.” 57 So they said: “Let us call the young woman and inquire at her mouth.” 58 Then they called Re·bek′ah and said to her: “Will you go with this man?” In turn she said: “I am willing to go.”

59 At that they sent off Re·bek′ah their sister and her nurse and Abraham’s servant and his men. 60 And they began to bless Re·bek′ah and say to her: “O you, our sister, may you become thousands times ten thousand, and let your seed take possession of the gate of those who hate it.” 61 After that Re·bek′ah and her lady attendants rose and they went riding on the camels and following the man; and the servant took Re·bek′ah and got on his way.

62 Now Isaac had come from the way that goes to Be′er-la′hai-roi, for he was dwelling in the land of the Neg′eb. 63 And Isaac was out walking in order to meditate in the field at about the falling of evening. When he raised his eyes and looked, why, there camels were coming! 64 When Re·bek′ah raised her eyes, she caught sight of Isaac and she swung herself down from off the camel. 65 Then she said to the servant: “Who is that man there walking in the field to meet us?” and the servant said: “It is my master.” And she proceeded to take a headcloth and to cover herself. 66 And the servant went relating to Isaac all the things he had done. 67 After that Isaac brought her into the tent of Sarah his mother. Thus he took Re·bek′ah and she became his wife; and he fell in love with her, and Isaac found comfort after the loss of his mother.

Genesis

27 Now it came about that when Isaac was old and his eyes were too dim to see he then called E′sau his older son and said to him: “My son!” at which he said to him: “Here I am!” 2 And he went on to say: “Here, now, I have become old. I do not know the day of my death. 3 So at this time take, please, your implements, your quiver and your bow, and go out to the field and hunt some venison for me. 4 Then make me a tasty dish such as I am fond of and bring it to me and, ah, let me eat, in order that my soul may bless you before I die.”

5 However, Re·bek′ah was listening while Isaac spoke to E′sau his son. And E′sau went on out into the field to hunt game and to bring it in. 6 And Re·bek′ah said to Jacob her son: “Here I just heard your father speaking to E′sau your brother, saying, 7 ‘Bring me some game and make me a tasty dish and, ah, let me eat, that I may bless you before Jehovah before my death.’ 8 And now, my son, listen to my voice in what I am commanding you. 9 Go, please, to the herd and get me from there two kids of the goats, good ones, that I may make them up into a tasty dish for your father such as he is fond of. 10 Then you must bring it to your father and he must eat it, in order that he may bless you before his death.”

11 And Jacob proceeded to say to Re·bek′ah his mother: “But E′sau my brother is a hairy man and I am a smooth man. 12 What if my father feels me? Then I shall certainly become in his eyes like one making a mockery, and I shall certainly bring upon myself a malediction and not a blessing.” 13 At this his mother said to him: “Upon me be the malediction meant for you, my son. Only listen to my voice and go, get them for me.” 14 Accordingly he went and got them and brought them to his mother, and his mother made a tasty dish such as his father was fond of. 15 After that Re·bek′ah took garments of E′sau her older son, the most desirable ones which were with her in the house, and put them on Jacob her younger son. 16 And the skins of the kids of the goats she put upon his hands and upon the hairless part of his neck. 17 Then she gave the tasty dish and the bread that she had made into the hand of Jacob her son.

18 So he went on in to his father and said: “My father!” to which he said: “Here I am! Who are you, my son?” 19 And Jacob went on to say to his father: “I am E′sau your firstborn. I have done just as you have spoken to me. Raise yourself up, please. Sit down and eat some of my game, in order that your soul may bless me.” 20 At that Isaac said to his son: “How is it that you have been so quick in finding it, my son?” In turn he said: “Because Jehovah your God caused it to meet up with me.” 21 Then Isaac said to Jacob: “Come near, please, that I may feel you, my son, to know whether you are really my son E′sau or not.” 22 So Jacob came near to Isaac his father, and he went feeling him, after which he said: “The voice is the voice of Jacob, but the hands are the hands of E′sau.” 23 And he did not recognize him, because his hands proved to be hairy like the hands of E′sau his brother. Hence he blessed him.

24 After that he said: “You are really my son E′sau?” to which he said: “I am.” 25 Then he said: “Bring it near to me that I may eat some of the game of my son, to the end that my soul may bless you.” With that he brought it near to him and he began to eat, and he brought him wine and he began to drink. 26 Then Isaac his father said to him: “Come near, please, and kiss me, my son.” 27 So he came near and kissed him, and he could smell the scent of his garments. And he proceeded to bless him and to say:

“See, the scent of my son is like the scent of the field which Jehovah has blessed. 28 And may the true God give you the dews of the heavens and the fertile soils of the earth and an abundance of grain and new wine. 29 Let peoples serve you and let national groups bow low to you. Become master over your brothers, and let the sons of your mother bow low to you. Cursed be each one of those cursing you, and blessed be each one of those blessing you.”

30 Now it came about as soon as Isaac had finished blessing Jacob, yes, it indeed came about when Jacob had barely come out from before the face of Isaac his father, that E′sau his brother came back from his hunting. 31 And he too went about making a tasty dish. Then he brought it to his father and said to his father: “Let my father get up and eat some of his son’s game, in order that your soul may bless me.” 32 At this Isaac his father said to him: “Who are you?” to which he said: “I am your son, your firstborn, E′sau.” 33 And Isaac began to shake with a great trembling in extreme measure, and so he said: “Who, then, was it that hunted for game and came bringing it to me, so that I ate of everything before you could come in and I blessed him? Blessed too he will become!”

34 On hearing his father’s words E′sau began to cry out in an extremely loud and bitter manner and to say to his father: “Bless me, even me too, my father!” 35 But he went on to say: “Your brother came with deception that he might get the blessing meant for you.” 36 At this he said: “Is that not why his name is called Jacob, in that he should supplant me these two times? My birthright he has already taken, and here at this time he has taken my blessing!” Then he added: “Have you not reserved a blessing for me?” 37 But in answer to E′sau Isaac continued: “Here I have appointed him master over you, and all his brothers I have given to him as servants, and grain and new wine I have bestowed for his support, and where is there anything I can do for you, my son?”

38 Then E′sau said to his father: “Is there just one blessing that you have, my father? Bless me, even me too, my father!” With that E′sau raised his voice and burst into tears. 39 So in answer Isaac his father said to him:

“Behold, away from the fertile soils of the earth your dwelling will be found, and away from the dew of the heavens above. 40 And by your sword you will live, and your brother you will serve. But it will certainly occur that, when you grow restless, you will indeed break his yoke off your neck.”

41 However, E′sau harbored animosity for Jacob on account of the blessing with which his father had blessed him, and E′sau kept saying in his heart: “The days of the period of mourning for my father are getting closer. After that I am going to kill Jacob my brother.” 42 When the words of E′sau her older son were told to Re·bek′ah, she at once sent and called Jacob her younger son and said to him: “Look! E′sau your brother is comforting himself in regard to you—to kill you. 43 Now, then, my son, listen to my voice and get up, run away to La′ban my brother at Ha′ran. 44 And you must dwell with him for some days until the rage of your brother calms down, 45 until the anger of your brother turns away from you and he has forgotten what you have done to him. And I shall certainly send and get you from there. Why should I be bereaved also of both of YOU in one day?”

46 After that Re·bek′ah kept saying to Isaac: “I have come to abhor this life of mine because of the daughters of Heth. If Jacob ever takes a wife from the daughters of Heth like these from the daughters of the land, of what good is life to me?”

Genesis

29 After that Jacob set his feet in motion and traveled on to the land of the Orientals. 2 Now he looked, and here there was a well in the field and here three droves of sheep were lying down there by it, because from that well they were accustomed to water the droves; and there was a great stone over the mouth of the well. 3 When all the droves had been gathered there, they rolled away the stone from off the mouth of the well, and they watered the flocks, after which they returned the stone over the mouth of the well to its place.

4 So Jacob said to them: “My brothers, from what place are YOU?” to which they said: “We are from Ha′ran.” 5 Then he said to them: “Do YOU know La′ban the grandson of Na′hor?” to which they said: “We know him.” 6 At this he said to them: “Is it all right with him?” In turn they said: “It is all right. And here is Rachel his daughter coming with the sheep!” 7 And he went on to say: “Why, it is yet full day. It is not the time for gathering the herds. WATER the sheep, then go feed them.” 8 To this they said: “We are not allowed to do so until all the droves are gathered and they actually roll away the stone from off the mouth of the well. Then we must water the sheep.”

9 While he was yet speaking with them, Rachel came with the sheep that belonged to her father, for she was a shepherdess. 10 And it came about that when Jacob saw Rachel the daughter of La′ban his mother’s brother and the sheep of La′ban his mother’s brother, Jacob immediately approached and rolled away the stone from off the mouth of the well and watered the sheep of La′ban his mother’s brother. 11 Then Jacob kissed Rachel and raised his voice and burst into tears. 12 And Jacob began to tell Rachel that he was the brother of her father and that he was the son of Re·bek′ah. And she went running and telling her father.

13 Now it came about that as soon as La′ban heard the report about Jacob the son of his sister, he went running to meet him. Then he embraced him and kissed him and brought him on into his house. And he began to relate to La′ban all these things. 14 After that La′ban said to him: “You are indeed my bone and my flesh.” So he dwelt with him a full month.

15 After that La′ban said to Jacob: “Are you my brother, and must you serve me for nothing? Tell me, What are your wages to be?” 16 As it was, La′ban had two daughters. The name of the older was Le′ah and the name of the younger Rachel. 17 But the eyes of Le′ah had no luster, whereas Rachel had become beautiful in form and beautiful of countenance. 18 And Jacob was in love with Rachel. So he said: “I am willing to serve you seven years for Rachel your younger daughter.” 19 To this La′ban said: “It is better for me to give her to you than for me to give her to another man. Keep dwelling with me.” 20 And Jacob proceeded to serve seven years for Rachel, but in his eyes they proved to be like some few days because of his love for her.

21 Then Jacob said to La′ban: “Give over my wife, because my days are up, and let me have relations with her.” 22 With that La′ban gathered all the men of the place and made a feast. 23 But it turned out that during the evening he resorted to taking Le′ah his daughter and bringing her to him that he might have relations with her. 24 Moreover, La′ban gave to her Zil′pah his maidservant, even to Le′ah his daughter, as a maidservant. 25 So it followed in the morning that here it was Le′ah! Consequently he said to La′ban: “What is this you have done to me? Was it not for Rachel that I served with you? So why have you tricked me?” 26 To this La′ban said: “It is not customary to do this way in our place, to give the younger woman before the firstborn. 27 Celebrate to the full the week of this woman. After that there shall be given to you also this other woman for the service that you can serve with me for seven years more.” 28 Accordingly Jacob did so and celebrated fully the week of this woman, after which he gave him Rachel his daughter as his wife. 29 Besides, La′ban gave Bil′hah his maidservant to Rachel his daughter as her maidservant.

30 Then he had relations also with Rachel and also expressed more love for Rachel than for Le′ah, and he went serving with him for yet seven years more. 31 When Jehovah came to see that Le′ah was hated, he then opened her womb, but Rachel was barren. 32 And Le′ah became pregnant and brought a son to birth and then called his name Reu′ben, for she said: “It is because Jehovah has looked upon my wretchedness, in that now my husband will begin to love me.” 33 And she became pregnant again and brought a son to birth and then said: “It is because Jehovah has listened, in that I was hated and so he gave me also this one.” Hence she called his name Sim′e·on. 34 And she became pregnant yet again and brought a son to birth and then said: “Now this time my husband will join himself to me, because I have borne him three sons.” His name was therefore called Le′vi. 35 And she became pregnant once more and brought a son to birth and then said: “This time I shall laud Jehovah.” She therefore called his name Judah. After that she left off giving birth.

Genesis

30 When Rachel came to see that she had borne nothing to Jacob, Rachel got jealous of her sister and began to say to Jacob: “Give me children or otherwise I shall be a dead woman.” 2 At this Jacob’s anger burned against Rachel and he said: “Am I in the place of God, who has held back the fruit of the belly from you?” 3 So she said: “Here is my slave girl Bil′hah. Have relations with her, that she may give birth upon my knees and that I, even I, may get children from her.” 4 With that she gave him Bil′hah her maidservant as wife, and Jacob had relations with her. 5 And Bil′hah became pregnant and in time bore Jacob a son. 6 Then Rachel said: “God has acted as my judge and has also listened to my voice, so that he gave me a son.” That is why she called his name Dan. 7 And Bil′hah, Rachel’s maidservant, became pregnant once more and in time bore a second son to Jacob. 8 Then Rachel said: “With strenuous wrestlings I have wrestled with my sister. I have also come off winner!” So she called his name Naph′ta·li.

9 When Le′ah came to see that she had left off giving birth, she proceeded to take Zil′pah her maidservant and to give her to Jacob as wife. 10 In time Zil′pah, Le′ah’s maidservant, bore a son to Jacob. 11 Then Le′ah said: “With good fortune!” So she called his name Gad. 12 After that Zil′pah, Le′ah’s maidservant, bore a second son to Jacob. 13 Then Le′ah said: “With my happiness! For the daughters will certainly pronounce me happy.” So she called his name Ash′er.

14 Now Reu′ben went walking in the days of the wheat harvest and got to find mandrakes in the field. So he brought them to Le′ah his mother. Then Rachel said to Le′ah: “Give me, please, some of your son’s mandrakes.” 15 At this she said to her: “Is this a little thing, your having taken my husband, with your now taking also my son’s mandrakes?” So Rachel said: “For that reason he is going to lie down with you tonight in exchange for your son’s mandrakes.”

16 When Jacob was coming from the field in the evening, Le′ah went on out to meet him and then said: “It is with me you are going to have relations, because I have hired you outright with my son’s mandrakes.” Accordingly he lay down with her that night. 17 And God heard and answered Le′ah and she became pregnant and in time bore to Jacob a fifth son. 18 Then Le′ah said: “God has given me a hireling’s wages, because I have given my maidservant to my husband.” So she called his name Is′sa·char. 19 And Le′ah became pregnant once more and in time bore a sixth son to Jacob. 20 Then Le′ah said: “God has endowed me, yes, me, with a good endowment. At last my husband will tolerate me, because I have borne him six sons.” So she called his name Zeb′u·lun. 21 And afterward she bore a daughter and then called her name Di′nah.

22 Finally God remembered Rachel, and God heard and answered her in that he opened her womb. 23 And she became pregnant and brought a son to birth. Then she said: “God has taken away my reproach!” 24 So she called his name Joseph, saying: “Jehovah is adding another son to me.”

25 And it followed that when Rachel had given birth to Joseph, Jacob immediately said to La′ban: “Send me away that I may go to my place and to my country. 26 Give over my wives and my children, for whom I have served with you, that I may go; for you yourself must know my service which I have rendered you.” 27 Then La′ban said to him: “If, now, I have found favor in your eyes,—I have taken the omens to the effect that Jehovah is blessing me due to you.” 28 And he added: “Stipulate your wages to me and I shall give them.” 29 So he said to him: “You yourself must know how I have served you and how your herd has fared with me; 30 that it was little that you actually had before my coming, and it went expanding to a multitude, in that Jehovah blessed you since I stepped in. So now when am I to do something also for my own house?”

31 Then he said: “What shall I give you?” And Jacob went on to say: “You will give me nothing whatsoever! If you will do this thing for me, I shall resume shepherding your flock. I shall continue guarding it. 32 I will pass among your whole flock today. You set aside from there every sheep speckled and with color patches, and every dark-brown sheep among the young rams and any color-patched and speckled one among the she-goats. Hereafter such must be my wages. 33 And my right-doing must answer for me on whatever future day you may come to look over my wages; every one that is not speckled and color-patched among the she-goats and dark brown among the young rams is something stolen if it is with me.”

34 To this La′ban said: “Why, that is fine! Let it be according to your word.” 35 Then he set aside on that day the he-goats striped and color-patched and all the she-goats speckled and color-patched, every one in which there was any white and every one dark brown among the young rams, but he gave them over into the hands of his sons. 36 After that he set a distance of three days’ journey between himself and Jacob, and Jacob was shepherding the flocks of La′ban that remained over.

37 Then Jacob took for his use staffs still moist of the storax tree and of the almond tree and of the plane tree and peeled in them white peeled spots by laying bare white places which were upon the staffs. 38 Finally the staffs that he had peeled he placed in front of the flock, in the gutters, in the water drinking troughs, where the flocks would come to drink, that they might get into a heat before them when they came to drink.

39 Consequently the flocks would get in heat before the staffs, and the flocks would produce striped, speckled and color-patched ones. 40 And Jacob separated the young rams and then turned the faces of the flocks to the striped ones and all the dark-brown ones among the flocks of La′ban. Then he set his own droves by themselves and did not set them by the flocks of La′ban. 41 And it always occurred that whenever the robust flocks would get in heat, Jacob would locate the staffs in the gutters before the eyes of the flocks, that they might get in heat by the staffs. 42 But when the flocks showed feebleness he would not locate them there. So the feeble ones always came to be La′ban’s, but the robust ones Jacob’s.

43 And the man went on increasing more and more, and great flocks and maidservants and menservants and camels and asses came to be his.

Genesis

32 And as for Jacob, he got on his way, and the angels of God now met up with him. 2 Immediately Jacob said, when he saw them: “The camp of God this is!” Hence he called the name of that place Ma·ha·na′im.

3 Then Jacob sent messengers ahead of him to E′sau his brother to the land of Se′ir, the field of E′dom, 4 and he commanded them, saying: “This is what YOU will say to my lord, to E′sau, ‘This is what your servant Jacob has said: “With La′ban I have resided as an alien and I have stayed for a long time till now. 5 And I have come to have bulls and asses, sheep, and menservants and maidservants, and I would like to send to notify my lord, that I may find favor in your eyes.”’”

6 In time the messengers returned to Jacob, saying: “We got to your brother E′sau, and he is also on his way to meet you, and four hundred men with him.” 7 And Jacob became very much afraid and grew anxious. So he divided the people who were with him, and the flocks and the cattle and the camels into two camps, 8 and he said: “If E′sau should come to the one camp and assault it, then there is certain to be a camp remaining to make an escape.”

9 After that Jacob said: “O God of my father Abraham and God of my father Isaac, O Jehovah, you who are saying to me, ‘Return to your land and to your relatives and I will deal well with you,’ 10 I am unworthy of all the loving-kindnesses and of all the faithfulness that you have exercised toward your servant, for with but my staff I crossed this Jordan and now I have become two camps. 11 Deliver me, I pray you, from my brother’s hand, from E′sau’s hand, because I am afraid of him that he may come and certainly assault me, mother together with children. 12 And you, you have said, ‘Unquestionably I shall deal well with you and I will constitute your seed like the grains of sand of the sea, which cannot be numbered for multitude.’”

13 And he kept lodging there on that night. And from what came to his hand he proceeded to take a gift for E′sau his brother: 14 two hundred she-goats and twenty he-goats, two hundred female sheep and twenty rams, 15 thirty camels giving suck and their young ones, forty cows and ten bulls, twenty she-asses and ten full-grown asses.

16 Then he handed over to his servants one drove after another by itself and repeatedly said to his servants: “Cross over ahead of me, and YOU are to set an interval between drove and drove.” 17 Further he commanded the first one, saying: “In case that E′sau my brother should meet you and ask you, saying, ‘To whom do you belong, and where are you going and to whom do these ahead of you belong?’ 18 then you must say, ‘To your servant, to Jacob. A gift it is, sent to my lord, to E′sau, and look! he himself is also behind us.’” 19 And he went on to command also the second, also the third, also all those following the droves, saying: “According to this word YOU are to speak to E′sau on YOUR encountering him. 20 And YOU must say also, ‘Here is your servant Jacob behind us.’” For he said to himself: “I may appease him by the gift going ahead of me, and afterward I shall see his face. Perhaps he will give a kindly reception.” 21 So the gift went crossing over ahead of him, but he himself lodged that night in the camp.

22 Later during that night he rose and took his two wives and his two maidservants and his eleven young sons and crossed over the ford of Jab′bok. 23 So he took them and brought them over the torrent valley, and he brought over what he had.

24 Finally Jacob was left by himself. Then a man began to grapple with him until the dawn ascended. 25 When he got to see that he had not prevailed over him, then he touched the socket of his thigh joint; and the socket of Jacob’s thigh joint got out of place during his grappling with him. 26 After that he said: “Let me go, for the dawn has ascended.” To this he said: “I am not going to let you go until you first bless me.” 27 So he said to him: “What is your name?” to which he said: “Jacob.” 28 Then he said: “Your name will no longer be called Jacob but Israel, for you have contended with God and with men so that you at last prevailed.” 29 In turn Jacob inquired and said: “Tell me, please, your name.” However, he said: “Why is it that you inquire for my name?” With that he blessed him there. 30 Hence Jacob called the name of the place Pe·ni′el, because, to quote him, “I have seen God face to face and yet my soul was delivered.”

31 And the sun began to flash upon him as soon as he passed by Pe·nu′el, but he was limping upon his thigh. 32 That is why the sons of Israel are not accustomed to eat the sinew of the thigh nerve, which is on the socket of the thigh joint, down to this day, because he touched the socket of Jacob’s thigh joint by the sinew of the thigh nerve.

Genesis

33 In time Jacob raised his eyes and looked, and here E′sau was coming and with him four hundred men. Consequently he divided off the children to Le′ah and to Rachel and to the two maidservants, 2 and he put the maidservants and their children foremost and Le′ah and her children after them and Rachel and Joseph to the rear of them. 3 And he himself passed on ahead of them and proceeded to bow down to the earth seven times until he got near to his brother.

4 And E′sau went running to meet him, and he began to embrace him and fall upon his neck and kiss him, and they burst into tears. 5 Then he raised his eyes and saw the women and the children and said: “Who are these with you?” to which he said: “The children with whom God has favored your servant.” 6 At that the maidservants came forward, they and their children, and bowed down; 7 and Le′ah too came forward, and her children, and they bowed down, and afterward Joseph came forward, and Rachel, and they bowed down.

8 He now said: “What do you mean by all this camp of travelers that I have met?” To this he said: “In order to find favor in the eyes of my lord.” 9 Then E′sau said: “I have a great many, my brother. Let continue yours what is yours.” 10 However, Jacob said: “No, please. If, now, I have found favor in your eyes, then you must take my gift at my hand, because in harmony with its purpose I have seen your face as though seeing God’s face in that you received me with pleasure. 11 Take, please, the gift conveying my blessing which was brought to you, because God has favored me and because I have everything.” And he continued to urge him, so that he took it.

12 Later on he said: “Let us pull out and go, and let me go in advance of you.” 13 But he said to him: “My lord is aware that the children are delicate and sheep and cattle that are giving suck are in my charge, and should they drive them too quickly for one day, then the whole flock will certainly die. 14 Let my lord, please, pass on ahead of his servant, but may I myself continue the journey at my leisure according to the pace of the livestock that is before me and according to the pace of the children until I shall come to my lord at Se′ir.” 15 Then E′sau said: “Let me, please, put at your disposal some of the people who are with me.” To this he said: “Why this? Let me find favor in the eyes of my lord.” 16 So on that day E′sau turned back on his way to Se′ir.

17 And Jacob pulled out for Suc′coth, and he proceeded to build himself a house and for his herd he made booths. That was why he called the name of the place Suc′coth.

18 In time Jacob came safe and sound to the city of She′chem, which is in the land of Ca′naan, while he was coming from Pad′dan-a′ram; and he pitched camp in front of the city. 19 Then he acquired a tract of the field where he pitched his tent at the hand of the sons of Ha′mor the father of She′chem, for a hundred pieces of money. 20 After that he set up there an altar and called it God the God of Israel.

Genesis

34 Now Di′nah the daughter of Le′ah, whom she had borne to Jacob, used to go out to see the daughters of the land. 2 And She′chem the son of Ha′mor the Hi′vite, a chieftain of the land, got to see her and then took her and lay down with her and violated her. 3 And his soul began clinging to Di′nah the daughter of Jacob, and he fell in love with the young woman and kept speaking persuasively to the young woman. 4 Finally She′chem said to Ha′mor his father: “Get me this young lady as a wife.”

5 And Jacob heard that he had defiled Di′nah his daughter. And his sons happened to be with his herd in the field; and Jacob kept silent until they should come in. 6 Later Ha′mor, She′chem’s father, went out to Jacob to speak with him. 7 And the sons of Jacob came in from the field as soon as they heard of it; and the men became hurt in their feelings and they grew very angry, because he had committed a disgraceful folly against Israel in lying down with Jacob’s daughter, whereas nothing like that ought to be done.

8 And Ha′mor proceeded to speak with them, saying: “As for She′chem my son, his soul is attached to YOUR daughter. Give her, please, to him as a wife, 9 and form marriage alliances with us. YOUR daughters YOU are to give to us, and our daughters YOU are to take for yourselves. 10 And with us YOU may dwell, and the land will become available for YOU. Dwell and carry on business in it and get settled in it.” 11 Then She′chem said to her father and to her brothers: “Let me find favor in YOUR eyes, and whatever YOU will say to me I shall give it. 12 Raise very high the marriage money and gift imposed upon me, and I stand willing to give according to what YOU may say to me; only give me the young woman as a wife.”

13 And Jacob’s sons began to answer She′chem and Ha′mor his father with deceit and to speak so because he had defiled Di′nah their sister. 14 And they went on to say to them: “We cannot possibly do such a thing, to give our sister to a man who has a foreskin, because that is a reproach to us. 15 Only on this condition can we give consent to YOU, that YOU become like us, by every male of YOURS getting circumcised. 16 Then we shall certainly give our daughters to YOU, and YOUR daughters we shall take for ourselves, and we shall certainly dwell with YOU and become one people. 17 But if YOU do not listen to us to get circumcised, then we will take our daughter and go.”

18 And their words seemed good in the eyes of Ha′mor and in the eyes of She′chem, Ha′mor’s son, 19 and the young man did not delay to perform the condition, because he did find delight in Jacob’s daughter and he was the most honorable of the whole house of his father.

20 So Ha′mor and She′chem his son went to the gate of their city and began to speak to the men of their city, saying: 21 “These men are peace-loving toward us. Hence let them dwell in the land and carry on business in it, as the land is quite wide before them. Their daughters we can take as wives for ourselves and our own daughters we can give to them. 22 Only on this condition will the men give us their consent to dwell with us so as to become one people, that every male of ours gets circumcised just the way they are circumcised. 23 Then their possessions and their wealth and all their livestock, will they not be ours? Only let us give them our consent that they may dwell with us.” 24 Then all those going out by the gate of his city listened to Ha′mor and to She′chem his son, and all the males got circumcised, all those going out by the gate of his city.

25 However, it came about that on the third day, when they got to be aching, the two sons of Jacob, Sim′e·on and Le′vi, brothers of Di′nah, proceeded to take each one his sword and to go unsuspectedly to the city and to kill every male. 26 And Ha′mor and She′chem his son they killed with the edge of the sword. Then they took Di′nah from She′chem’s house and went on out. 27 The other sons of Jacob attacked the fatally wounded men and went plundering the city, because they had defiled their sister. 28 Their flocks and their herds and their asses and what was in the city and what was in the field they took. 29 And all their means of maintenance and all their little children and their wives they carried off captive, so that they plundered all that was in the houses.

30 At this Jacob said to Sim′e·on and to Le′vi: “YOU have brought ostracism upon me in making me a stench to the inhabitants of the land, with the Ca′naan·ites and the Per′iz·zites; whereas I am few in number, and they will certainly gather together against me and assault me and I must be annihilated, I and my house.” 31 In turn they said: “Ought anyone to treat our sister like a prostitute?”

Genesis

36 And this is the history of E′sau, that is to say, E′dom.

2 E′sau took his wives from the daughters of Ca′naan: A′dah the daughter of E′lon the Hit′tite and O·hol·i·ba′mah the daughter of A′nah, the granddaughter of Zib′e·on the Hi′vite, 3 and Bas′e·math, Ish′ma·el’s daughter, the sister of Ne·ba′ioth.

4 And A′dah proceeded to bear El′i·phaz to E′sau, and Bas′e·math bore Reu′el,

5 and O·hol·i·ba′mah bore Je′ush and Ja′lam and Ko′rah.

These are the sons of E′sau who were born to him in the land of Ca′naan. 6 After that E′sau took his wives and his sons and his daughters and all the souls of his house and his herd and all his other beasts and all his wealth, which he had accumulated in the land of Ca′naan, and went to a land away from Jacob his brother, 7 because their goods had become too great for them to dwell together and the land of their alien residences was not able to sustain them as a result of their herds. 8 So E′sau took up dwelling in the mountainous region of Se′ir. E′sau is E′dom.

9 And this is the history of E′sau the father of E′dom in the mountainous region of Se′ir.

10 These are the names of the sons of E′sau: El′i·phaz the son of A′dah, E′sau’s wife; Reu′el the son of Bas′e·math, E′sau’s wife.

11 And the sons of El′i·phaz came to be Te′man, O′mar, Ze′pho and Ga′tam and Ke′naz. 12 And Tim′na became the concubine of El′i·phaz, E′sau’s son. In time she bore to El′i·phaz Am′a·lek. These are the sons of A′dah, E′sau’s wife.

13 These are the sons of Reu′el: Na′hath and Ze′rah, Sham′mah and Miz′zah. These came to be the sons of Bas′e·math, E′sau’s wife.

14 And these came to be the sons of O·hol·i·ba′mah the daughter of A′nah, the granddaughter of Zib′e·on, E′sau’s wife, in that she bore to E′sau Je′ush and Ja′lam and Ko′rah.

15 These are the sheiks of the sons of E′sau: The sons of El′i·phaz, E′sau’s firstborn: Sheik Te′man, sheik O′mar, sheik Ze′pho, sheik Ke′naz, 16 sheik Ko′rah, sheik Ga′tam, sheik Am′a·lek. These are the sheiks of El′i·phaz in the land of E′dom. These are the sons by A′dah.

17 These are the sons of Reu′el, E′sau’s son: Sheik Na′hath, sheik Ze′rah, sheik Sham′mah, sheik Miz′zah. These are the sheiks of Reu′el in the land of E′dom. These are the sons by Bas′e·math, E′sau’s wife.

18 Finally these are the sons of O·hol·i·ba′mah, E′sau’s wife: Sheik Je′ush, sheik Ja′lam, sheik Ko′rah. These are the sheiks of O·hol·i·ba′mah the daughter of A′nah, E′sau’s wife.

19 These are the sons of E′sau, and these are their sheiks. He is E′dom.

20 These are the sons of Se′ir the Hor′ite, the inhabitants of the land: Lo′tan and Sho′bal and Zib′e·on and A′nah 21 and Di′shon and E′zer and Di′shan. These are the sheiks of the Hor′ite, the sons of Se′ir, in the land of E′dom.

22 And the sons of Lo′tan came to be Ho′ri and He′mam; and Lo′tan’s sister was Tim′na.

23 And these are the sons of Sho′bal: Al′van and Man′a·hath and E′bal, She′pho and O′nam.

24 And these are the sons of Zib′e·on: A′iah and A′nah. This is the A′nah who found the hot springs in the wilderness while he was tending the asses for Zib′e·on his father.

25 And these are the children of A′nah: Di′shon and O·hol·i·ba′mah the daughter of A′nah.

26 And these are the sons of Di′shon: Hem′dan and Esh′ban and Ith′ran and Che′ran.

27 These are the sons of E′zer: Bil′han and Za′a·van and A′kan.

28 These are the sons of Di′shan: Uz and A′ran.

29 These are the sheiks of the Hor′ite: Sheik Lo′tan, sheik Sho′bal, sheik Zib′e·on, sheik A′nah, 30 sheik Di′shon, sheik E′zer, sheik Di′shan. These are the sheiks of the Hor′ite according to their sheiks in the land of Se′ir.

31 Now these are the kings who reigned in the land of E′dom before any king reigned over the sons of Israel. 32 And Be′la son of Be′or proceeded to reign in E′dom, and the name of his city was Din′ha·bah. 33 When Be′la died, Jo′bab son of Ze′rah from Boz′rah began to reign instead of him. 34 When Jo′bab died, Hu′sham from the land of the Te′man·ites began to reign instead of him. 35 When Hu′sham died, Ha′dad son of Be′dad, who defeated the Mid′i·an·ites in the field of Mo′ab, began to reign instead of him, and the name of his city was A′vith. 36 When Ha′dad died, Sam′lah from Mas·re′kah began to reign instead of him. 37 When Sam′lah died, Sha′ul from Re·ho′both by the River began to reign instead of him. 38 When Sha′ul died, Ba′al-ha′nan son of Ach′bor began to reign instead of him. 39 When Ba′al-ha′nan son of Ach′bor died, Ha′dar began to reign instead of him; and the name of his city was Pa′u, and the name of his wife was Me·het′a·bel the daughter of Ma′tred the daughter of Me′za·hab.

40 So these are the names of the sheiks of E′sau according to their families, according to their places, by their names: Sheik Tim′na, sheik Al′vah, sheik Je′theth, 41 sheik O·hol·i·ba′mah, sheik E′lah, sheik Pi′non, 42 sheik Ke′naz, sheik Te′man, sheik Mib′zar, 43 sheik Mag′di·el, sheik I′ram. These are the sheiks of E′dom according to their dwellings in the land of their possession. This is E′sau the father of E′dom.

Genesis

37 And Jacob continued to dwell in the land of the alien residences of his father, in the land of Ca′naan.

2 This is the history of Jacob.

Joseph, when seventeen years old, happened to be tending sheep with his brothers among the flock, and, being but a boy, he was with the sons of Bil′hah and the sons of Zil′pah, the wives of his father. So Joseph brought a bad report about them to their father. 3 And Israel loved Joseph more than all his other sons, because he was the son of his old age; and he had a long, striped shirtlike garment made for him. 4 When his brothers came to see that their father loved him more than all his brothers, they began to hate him, and they were not able to speak peacefully to him.

5 Later on Joseph had a dream and told it to his brothers, and they found further reason to hate him. 6 And he went on to say to them: “Listen, please, to this dream that I have dreamed. 7 Well, here we were binding sheaves in the middle of the field when here my sheaf got up and also stood erect and here YOUR sheaves proceeded to encircle and bow down to my sheaf.” 8 And his brothers began to say to him: “Are you going to be king over us for certain? or, Are you going to dominate over us for certain?” So they found fresh reason to hate him over his dreams and over his words.

9 After that he had still another dream, and he related it to his brothers and said: “Here I have had a dream once more, and here the sun and the moon and eleven stars were bowing down to me.” 10 Then he related it to his father as well as his brothers, and his father began to rebuke him and say to him: “What does this dream that you have dreamed mean? Am I and also your mother and your brothers for certain going to come and bow down to the earth to you?” 11 And his brothers grew jealous of him, but his father observed the saying.

12 His brothers now went to feed the flock of their father close by She′chem. 13 After a while Israel said to Joseph: “Your brothers are tending flocks close by She′chem, are they not? Come, and let me send you to them.” At this he said to him: “Here I am!” 14 So he said to him: “Go, please. See whether your brothers are safe and sound and whether the flock is safe and sound, and bring me back word.” With that he sent him away from the low plain of He′bron, and he went on toward She′chem. 15 Later a man found him and here he was wandering in a field. Then the man inquired of him, saying: “What are you looking for?” 16 To this he said: “It is my brothers I am looking for. Tell me, please, Where are they tending flocks?” 17 And the man continued: “They have pulled away from here, because I heard them saying, ‘Let us go to Do′than.’” So Joseph kept on after his brothers and found them at Do′than.

18 Well, they caught sight of him from a distance, and before he could get close by them they began plotting cunningly against him to put him to death. 19 So they said to one another: “Look! Here comes that dreamer. 20 And now come and let us kill him and pitch him into one of the waterpits; and we must say a vicious wild beast devoured him. Then let us see what will become of his dreams.” 21 When Reu′ben heard this he tried to deliver him out of their hand. So he said: “Let us not strike his soul fatally.” 22 And Reu′ben went on to say to them: “Do not spill blood. Pitch him into this waterpit which is in the wilderness and do not lay a violent hand upon him.” His purpose was to deliver him out of their hand in order to return him to his father.

23 So it came about that as soon as Joseph came to his brothers, they went stripping Joseph of his long garment, even the long striped garment that was upon him; 24 after which they took him and pitched him into the waterpit. At the time the pit was empty; there was no water in it.

25 Then they sat down to eat bread. When they raised their eyes and took a look, why, here was a caravan of Ish′ma·el·ites that was coming from Gil′e·ad, and their camels were carrying labdanum and balsam and resinous bark, on their way to take it down to Egypt. 26 At this Judah said to his brothers: “What profit would there be in case we killed our brother and did cover over his blood? 27 Come and let us sell him to the Ish′ma·el·ites, and do not let our hand be upon him. After all, he is our brother, our flesh.” So they listened to their brother. 28 Now men, Mid′i·an·ite merchants, went passing by. Hence they drew and lifted up Joseph out of the waterpit and then sold Joseph to the Ish′ma·el·ites for twenty silver pieces. Eventually these brought Joseph into Egypt.

29 Later Reu′ben returned to the waterpit and here Joseph was not in the waterpit. Consequently he ripped his garments apart. 30 When he returned to his other brothers he exclaimed: “The child is gone! And I—where am I really to go?”

31 However, they took Joseph’s long garment and slaughtered a male goat and repeatedly dipped the long garment in the blood. 32 After that they sent the long striped garment and had it brought to their father and said: “This is what we found. Examine, please, whether it is your son’s long garment or not.” 33 And he went examining it and exclaimed: “It is my son’s long garment! A vicious wild beast must have devoured him! Joseph is surely torn to pieces!” 34 With that Jacob ripped his mantles apart and put sackcloth upon his hips and carried on mourning over his son for many days. 35 And all his sons and all his daughters kept rising up to comfort him, but he kept refusing to take comfort and saying: “For I shall go down mourning to my son into She′ol!” And his father continued weeping for him.

36 However, the Mid′i·an·ites sold him into Egypt to Pot′i·phar a court official of Phar′aoh, the chief of the bodyguard.

Genesis

40 Now after these things it came about that the cupbearer of the king of Egypt and the baker sinned against their lord the king of Egypt. 2 And Phar′aoh grew indignant at his two officers, at the chief of the cupbearers and at the chief of the bakers. 3 So he committed them to the jail of the house of the chief of the bodyguard, to the prison house, the place where Joseph was a prisoner. 4 Then the chief of the bodyguard assigned Joseph to be with them that he might wait upon them; and they continued in jail for some days.

5 And both of them proceeded to dream a dream, each one his own dream in the one night, each one his dream with its own interpretation, the cupbearer and the baker who belonged to the king of Egypt who were prisoners in the prison house. 6 When Joseph came in to them in the morning and saw them, why, here they were looking dejected. 7 And he began to inquire of the officers of Phar′aoh who were with him in the jail of his master’s house, saying: “For what reason are YOUR faces gloomy today?” 8 At this they said to him: “We have dreamed a dream, and there is no interpreter with us.” So Joseph said to them: “Do not interpretations belong to God? Relate it to me, please.”

9 And the chief of the cupbearers went on to relate his dream to Joseph and to say to him: “In my dream, why, here there was a vine before me. 10 And on the vine there were three twigs, and it was apparently sprouting shoots. Its blossoms pushed forth. Its clusters ripened their grapes. 11 And Phar′aoh’s cup was in my hand, and I proceeded to take the grapes and squeeze them out into Phar′aoh’s cup. After that I gave the cup into Phar′aoh’s hand.” 12 Then Joseph said to him: “This is its interpretation: The three twigs are three days. 13 In three days from now Phar′aoh will lift up your head and he will certainly return you to your office; and you will certainly give Phar′aoh’s cup into his hand, according to the former custom when you acted as his cupbearer. 14 Nevertheless, you must keep me in your remembrance as soon as it goes well with you, and you must, please, perform loving-kindness with me and mention me to Phar′aoh, and you must get me out of this house. 15 For I was in fact kidnapped from the land of the Hebrews; and here also I have done nothing at all for which they should put me in the prison hole.”

16 When the chief of the bakers saw that he had interpreted something good, he, in turn, said to Joseph: “I too was in my dream, and here there were three baskets of white bread upon my head, 17 and in the topmost basket there were all sorts of eatables for Phar′aoh, the product of a baker, and there were fowls eating them out of the basket on top of my head.” 18 Then Joseph answered and said: “This is its interpretation: The three baskets are three days. 19 In three days from now Phar′aoh will lift up your head from off you and will certainly hang you upon a stake; and the fowls will certainly eat your flesh from off you.”

20 Now on the third day it turned out to be Phar′aoh’s birthday, and he proceeded to make a feast for all his servants and to lift up the head of the chief of the cupbearers and the head of the chief of the bakers in the midst of his servants. 21 Accordingly he returned the chief of the cupbearers to his post of cupbearer, and he continued to give the cup into Phar′aoh’s hand. 22 But the chief of the bakers he hung up, just as Joseph had given them the interpretation. 23 However, the chief of the cupbearers did not remember Joseph and went on forgetting him.

Genesis

42 Eventually Jacob got to see that there were cereals in Egypt. Then Jacob said to his sons: “Why do YOU keep looking at one another?” 2 And he added: “Here I have heard that there are cereals in Egypt. Go down there and buy for us from there, that we may keep alive and not die off.” 3 Accordingly ten brothers of Joseph went down to buy grain from Egypt. 4 But Jacob did not send Benjamin, Joseph’s brother, with his other brothers, because he said: “Otherwise a fatal accident may befall him.”

5 So Israel’s sons came along with the others who were coming to buy, because the famine existed in the land of Ca′naan. 6 And Joseph was the man in power over the land. He was the one that did the selling to all people of the earth. Consequently Joseph’s brothers came and bowed low to him with their faces to the earth. 7 When Joseph got to see his brothers, he at once recognized them, but he made himself unrecognizable to them. So he spoke harshly with them and said to them: “Where have YOU come from?” to which they said: “From the land of Ca′naan to buy foodstuffs.”

8 Thus Joseph recognized his brothers, but they themselves did not recognize him. 9 Immediately Joseph remembered the dreams that he had dreamed respecting them, and he went on to say to them: “YOU are spies! YOU have come to see the exposed condition of the land!” 10 Then they said to him: “No, my lord, but your servants have come to buy foodstuffs. 11 We are all of us sons of but one man. We are upright men. Your servants do not act as spies.” 12 But he said to them: “Not so! Because YOU have come to see the exposed condition of the land!” 13 At this they said: “Your servants are twelve brothers. We are the sons of but one man in the land of Ca′naan; and here the youngest is with our father today, whereas the other one is no more.”

14 However, Joseph said to them: “It is what I have spoken to YOU, saying, ‘YOU are spies!’ 15 By this YOU will be tested out. As Phar′aoh lives, YOU will not go out of here except when YOUR youngest brother comes here. 16 Send one of YOU that he may get YOUR brother while YOU have been bound, that YOUR words may be tested out as the truth in YOUR case. And if not, then, as Phar′aoh lives, YOU are spies.” 17 With that he put them together in custody for three days.

18 After that Joseph said to them on the third day: “Do this and keep alive. I fear the true God. 19 If YOU are upright, let one of YOUR brothers be kept bound in YOUR house of custody, but the rest of YOU go, take cereals for the famine in YOUR houses. 20 Then YOU will bring YOUR youngest brother to me, that YOUR words may be found trustworthy; and YOU will not die.” And they proceeded to do so.

21 And they began to say one to the other: “Unquestionably we are guilty with regard to our brother, because we saw the distress of his soul when he implored compassion on our part, but we did not listen. That is why this distress has come upon us.” 22 Then Reu′ben answered them, saying: “Did not I say to YOU, ‘Do not sin against the child,’ but YOU did not listen? And now his blood, here it is certainly asked back.” 23 As for them, they did not know that Joseph was listening, because there was an interpreter between them. 24 Consequently he turned away from them and began to weep. Then he returned to them and spoke to them and took Sim′e·on from them and bound him before their eyes. 25 After that Joseph gave the command, and they went filling up their receptacles with grain. Also, they were to return the money of the men to each one’s individual sack and to give them provisions for the journey. Accordingly it was done so to them.

26 So they loaded their cereals upon their asses and got on their way from there. 27 When one opened his sack to give fodder to his ass at the lodging place, he got to see his money, and here it was in the mouth of his bag. 28 At that he said to his brothers: “My money has been returned and now here it is in my bag!” Then their hearts sank, so that they turned trembling to one another, saying: “What is this God has done to us?”

29 At length they came to Jacob their father to the land of Ca′naan and told him all the things that had befallen them, saying: 30 “The man who is the lord of the country spoke harshly with us, since he took us for men spying on the country. 31 But we said to him, ‘We are upright men. We do not act as spies. 32 We are twelve brothers, the sons of our father. One is no more, and the youngest is today with our father in the land of Ca′naan.’ 33 But the man who is the lord of the country said to us, ‘By this I am going to know YOU are upright: Have one brother of YOURS stay with me. Then YOU take something for the famine in YOUR houses and go. 34 And bring YOUR youngest brother to me, that I may know that YOU are no spies but YOU are upright. YOUR brother I shall give back to YOU, and YOU may carry on business in the land.’”

35 And it came about that when they were emptying their sacks here was each one’s bundle of money in his sack. And they as well as their father got to see their bundles of money, and they became afraid. 36 Then Jacob their father exclaimed to them: “It is I YOU have bereaved! Joseph is no more and Sim′e·on is no more, and Benjamin YOU are going to take! It is upon me that all these things have come!” 37 But Reu′ben said to his father: “My own two sons you may put to death if I do not bring him back to you. Give him over to my care, and I shall be the one to return him to you.” 38 However, he said: “My son will not go down with YOU men, because his brother is dead and he has been left by himself. If a fatal accident should befall him on the way on which YOU would go, then YOU would certainly bring down my gray hairs with grief to She′ol.”

Genesis

43 And the famine was severe in the land. 2 And it came about that as soon as they had finished eating up the cereals they had brought from Egypt, their father proceeded to say to them: “Return, buy a little food for us.” 3 Then Judah said to him: “The man unmistakably bore witness to us, saying, ‘YOU must not see my face again unless YOUR brother is with YOU.’ 4 If you are sending our brother with us, we are willing to go down and buy food for you. 5 But if you are not sending him, we shall not go down, because the man did say to us, ‘YOU must not see my face again unless YOUR brother is with YOU.’” 6 And Israel exclaimed: “Why did YOU have to do harm to me by telling the man YOU had another brother?” 7 At this they said: “The man directly inquired concerning us and our relatives, saying, ‘Is YOUR father yet alive? Do YOU have another brother?’ and we went on to tell him according to these facts. How could we know for certain that he would say, ‘Bring YOUR brother down’?”

8 Finally Judah said to Israel his father: “Send the boy with me, that we may get up and go and that we may keep alive and not die off, both we and you and our little children. 9 I shall be the one to be surety for him. Out of my hand you may exact the penalty for him. If I fail to bring him to you and present him to you, then I shall have sinned against you for all time. 10 But if we had not lingered around, we should by now have been there and back these two times.”

11 So Israel their father said to them: “If, then, that is the case, do this: Take the finest products of the land in YOUR receptacles and carry them down to the man as a gift: a little balsam, and a little honey, labdanum and resinous bark, pistachio nuts and almonds. 12 Also, take double the money in YOUR hand; and the money that was returned in the mouth of YOUR bags YOU will take back in YOUR hand. Maybe it was a mistake. 13 And take YOUR brother and get up, return to the man. 14 And may God Almighty give YOU pity before the man, that he may certainly release to YOU YOUR other brother and Benjamin. But I, in case I must be bereaved, I shall certainly be bereaved!”

15 Accordingly the men took this gift, and they took double the money in their hand and Benjamin. Then they rose and went their way down to Egypt and got to stand before Joseph. 16 When Joseph saw Benjamin with them, he at once said to the man who was over his house: “Take the men to the house and slaughter animals and make preparation, because the men are to eat with me at noon.” 17 Immediately the man did just as Joseph had said. So the man took the men to Joseph’s house. 18 But the men got afraid because they had been taken to Joseph’s house, and they began to say: “It is because of the money that went back with us in our bags at the start that we are being brought here for them to fall upon us and attack us and to take us for slaves and also our asses!”

19 Hence they approached the man who was over Joseph’s house and spoke to him at the entrance of the house, 20 and they said: “Excuse us, my lord! We surely did come down at the start to buy food. 21 But what occurred was that when we came to the lodging place and began opening our bags, why, here was the money of each one in the mouth of his bag, our money in full weight. So we would like to return it with our own hands. 22 And more money we have brought down in our hands to buy food. We certainly do not know who placed our money in our bags.” 23 Then he said: “It is all right with YOU. Do not be afraid. YOUR God and the God of YOUR father gave YOU treasure in YOUR bags. YOUR money came first to me.” After that he brought out Sim′e·on to them.

24 Then the man brought the men into Joseph’s house and gave water that they might have their feet washed, and he gave fodder for their asses. 25 And they proceeded to get the gift ready for Joseph’s coming at noon, because they had heard that it was there they were going to eat bread. 26 When Joseph went on into the house, then they brought the gift that was in their hand to him into the house, and prostrated themselves to him to the earth. 27 After this he inquired whether they were getting along well and said: “Is YOUR father, the aged man of whom YOU have spoken, getting along well? Is he still alive?” 28 To this they said: “Your servant our father is getting along well. He is still alive.” Then they bowed down and prostrated themselves.

29 When he raised his eyes and saw Benjamin his brother, the son of his mother, he went on to say: “Is this YOUR brother, the youngest one of whom YOU have spoken to me?” And he added: “May God show you his favor, my son.” 30 Joseph was now in a hurry, because his inward emotions were excited toward his brother, so that he looked for a place to weep and he went into an interior room and gave way to tears there. 31 After that he washed his face and went out and kept control of himself and said: “SET on the meal.” 32 And they proceeded to set it on for him by himself and for them by themselves and for the Egyptians who were eating with him by themselves; for the Egyptians were not able to eat a meal with the Hebrews, because that is a detestable thing to the Egyptians.

33 And they were seated before him, the firstborn according to his right as firstborn and the youngest according to his youngness; and the men kept looking at one another in amazement. 34 And he kept having portions carried from before him to them, but he would increase Benjamin’s portion five times the size of the portions of all the others. So they continued banqueting and drinking with him to the full.

Genesis

45 At this Joseph was no longer able to control himself before all those who were stationed by him. So he cried out: “HAVE everybody go out from me!” And no one else stood with him while Joseph made himself known to his brothers.

2 And he began to raise his voice in weeping, so that the Egyptians got to hear it and Phar′aoh’s house got to hear it. 3 Finally Joseph said to his brothers: “I am Joseph. Is my father still alive?” But his brothers were unable to answer him at all, because they were disturbed by reason of him. 4 So Joseph said to his brothers: “Come close to me, please.” With that they came close to him.

Then he said: “I am Joseph YOUR brother, whom YOU sold into Egypt. 5 But now do not feel hurt and do not be angry with yourselves because YOU sold me here; because for the preservation of life God has sent me ahead of YOU. 6 For this is the second year of the famine in the midst of the earth, and there are yet five years in which there will be no plowing time or harvest. 7 Consequently God sent me ahead of YOU in order to place a remnant for YOU men in the earth and to keep YOU alive by a great escape. 8 So now it was not YOU who sent me here, but it was the true God, that he might appoint me a father to Phar′aoh and a lord for all his house and as one dominating over all the land of Egypt.

9 “Go up quickly to my father, and YOU must say to him, ‘This is what your son Joseph has said: “God has appointed me lord for all Egypt. Come down to me. Do not delay. 10 And you must dwell in the land of Go′shen, and you must continue near me, you and your sons and the sons of your sons and your flocks and your herds and everything you have. 11 And I will supply you with food there, for there are yet five years of famine; for fear you and your house and everything you have may come to poverty.”’ 12 And here YOUR eyes and the eyes of my brother Benjamin are seeing that it is my mouth that is speaking to YOU. 13 So YOU must tell my father about all my glory in Egypt and everything YOU have seen; and YOU must hurry and bring my father down here.”

14 Then he fell upon the neck of Benjamin his brother and gave way to weeping, and Benjamin wept upon his neck. 15 And he proceeded to kiss all his brothers and to weep over them, and after that his brothers spoke with him.

16 And the news was heard at the house of Phar′aoh, saying: “Joseph’s brothers have come!” And it proved to be good in the eyes of Phar′aoh and of his servants. 17 Accordingly Phar′aoh said to Joseph: “Say to your brothers, ‘Do this: Load YOUR beasts of burden and go enter the land of Ca′naan, 18 and take YOUR father and YOUR households and come here to me, that I may give YOU the good of the land of Egypt; and eat the fat part of the land. 19 And you yourself are commanded: “Do this: TAKE for yourselves wagons from the land of Egypt for YOUR little ones and YOUR wives, and YOU must lift YOUR father on one and come here. 20 And do not let YOUR eye feel sorry over YOUR equipment, because the good of all the land of Egypt is YOURS.”’”

21 Following that the sons of Israel did so, and Joseph gave them wagons according to Phar′aoh’s orders and gave them provisions for the way. 22 To each of them he gave individual changes of mantles, but to Benjamin he gave three hundred silver pieces and five changes of mantles. 23 And to his father he sent as follows: ten asses carrying good things of Egypt and ten she-asses carrying grain and bread and sustenance for his father for the way. 24 Thus he sent his brothers off, and they proceeded to go. However, he said to them: “Do not get exasperated at one another on the way.”

25 And they began going up out of Egypt and at length came into the land of Ca′naan to Jacob their father. 26 Then they reported to him, saying: “Joseph is still alive, and he is the one dominating over all the land of Egypt!” But his heart grew numb, because he did not believe them. 27 When they went on speaking to him all of Joseph’s words that he had spoken to them and he got to see the wagons that Joseph had sent to carry him, the spirit of Jacob their father began to revive. 28 Then Israel exclaimed: “It is enough! Joseph my son is still alive! Ah, let me go and see him before I die!”

Genesis

46 Accordingly Israel and all who were his pulled out and came to Be′er-she′ba, and he proceeded to sacrifice sacrifices to the God of his father Isaac. 2 Then God talked to Israel in visions of the night and said: “Jacob, Jacob!” to which he said: “Here I am!” 3 And he went on to say: “I am the true God, the God of your father. Do not be afraid to go down to Egypt, for I shall constitute you there into a great nation. 4 I myself shall go down with you to Egypt and I myself shall surely bring you up also; and Joseph will lay his hand upon your eyes.”

5 After that Jacob got up out of Be′er-she′ba, and the sons of Israel continued transporting Jacob their father and their little ones and their wives in the wagons that Phar′aoh had sent to transport him. 6 Further, they took along their herds and their goods, which they had accumulated in the land of Ca′naan. Eventually they came into Egypt, Jacob and all his offspring with him. 7 He brought his sons and his sons’ sons with him, his daughters and his sons’ daughters, even all his offspring, with him into Egypt.

8 Now these are the names of Israel’s sons who came into Egypt: Jacob and his sons: Jacob’s firstborn was Reu′ben.

9 And the sons of Reu′ben were Ha′noch and Pal′lu and Hez′ron and Car′mi.

10 And the sons of Sim′e·on were Jem·u′el and Ja′min and O′had and Ja′chin and Zo′har and Sha′ul the son of a Ca′naan·ite woman.

11 And the sons of Le′vi were Ger′shon, Ko′hath and Me·rar′i.

12 And the sons of Judah were Er and O′nan and She′lah and Pe′rez and Ze′rah. However, Er and O′nan died in the land of Ca′naan.

And the sons of Pe′rez came to be Hez′ron and Ha′mul.

13 And the sons of Is′sa·char were To′la and Pu′vah and Iob and Shim′ron.

14 And the sons of Zeb′u·lun were Se′red and E′lon and Jah′le·el.

15 These are the sons of Le′ah, whom she bore to Jacob in Pad′dan-a′ram, together with his daughter Di′nah. All the souls of his sons and of his daughters were thirty-three.

16 And the sons of Gad were Ziph′i·on and Hag′gi, Shu′ni and Ez′bon, E′ri and Ar·o′di and A·re′li.

17 And the sons of Ash′er were Im′nah and Ish′vah and Ish′vi and Be·ri′ah, and there was Se′rah their sister.

And the sons of Be·ri′ah were He′ber and Mal′chi·el.

18 These are the sons of Zil′pah, whom La′ban gave to his daughter Le′ah. In time she bore these to Jacob: sixteen souls.

19 The sons of Rachel, Jacob’s wife, were Joseph and Benjamin.

20 And there came to be born to Joseph in the land of Egypt Ma·nas′seh and E′phra·im, whom As′e·nath the daughter of Pot·i′phe·ra the priest of On bore to him.

21 And the sons of Benjamin were Be′la and Be′cher and Ash′bel, Ge′ra and Na′a·man, E′hi and Rosh, Mup′pim and Hup′pim and Ard.

22 These are the sons of Rachel who were born to Jacob. All the souls were fourteen.

23 And the sons of Dan were Hu′shim.

24 And the sons of Naph′ta·li were Jah′ze·el and Gu′ni and Je′zer and Shil′lem.

25 These are the sons of Bil′hah, whom La′ban gave to his daughter Rachel. In time she bore these to Jacob; all the souls were seven.

26 All the souls who came to Jacob into Egypt were those who issued out of his upper thigh, aside from the wives of Jacob’s sons. All the souls were sixty-six. 27 And Joseph’s sons who were born to him in Egypt were two souls. All the souls of the house of Jacob who came into Egypt were seventy.

28 And he sent Judah in advance of him to Joseph to impart information ahead of him to Go′shen. After that they came into the land of Go′shen. 29 Then Joseph had his chariot made ready and went up to meet Israel his father at Go′shen. When he appeared to him he at once fell upon his neck and gave way to tears upon his neck again and again. 30 Finally Israel said to Joseph: “This time I am willing to die, now that I have seen your face, since you are still alive.”

31 Then Joseph said to his brothers and to his father’s household: “Let me go up and report to Phar′aoh and say to him, ‘My brothers and my father’s household who were in the land of Ca′naan have come here to me. 32 And the men are shepherds, because they became stock raisers; and their flocks and their herds and all they have they have brought here.’ 33 And what must occur is that when Phar′aoh will call YOU and actually say, ‘What is YOUR occupation?’ 34 YOU must say, ‘Your servants have continued to be stock raisers from our youth until now, both we and our forefathers,’ in order that YOU may dwell in the land of Go′shen, because every herder of sheep is a detestable thing to Egypt.”

Genesis

47 Accordingly Joseph came and reported to Phar′aoh and said: “My father and my brothers and their flocks and their herds and all they have have come from the land of Ca′naan, and here they are in the land of Go′shen.” 2 And from the whole number of his brothers he took five men, that he might present them to Phar′aoh.

3 Then Phar′aoh said to his brothers: “What is YOUR occupation?” So they said to Phar′aoh: “Your servants are herders of sheep, both we and our forefathers.” 4 After that they said to Phar′aoh: “We have come to reside as aliens in the land, because there is no pasturage for the flock that your servants have, for the famine is severe in the land of Ca′naan. And now let your servants dwell, please, in the land of Go′shen.” 5 At that Phar′aoh said to Joseph: “Your father and your brothers have come here to you. 6 The land of Egypt is at your disposal. Have your father and your brothers dwell in the very best of the land. Let them dwell in the land of Go′shen, and if you know that there are among them courageous men, you must appoint them cattle chiefs over what is mine.”

7 Then Joseph brought in Jacob his father and introduced him to Phar′aoh, and Jacob proceeded to bless Phar′aoh. 8 Phar′aoh now said to Jacob: “How many are the days of the years of your life?” 9 So Jacob said to Phar′aoh: “The days of the years of my alien residences are a hundred and thirty years. Few and distressing the days of the years of my life have proved, and they have not reached the days of the years of the lives of my fathers in the days of their alien residences.” 10 After that Jacob blessed Phar′aoh and went out from before Phar′aoh.

11 Thus Joseph had his father and his brothers dwell and he gave them a possession in the land of Egypt, in the very best of the land, in the land of Ram′e·ses, just as Phar′aoh had commanded. 12 And Joseph kept supplying his father and his brothers and the entire household of his father with bread, according to the number of the little ones.

13 Now there was no bread in all the land, because the famine was very severe; and the land of Egypt and the land of Ca′naan became exhausted as a result of the famine. 14 And Joseph went on picking up all the money that was to be found in the land of Egypt and in the land of Ca′naan for the cereals which people were buying; and Joseph kept bringing the money into Phar′aoh’s house. 15 In time the money from the land of Egypt and the land of Ca′naan was spent, and all the Egyptians began coming to Joseph, saying: “Give us bread! And why should we die in front of you because money has run out?” 16 Then Joseph said: “Hand over YOUR livestock and I shall give YOU bread in exchange for YOUR livestock, if money has run out.” 17 And they began bringing their livestock to Joseph; and Joseph kept giving them bread in exchange for their horses and the livestock of the flock and the livestock of the herd and the asses, and he kept providing them with bread in exchange for all their livestock during that year.

18 Gradually that year came to its close, and they began coming to him in the next year and saying to him: “We shall not hide it from my lord but the money and the stock of domestic animals have been spent to my lord. There remains nothing before my lord but our bodies and our land. 19 Why should we die before your eyes, both we and our land? Buy us and our land for bread, and we together with our land will become slaves to Phar′aoh; and give us seed that we may live and not die and our land not be laid desolate.” 20 So Joseph bought all the land of the Egyptians for Phar′aoh, because the Egyptians sold each one his field, for the famine had got a strong grip on them; and the land came to be Phar′aoh’s.

21 As for the people, he removed them into cities from one end of the territory of Egypt to its other end. 22 Only the land of the priests he did not buy, because the rations for the priests were from Phar′aoh and they ate their rations that Phar′aoh gave them. That is why they did not sell their land. 23 Then Joseph said to the people: “See, I have today bought YOU and YOUR land for Phar′aoh. Here is seed for YOU, and YOU must sow the land with it. 24 When it has resulted in produce, then YOU must give a fifth to Phar′aoh, but four parts will become YOURS as seed for the field and as food for YOU and for those who are in YOUR houses and for YOUR little ones to eat.” 25 Consequently they said: “You have preserved our lives. Let us find favor in the eyes of my lord, and we will become slaves to Phar′aoh.” 26 And Joseph proceeded to make it a decree down to this day over the landed estate of Egypt for Phar′aoh to have to the amount of a fifth. Only the land of the priests as a distinct group did not become Phar′aoh’s.

27 And Israel continued to dwell in the land of Egypt, in the land of Go′shen; and they became settled in it and were fruitful and grew to be very many. 28 And Jacob lived on in the land of Egypt for seventeen years, so that Jacob’s days, the years of his life, came to be a hundred and forty-seven years.

29 Gradually the days approached for Israel to die. So he called his son Joseph and said to him: “If, now, I have found favor in your eyes, place your hand, please, under my thigh, and you must exercise loving-kindness and trustworthiness toward me. (Please, do not bury me in Egypt.) 30 And I must lie with my fathers, and you must carry me out of Egypt and bury me in their grave.” Accordingly he said: “I myself shall do in keeping with your word.” 31 Then he said: “Swear to me.” So he swore to him. At that Israel prostrated himself over the head of the couch.

Genesis

48 And it came about after these things that it was said to Joseph: “Look, your father is becoming weak.” At that he took with him his two sons Ma·nas′seh and E′phra·im. 2 Then it was reported to Jacob and said: “Here your son Joseph has come to you.” So Israel exerted his strength and sat up on his couch. 3 And Jacob proceeded to say to Joseph:

“God Almighty appeared to me at Luz in the land of Ca′naan that he might bless me. 4 And he went on to say to me, ‘Here I am making you fruitful, and I will make you many and I will transform you into a congregation of peoples and I will give this land to your seed after you for a possession to time indefinite.’ 5 And now your two sons who were born to you in the land of Egypt before I came here to you into Egypt, they are mine. E′phra·im and Ma·nas′seh will become mine like Reu′ben and Sim′e·on. 6 But your progeny to which you shall become father after them will become yours. Together with the name of their brothers they will be called in their inheritance. 7 And as for me, when I was coming from Pad′dan, Rachel died alongside me in the land of Ca′naan on the way while there was yet a good stretch of land before coming to Eph′rath, so that I buried her there on the way to Eph′rath, that is to say, Beth′le·hem.”

8 Then Israel saw Joseph’s sons and said: “Who are these?” 9 So Joseph said to his father: “They are my sons whom God has given me in this place.” At this he said: “Bring them, please, to me that I may bless them.” 10 Now the eyes of Israel were dull from old age. He was unable to see. Accordingly he brought them close to him, and he then kissed them and embraced them. 11 And Israel went on to say to Joseph: “I had no idea of seeing your face, but here God has let me see also your offspring.” 12 After that Joseph brought them out away from his knees, and he bowed down with his face to the earth.

13 Joseph now took the two of them, E′phra·im by his right hand to Israel’s left, and Ma·nas′seh by his left hand to Israel’s right, and brought them close to him. 14 However, Israel put out his right hand and placed it on E′phra·im’s head, although he was the younger, and his left hand upon Ma·nas′seh’s head. He purposely laid his hands so, since Ma·nas′seh was the firstborn. 15 And he proceeded to bless Joseph and to say:

“The true God before whom my fathers Abraham and Isaac walked,

The true God who has been shepherding me during all my existence until this day,

16 The angel who has been recovering me from all calamity, bless the boys.

And let my name be called upon them and the name of my fathers, Abraham and Isaac,

And let them increase to a multitude in the midst of the earth.”

17 When Joseph saw that his father kept his right hand placed on E′phra·im’s head, it was displeasing to him, and he tried to take hold of his father’s hand to remove it from E′phra·im’s head to Ma·nas′seh’s head. 18 Hence Joseph said to his father: “Not so, my father, because this is the firstborn. Put your right hand on his head.” 19 But his father kept refusing and said: “I know it, my son, I know it. He too will become a people and he too will become great. But, just the same, his younger brother will become greater than he will, and his offspring will become the full equivalent of nations.” 20 And he continued to bless them on that day, saying:

“By means of you let Israel repeatedly pronounce blessing, saying,

‘May God constitute you like E′phra·im and like Ma·nas′seh.’”

Thus he kept putting E′phra·im before Ma·nas′seh.

21 After that Israel said to Joseph: “Look, I am dying, but God will certainly continue with YOU people and return YOU to the land of YOUR forefathers. 22 As for me, I do give you one shoulder of land more than to your brothers, which I took from the hand of the Am′or·ites by my sword and by my bow.”

Exodus

6 So Jehovah said to Moses: “Now you will see what I shall do to Phar′aoh, because on account of a strong hand he will send them away and on account of a strong hand he will drive them out of his land.”

2 And God went on to speak to Moses and to say to him: “I am Jehovah. 3 And I used to appear to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob as God Almighty, but as respects my name Jehovah I did not make myself known to them. 4 And I also established my covenant with them to give them the land of Ca′naan, the land of their alien residences in which they resided as aliens. 5 And I, even I, have heard the groaning of the sons of Israel, whom the Egyptians are enslaving, and I remember my covenant.

6 “Therefore say to the sons of Israel, ‘I am Jehovah, and I shall certainly bring YOU out from under the burdens of the Egyptians and deliver YOU from their slavery, and I shall indeed reclaim YOU with an outstretched arm and with great judgments. 7 And I shall certainly take YOU to me as a people, and I shall indeed prove to be God to YOU; and YOU will certainly know that I am Jehovah YOUR God who is bringing YOU out from under the burdens of Egypt. 8 And I shall certainly bring YOU into the land that I raised my hand in oath to give to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob; and I shall indeed give it to YOU as something to possess. I am Jehovah.’”

9 Afterward Moses spoke to this effect to the sons of Israel, but they did not listen to Moses out of discouragement and for the hard slavery.

10 Then Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 11 “Go in, speak to Phar′aoh, Egypt’s king, that he should send the sons of Israel away out of his land.” 12 However, Moses spoke before Jehovah, saying: “Look! The sons of Israel have not listened to me; and how will Phar′aoh ever listen to me, as I am uncircumcised in lips?” 13 But Jehovah continued to speak to Moses and Aaron and to issue the command by them to the sons of Israel and to Phar′aoh, Egypt’s king, in order to bring the sons of Israel out from the land of Egypt.

14 These are the heads of the house of their fathers: The sons of Reu′ben, Israel’s firstborn, were Ha′noch and Pal′lu, Hez′ron and Car′mi. These are the families of Reu′ben.

15 And the sons of Sim′e·on were Jem·u′el and Ja′min and O′had and Ja′chin and Zo′har and Sha′ul the son of a Ca′naan·ite woman. These are the families of Sim′e·on.

16 And these are the names of the sons of Le′vi, according to their family descents: Ger′shon and Ko′hath and Me·rar′i. And the years of Le′vi’s life were a hundred and thirty-seven years.

17 The sons of Ger′shon were Lib′ni and Shim′e·i, according to their families.

18 And the sons of Ko′hath were Am′ram and Iz′har and He′bron and Uz′zi·el. And the years of Ko′hath’s life were a hundred and thirty-three years.

19 And the sons of Me·rar′i were Mah′li and Mu′shi.

These were the families of the Levites, according to their family descents.

20 Now Am′ram took Joch′e·bed his father’s sister as his wife. Later she bore him Aaron and Moses. And the years of Am′ram’s life were a hundred and thirty-seven years.

21 And the sons of Iz′har were Ko′rah and Ne′pheg and Zich′ri.

22 And the sons of Uz′zi·el were Mish′a·el and El·za′phan and Sith′ri.

23 Now Aaron took E·li′she·ba, Am·min′a·dab’s daughter, the sister of Nah′shon, as his wife. Later she bore him Na′dab and A·bi′hu, El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar.

24 And the sons of Ko′rah were As′sir and El·ka′nah and A·bi′a·saph. These were the families of the Ko′rah·ites.

25 And El·e·a′zar, Aaron’s son, took for himself one of the daughters of Pu′ti·el as his wife. Later she bore him Phin′e·has.

These are the heads of the fathers of the Levites, according to their families.

26 This is the Aaron and Moses to whom Jehovah said: “BRING the sons of Israel out from the land of Egypt according to their armies.” 27 They were the ones speaking to Phar′aoh, Egypt’s king, to bring the sons of Israel out from Egypt. This is the Moses and Aaron.

28 And it came about on the day that Jehovah spoke to Moses in the land of Egypt, 29 that Jehovah went on to speak to Moses, saying: “I am Jehovah. Speak to Phar′aoh king of Egypt everything I am speaking to you.” 30 Then Moses said before Jehovah: “Look! I am uncircumcised in lips, so how will Phar′aoh ever listen to me?”

Exodus

7 Consequently Jehovah said to Moses: “See, I have made you God to Phar′aoh, and Aaron your own brother will become your prophet. 2 You—you will speak all that I shall command you; and Aaron your brother will do the speaking to Phar′aoh, and he must send the sons of Israel away from his land. 3 As for me, I shall let Phar′aoh’s heart become obstinate, and I shall certainly multiply my signs and my miracles in the land of Egypt. 4 And Phar′aoh will not listen to YOU men; and I shall have to lay my hand upon Egypt and bring my armies, my people, the sons of Israel, out from the land of Egypt with great judgments. 5 And the Egyptians will certainly know that I am Jehovah when I stretch out my hand against Egypt, and I shall indeed bring the sons of Israel out from their midst.” 6 And Moses and Aaron went ahead doing as Jehovah had commanded them. They did just so. 7 And Moses was eighty years old and Aaron was eighty-three years old at the time of their speaking to Phar′aoh.

8 Jehovah now said to Moses and Aaron: 9 “In case that Phar′aoh speaks to YOU, saying, ‘Produce a miracle for yourselves,’ then you must say to Aaron, ‘Take your rod and throw it down before Phar′aoh.’ It will become a big snake.” 10 So Moses and Aaron went on in to Phar′aoh and did exactly as Jehovah had commanded. Accordingly Aaron threw his rod down before Phar′aoh and his servants and it became a big snake. 11 However, Phar′aoh also called for the wise men and the sorcerers; and the magic-practicing priests of Egypt themselves also proceeded to do the same thing with their magic arts. 12 So they threw down each one his rod, and they became big snakes; but Aaron’s rod swallowed up their rods. 13 Still, Phar′aoh’s heart became obstinate, and he did not listen to them, just as Jehovah had spoken.

14 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Phar′aoh’s heart is unresponsive. He has refused to send the people away. 15 Go to Phar′aoh in the morning. Look! He is going out to the water! And you must put yourself in position to meet him by the edge of the Nile River, and the rod that turned into a serpent you are to take in your hand. 16 And you must say to him, ‘Jehovah the God of the Hebrews has sent me to you, saying: “Send my people away that they may serve me in the wilderness,” but here you have not obeyed until now. 17 This is what Jehovah has said: “By this you will know that I am Jehovah. Here I am striking with the rod that is in my hand upon the water that is in the Nile River, and it will certainly turn into blood. 18 And the fish that are in the Nile River will die, and the Nile River will actually stink, and the Egyptians will simply have no stomach for drinking water from the Nile River.”’”

19 Subsequently Jehovah said to Moses: “Say to Aaron, ‘Take your rod and stretch your hand out over the waters of Egypt, over their rivers, over their Nile canals and over their reedy pools and over all their impounded waters, that they may become blood.’ And there will certainly be blood in all the land of Egypt and in the wooden vessels and in the stone vessels.” 20 Immediately Moses and Aaron did so, just as Jehovah had commanded, and he lifted up the rod and struck the water that was in the Nile River under the eyes of Phar′aoh and his servants, and all the water that was in the Nile River was turned into blood. 21 And the fish that were in the Nile River died, and the Nile River began to stink; and the Egyptians were unable to drink water from the Nile River; and the blood came to be in all the land of Egypt.

22 Nevertheless, the magic-practicing priests of Egypt proceeded to do the same thing with their secret arts; so that Phar′aoh’s heart continued to be obstinate, and he did not listen to them, just as Jehovah had spoken. 23 Hence Phar′aoh turned and went into his house, and he did not set his heart to have any regard for this either. 24 And all the Egyptians went digging round about the Nile River for water to drink, because they were unable to drink any water of the Nile River. 25 And seven days came to be fulfilled after Jehovah’s striking the Nile River.

Exodus

9 Consequently Jehovah said to Moses: “Go in to Phar′aoh and you must state to him, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of the Hebrews has said: “Send my people away that they may serve me. 2 But if you continue refusing to send them away and you are still keeping hold of them, 3 look! Jehovah’s hand is coming upon your livestock that is in the field. On the horses, the asses, the camels, the herd and the flock there will be a very heavy pestilence. 4 And Jehovah will certainly make a distinction between the livestock of Israel and the livestock of Egypt, and not a thing of all that belongs to the sons of Israel will die.”’” 5 Moreover, Jehovah set an appointed time, saying: “Tomorrow Jehovah will do this thing in the land.”

6 Accordingly Jehovah did this thing on the next day, and all sorts of livestock of Egypt began to die; but not one of the livestock of the sons of Israel died. 7 Then Phar′aoh sent, and, look! not so much as one of Israel’s livestock had died. Nevertheless, Phar′aoh’s heart continued to be unresponsive, and he did not send the people away.

8 After that Jehovah said to Moses and Aaron: “Take for yourselves both hands full of soot from a kiln, and Moses must toss it toward the heavens in Phar′aoh’s sight. 9 And it must become a powder upon all the land of Egypt, and it must become boils breaking out with blisters upon man and beast in all the land of Egypt.”

10 So they took the soot of a kiln and stood before Phar′aoh, and Moses tossed it toward the heavens, and it became boils with blisters, breaking out on man and beast. 11 And the magic-practicing priests were unable to stand before Moses as a result of the boils, because the boils had developed on the magic-practicing priests and on all the Egyptians. 12 But Jehovah let Phar′aoh’s heart become obstinate, and he did not listen to them, just as Jehovah had stated to Moses.

13 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Get up early in the morning and take a position in front of Phar′aoh, and you must say to him, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of the Hebrews has said: “Send my people away that they may serve me. 14 For at this time I am sending all my blows against your heart and upon your servants and your people, to the end that you may know that there is none like me in all the earth. 15 For by now I could have thrust my hand out that I might strike you and your people with pestilence and that you might be effaced from the earth. 16 But, in fact, for this cause I have kept you in existence, for the sake of showing you my power and in order to have my name declared in all the earth. 17 Are you still behaving haughtily against my people in not sending them away? 18 Here I am causing it to rain down tomorrow about this time a very heavy hail, the like of which has never occurred in Egypt from the day it was founded until now. 19 And now send, bring all your livestock and all that is yours in the field under shelter. As for any man and beast that will be found in the field and not gathered into the house, the hail will have to come down upon them, and they will have to die.”’”

20 Anyone who feared Jehovah’s word among Phar′aoh’s servants caused his own servants and his livestock to flee into the houses, 21 but whoever did not set his heart to have any regard for Jehovah’s word left his servants and his livestock in the field.

22 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Stretch out your hand toward the heavens, that hail may come on all the land of Egypt, upon man and beast and all vegetation of the field in the land of Egypt.” 23 So Moses stretched out his rod toward the heavens; and Jehovah gave thunders and hail, and fire would run down to the earth, and Jehovah kept making it rain down hail upon the land of Egypt. 24 Thus there came hail, and fire quivering in among the hail. It was very heavy, so that there had not occurred any like it in all the land of Egypt from the time it became a nation. 25 And the hail went striking at all the land of Egypt. The hail struck everything that was in the field, from man to beast, and all sorts of vegetation of the field; and it shattered all sorts of trees of the field. 26 Only in the land of Go′shen, where the sons of Israel were, there occurred no hail.

27 Eventually Phar′aoh sent and called Moses and Aaron and said to them: “I have sinned this time. Jehovah is righteous, and I and my people are in the wrong. 28 Entreat Jehovah that this may be enough of the occurring of God’s thunders and hail. Then I am willing to send YOU away, and YOU will not stay any longer.” 29 So Moses said to him: “As soon as I go out of the city I shall spread my hands up to Jehovah. The thunders will stop and the hail will not continue any longer, in order that you may know that the earth belongs to Jehovah. 30 As for you and your servants, I know already that YOU will not even then show fear because of Jehovah God.”

31 As it was, the flax and the barley had been struck, because the barley was in the ear and the flax had flower buds. 32 But the wheat and the spelt had not been struck, because they were seasonally late. 33 Moses now went out of the city from Phar′aoh and spread his hands up to Jehovah, and the thunders and the hail began to stop and rain did not pour down on the earth. 34 When Phar′aoh got to see that the rain and the hail and the thunders had stopped, he went sinning again and making his heart unresponsive, he as well as his servants. 35 And Phar′aoh’s heart continued obstinate, and he did not send the sons of Israel away, just as Jehovah had stated by means of Moses.

Exodus

13 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses, saying: 2 “Sanctify to me every male firstborn that opens each womb among the sons of Israel, among men and beasts. It is mine.”

3 And Moses went on to say to the people: “Let there be a remembering of this day on which YOU went out of Egypt, from the house of slaves, because by strength of hand Jehovah brought YOU out from here. So nothing leavened may be eaten. 4 Today YOU are going out in the month of A′bib. 5 And it must occur that when Jehovah will have brought you into the land of the Ca′naan·ites and the Hit′tites and the Am′or·ites and the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites, which he swore to your forefathers to give you, a land flowing with milk and honey, then you must render this service in this month. 6 Seven days you are to eat unfermented cakes, and on the seventh day is a festival to Jehovah. 7 Unfermented cakes are to be eaten for the seven days; and nothing leavened is to be seen with you, and no sourdough is to be seen with you within all your boundaries. 8 And you must tell your son on that day, saying, ‘It is because of that which Jehovah has done to me when I came out of Egypt.’ 9 And it must serve for you as a sign upon your hand and as a memorial between your eyes, in order that Jehovah’s law may prove to be in your mouth; because by a strong hand Jehovah brought you out of Egypt. 10 And you must keep this statute at its appointed time from year to year.

11 “And it must occur that when Jehovah brings you into the land of the Ca′naan·ites, just as he has sworn to you and to your forefathers, and when he does give it to you, 12 then you must devote everyone that opens the womb to Jehovah, and every firstling, the young of a beast, which will come to be yours. The males belong to Jehovah. 13 And every firstling ass you are to redeem with a sheep, and if you will not redeem it, then you must break its neck. And every firstborn of man among your sons you are to redeem.

14 “And it must occur that in case your son should inquire of you later on, saying, ‘What does this mean?’ then you must say to him, ‘By strength of hand Jehovah brought us out of Egypt, from the house of slaves. 15 And it came about that Phar′aoh showed obstinacy toward sending us away, and Jehovah proceeded to kill every firstborn in the land of Egypt, from the firstborn of man to the firstborn of beast. That is why I am sacrificing to Jehovah all the males that open the womb, and every firstborn of my sons I redeem.’ 16 And it must serve as a sign upon your hand and as a frontlet band between your eyes, because by strength of hand Jehovah brought us out of Egypt.”

17 And it came about at the time of Phar′aoh’s sending the people away that God did not lead them by the way of the land of the Phi·lis′tines just because it was near, for God said: “It might be the people will feel regret when they see war and will certainly return to Egypt.” 18 Hence God made the people go round about by the way of the wilderness of the Red Sea. But it was in battle formation that the sons of Israel went up out of the land of Egypt. 19 And Moses was taking Joseph’s bones with him, because he had made the sons of Israel solemnly swear, saying: “God will without fail turn his attention to YOU, and YOU must take my bones up out of here with YOU.” 20 And they proceeded to depart from Suc′coth and to encamp at E′tham at the edge of the wilderness.

21 And Jehovah was going ahead of them in the daytime in a pillar of cloud to lead them by the way, and in the nighttime in a pillar of fire to give them light to go in the daytime and nighttime. 22 The pillar of cloud would not move away from before the people in the daytime nor the pillar of fire in the nighttime.

Exodus

16 Later they departed from E′lim, and the entire assembly of the sons of Israel finally came to the wilderness of Sin, which is between E′lim and Si′nai, on the fifteenth day of the second month after their coming out of the land of Egypt.

2 And the entire assembly of the sons of Israel began to murmur against Moses and Aaron in the wilderness. 3 And the sons of Israel kept saying to them: “If only we had died by Jehovah’s hand in the land of Egypt while we were sitting by the pots of meat, while we were eating bread to satisfaction, because YOU have brought us out into this wilderness to put this whole congregation to death by famine.”

4 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Here I am raining down bread for YOU from the heavens; and the people must go out and pick up each his amount day for day, in order that I may put them to the test as to whether they will walk in my law or not. 5 And it must occur on the sixth day that they must prepare what they will bring in, and it must prove double what they keep picking up day by day.”

6 So Moses and Aaron said to all the sons of Israel: “At evening YOU will certainly know that it is Jehovah who has brought YOU out from the land of Egypt. 7 And in the morning YOU will indeed see Jehovah’s glory, because he has heard YOUR murmurings against Jehovah. And what are we that YOU should murmur against us?” 8 And Moses continued: “It will be when Jehovah gives YOU in the evening meat to eat and in the morning bread to satisfaction, because Jehovah has heard YOUR murmurings that YOU are murmuring against him. And what are we? YOUR murmurings are not against us, but against Jehovah.”

9 And Moses went on to say to Aaron: “Say to the entire assembly of the sons of Israel, ‘Come near before Jehovah, because he has heard YOUR murmurings.’” 10 Then it occurred that as soon as Aaron had spoken to the entire assembly of the sons of Israel, they turned and faced toward the wilderness, and, look! Jehovah’s glory appeared in the cloud.

11 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses, saying: 12 “I have heard the murmurings of the sons of Israel. Speak to them, saying, ‘Between the two evenings YOU will eat meat and in the morning YOU will be satisfied with bread; and YOU will certainly know that I am Jehovah YOUR God.’”

13 Accordingly it occurred that in the evening the quails began to come up and cover the camp, and in the morning there had developed a layer of dew round about the camp. 14 In time the layer of dew evaporated and here upon the surface of the wilderness there was a fine flaky thing, fine like hoarfrost upon the earth. 15 When the sons of Israel got to see it, they began to say to one another: “What is it?” For they did not know what it was. Hence Moses said to them: “It is the bread that Jehovah has given YOU for food. 16 This is the word that Jehovah has commanded, ‘Pick up some of it, each one in proportion to his eating. YOU are to take an omer measure for each individual according to the number of the souls that each of YOU has in his tent.’” 17 And the sons of Israel began to do so; and they went picking it up, some gathering much and some gathering little. 18 When they would measure it by the omer, he that had gathered much had no surplus and he that had gathered little had no shortage. They picked it up each one in proportion to his eating.

19 Then Moses said to them: “Let nobody leave any of it until the morning.” 20 But they did not listen to Moses. When some men would leave some of it until the morning, it would breed worms and stink; so that Moses became indignant at them. 21 And they would pick it up morning by morning, each one in proportion to his eating. When the sun got hot, it melted.

22 And it came about on the sixth day that they picked up twice as much bread, two omer measures for one person. So all the chieftains of the assembly came and reported it to Moses. 23 At that he said to them: “It is what Jehovah has spoken. Tomorrow there will be a sabbath observance of a holy sabbath to Jehovah. What YOU can bake, bake, and what YOU can boil, boil, and all the surplus that there is save it up for YOU as something to be kept until the morning.” 24 Accordingly they saved it up until the morning, just as Moses had commanded; and it did not stink nor did maggots develop in it. 25 Then Moses said: “Eat it today, because today is a sabbath to Jehovah. Today YOU will not find it in the field. 26 Six days YOU will pick it up, but on the seventh day is a sabbath. On it none will form.” 27 However, it came about on the seventh day that some of the people did go out to pick it up, but they found none.

28 Consequently Jehovah said to Moses: “How long must YOU people refuse to keep my commandments and my laws? 29 Mark the fact that Jehovah has given YOU the sabbath. That is why he is giving YOU on the sixth day the bread of two days. Keep sitting each one in his own place. Let nobody go out from his locality on the seventh day.” 30 And the people proceeded to observe the sabbath on the seventh day.

31 And the house of Israel began to call its name “manna.” And it was white like coriander seed, and its taste was like that of flat cakes with honey. 32 Then Moses said: “This is the word that Jehovah has commanded, ‘Fill an omer measure of it as something to be kept throughout YOUR generations, in order that they may see the bread that I made YOU eat in the wilderness when I was bringing YOU out of the land of Egypt.’” 33 So Moses said to Aaron: “Take a jar and put in it an omerful of manna and deposit it before Jehovah as something to be kept throughout YOUR generations.” 34 Just as Jehovah had commanded Moses, Aaron proceeded to deposit it before the Testimony as something to be kept. 35 And the sons of Israel ate the manna forty years, until their coming to a land inhabited. The manna was what they ate until their coming to the frontier of the land of Ca′naan. 36 Now an omer is a tenth of an e′phah measure.

Exodus

17 And the entire assembly of the sons of Israel proceeded to depart from the wilderness of Sin by stages, which they took according to the order of Jehovah, and went camping at Reph′i·dim. But there was no water for the people to drink.

2 And the people fell to quarreling with Moses and saying: “Give us water that we may drink.” But Moses said to them: “Why are YOU quarreling with me? Why do YOU keep putting Jehovah to the test?” 3 And the people went on thirsting there for water, and the people kept murmuring against Moses and saying: “Why is it that you have brought us up out of Egypt to put us and our sons and our livestock to death by thirst?” 4 Finally Moses cried out to Jehovah, saying: “What shall I do with this people? A little longer and they will stone me!”

5 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Pass in front of the people and take with you some of the older men of Israel and your rod with which you struck the Nile River. Take it in your hand and you must walk on. 6 Look! I am standing before you there on the rock in Ho′reb. And you must strike on the rock, and water must come out of it, and the people must drink it.” Subsequently Moses did so under the eyes of the older men of Israel. 7 So he called the name of the place Mas′sah and Mer′i·bah, because of the quarreling of the sons of Israel and because of their putting Jehovah to the test, saying: “Is Jehovah in our midst or not?”

8 And the A·mal′ek·ites proceeded to come and fight against Israel in Reph′i·dim. 9 At this Moses said to Joshua: “Choose men for us and go out, fight against the A·mal′ek·ites. Tomorrow I am stationing myself upon the top of the hill, with the rod of the true God in my hand.” 10 Then Joshua did just as Moses had said to him, in order to fight against the A·mal′ek·ites; and Moses, Aaron and Hur went up to the top of the hill.

11 And it occurred that as soon as Moses would lift his hand up, the Israelites proved superior; but as soon as he would let down his hand, the A·mal′ek·ites proved superior. 12 When the hands of Moses were heavy, then they took a stone and put it under him, and he sat upon it; and Aaron and Hur supported his hands, one on this side and the other on that side, so that his hands held steady until the sun set. 13 Hence Joshua vanquished Am′a·lek and his people with the edge of the sword.

14 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Write this as a memorial in the book and propound it in Joshua’s ears, ‘I shall completely wipe out the remembrance of Am′a·lek from under the heavens.’” 15 And Moses proceeded to build an altar and to call its name Je·ho′vah-nis′si, 16 saying: “Because a hand is against the throne of Jah, Jehovah will have war with Am′a·lek from generation to generation.”

Exodus

20 And God proceeded to speak all these words, saying:

2 “I am Jehovah your God, who have brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of slaves. 3 You must not have any other gods against my face.

4 “You must not make for yourself a carved image or a form like anything that is in the heavens above or that is on the earth underneath or that is in the waters under the earth. 5 You must not bow down to them nor be induced to serve them, because I Jehovah your God am a God exacting exclusive devotion, bringing punishment for the error of fathers upon sons, upon the third generation and upon the fourth generation, in the case of those who hate me; 6 but exercising loving-kindness toward the thousandth generation in the case of those who love me and keep my commandments.

7 “You must not take up the name of Jehovah your God in a worthless way, for Jehovah will not leave the one unpunished who takes up his name in a worthless way.

8 “Remembering the sabbath day to hold it sacred, 9 you are to render service and you must do all your work six days. 10 But the seventh day is a sabbath to Jehovah your God. You must not do any work, you nor your son nor your daughter, your slave man nor your slave girl nor your domestic animal nor your alien resident who is inside your gates. 11 For in six days Jehovah made the heavens and the earth, the sea and everything that is in them, and he proceeded to rest on the seventh day. That is why Jehovah blessed the sabbath day and proceeded to make it sacred.

12 “Honor your father and your mother in order that your days may prove long upon the ground that Jehovah your God is giving you.

13 “You must not murder.

14 “You must not commit adultery.

15 “You must not steal.

16 “You must not testify falsely as a witness against your fellowman.

17 “You must not desire your fellowman’s house. You must not desire your fellowman’s wife, nor his slave man nor his slave girl nor his bull nor his ass nor anything that belongs to your fellowman.”

18 Now all the people were seeing the thunders and the lightning flashes and the sound of the horn and the mountain smoking. When the people got to see it, then they quivered and stood at a distance. 19 And they began to say to Moses: “You speak with us, and let us listen; but let not God speak with us for fear we may die.” 20 So Moses said to the people: “Do not be afraid, because for the sake of putting YOU to the test the true God has come, and in order that the fear of him may continue before YOUR faces that YOU may not sin.” 21 And the people kept standing at a distance, but Moses went near to the dark cloud mass where the true God was.

22 And Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “This is what you are to say to the sons of Israel, ‘YOU yourselves have seen that it was from the heavens I spoke with YOU. 23 YOU must not make along with me gods of silver, and YOU must not make gods of gold for yourselves. 24 An altar of ground you are to make for me, and you must sacrifice upon it your burnt offerings and your communion sacrifices, your flock and your herd. In every place where I shall cause my name to be remembered I shall come to you and shall certainly bless you. 25 And if you should make an altar of stones for me, you must not build them as hewn stones. In the event that you do wield your chisel upon it, then you will profane it. 26 And you must not go up by steps to my altar, that your private parts may not be exposed upon it.’

Exodus

26 “And the tabernacle you are to make of ten tent cloths, of fine twisted linen and blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material. With cherubs, the work of an embroiderer, you will make them. 2 The length of each tent cloth is twenty-eight cubits and the width of each tent cloth is four cubits. There is one measure for all the tent cloths. 3 Five tent cloths are to form a series with the one joined to the other, and five tent cloths a series with the one joined to the other. 4 And you must make loops of blue thread upon the edge of the one tent cloth at the end of the series; and you are to do the same upon the edge of the outermost tent cloth at the other place of junction. 5 You will make fifty loops on the one tent cloth, and fifty loops you will make on the extremity of the tent cloth that is at the other place of junction, the loops being opposite one to the other. 6 And you must make fifty hooks of gold and join the tent cloths one to the other by means of the hooks, and it must become one tabernacle.

7 “And you must make cloths of goat’s hair for the tent upon the tabernacle. You will make eleven tent cloths. 8 The length of each tent cloth is thirty cubits, and the width of each tent cloth is four cubits. There is one measure for the eleven tent cloths. 9 And you must join five tent cloths by themselves and six tent cloths by themselves, and you must fold double the sixth tent cloth at the forefront of the tent. 10 And you must make fifty loops upon the edge of the one tent cloth, the outermost one in the series, and fifty loops upon the edge of the tent cloth at the other place of junction. 11 And you must make fifty hooks of copper and put the hooks in the loops and join the tent together, and it must become one. 12 And what remains over of the cloths of the tent is an overhanging. Half of the tent cloth that remains over is to hang over the back of the tabernacle. 13 And the cubit on this side and the cubit on that side in what remains over in the length of the cloths of the tent will serve as an overhanging on the sides of the tabernacle, to cover it on this side and on that.

14 “And you must make a covering for the tent of ram skins dyed red and a covering of sealskins up on top.

15 “And you must make the panel frames for the tabernacle of acacia wood, standing on end. 16 Ten cubits is the length of a panel frame, and a cubit and a half is the width of each panel frame. 17 Each panel frame has two tenons joined one to the other. That is the way you will do with all the panel frames of the tabernacle. 18 And you must make the panel frames for the tabernacle, twenty panel frames for the side toward the Neg′eb, to the south.

19 “And you will make forty socket pedestals of silver under the twenty panel frames; two socket pedestals under the one panel frame with its two tenons, and two socket pedestals under the other panel frame with its two tenons. 20 And for the other side of the tabernacle, the northern side, twenty panel frames, 21 and their forty socket pedestals of silver, two socket pedestals under the one panel frame and two socket pedestals under the other panel frame. 22 And for the rear sections of the tabernacle to the west you will make six panel frames. 23 And you will make two panel frames as corner posts of the tabernacle on its two rear sections. 24 And they should be duplicates at the bottom, and together they should be duplicates up to the top of each one at the first ring. That is the way it should be for the two of them. They will serve as two corner posts. 25 And there must be eight panel frames and their socket pedestals of silver, sixteen pedestals, two socket pedestals under the one panel frame and two socket pedestals under the other panel frame.

26 “And you must make bars of acacia wood, five for the panel frames of the one side of the tabernacle, 27 and five bars for the panel frames of the other side of the tabernacle and five bars for the panel frames of the side of the tabernacle for the two rear sections to the west. 28 And the middle bar at the center of the panel frames is running through from end to end.

29 “And you will overlay the panel frames with gold, and their rings you will make of gold as supports for the bars; and you must overlay the bars with gold. 30 And you must set up the tabernacle according to the plan of it that you have been shown in the mountain.

31 “And you must make a curtain of blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine twisted linen. He will make it with cherubs, the work of an embroiderer. 32 And you must put it upon four pillars of acacia overlaid with gold. Their pegs are of gold. They are upon four socket pedestals of silver. 33 And you must put the curtain under the hooks and bring the ark of the testimony there within the curtain; and the curtain must make a division for YOU between the Holy and the Most Holy. 34 And you must put the cover upon the ark of the testimony in the Most Holy.

35 “And you must set the table outside the curtain, and the lampstand opposite the table on the side of the tabernacle toward the south; and the table you will put on the north side. 36 And you must make a screen for the entrance of the tent of blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine twisted linen, the work of a weaver. 37 And you must make for the screen five pillars of acacia and overlay them with gold. Their pegs are of gold. And you must cast for them five socket pedestals of copper.

Exodus

30 “And you must make an altar as a place for burning incense; out of acacia wood you will make it. 2 A cubit in length and a cubit in width, it should be foursquare, and its height two cubits. Its horns extend out of it. 3 And you must overlay it with pure gold, its top surface and its sides round about and its horns; and you must make a border of gold round about for it. 4 You will also make for it two rings of gold. Down below its border upon two of its sides you will make them, upon two opposite sides of it, as they must serve as supports for the poles with which to carry it. 5 And you must make the poles of acacia wood and overlay them with gold. 6 And you must put it before the curtain that is near the ark of the testimony, before the cover that is over the Testimony, where I shall present myself to you.

7 “And Aaron must make perfumed incense smoke upon it. Morning by morning, when he dresses the lamps, he will make it smoke. 8 And when Aaron lights up the lamps between the two evenings, he will make it smoke. It is an incense constantly before Jehovah during YOUR generations. 9 YOU must not offer upon it illegitimate incense or a burnt offering or a grain offering; and YOU must not pour a drink offering upon it. 10 And Aaron must make atonement upon its horns once a year. With some of the blood of the sin offering of the atonement he will make atonement for it once a year during YOUR generations. It is most holy to Jehovah.”

11 And Jehovah went on to speak to Moses, saying: 12 “Whenever you take the sum of the sons of Israel as a census of them, then they must each give a ransom for his soul to Jehovah when taking a census of them, that there may come to be no plague upon them when taking a census of them. 13 This is what all those will give who pass over to those numbered: a half shekel by the shekel of the holy place. Twenty ge′rahs equal a shekel. A half shekel is the contribution to Jehovah. 14 Everyone passing over to those registered from twenty years old and upward will give Jehovah’s contribution. 15 The rich should not give more, and the lowly must not give less than the half shekel, in order to give Jehovah’s contribution so as to make atonement for YOUR souls. 16 And you must take the silver money of the atonement from the sons of Israel and give it in behalf of the service of the tent of meeting, that it may indeed serve as a memorial before Jehovah for the sons of Israel, to make atonement for YOUR souls.”

17 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses, saying: 18 “You must make a basin of copper and its stand of copper for washing, and you must put it between the tent of meeting and the altar and put water into it. 19 And Aaron and his sons must wash their hands and their feet at it. 20 When they go into the tent of meeting they will wash with water that they may not die, or when they go near the altar to minister in order to make an offering made by fire smoke to Jehovah. 21 And they must wash their hands and their feet that they may not die, and it must serve as a regulation to time indefinite for them, for him and his offspring throughout their generations.”

22 And Jehovah continued to speak to Moses, saying: 23 “As for you, take to yourself the choicest perfumes: myrrh in congealed drops five hundred units, and sweet cinnamon in half that amount, two hundred and fifty units, and sweet calamus two hundred and fifty units, 24 and cassia five hundred units by the shekel of the holy place, and olive oil a hin. 25 Then you must make out of it a holy anointing oil, an ointment, a mixture that is the work of an ointment maker. It is to be a holy anointing oil.

26 “And you must anoint with it the tent of meeting and the ark of the testimony, 27 and the table and all its utensils and the lampstand and its utensils and the altar of incense, 28 and the altar of burnt offering and all its utensils and the basin and its stand. 29 And you must sanctify them that they may indeed become most holy. Anyone touching them is to be holy. 30 And you will anoint Aaron and his sons, and you must sanctify them for acting as priests to me.

31 “And you will speak to the sons of Israel, saying, ‘This is to continue as a holy anointing oil to me during YOUR generations. 32 It is not to be rubbed in the flesh of mankind, and with its composition YOU must not make any like it. It is something holy. It is to continue as something holy for YOU. 33 Anyone who makes an ointment like it and who puts some of it upon a stranger must be cut off from his people.’”

34 And Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “Take to yourself perfumes: stacte drops and onycha and perfumed galbanum and pure frankincense. There should be the same portion of each. 35 And you must make it into an incense, a spice mixture, the work of an ointment maker, salted, pure, something holy. 36 And you must pound some of it into fine powder and put some of it before the Testimony in the tent of meeting, where I shall present myself to you. It should be most holy to YOU people. 37 And the incense that you will make with this composition, YOU must not make for yourselves. For you it is to continue as something holy to Jehovah. 38 Whoever makes any like it to enjoy its smell must be cut off from his people.”

Exodus

33 And Jehovah said further to Moses: “Go, move up from here, you and the people whom you led up out of the land of Egypt, to the land about which I swore to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, saying, ‘To your seed I shall give it.’ 2 And I will send an angel ahead of you and drive out the Ca′naan·ites, the Am′or·ites, and the Hit′tites and the Per′iz·zites, the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites; 3 to a land flowing with milk and honey, for I shall not go up in the midst of you, because you are a stiff-necked people, that I may not exterminate you on the way.”

4 When the people got to hear this evil word, they began to mourn; and none of them put his ornaments on himself. 5 And Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “Say to the sons of Israel, ‘YOU are a stiff-necked people. In one moment I could go up into the midst of you and certainly exterminate you. So now put down your ornaments off yourself, as I want to know what I am going to do to you.’” 6 And the sons of Israel went stripping their ornaments off themselves from Mount Ho′reb onward.

7 As for Moses, he proceeded to take his tent away and he pitched it outside the camp, far away from the camp; and he called it a tent of meeting. And it occurred that everyone inquiring of Jehovah would go out to the tent of meeting, which was outside the camp. 8 And it occurred that as soon as Moses went out to the tent, all the people would rise, and they stationed themselves each one at the entrance of his own tent, and they gazed after Moses until he went into the tent. 9 It also occurred that as soon as Moses had gone into the tent, the pillar of cloud would come down, and it stood at the entrance of the tent and he spoke with Moses. 10 And all the people saw the pillar of cloud standing at the entrance of the tent, and all the people rose and bowed down each one at the entrance of his own tent. 11 And Jehovah spoke to Moses face to face, just as a man would speak to his fellow. When he returned to the camp, his minister Joshua, the son of Nun, as attendant, would not withdraw from the midst of the tent.

12 Now Moses said to Jehovah: “See, you are saying to me, ‘Lead this people up,’ but you yourself have not let me know whom you will send with me. Moreover, you yourself have said, ‘I do know you by name and, besides, you have found favor in my eyes.’ 13 And now, if, please, I have found favor in your eyes, make me know, please, your ways, that I may know you, in order that I may find favor in your eyes. And consider that this nation is your people.” 14 So he said: “My own person will go along and I shall certainly give you rest.” 15 At this he said to him: “If your own person is not going along, do not lead us up from here. 16 And by what, now, will it be known that I have found favor in your eyes, I and your people? Is it not by your going along with us, in that I and your people have been made distinct from all the other people who are upon the surface of the ground?”

17 And Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “This thing, too, of which you have spoken, I shall do, because you have found favor in my eyes and I know you by name.” 18 At this he said: “Cause me to see, please, your glory.” 19 But he said: “I myself shall cause all my goodness to pass before your face, and I will declare the name of Jehovah before you; and I will favor the one whom I may favor, and I will show mercy to the one to whom I may show mercy.” 20 And he added: “You are not able to see my face, because no man may see me and yet live.”

21 And Jehovah said further: “Here is a place with me, and you must station yourself upon the rock. 22 And it has to occur that while my glory is passing by I must place you in a hole in the rock, and I must put my palm over you as a screen until I have passed by. 23 After that I must take my palm away, and you will indeed see my back. But my face may not be seen.”

Exodus

36 “And Bez′al·el must work, also O·ho′li·ab and every wise-hearted man to whom Jehovah has given wisdom and understanding in these things in order to know how to do all the work of the holy service according to all that Jehovah has commanded.”

2 And Moses proceeded to call Bez′al·el and O·ho′li·ab and every wise-hearted man into whose heart Jehovah had put wisdom, everyone whose heart impelled him to approach the work in order to do it. 3 Then they took from before Moses all the contribution that the sons of Israel had brought for the work of the holy service so as to do it, and, as for the latter, they still brought to him a voluntary offering morning after morning.

4 And all the wise ones who were doing all the holy work began to come, one man after another, from their work that they were doing, 5 and to say to Moses: “The people are bringing much more than what the service needs for the work that Jehovah has commanded to be done.” 6 So Moses commanded that they should cause an announcement to pass through the camp, saying: “Men and women, do not produce any more stuff for the holy contribution.” With that the people were restrained from bringing it in. 7 And the stuff proved to be enough for all the work to be done, and more than enough.

8 And all the wise-hearted among those doing the work went making the tabernacle, the ten tent cloths of fine twisted linen and blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material; with cherubs, the work of an embroiderer, he made them. 9 The length of each tent cloth was twenty-eight cubits, and the width of each tent cloth four cubits. There was one measure for all the tent cloths. 10 Then he joined five tent cloths one to another, and the five other tent cloths he joined one to another. 11 After that he made loops of blue thread upon the edge of the one tent cloth at the junction end. He did the same on the edge of the outermost tent cloth at the other place of junction. 12 He made fifty loops on the one tent cloth, and he made fifty loops on the extremity of the tent cloth that was at the other place of junction, the loops being opposite one another. 13 Finally he made fifty hooks of gold and joined the tent cloths to one another by the hooks, so that it became one tabernacle.

14 And he went on to make tent cloths of goat’s hair for the tent upon the tabernacle. Eleven tent cloths were what he made. 15 The length of each tent cloth was thirty cubits, and the width of each tent cloth four cubits. There was one measure for the eleven tent cloths. 16 Then he joined five tent cloths together by themselves and the six other tent cloths by themselves. 17 Next he made fifty loops upon the edge of the outermost tent cloth at the place of junction, and he made fifty loops upon the edge of the other tent cloth that joined with it. 18 After that he made fifty hooks of copper for joining the tent together to become one piece.

19 And he proceeded to make a covering for the tent out of ram skins dyed red and a covering out of sealskins up on top.

20 Then he made the panel frames for the tabernacle out of acacia wood, standing on end. 21 Ten cubits was the length of a panel frame, and one cubit and a half the width of each panel frame. 22 Each panel frame had two tenons fitted one to the other. That is the way he did to all the panel frames of the tabernacle. 23 So he made the panel frames for the tabernacle, twenty panel frames for the side toward the Neg′eb, to the south. 24 And he made forty socket pedestals of silver for beneath the twenty panel frames, two socket pedestals beneath the one panel frame with its two tenons and two socket pedestals beneath the other panel frame with its two tenons. 25 And for the other side of the tabernacle, the northern side, he made twenty panel frames 26 and their forty socket pedestals of silver, two socket pedestals beneath the one panel frame and two socket pedestals beneath the other panel frame.

27 And for the rear sections of the tabernacle to the west he made six panel frames. 28 And he made two panel frames as corner posts of the tabernacle on its two rear sections. 29 And they proved to be duplicates at the bottom and together they came to be twins to the top of each one at the first ring. That is what he did to them both, to the two corner posts. 30 So they amounted to eight panel frames and their socket pedestals of silver to sixteen, two socket pedestals next to two socket pedestals beneath each panel frame.

31 And he went on to make bars of acacia wood, five for the panel frames of the one side of the tabernacle 32 and five bars for the panel frames of the other side of the tabernacle and five bars for the panel frames of the tabernacle for the two rear sections to the west. 33 Then he made the middle bar to run through at the middle of the panel frames from one end to the other. 34 And he overlaid the panel frames with gold, and he made their rings of gold as supports for the bars, and he went on to overlay the bars with gold.

35 And he proceeded to make a curtain of blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine twisted linen. With the work of an embroiderer he made it with cherubs. 36 Then he made for it four acacia pillars and overlaid them with gold, their pegs being of gold, and cast four socket pedestals of silver for them. 37 And he went on to make a screen for the entrance of the tent out of blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple and coccus scarlet material and fine twisted linen, the work of a weaver, 38 and its five pillars and their pegs. And he overlaid their tops and their joints with gold, but their five socket pedestals were of copper.

Leviticus

2 “‘Now in case some soul would present as an offering a grain offering to Jehovah, his offering should prove to be fine flour; and he must pour oil over it and put frankincense upon it. 2 And he must bring it to the sons of Aaron, the priests, and the priest must grasp from it his handful of its fine flour and its oil along with all its frankincense; and he must make it smoke as a remembrancer of it upon the altar, as an offering made by fire of a restful odor to Jehovah. 3 And what is left of the grain offering belongs to Aaron and his sons, as something most holy from Jehovah’s offerings made by fire.

4 “‘And in case you would present as an offering a grain offering in the way of something baked in the oven, it should be of fine flour, unfermented ring-shaped cakes moistened with oil or unfermented wafers smeared with oil.

5 “‘And if your offering is a grain offering from off the griddle, it should prove to be of fine flour moistened with oil, unfermented. 6 There should be a breaking of it up into pieces, and you must pour oil upon it. It is a grain offering.

7 “‘And if your offering is a grain offering out of the deep-fat kettle, it should be made of fine flour with oil. 8 And you must bring the grain offering that was made of these to Jehovah; and it must be presented to the priest and he must bring it near to the altar. 9 And the priest must lift off some of the grain offering as a remembrancer of it and must make it smoke on the altar, as an offering made by fire of a restful odor to Jehovah. 10 And what is left of the grain offering belongs to Aaron and his sons, as something most holy of Jehovah’s offerings by fire.

11 “‘No grain offering that YOU will present to Jehovah should be made a leavened thing, because YOU must make no sourdough and no honey at all smoke as an offering made by fire to Jehovah.

12 “‘As an offering of the firstfruits, YOU will present them to Jehovah, and they must not come up onto the altar for a restful odor.

13 “‘And every offering of your grain offering you will season with salt; and you must not allow the salt of the covenant of your God to be missing upon your grain offering. Along with every offering of yours you will present salt.

14 “‘And if you would present the grain offering of the first ripe fruits to Jehovah, you should present green ears roasted with fire, the grits of new grain, as the grain offering of your first ripe fruits. 15 And you must put oil upon it and place frankincense upon it. It is a grain offering. 16 And the priest must make the remembrancer of it smoke, that is, some of its grits and oil, along with all its frankincense, as an offering made by fire to Jehovah.

Leviticus

8 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses, saying: 2 “Take Aaron and his sons with him and the garments and the anointing oil and the bull of the sin offering and the two rams and the basket of unfermented cakes, 3 and make all the assembly congregate at the entrance of the tent of meeting.”

4 Then Moses did just as Jehovah had commanded him, and the assembly congregated at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 5 Moses now said to the assembly: “This is the thing that Jehovah has given command to do.” 6 So Moses brought Aaron and his sons near and washed them with water. 7 After that he put the robe upon him and girded him with the sash and clothed him with the sleeveless coat and put the eph′od upon him and girded him with the girdle of the eph′od and bound it closely to him with it. 8 Next he placed the breastpiece upon him and put in the breastpiece the U′rim and the Thum′mim. 9 Then he placed the turban upon his head and placed upon the turban at the forefront of it the shining plate of gold, the holy sign of dedication, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

10 Moses now took the anointing oil and anointed the tabernacle and all that was in it and sanctified them. 11 After that he spattered some of it seven times upon the altar and anointed the altar and all its utensils and the basin and its stand so as to sanctify them. 12 Finally he poured some of the anointing oil upon Aaron’s head and anointed him so as to sanctify him.

13 Moses then brought Aaron’s sons near and clothed them with robes and girded them with sashes and wrapped the headgear upon them, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

14 Then he led up the bull of the sin offering and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the bull of the sin offering. 15 And Moses proceeded to slaughter it and take the blood and put it with his finger upon the horns of the altar round about and purify the altar from sin, but the rest of the blood he poured at the base of the altar, that he might sanctify it to make atonement upon it. 16 After that he took all the fat that was upon the intestines, and the appendage of the liver and the two kidneys and their fat and Moses made them smoke upon the altar. 17 And he had the bull and its skin and its flesh and its dung burned with fire outside the camp, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

18 He now brought the ram of the burnt offering near, and Aaron and his sons then laid their hands upon the head of the ram. 19 After that Moses slaughtered it and sprinkled the blood round about upon the altar. 20 And he cut up the ram into its pieces, and Moses proceeded to make the head and the pieces and the suet smoke. 21 And the intestines and the shanks he washed with water, and Moses then made the entire ram smoke upon the altar. It was a burnt offering for a restful odor. It was an offering made by fire to Jehovah, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

22 Then he brought the second ram, the ram of the installation, near, and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the ram’s head. 23 After that Moses slaughtered it and took some of its blood and put it upon the lobe of Aaron’s right ear and upon the thumb of his right hand and upon the big toe of his right foot. 24 Next Moses brought Aaron’s sons near and put some of the blood upon the lobe of their right ear and upon the thumb of their right hand and upon the big toe of their right foot; but Moses sprinkled the rest of the blood round about upon the altar.

25 Then he took the fat and the fat tail and all the fat that was upon the intestines, and the appendage of the liver and the two kidneys and their fat and the right leg. 26 And out of the basket of unfermented cakes that was before Jehovah he took one unfermented ring-shaped cake and one ring-shaped cake of oiled bread and one wafer. He then placed them upon the fatty pieces and the right leg. 27 After that he put all of them upon the palms of Aaron and the palms of his sons and began to wave them to and fro as a wave offering before Jehovah. 28 Then Moses took them off their palms and made them smoke upon the altar on top of the burnt offering. They were an installation sacrifice for a restful odor. It was an offering made by fire to Jehovah.

29 And Moses proceeded to take the breast and to wave it to and fro as a wave offering before Jehovah. From the installation ram it became the portion for Moses, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

30 After that Moses took some of the anointing oil and some of the blood that was upon the altar and spattered it upon Aaron and his garments and upon his sons and the garments of his sons with him. Thus he sanctified Aaron and his garments and his sons and the garments of his sons with him.

31 Then Moses said to Aaron and his sons: “Boil the flesh at the entrance of the tent of meeting, and there is where YOU will eat it and the bread that is in the installation basket, just as I was given the command, saying, ‘Aaron and his sons will eat it.’ 32 And what is left over of the flesh and the bread YOU will burn with fire. 33 And YOU must not go out from the entrance of the tent of meeting for seven days, until the day of fulfilling the days of YOUR installation, because it will take seven days to fill YOUR hand with power. 34 Just as it has been done this day, Jehovah has commanded to be done so as to make atonement for YOU. 35 And YOU will stay at the entrance of the tent of meeting day and night for seven days, and YOU must keep the obligatory watch of Jehovah, that YOU may not die; for so I have been commanded.”

36 And Aaron and his sons proceeded to do all the things that Jehovah had commanded by means of Moses.

Leviticus

17 And Jehovah went on to speak to Moses, saying: 2 “Speak to Aaron and his sons and all the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘This is the thing that Jehovah has commanded, saying:

3 “‘“As for any man of the house of Israel who slaughters a bull or a young ram or a goat in the camp or who slaughters it outside the camp 4 and does not actually bring it to the entrance of the tent of meeting to present it as an offering to Jehovah before the tabernacle of Jehovah, bloodguilt will be counted to that man. He has shed blood, and that man must be cut off from among his people, 5 in order that the sons of Israel may bring their sacrifices, which they are sacrificing in the open field, and they must bring them to Jehovah to the entrance of the tent of meeting to the priest, and they must sacrifice these as communion sacrifices to Jehovah. 6 And the priest must sprinkle the blood upon Jehovah’s altar at the entrance of the tent of meeting, and he must make the fat smoke as a restful odor to Jehovah. 7 So they should no longer sacrifice their sacrifices to the goat-shaped demons with which they are having immoral intercourse. This will serve as a statute to time indefinite for YOU, throughout YOUR generations.”’

8 “And you should say to them, ‘As for any man of the house of Israel or some alien resident who may be residing as an alien in YOUR midst who offers up a burnt offering or a sacrifice 9 and does not bring it to the entrance of the tent of meeting to render it to Jehovah, that man must be cut off from his people.

10 “‘As for any man of the house of Israel or some alien resident who is residing as an alien in YOUR midst who eats any sort of blood, I shall certainly set my face against the soul that is eating the blood, and I shall indeed cut him off from among his people. 11 For the soul of the flesh is in the blood, and I myself have put it upon the altar for YOU to make atonement for YOUR souls, because it is the blood that makes atonement by the soul in it. 12 That is why I have said to the sons of Israel: “No soul of YOU must eat blood and no alien resident who is residing as an alien in YOUR midst should eat blood.”

13 “‘As for any man of the sons of Israel or some alien resident who is residing as an alien in YOUR midst who in hunting catches a wild beast or a fowl that may be eaten, he must in that case pour its blood out and cover it with dust. 14 For the soul of every sort of flesh is its blood by the soul in it. Consequently I said to the sons of Israel: “YOU must not eat the blood of any sort of flesh, because the soul of every sort of flesh is its blood. Anyone eating it will be cut off.” 15 As for any soul that eats a body already dead or something torn by a wild beast, whether a native or an alien resident, he must in that case wash his garments and bathe in water and be unclean until the evening; and he must be clean. 16 But if he will not wash them and will not bathe his flesh, he must then answer for his error.’”

Leviticus

19 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses, saying: 2 “Speak to the entire assembly of the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘YOU should prove yourselves holy, because I Jehovah YOUR God am holy.

3 “‘YOU should fear each one his mother and his father, and my sabbaths YOU should keep. I am Jehovah YOUR God. 4 Do not turn yourselves to valueless gods, and YOU must not make molten gods for yourselves. I am Jehovah YOUR God.

5 “‘Now in case YOU should sacrifice a communion sacrifice to Jehovah, YOU should sacrifice it to gain approval for yourselves. 6 On the day of YOUR sacrifice and directly the next day it should be eaten, but what is left over till the third day should be burned in the fire. 7 If, though, it should at all be eaten on the third day, it is a foul thing. It will not be accepted with approval. 8 And the one eating it will answer for his error, because he has profaned a holy thing of Jehovah; and that soul must be cut off from his people.

9 “‘And when YOU people reap the harvest of YOUR land, you must not reap the edge of your field completely, and the gleaning of your harvest you must not pick up. 10 Also, you must not gather the leftovers of your vineyard, and you must not pick up the scattered grapes of your vineyard. For the afflicted one and the alien resident you should leave them. I am Jehovah YOUR God.

11 “‘YOU people must not steal, and YOU must not deceive, and YOU must not deal falsely anyone with his associate. 12 And YOU must not swear in my name to a lie, so that you do profane the name of your God. I am Jehovah. 13 You must not defraud your fellow, and you must not rob. The wages of a hired laborer should not stay all night with you until morning.

14 “‘You must not call down evil upon a deaf man, and before a blind man you must not put an obstacle; and you must be in fear of your God. I am Jehovah.

15 “‘YOU people must not do injustice in the judgment. You must not treat the lowly with partiality, and you must not prefer the person of a great one. With justice you should judge your associate.

16 “‘You must not go around among your people for the sake of slandering. You must not stand up against your fellow’s blood. I am Jehovah.

17 “‘You must not hate your brother in your heart. You should by all means reprove your associate, that you may not bear sin along with him.

18 “‘You must not take vengeance nor have a grudge against the sons of your people; and you must love your fellow as yourself. I am Jehovah.

19 “‘YOU people should keep my statutes: You must not interbreed your domestic animals of two sorts. You must not sow your field with seeds of two sorts, and you must not put upon yourself a garment of two sorts of thread, mixed together.

20 “‘Now in case a man lies down with a woman and has an emission of semen, when she is a maidservant designated for another man, and she has not in any way been redeemed nor has freedom been given her, punishment should take place. They should not be put to death, because she was not set free. 21 And he must bring his guilt offering to Jehovah to the entrance of the tent of meeting, a ram of guilt offering. 22 And the priest must make atonement for him with the ram of the guilt offering before Jehovah for his sin that he committed; and his sin that he committed must be forgiven him.

23 “‘And in case YOU people come into the land, and YOU must plant any tree for food, YOU must also consider its fruitage impure as its “foreskin.” For three years it will continue uncircumcised for YOU. It should not be eaten. 24 But in the fourth year all its fruit will become a holy thing of festal exultation to Jehovah. 25 And in the fifth year YOU may eat its fruit in order to add its produce to yourselves. I am Jehovah YOUR God.

26 “‘YOU must eat nothing along with blood.

“‘YOU must not look for omens, and YOU must not practice magic.

27 “‘YOU must not cut YOUR sidelocks short around, and you must not destroy the extremity of your beard.

28 “‘And YOU must not make cuts in YOUR flesh for a deceased soul, and YOU must not put tattoo marking upon yourselves. I am Jehovah.

29 “‘Do not profane your daughter by making her a prostitute, in order that the land may not commit prostitution and the land actually be filled with loose morals.

30 “‘My sabbaths YOU should keep, and YOU should stand in awe of my sanctuary. I am Jehovah.

31 “‘Do not turn yourselves to the spirit mediums, and do not consult professional foretellers of events, so as to become unclean by them. I am Jehovah YOUR God.

32 “‘Before gray hair you should rise up, and you must show consideration for the person of an old man, and you must be in fear of your God. I am Jehovah.

33 “‘And in case an alien resident resides with you as an alien in YOUR land, YOU must not mistreat him. 34 The alien resident who resides as an alien with YOU should become to YOU like a native of YOURS; and you must love him as yourself, for YOU became alien residents in the land of Egypt. I am Jehovah YOUR God.

35 “‘YOU must not commit injustice in judging, in measuring, in weighing or in measuring liquids. 36 YOU should prove to have accurate scales, accurate weights, an accurate e′phah and an accurate hin. Jehovah YOUR God I am, who have brought YOU out of the land of Egypt. 37 So YOU must keep all my statutes and all my judicial decisions, and YOU must do them. I am Jehovah.’”

Leviticus

24 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses, saying: 2 “Command the sons of Israel that they get for you pure, beaten olive oil for the luminary, to light up the lamp constantly. 3 Outside the curtain of the Testimony in the tent of meeting Aaron should set it in order from evening to morning before Jehovah constantly. It is a statute to time indefinite during YOUR generations. 4 Upon the lampstand of pure gold he should set the lamps in order before Jehovah constantly.

5 “And you must take fine flour and bake it up into twelve ring-shaped cakes. Two tenths of an e′phah should go to each ring-shaped cake. 6 And you must place them in two sets of layers, six to the layer set, upon the table of pure gold before Jehovah. 7 And you must put pure frankincense upon each layer set, and it must serve as the bread for a remembrancer, an offering made by fire to Jehovah. 8 On one sabbath day after another he should set it in order before Jehovah constantly. It is a covenant to time indefinite with the sons of Israel. 9 And it must become Aaron’s and his sons’, and they must eat it in a holy place, because it is something most holy for him from Jehovah’s offerings made by fire, as a regulation to time indefinite.”

10 Now a son of an Israelite woman, who, however, was the son of an Egyptian man, went out into the midst of the sons of Israel, and the son of the Israelitess and an Israelite man began to struggle with each other in the camp. 11 And the son of the Israelite woman began to abuse the Name and to call down evil upon it. So they brought him to Moses. Incidentally, his mother’s name was She·lo′mith, the daughter of Dib′ri of the tribe of Dan. 12 Then they committed him into custody till there should be a distinct declaration to them according to the saying of Jehovah.

13 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses, saying: 14 “Bring forth the one who called down evil to the outside of the camp; and all those who heard him must lay their hands upon his head, and the entire assembly must pelt him with stones. 15 And you should speak to the sons of Israel, saying, ‘In case any man calls down evil upon his God, he must then answer for his sin. 16 So the abuser of Jehovah’s name should be put to death without fail. The entire assembly should without fail pelt him with stones. The alien resident the same as the native should be put to death for his abusing the Name.

17 “‘And in case a man strikes any soul of mankind fatally, he should be put to death without fail. 18 And the fatal striker of the soul of a domestic animal should make compensation for it, soul for soul. 19 And in case a man should cause a defect in his associate, then just as he has done, so it should be done to him. 20 Fracture for fracture, eye for eye, tooth for tooth; the same sort of defect he may cause in the man, that is what should be caused in him. 21 And the fatal striker of a beast should make compensation for it, but the fatal striker of a man should be put to death.

22 “‘One judicial decision should hold good for YOU. The alien resident should prove to be the same as the native, because I am Jehovah YOUR God.’”

23 After that Moses spoke to the sons of Israel, and they brought forth the one who had called down evil to the outside of the camp, and they pelted him with stones. Thus the sons of Israel did just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

Leviticus

26 “‘YOU must not make valueless gods for yourselves, and YOU must not set up a carved image or a sacred pillar for yourselves, and YOU must not put a stone as a showpiece in YOUR land in order to bow down toward it; for I am Jehovah YOUR God. 2 YOU should keep my sabbaths and stand in awe of my sanctuary. I am Jehovah.

3 “‘If YOU continue walking in my statutes and keeping my commandments and YOU do carry them out, 4 I shall also certainly give YOUR showers of rain at their proper time, and the land will indeed give its yield, and the tree of the field will give its fruit. 5 And YOUR threshing will certainly reach to YOUR grape gathering, and the grape gathering will reach to the sowing of seed; and YOU will indeed eat YOUR bread to satisfaction and dwell in security in YOUR land. 6 And I will put peace in the land, and YOU will indeed lie down, with no one making YOU tremble; and I will make the injurious wild beast cease out of the land, and a sword will not pass through YOUR land. 7 And YOU will certainly chase YOUR enemies, and they will indeed fall before YOU by the sword. 8 And five of YOU will certainly chase a hundred, and a hundred of YOU will chase ten thousand, and YOUR enemies will indeed fall before YOU by the sword.

9 “‘And I will turn myself to YOU and make YOU fruitful and multiply YOU, and I will carry out my covenant with YOU. 10 And YOU will certainly eat the old of the preceding year, and YOU will bring out the old ahead of the new. 11 And I shall certainly put my tabernacle in the midst of YOU, and my soul will not abhor YOU. 12 And I shall indeed walk in the midst of YOU and prove myself YOUR God, and YOU, on YOUR part, will prove yourselves my people. 13 I am Jehovah YOUR God, who brought YOU out of the land of Egypt from acting as slaves to them, and I proceeded to break the bars of YOUR yoke and make YOU walk erect.

14 “‘However, if YOU will not listen to me nor do all these commandments, 15 and if YOU will reject my statutes, and if YOUR souls will abhor my judicial decisions so as not to do all my commandments, to the extent of YOUR violating my covenant, 16 then I, for my part, shall do the following to YOU, and in punishment I shall certainly bring upon YOU disturbance with tuberculosis and burning fever, causing the eyes to fail and making the soul pine away. And YOU will simply sow YOUR seed for nothing, as YOUR enemies will certainly eat it up. 17 And I shall indeed set my face against YOU, and YOU will certainly be defeated before YOUR enemies; and those who hate YOU will just tread down upon YOU, and YOU will actually flee when no one is pursuing YOU.

18 “‘If, though, despite these things, YOU will not listen to me, I shall then have to chastise YOU seven times as much for YOUR sins. 19 And I shall have to break the pride of YOUR strength and make YOUR heavens like iron and YOUR earth like copper. 20 And YOUR power will simply be expended for nothing, as YOUR earth will not give its yield, and the tree of the earth will not give its fruit.

21 “‘But if YOU keep walking in opposition to me and not wishing to listen to me, I shall then have to inflict seven times more blows upon YOU according to YOUR sins. 22 And I will send the wild beasts of the field among YOU, and they will certainly bereave YOU of children and cut off YOUR domestic animals and reduce the number of YOU, and YOUR roads will actually be desolated.

23 “‘Nevertheless, if with these things YOU do not let yourselves be corrected by me and YOU just have to walk in opposition to me, 24 I, yes, I, shall then have to walk in opposition to YOU; and I, even I, shall have to strike YOU seven times for YOUR sins. 25 And I shall certainly bring upon YOU a sword wreaking vengeance for the covenant; and YOU will indeed gather yourselves into YOUR cities, and I shall certainly send pestilence into the midst of YOU, and YOU must be given into the hand of an enemy. 26 When I have broken for YOU the rods around which ring-shaped loaves are suspended, ten women will then actually bake YOUR bread in but one oven and give back YOUR bread by weight; and YOU must eat but YOU will not be satisfied.

27 “‘If, however, with this YOU will not listen to me and YOU just must walk in opposition to me, 28 I shall then have to walk in heated opposition to YOU, and I, yes, I, shall have to chastise YOU seven times for YOUR sins. 29 So YOU will have to eat the flesh of YOUR sons, and YOU will eat the flesh of YOUR daughters. 30 And I shall certainly annihilate YOUR sacred high places and cut off YOUR incense stands and lay YOUR own carcasses upon the carcasses of YOUR dungy idols; and my soul will simply abhor YOU. 31 And I shall indeed give YOUR cities to the sword and lay YOUR sanctuaries desolate, and I shall not smell YOUR restful odors. 32 And I, for my part, will lay the land desolate, and YOUR enemies who are dwelling in it will simply stare in amazement over it. 33 And YOU I shall scatter among the nations, and I will unsheathe a sword after YOU; and YOUR land must become a desolation, and YOUR cities will become a desolate ruin.

34 “‘At that time the land will pay off its sabbaths all the days of its lying desolated, while YOU are in the land of YOUR enemies. At that time the land will keep sabbath, as it must repay its sabbaths. 35 All the days of its lying desolated it will keep sabbath, for the reason that it did not keep sabbath during YOUR sabbaths when YOU were dwelling upon it.

36 “‘As for those remaining among YOU, I shall certainly bring timidity into their hearts in the lands of their enemies; and the sound of a leaf driven about will indeed chase them away, and they will actually flee as in flight from a sword and fall without anyone chasing. 37 And they will certainly stumble against one another as if from before a sword without anyone chasing, and for YOU there will prove to be no ability to stand in resistance before YOUR enemies. 38 And YOU must perish among the nations, and the land of YOUR enemies must eat YOU up. 39 As for those remaining among YOU, they will rot away because of their error in the lands of YOUR enemies. Yes, even because of the errors of their fathers, with them they will rot away. 40 And they will certainly confess their own error and the error of their fathers in their unfaithfulness when they behaved unfaithfully toward me, yes, even when they walked in opposition to me. 41 Yet I, for my part, proceeded to walk in opposition to them, and I had to bring them into the land of their enemies.

“‘Perhaps at that time their uncircumcised heart will be humbled, and at that time they will pay off their error. 42 And I shall indeed remember my covenant with Jacob; and even my covenant with Isaac and even my covenant with Abraham I shall remember, and the land I shall remember. 43 All the while the land was left abandoned by them and was paying off its sabbaths while it was lying desolated without them and they themselves were paying for their error, because, even because, they had rejected my judicial decisions, and their souls had abhorred my statutes. 44 And yet for all this, while they continue in the land of their enemies, I shall certainly not reject them nor abhor them so as to exterminate them, to violate my covenant with them; for I am Jehovah their God. 45 And I will remember in their behalf the covenant of the ancestors whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt under the eyes of the nations, in order to prove myself their God. I am Jehovah.’”

46 These are the regulations and the judicial decisions and the laws that Jehovah set between himself and the sons of Israel in Mount Si′nai by means of Moses.

Numbers

3 Now these were the generations of Aaron and Moses in the day that Jehovah spoke with Moses in Mount Si′nai. 2 And these were the names of Aaron’s sons: the firstborn Na′dab and A·bi′hu, El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar. 3 These were the names of Aaron’s sons, the anointed priests whose hands had been filled with power to act as priests. 4 However, Na′dab and A·bi′hu died before Jehovah when they offered illegitimate fire before Jehovah in the wilderness of Si′nai; and they did not come to have any sons. But El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar continued to act as priests along with Aaron their father.

5 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses, saying: 6 “Bring the tribe of Le′vi near, and you must stand them before Aaron the priest, and they must minister to him. 7 And they must keep their obligation to him and their obligation to all the assembly before the tent of meeting in discharging the service of the tabernacle. 8 And they must take care of all the utensils of the tent of meeting, even the obligation of the sons of Israel in discharging the service of the tabernacle. 9 And you must give the Levites to Aaron and his sons. They are given ones, given to him from the sons of Israel. 10 And you should appoint Aaron and his sons, and they must take care of their priesthood; and any stranger coming near should be put to death.”

11 And Jehovah continued to speak to Moses, saying: 12 “As for me, look! I do take the Levites from among the sons of Israel in place of all the firstborn opening the womb of the sons of Israel; and the Levites must become mine. 13 For every firstborn is mine. In the day that I struck every firstborn in the land of Egypt I sanctified to myself every firstborn in Israel from man to beast. They should become mine. I am Jehovah.”

14 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses in the wilderness of Si′nai, saying: 15 “Register the sons of Le′vi according to the house of their fathers by their families. Every male from a month old upward you should register.” 16 And Moses began to register them at the order of Jehovah, just as he had been commanded. 17 And these came to be the sons of Le′vi by their names: Ger′shon and Ko′hath and Me·rar′i.

18 Now these were the names of the sons of Ger′shon by their families: Lib′ni and Shim′e·i.

19 And the sons of Ko′hath by their families were Am′ram and Iz′har, He′bron and Uz′zi·el.

20 And the sons of Me·rar′i by their families were Mah′li and Mu′shi.

These were the families of the Levites according to the house of their fathers.

21 Of Ger′shon there were the family of the Lib′nites and the family of the Shim′e·ites. These were the families of the Ger′shon·ites. 22 Their registered ones were by number of all males from a month old upward. Their registered ones were seven thousand five hundred. 23 The families of the Ger′shon·ites were behind the tabernacle. They were encamped to the west. 24 And the chieftain of the paternal house for the Ger′shon·ites was E·li′a·saph the son of La′el. 25 And the obligation of the sons of Ger′shon in the tent of meeting was the tabernacle and the tent, its covering and the screen of the entrance of the tent of meeting, 26 and the hangings of the courtyard and the screen of the entrance of the courtyard that is round about the tabernacle and the altar, and its tent cords, for all its service.

27 And of Ko′hath there were the family of the Am′ram·ites and the family of the Iz′har·ites and the family of the He′bron·ites and the family of the Uz·zi′el·ites. These were the families of the Ko′hath·ites. 28 Among the number of all the males from a month old upward there were eight thousand six hundred, taking care of the obligation to the holy place. 29 The families of the sons of Ko′hath were encamped on the side of the tabernacle to the south. 30 And the chieftain of the paternal house for the families of the Ko′hath·ites was E·li·za′phan the son of Uz′zi·el. 31 And their obligation was the Ark and the table and the lampstand and the altars and the utensils of the holy place with which they would minister and the screen, and all its service.

32 And the chieftain of the chieftains of the Levites was El·e·a′zar the son of Aaron the priest, who had the oversight of those taking care of the obligation to the holy place.

33 Of Me·rar′i there were the family of the Mah′lites and the family of the Mu′shites. These were the families of Me·rar′i. 34 And their registered ones by the number of all the males from a month old upward were six thousand two hundred. 35 And the chieftain of the paternal house for the families of Me·rar′i was Zu′ri·el the son of Ab′i·ha·il. They were encamped on the side of the tabernacle toward the north. 36 And the oversight for which the sons of Me·rar′i were obligated was over the panel frames of the tabernacle and its bars and its pillars and its socket pedestals and all its utensils and all its service, 37 and the pillars of the courtyard round about and their socket pedestals and their tent pins and their tent cords.

38 And those camping before the tabernacle toward the east, before the tent of meeting toward the sunrising, were Moses and Aaron and his sons, those taking care of the obligation to the sanctuary, as the obligation for the sons of Israel. And any stranger coming near would be put to death.

39 All the registered ones of the Levites whom Moses and Aaron registered at the order of Jehovah by their families, all the males from a month old upward, were twenty-two thousand.

40 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Register all the firstborn males of the sons of Israel from a month old upward, and take the number of their names. 41 And you must take the Levites for me—I am Jehovah—in place of all the firstborn among the sons of Israel, and the domestic animals of the Levites in place of all the firstborn among the domestic animals of the sons of Israel.” 42 And Moses proceeded, just as Jehovah had commanded him, to register all the firstborn among the sons of Israel. 43 And all the firstborn males by the number of the names from a month old upward of their registered ones came to be twenty-two thousand two hundred and seventy-three.

44 And Jehovah continued to speak to Moses, saying: 45 “Take the Levites in place of all the firstborn among the sons of Israel, and the domestic animals of the Levites in place of their domestic animals; and the Levites must become mine. I am Jehovah. 46 And as the ransom price of the two hundred and seventy-three from the firstborn of the sons of Israel, who are in excess of the Levites, 47 you must take five shekels for each individual. In the shekel of the holy place you should take it. A shekel is twenty ge′rahs. 48 And you must give the money to Aaron and his sons as the ransom price of those who are in excess of them.” 49 So Moses took the money of the redemption price from those who were in excess of the ransom price of the Levites. 50 From the firstborn of the sons of Israel he took the money, a thousand three hundred and sixty-five shekels, in the shekel of the holy place. 51 Then Moses gave the money of the ransom price to Aaron and his sons according to the order of Jehovah, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

Numbers

4 Jehovah now spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying: 2 “There will be a taking of the sum of the sons of Ko′hath from among the sons of Le′vi, according to their families in the house of their fathers, 3 from thirty years old upward to fifty years old, all those going into the service group to do the work in the tent of meeting.

4 “This is the service of the sons of Ko′hath in the tent of meeting. It is something most holy: 5 And Aaron and his sons must come in when the camp is departing, and they must take down the screening curtain and must cover the ark of the testimony with it. 6 And they must put a covering of sealskins over it and spread out an entire cloth of blue on top and put in its poles.

7 “And they will spread out a cloth of blue over the table of showbread, and they must put upon it the dishes and the cups and the bowls and the pitchers of the drink offering; and the constant bread should continue on it. 8 And they must spread out a cloth of coccus scarlet over them, and they must cover it with a covering of sealskins and put in its poles. 9 And they must take a cloth of blue and cover the lampstand of the luminary and its lamps and its snuffers and its fire holders and all its vessels for oil with which they regularly minister to it. 10 And they must put it and all its utensils into a covering of sealskins and put it upon a bar. 11 And over the golden altar they will spread out a cloth of blue, and they must cover it with a covering of sealskins and put in its poles. 12 And they must take all the utensils of the ministry with which they regularly minister in the holy place, and they must put them in a cloth of blue and cover them with a covering of sealskins and put them upon a bar.

13 “And they must clear away the fatty ashes of the altar and spread out a cloth of wool dyed reddish purple over it. 14 And they must put upon it all its utensils with which they regularly minister at it, the fire holders, the forks and the shovels and the bowls, all the utensils of the altar; and they must spread out over it a covering of sealskins and put in its poles.

15 “And Aaron and his sons must finish covering the holy place and all the utensils of the holy place when the camp is departing, and after that the sons of Ko′hath will come in to carry them, but they must not touch the holy place so that they have to die. These things are the load of the sons of Ko′hath in the tent of meeting.

16 “And the oversight of El·e·a′zar the son of Aaron the priest is over the oil of the luminary and the perfumed incense and the constant grain offering and the anointing oil, the oversight of all the tabernacle and all that is in it, namely, the holy place and its utensils.”

17 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses and Aaron, saying: 18 “Do not let the tribe of the families of the Ko′hath·ites be cut off from among the Levites. 19 But do this for them that they may indeed keep alive and may not die for their approaching the most holy things. Aaron and his sons will come in, and they must assign them each one to his service and to his load. 20 And they must not come in to see the holy things for the least moment of time, and so they have to die.”

21 Then Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 22 “There will be a taking of the sum of the sons of Ger′shon, yes, them by the house of their fathers according to their families. 23 From thirty years old upward to fifty years you will register them, all who come to enter into the service group to render service in the tent of meeting. 24 This is the service of the families of the Ger′shon·ites as to serving and as to carrying. 25 And they must carry the tent cloths of the tabernacle and the tent of meeting, its covering and the sealskin covering that is on top over it, and the screen of the entrance of the tent of meeting, 26 and the hangings of the courtyard and the entrance screen of the gate of the courtyard that is round about the tabernacle and the altar, and their tent cords and all their service utensils, and all things with which work is regularly done. Thus they must serve. 27 At the order of Aaron and his sons all the service of the sons of the Ger′shon·ites should take place as regards all their loads and all their service, and YOU must assign all their loads to them by obligation. 28 This is the service of the families of the sons of the Ger′shon·ites in the tent of meeting, and their obligatory service is under the hand of Ith′a·mar the son of Aaron the priest.

29 “As for the sons of Me·rar′i, you will register them by their families in the house of their fathers. 30 From thirty years old upward to fifty years you will register them, all who enter into the service group to render the service of the tent of meeting. 31 And this is their obligation, their load, according to all their service in the tent of meeting: the panel frames of the tabernacle and its bars and its pillars and its socket pedestals, 32 and the pillars of the courtyard round about and their socket pedestals and their tent pins and their tent cords together with all their equipment and all their service. And by their names YOU will assign the equipment for which they are obligated, as their load. 33 This is the service of the families of the sons of Me·rar′i according to all their service in the tent of meeting, under the hand of Ith′a·mar the son of Aaron the priest.”

34 And Moses and Aaron and the chieftains of the assembly proceeded to register the sons of the Ko′hath·ites by their families and by the house of their fathers, 35 from thirty years old upward to fifty years, all who entered into the service group for the service in the tent of meeting. 36 And the ones registered of them by their families came to be two thousand seven hundred and fifty. 37 These are the registered ones of the families of the Ko′hath·ites, all those serving in the tent of meeting, whom Moses and Aaron registered at the order of Jehovah by means of Moses.

38 As for the registered ones of the sons of Ger′shon by their families and by the house of their fathers, 39 from thirty years old upward to fifty years, all who entered into the service group for the service in the tent of meeting, 40 the ones registered of them by their families, by the house of their fathers, came to be two thousand six hundred and thirty. 41 These were the registered ones of the families of the sons of Ger′shon, all those serving in the tent of meeting, whom Moses and Aaron registered at the order of Jehovah.

42 As for the registered ones of the families of the sons of Me·rar′i by their families, by the house of their fathers, 43 from thirty years old upward to fifty years old, all those entering into the service group for the service in the tent of meeting, 44 the ones registered of them by their families came to be three thousand two hundred. 45 These were the registered ones of the families of the sons of Me·rar′i, whom Moses and Aaron registered at the order of Jehovah by means of Moses.

46 All the registered ones whom Moses and Aaron and the chieftains of Israel registered as Levites by their families and by the house of their fathers, 47 from thirty years old upward to fifty years old, all those coming to render the laborious service and the service of carrying loads in the tent of meeting, 48 their registered ones came to be eight thousand five hundred and eighty. 49 At the order of Jehovah they were registered by means of Moses, each one according to his service and his load; and they were registered just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

Numbers

5 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses, saying: 2 “Command the sons of Israel that they send out of the camp every leprous person and everyone having a running discharge and everyone unclean by a deceased soul. 3 Whether a male or a female YOU should send them out. YOU should send them outside the camp, that they may not contaminate the camps of those in the midst of whom I am tabernacling.” 4 And the sons of Israel proceeded to do so, even to send them outside the camp. Just as Jehovah had spoken to Moses, so the sons of Israel did.

5 And Jehovah continued speaking to Moses, saying: 6 “Speak to the sons of Israel, ‘As for a man or a woman, in case they do any of all the sins of mankind in committing an act of unfaithfulness against Jehovah, that soul has also become guilty. 7 And they must confess their sin that they have done, and he must return the amount of his guilt in its principal, also adding a fifth of it to it, and he must give it to the one against whom he did wrong. 8 But if the latter has no near relative to whom to return the amount of the guilt, the amount of the guilt that is being returned to Jehovah belongs to the priest, except the ram of atonement with which he will make atonement for him.

9 “‘And every contribution of all the holy things of the sons of Israel, which they will present to the priest, should become his. 10 And the holy things of each one will remain his own. Whatever each one may give to the priest, that will become his.’”

11 And Jehovah went on to speak to Moses, saying: 12 “Speak to the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘In case any man’s wife turns aside in that she does commit an act of unfaithfulness against him, 13 and another man actually lies down with her and has an emission of semen, and it has been hidden from the eyes of her husband and has remained undiscovered, and she, on her part, has defiled herself but there is no witness against her, and she herself has not been caught; 14 and the spirit of jealousy has passed upon him, and he has become suspicious of his wife’s faithfulness, and she in fact has defiled herself, or the spirit of jealousy has passed upon him, and he has become suspicious of his wife’s faithfulness, but she in fact has not defiled herself; 15 then the man must bring his wife to the priest and bring her offering along with her, a tenth of an e′phah of barley flour. He must not pour oil upon it nor put frankincense upon it, because it is a grain offering of jealousy, a memorial grain offering bringing error to remembrance.

16 “‘And the priest must bring her forward and make her stand before Jehovah. 17 And the priest must take holy water in an earthenware vessel, and the priest will take some of the dust that happens to be on the floor of the tabernacle, and he must put it in the water. 18 And the priest must make the woman stand before Jehovah and loosen the hair of the woman’s head and put upon her palms the memorial grain offering, that is, the grain offering of jealousy, and in the hand of the priest there should be the bitter water that brings a curse.

19 “‘And the priest must make her swear, and he must say to the woman: “If no man has lain down with you and if while under your husband you have not turned aside in any uncleanness, be free of the effect of this bitter water that brings a curse. 20 But you, in case you have turned aside while under your husband and in case you have defiled yourself and some man has put in you his seminal emission, besides your husband,—” 21 The priest must now make the woman swear with an oath involving cursing, and the priest must say to the woman: “May Jehovah set you for a cursing and an oath in the midst of your people by Jehovah’s letting your thigh fall away, and your belly swell. 22 And this water that brings a curse must enter into your intestines to cause your belly to swell and the thigh to fall away.” To this the woman must say: “Amen! Amen!”

23 “‘And the priest must write these cursings in the book and must wipe them out into the bitter water. 24 And he must make the woman drink the bitter water that brings a curse, and the water that brings a curse must enter into her as something bitter. 25 And the priest must take the grain offering of jealousy from the woman’s hand and wave the grain offering to and fro before Jehovah, and he must bring it near the altar. 26 And the priest must grasp some of the grain offering as a remembrancer of it and must make it smoke upon the altar, and afterward he will make the woman drink the water. 27 When he has made her drink the water, it must also occur that if she has defiled herself in that she committed an act of unfaithfulness toward her husband, the water that brings a curse must then enter into her as something bitter, and her belly must swell, and her thigh must fall away, and the woman must become a cursing in among her people. 28 However, if the woman has not defiled herself but she is clean, she must then be free from such punishment; and she must be made pregnant with semen.

29 “‘This is the law about jealousy, where a woman may turn aside while under her husband, and she does defile herself, 30 or in the case of a man where the spirit of jealousy may pass upon him, and he does suspect his wife of unfaithfulness; and he must make the wife stand before Jehovah, and the priest must carry out toward her all this law. 31 And the man must be innocent of error, but that wife will answer for her error.’”

Numbers

10 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses, saying: 2 “Make for yourself two trumpets of silver. You will make them of hammered work, and they must be at your service for convening the assembly and for breaking up the camps. 3 And they must blow on them both, and the whole assembly must keep their appointment with you at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 4 And if they should blow on just one, the chieftains as heads of the thousands of Israel must also keep their appointment with you.

5 “And YOU men must blow a fluctuating blast, and the camps of those camping to the east must pull away. 6 And YOU must blow a fluctuating blast a second time, and the camps of those camping to the south must pull away. They should blow a fluctuating blast for each time one of them pulls away.

7 “Now when calling the congregation together, YOU should blow, but YOU must not sound a fluctuating blast. 8 And Aaron’s sons, the priests, should blow on the trumpets, and the use of them must serve as a statute for YOU men to time indefinite during YOUR generations.

9 “And in case YOU should enter into war in YOUR land against the oppressor who is harassing YOU, YOU must also sound a war call on the trumpets, and YOU will certainly be remembered before Jehovah YOUR God and be saved from YOUR enemies.

10 “And in the day of YOUR rejoicing and in YOUR festal seasons and at the commencements of YOUR months, YOU must blow on the trumpets over YOUR burnt offerings and YOUR communion sacrifices; and their use must serve as a memorial for YOU before YOUR God. I am Jehovah YOUR God.”

11 Now it came about that in the second year, in the second month, on the twentieth day in the month, the cloud lifted itself from over the tabernacle of the Testimony. 12 And the sons of Israel began to pull away in the manner of their departures from the wilderness of Si′nai, and the cloud proceeded to reside in the wilderness of Pa′ran. 13 And they began pulling away for the first time, according to the order of Jehovah by means of Moses.

14 So the three-tribe division of the camp of the sons of Judah pulled away first of all in their armies, and Nah′shon the son of Am·min′a·dab was over its army. 15 And over the army of the tribe of the sons of Is′sa·char there was Ne·than′el the son of Zu′ar. 16 And over the army of the tribe of the sons of Zeb′u·lun there was E·li′ab the son of He′lon.

17 And the tabernacle was taken down, and the sons of Ger′shon and the sons of Me·rar′i as carriers of the tabernacle pulled away.

18 And the three-tribe division of the camp of Reu′ben pulled away in their armies, and E·li′zur the son of Shed′e·ur was over its army. 19 And over the army of the tribe of the sons of Sim′e·on there was She·lu′mi·el the son of Zu·ri·shad′dai. 20 And over the army of the tribe of the sons of Gad there was E·li′a·saph the son of Deu′el.

21 And the Ko′hath·ites as carriers of the sanctuary pulled away, as they will have set up the tabernacle by the time of their coming.

22 And the three-tribe division of the camp of the sons of E′phra·im pulled away in their armies, and E·lish′a·ma the son of Am·mi′hud was over its army. 23 And over the army of the tribe of the sons of Ma·nas′seh there was Ga·ma′li·el the son of Pe·dah′zur. 24 And over the army of the tribe of the sons of Benjamin there was Ab′i·dan the son of Gid·e·o′ni.

25 And the three-tribe division of the camp of the sons of Dan pulled away as forming the rear guard for all the camps in their armies, and A·hi·e′zer the son of Am·mi·shad′dai was over its army. 26 And over the army of the tribe of the sons of Ash′er there was Pa′gi·el the son of Och′ran. 27 And over the army of the tribe of the sons of Naph′ta·li there was A·hi′ra the son of E′nan. 28 In this manner were the departures of the sons of Israel in their armies when they would pull away.

29 Then Moses said to Ho′bab the son of Reu′el the Mid′i·an·ite, the father-in-law of Moses: “We are pulling away for the place about which Jehovah said, ‘I shall give it to YOU.’ Do come with us, and we shall certainly do good to you, because Jehovah has spoken good concerning Israel.” 30 But he said to him: “I shall not go along, but I shall go to my own country and to my relatives.” 31 At this he said: “Please, do not leave us, because, for the reason that you well know where we may encamp in the wilderness, you must serve as eyes for us. 32 And it must occur that in case you should come with us, yes, it must occur that with what goodness Jehovah will do good with us, we, in turn, will do good to you.”

33 So they went marching from the mountain of Jehovah for a journey of three days, and the ark of Jehovah’s covenant was marching before them for a journey of three days to search out a resting-place for them. 34 And Jehovah’s cloud was over them by day at their marching out from the encampment.

35 And it would occur that when the Ark would set out, Moses would say: “Do arise, O Jehovah, and let your enemies be scattered; and let those who intensely hate you flee from before you.” 36 And when it would rest, he would say: “Do return, O Jehovah, to the myriads of thousands of Israel.”

Numbers

17 Jehovah now spoke to Moses, saying: 2 “Speak to the sons of Israel and take from them one rod for each paternal house from all their chieftains, by the house of their fathers, twelve rods. You will write the name of each one upon his rod. 3 And Aaron’s name you will write upon Le′vi’s rod, because there is one rod for the head of the house of their fathers. 4 And you must deposit them in the tent of meeting before the Testimony, where I regularly present myself to YOU. 5 And what must occur is that the man whom I shall choose, his rod will bud, and I shall certainly make subside from against me the murmurings of the sons of Israel, which they are murmuring against YOU.”

6 So Moses spoke to the sons of Israel, and all their chieftains went giving him a rod for each chieftain, a rod for each chieftain, by the house of their fathers, twelve rods; and Aaron’s rod was in among their rods. 7 Then Moses deposited the rods before Jehovah in the tent of the Testimony.

8 And it came about the next day that when Moses went into the tent of the Testimony, look! Aaron’s rod for the house of Le′vi had budded, and it was bringing forth buds and blossoming flowers and was bearing ripe almonds. 9 Moses then brought out all the rods from before Jehovah to all the sons of Israel, and they went looking and taking each man his own rod.

10 Subsequently Jehovah said to Moses: “Put Aaron’s rod back before the Testimony as something to be kept for a sign to the sons of rebelliousness, that their murmurings may cease from against me, that they may not die.” 11 At once Moses did just as Jehovah had commanded him. He did just so.

12 And the sons of Israel began to say this to Moses: “Now we are bound to expire, we are bound to perish, we are all of us bound to perish. 13 Anyone approaching, coming near to Jehovah’s tabernacle, will die! Must we end up in expiring that way?”

Numbers

21 Now the Ca′naan·ite the king of A′rad, who dwelt in the Neg′eb, got to hear that Israel had come by the way of Ath′a·rim, and he began to fight with Israel and carry away some of them as captives. 2 Consequently Israel made a vow to Jehovah and said: “If you will without fail give this people into my hand, I shall also certainly devote their cities to destruction.” 3 So Jehovah listened to Israel’s voice and gave the Ca′naan·ites over; and they devoted them and their cities to destruction. Hence they called the name of the place Hor′mah.

4 While they continued trekking from Mount Hor by the way of the Red Sea to go around the land of E′dom, the soul of the people began tiring out because of the way. 5 And the people kept speaking against God and Moses: “Why have YOU brought us up out of Egypt to die in the wilderness? For there is no bread and no water, and our soul has come to abhor the contemptible bread.” 6 So Jehovah sent poisonous serpents among the people, and they kept biting the people, so that many people of Israel died.

7 Finally the people came to Moses and said: “We have sinned, because we have spoken against Jehovah and against you. Intercede with Jehovah that he may remove the serpents from upon us.” And Moses went interceding in behalf of the people. 8 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Make for yourself a fiery snake and place it upon a signal pole. And it must occur that when anyone has been bitten, he then has to look at it and so must keep alive.” 9 Moses at once made a serpent of copper and placed it upon the signal pole; and it did occur that if a serpent had bitten a man and he gazed at the copper serpent, he then kept alive.

10 After that the sons of Israel pulled away and encamped in O′both. 11 Then they pulled away from O′both and encamped in I′ye-ab′a·rim, in the wilderness that is toward the front of Mo′ab, toward the rising of the sun. 12 From there they pulled away and took up camping by the torrent valley of Ze′red. 13 From there they pulled away and went camping in the region of the Ar′non, which is in the wilderness that extends from the border of the Am′or·ites; for the Ar′non is the boundary of Mo′ab, between Mo′ab and the Am′or·ites. 14 That is why it is said in the book of the Wars of Jehovah:

“Va′heb in Su′phah and the torrent valleys of Ar′non, 15 and the mouth of the torrent valleys, which has bent itself toward the seat of Ar and has leaned against the border of Mo′ab.”

16 Next from there on to Be′er. This is the well about which Jehovah said to Moses: “Gather the people, and let me give them water.”

17 At that time Israel proceeded to sing this song:

“Spring up, O well! Respond to it, YOU people!

18 A well, princes dug it. The nobles of the people excavated it,

With a commander’s staff, with their own staffs.”

Then from the wilderness on to Mat′ta·nah. 19 And from Mat′ta·nah on to Na·hal′i·el, and from Na·hal′i·el on to Ba′moth. 20 And from Ba′moth on to the valley that is in the field of Mo′ab, at the head of Pis′gah, and it projects over toward the face of Je·shi′mon.

21 Israel now sent messengers to Si′hon the king of the Am′or·ites, saying: 22 “Let me pass through your land. We shall not turn off into a field or a vineyard. We shall drink water of no well. On the king’s road we shall march until we pass through your territory.” 23 And Si′hon did not allow Israel to pass through his territory, but Si′hon gathered all his people and went out to meet Israel in the wilderness, and came to Ja′haz and began fighting with Israel. 24 At that Israel struck him with the edge of the sword and took possession of his land from the Ar′non to the Jab′bok, near the sons of Am′mon; because Ja′zer is the border of the sons of Am′mon.

25 So Israel took all these cities, and Israel began dwelling in all the cities of the Am′or·ites, in Hesh′bon and all its dependent towns. 26 For Hesh′bon was the city of Si′hon. He was the king of the Am′or·ites, and it was he who fought with the king of Mo′ab formerly and went taking all his land out of his hand as far as the Ar′non. 27 That is why the sayers of mock verses would say:

“Come to Hesh′bon.

Let the city of Si′hon be built and be proved firmly set up.

28 For a fire has come out of Hesh′bon, a flame from the town of Si′hon.

It has consumed Ar of Mo′ab, the owners of the high places of the Ar′non.

29 Woe to you, Mo′ab! You will certainly perish, O people of Che′mosh!

He will certainly give his sons as escaped ones and his daughters in the captivity to the king of the Am′or·ites, Si′hon.

30 So let us shoot at them.

Hesh′bon will certainly perish up to Di′bon,

And the women up to No′phah, the men up to Med′e·ba.”

31 And Israel began to dwell in the land of the Am′or·ites. 32 Then Moses sent some to spy on Ja′zer. So they captured its dependent towns and dispossessed the Am′or·ites who were there. 33 After that they turned and went up by the way of Ba′shan. At this Og the king of Ba′shan came out to meet them, he and all his people, to the battle of Ed′re·i. 34 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Do not be afraid of him, for into your hand I shall certainly give him and all his people and his land; and you must do to him just as you did to Si′hon, the king of the Am′or·ites, who used to dwell in Hesh′bon.” 35 So they went striking him and his sons and all his people, until there was no survivor remaining to him; and they went taking possession of his land.

Numbers

25 Now Israel was dwelling in Shit′tim. Then the people started to have immoral relations with the daughters of Mo′ab. 2 And the women came calling the people to the sacrifices of their gods, and the people began to eat and to bow down to their gods. 3 So Israel attached itself to the Ba′al of Pe′or; and the anger of Jehovah began to blaze against Israel. 4 Hence Jehovah said to Moses: “Take all the head ones of the people and expose them to Jehovah toward the sun, that the burning anger of Jehovah may turn back from Israel.” 5 Then Moses said to the judges of Israel: “Each one of YOU kill his men who have an attachment with the Ba′al of Pe′or.”

6 But, look! a man of the sons of Israel came, and he was bringing near to his brothers a Mid′i·an·ite woman before Moses’ eyes and before the eyes of all the assembly of the sons of Israel, while they were weeping at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 7 When Phin′e·has the son of El·e·a′zar the son of Aaron the priest caught sight of it, he at once got up from the midst of the assembly and took a lance in his hand. 8 Then he went after the man of Israel into the vaulted tent and pierced both of them through, the man of Israel and the woman through her genital parts. At that the scourge was halted from upon the sons of Israel. 9 And those who died from the scourge amounted to twenty-four thousand.

10 Then Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 11 “Phin′e·has the son of El·e·a′zar the son of Aaron the priest has turned back my wrath from upon the sons of Israel by his tolerating no rivalry at all toward me in the midst of them, so that I have not exterminated the sons of Israel in my insistence on exclusive devotion. 12 For that reason say, ‘Here I am giving him my covenant of peace. 13 And it must serve as the covenant of a priesthood to time indefinite for him and his offspring after him, due to the fact that he tolerated no rivalry toward his God and proceeded to make atonement for the sons of Israel.’”

14 Incidentally the name of the fatally struck Israelite man who was fatally struck with the Mid′i·an·i·tess was Zim′ri the son of Sa′lu, a chieftain of a paternal house of the Sim′e·on·ites. 15 And the name of the Mid′i·an·ite woman fatally struck was Coz′bi the daughter of Zur; he was a head one of the clans of a paternal house in Mid′i·an.

16 Later Jehovah spoke to Moses, saying: 17 “Let there be a harassing of the Mid′i·an·ites, and YOU men must strike them, 18 because they are harassing YOU with their deeds of cunning that they committed against YOU cunningly in the affair of Pe′or and in the affair of Coz′bi the daughter of a chieftain of Mid′i·an, their sister who was fatally struck in the day of the scourge over the affair of Pe′or.”

Numbers

28 And Jehovah spoke further to Moses, saying: 2 “Command the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘YOU should take care to present to me my offering, my bread, for my offerings made by fire as a restful odor to me, at their appointed times.’

3 “And you must say to them, ‘This is the offering made by fire that YOU will present to Jehovah: two sound year-old male lambs a day as a burnt offering constantly. 4 The one male lamb you will render up in the morning, and the other male lamb you will render up between the two evenings, 5 together with the tenth of an e′phah of fine flour as a grain offering moistened with the fourth of a hin of beaten oil; 6 the constant burnt offering, which was rendered up at Mount Si′nai as a restful odor, an offering made by fire to Jehovah, 7 along with its drink offering, the fourth of a hin to each male lamb. Pour out in the holy place the drink offering of intoxicating liquor to Jehovah. 8 And you will render up the other male lamb between the two evenings. With the same grain offering as of the morning and with its same drink offering you will render it up as an offering made by fire, of a restful odor to Jehovah.

9 “‘However, on the sabbath day there will be two sound year-old male lambs and two tenth measures of fine flour as a grain offering moistened with oil, together with its drink offering, 10 as a sabbath burnt offering on its sabbath, along with the constant burnt offering and its drink offering.

11 “‘And at the commencements of YOUR months YOU people will present as a burnt offering to Jehovah two young bulls and one ram, seven sound male lambs each a year old, 12 and three tenth measures of fine flour as a grain offering moistened with oil for each bull and two tenth measures of fine flour as a grain offering moistened with oil for the one ram, 13 and a tenth measure of fine flour respectively as a grain offering moistened with oil for each male lamb, as a burnt offering, a restful odor, an offering made by fire to Jehovah. 14 And as their drink offerings there should go half a hin of wine for a bull and a third of a hin for the ram and a fourth of a hin for a male lamb. This is the monthly burnt offering in its month for the months of the year. 15 Also, one kid of the goats should be rendered up as a sin offering to Jehovah in addition to the constant burnt offering together with its drink offering.

16 “‘And in the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month, will be Jehovah’s passover. 17 And on the fifteenth day of this month will be a festival. Seven days unfermented cakes will be eaten. 18 On the first day there will be a holy convention. No sort of laborious work must YOU do. 19 And YOU must present as an offering made by fire, a burnt offering to Jehovah, two young bulls and one ram and seven male lambs each a year old. They should prove to be sound ones for YOU. 20 And as their grain offerings of fine flour moistened with oil YOU will render up three tenth measures for a bull and two tenth measures for the ram. 21 You will render up a tenth measure respectively for each male lamb of the seven male lambs; 22 and one goat of sin offering to make atonement for YOU. 23 Aside from the morning burnt offering, which is for the constant burnt offering, YOU will render these up. 24 The same as these YOU will render up daily for the seven days as bread, an offering made by fire, of a restful odor to Jehovah. Along with the constant burnt offering it should be rendered, and its drink offering. 25 And on the seventh day YOU should hold a holy convention. No sort of laborious work must YOU do.

26 “‘And on the day of the first ripe fruits, when YOU present a new grain offering to Jehovah, in YOUR feast of weeks YOU should hold a holy convention. No sort of laborious work must YOU do. 27 And YOU must present as a burnt offering for a restful odor to Jehovah two young bulls, one ram, seven male lambs each a year old; 28 and as their grain offering of fine flour moistened with oil three tenth measures for each bull, two tenth measures for the one ram, 29 a tenth measure respectively for each male lamb of the seven male lambs; 30 one kid of the goats to make atonement for YOU. 31 Aside from the constant burnt offering and its grain offering YOU will render them up. They should prove to be sound ones for YOU, together with their drink offerings.

Numbers

33 These were the stages of the sons of Israel who went out of the land of Egypt in their armies by the hand of Moses and Aaron. 2 And Moses kept recording the departure places by their stages at the order of Jehovah; and these were their stages from one departure place to another: 3 And they proceeded to pull away from Ram′e·ses in the first month, on the fifteenth day of the first month. Directly the day after the passover the sons of Israel went out with uplifted hand before the eyes of all the Egyptians. 4 All the while the Egyptians were burying those whom Jehovah had struck among them, that is, all the firstborn; and upon their gods Jehovah had executed judgments.

5 So the sons of Israel pulled away from Ram′e·ses and went camping in Suc′coth. 6 Then they pulled away from Suc′coth and went camping in E′tham, which is on the edge of the wilderness. 7 Next they pulled away from E′tham and turned back toward Pi·ha·hi′roth, which is in view of Ba′al-ze′phon; and they went camping before Mig′dol. 8 After that they pulled away from Pi·ha·hi′roth and went passing through the midst of the sea to the wilderness and kept marching a three-day journey in the wilderness of E′tham and took up camping at Ma′rah.

9 Then they pulled away from Ma′rah and came to E′lim. Now in E′lim there were twelve springs of water and seventy palm trees. So they camped there. 10 Next they pulled away from E′lim and went camping by the Red Sea. 11 After that they pulled away from the Red Sea and took up camping in the wilderness of Sin. 12 Then they pulled away from the wilderness of Sin and went camping at Doph′kah. 13 Later they pulled away from Doph′kah and went camping at A′lush. 14 They next pulled away from A′lush and went camping in Reph′i·dim. And there proved to be no water there for the people to drink. 15 After that they pulled away from Reph′i·dim and went camping in the wilderness of Si′nai.

16 Subsequently they pulled away from the wilderness of Si′nai and went camping at Kib′roth-hat·ta′a·vah. 17 Then they pulled away from Kib′roth-hat·ta′a·vah and went camping in Ha·ze′roth. 18 After that they pulled away from Ha·ze′roth and went camping in Rith′mah. 19 Next they pulled away from Rith′mah and took up camping in Rim′mon-pe′rez. 20 Then they pulled away from Rim′mon-pe′rez and went camping in Lib′nah. 21 Later they pulled away from Lib′nah and went camping in Ris′sah. 22 Next they pulled away from Ris′sah and went camping in Ke·he·la′thah. 23 Then they pulled away from Ke·he·la′thah and went camping in Mount She′pher.

24 After that they pulled away from Mount She′pher and went camping in Har·a′dah. 25 Then they pulled away from Har·a′dah and went camping in Mak·he′loth. 26 Next they pulled away from Mak·he′loth and went camping in Ta′hath. 27 After that they pulled away from Ta′hath and went camping in Te′rah. 28 Then they pulled away from Te′rah and went camping in Mith′kah. 29 Later they pulled away from Mith′kah and went camping in Hash·mo′nah. 30 Next they pulled away from Hash·mo′nah and went camping in Mo·se′roth. 31 Then they pulled away from Mo·se′roth and went camping in Ben′e-ja′a·kan. 32 After that they pulled away from Ben′e-ja′a·kan and went camping in Hor-hag·gid′gad. 33 Next they pulled away from Hor-hag·gid′gad and went camping in Jot′ba·thah. 34 Later they pulled away from Jot′ba·thah and went camping in A·bro′nah. 35 Then they pulled away from A·bro′nah and went camping in E′zi·on-ge′ber. 36 After that they pulled away from E′zi·on-ge′ber and went camping in the wilderness of Zin, that is to say, Ka′desh.

37 Later they pulled away from Ka′desh and went camping in Mount Hor, on the frontier of the land of E′dom. 38 And Aaron the priest proceeded to go up into Mount Hor at the order of Jehovah and to die there in the fortieth year of the going out of the sons of Israel from the land of Egypt, in the fifth month, on the first of the month. 39 And Aaron was a hundred and twenty-three years old at his death on Mount Hor.

40 Now the Ca′naan·ite, the king of A′rad, as he was dwelling in the Neg′eb, in the land of Ca′naan, got to hear about the coming of the sons of Israel.

41 In time they pulled away from Mount Hor and went camping in Zal·mo′nah. 42 After that they pulled away from Zal·mo′nah and went camping in Pu′non. 43 Next they pulled away from Pu′non and went camping in O′both. 44 Then they pulled away from O′both and went camping in I′ye-ab′a·rim on the border of Mo′ab. 45 Later they pulled away from I′yim and went camping in Di′bon-gad. 46 After that they pulled away from Di′bon-gad and went camping in Al′mon-dib·la·tha′im. 47 Then they pulled away from Al′mon-dib·la·tha′im and went camping in the mountains of Ab′a·rim before Ne′bo. 48 Finally they pulled away from the mountains of Ab′a·rim and took up camping on the desert plains of Mo′ab by the Jordan at Jer′i·cho. 49 And they continued camping by the Jordan from Beth-jesh′i·moth to A′bel-shit′tim on the desert plains of Mo′ab.

50 And Jehovah proceeded to speak to Moses on the desert plains of Mo′ab by the Jordan at Jer′i·cho, saying: 51 “Speak to the sons of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘YOU are crossing the Jordan into the land of Ca′naan. 52 And YOU must drive away all the inhabitants of the land from before YOU and destroy all their stone figures, and all their images of molten metal YOU should destroy, and all their sacred high places YOU should annihilate. 53 And YOU must take possession of the land and dwell in it, because to YOU I shall certainly give the land to take possession of it. 54 And YOU must apportion the land to yourselves as a possession by lot according to YOUR families. To the populous one YOU should increase his inheritance, and to the sparse one YOU should reduce his inheritance. To where the lot will come out for him, there it will become his. By the tribes of YOUR fathers YOU should provide yourselves with landed property.

55 “‘If, though, YOU will not drive the inhabitants of the land away from before YOU, then those whom YOU leave of them will certainly become as pricks in YOUR eyes and as thorns in YOUR sides, and they will indeed harass YOU on the land in which YOU will be dwelling. 56 And it must occur that just as I had figured doing to them I shall do to YOU.’”

Numbers

36 And the heads of the fathers of the family of the sons of Gil′e·ad the son of Ma′chir the son of Ma·nas′seh of the families of the sons of Joseph proceeded to come near and speak before Moses and the chieftains, the heads of the fathers of the sons of Israel, 2 and say: “Jehovah commanded my lord to give the land in inheritance by lot to the sons of Israel; and my lord was commanded by Jehovah to give the inheritance of Ze·lo′phe·had our brother to his daughters. 3 If any of the sons of the other tribes of the sons of Israel happened to get them as wives, the women’s inheritance must also be withdrawn from the inheritance of our fathers and must be added to the inheritance of the tribe to which they may come to belong, so that it would be withdrawn from the lot of our inheritance. 4 Now if the Jubilee takes place for the sons of Israel, the women’s inheritance must also be added to the inheritance of the tribe to which they may come to belong; so that their inheritance would be withdrawn from the inheritance of the tribe of our fathers.”

5 Then Moses commanded the sons of Israel at the order of Jehovah, saying: “The tribe of the sons of Joseph is speaking right. 6 This is the word that Jehovah has commanded for the daughters of Ze·lo′phe·had, saying, ‘To whom it is good in their eyes they may become wives. Only it is to the family of the tribe of their fathers that they should become wives. 7 And no inheritance of the sons of Israel should circulate from tribe to tribe, because the sons of Israel should cleave each one to the inheritance of the tribe of his forefathers. 8 And every daughter getting possession of an inheritance out of the tribes of the sons of Israel, to one of the family of the tribe of her father she should become a wife, in order that the sons of Israel may get possession each one of the inheritance of his forefathers. 9 And no inheritance should circulate from one tribe to another tribe, because the tribes of the sons of Israel should cleave each to its own inheritance.’”

10 Just as Jehovah had commanded Moses, that is the way the daughters of Ze·lo′phe·had did. 11 Accordingly Mah′lah, Tir′zah and Hog′lah and Mil′cah and Noah, the daughters of Ze·lo′phe·had, became the wives of the sons of their father’s brothers. 12 To some of the families of the sons of Ma·nas′seh the son of Joseph they became wives, that their inheritance might continue together with the tribe of the family of their father.

13 These are the commandments and the judicial decisions that Jehovah commanded by means of Moses to the sons of Israel on the desert plains of Mo′ab by the Jordan at Jer′i·cho.

Deuteronomy

2 “Then we turned and pulled away for the wilderness by the way of the Red Sea, just as Jehovah had spoken to me; and we were many days in going around Mount Se′ir. 2 Finally Jehovah said this to me, 3 ‘YOU have gone around this mountain long enough. Change YOUR direction to the north. 4 And command the people, saying: “YOU are passing along by the border of YOUR brothers, the sons of E′sau, who are dwelling in Se′ir; and they will be afraid because of YOU, and YOU must be very careful. 5 Do not engage in strife with them, because I shall not give YOU of their land so much as the width of the sole of the foot; because I have given Mount Se′ir to E′sau as a holding. 6 What food YOU may buy from them for money, YOU must eat; and also what water YOU may purchase from them for money, YOU must drink. 7 For Jehovah your God has blessed you in every deed of your hand. He well knows of your walking through this great wilderness. These forty years Jehovah your God has been with you. You have not lacked a thing.”’ 8 So we passed on away from our brothers, the sons of E′sau, who are dwelling in Se′ir, from the way of the Ar′a·bah, from E′lath and from E′zi·on-ge′ber.

“Next we turned and passed on by the way of the wilderness of Mo′ab. 9 Jehovah then said to me, ‘Do not molest Mo′ab or engage in war with them, because I shall not give you any of his land as a holding, for to the sons of Lot I have given Ar as a holding. 10 (The E′mim dwelt in it in former times, a people great and numerous and tall like the An′a·kim. 11 As for the Reph′a·im, they also were considered like the An′a·kim, and the Mo′ab·ites used to call them E′mim. 12 And the Hor′ites dwelt in Se′ir in former times, and the sons of E′sau proceeded to dispossess them and to annihilate them from before them and to dwell in their place, just the same as Israel must do to the land that is his holding, which Jehovah will certainly give to them.) 13 At this time rise and make YOUR way across the torrent valley of Ze′red.’ Accordingly we went crossing the torrent valley of Ze′red. 14 And the days that we walked from Ka′desh-bar′ne·a until we crossed the torrent valley of Ze′red were thirty-eight years, until all the generation of the men of war had come to their end from the midst of the camp, just as Jehovah had sworn to them. 15 And the hand of Jehovah also proved to be upon them to disquiet them out of the midst of the camp, until they came to their end.

16 “And it came about that as soon as all the men of war had finished dying off from the midst of the people, 17 Jehovah spoke further to me, saying, 18 ‘You are passing today by the territory of Mo′ab, that is, Ar, 19 and you must get close in front of the sons of Am′mon. Do not molest them or engage in strife with them, because I shall not give you any of the land of the sons of Am′mon as a holding, for it is to the sons of Lot that I have given it as a holding. 20 As the land of the Reph′a·im it also used to be considered. (The Reph′a·im dwelt in it in former times, and the Am′mon·ites used to call them Zam·zum′mim. 21 They were a great and numerous and tall people like the An′a·kim; and Jehovah went annihilating them from before them, that they might dispossess them and dwell in their place; 22 just the same as he did for the sons of E′sau, who are dwelling in Se′ir, when he annihilated the Hor′ites from before them, that they might dispossess them and dwell in their place until this day. 23 As for the Av′vim, who were dwelling in settlements as far as Ga′za, the Caph′to·rim, who came out from Caph′tor, annihilated them, that they might dwell in their place.)

24 “‘GET up, pull away and cross the torrent valley of Ar′non. See, I have given into your hand Si′hon the king of Hesh′bon, the Am′or·ite. So start to take possession of his land, and engage in war with him. 25 This day I shall start to put the dread of you and the fear of you before the peoples beneath all the heavens, who will hear the report about you; and they will indeed be agitated and have pains like those of childbirth because of you.’

26 “Then I sent messengers from the wilderness of Ked′e·moth to Si′hon the king of Hesh′bon with words of peace, saying, 27 ‘Let me pass through your land. Only on the road I shall walk. I shall not turn to the right or to the left. 28 What food you will sell me for money, I must eat; and what water you will give me for money, I must drink. Only let me pass through on my feet, 29 just the same as the sons of E′sau dwelling in Se′ir and the Mo′ab·ites dwelling in Ar did to me, until I shall pass over the Jordan into the land that Jehovah our God is giving to us.’ 30 And Si′hon the king of Hesh′bon did not let us pass through him, because Jehovah your God had let his spirit become obstinate and his heart become hard, in order to give him into your hand just as at this day.

31 “At this Jehovah said to me, ‘See, I have started to abandon Si′hon and his land to you. Start to take possession of his land.’ 32 When Si′hon came on out, he and all his people, to meet us in battle at Ja′haz, 33 then Jehovah our God abandoned him to us, so that we defeated him and his sons and all his people. 34 And we went capturing all his cities at that particular time and devoting every city to destruction, men and women and little children. We left no survivor. 35 Only the domestic animals did we take as plunder for ourselves, together with the spoil of the cities that we had captured. 36 From A·ro′er, which is by the bank of the torrent valley of Ar′non, and the city that is in the torrent valley, as far as Gil′e·ad, there proved to be no town that was too high up for us. Jehovah our God abandoned them all to us. 37 Only you did not go near the land of the sons of Am′mon, the whole bank of the torrent valley of Jab′bok, nor the cities of the mountainous region, nor anything about which Jehovah our God had given command.

Deuteronomy

3 “Then we turned and went up by the way of Ba′shan. At this Og the king of Ba′shan came on out, he and all his people, to meet us in battle at Ed′re·i. 2 So Jehovah said to me, ‘Do not be afraid of him, for I shall certainly give him and all his people and his land into your hand; and you must do to him just as you did to Si′hon the king of the Am′or·ites, who was dwelling in Hesh′bon.’ 3 Accordingly Jehovah our God gave into our hand also Og the king of Ba′shan and all his people, and we kept striking him until he had no survivor remaining. 4 And we went capturing all his cities at that particular time. There proved to be no town that we did not take from them, sixty cities, all the region of Ar′gob, the kingdom of Og in Ba′shan. 5 All these were cities fortified with a high wall, doors and bar, aside from very many rural towns. 6 However, we devoted them to destruction, just as we had done to Si′hon the king of Hesh′bon, in devoting every city to destruction, men, women and little children. 7 And all the domestic animals and the spoil of the cities we took as plunder for ourselves.

8 “And we proceeded to take at that particular time the land from the hand of the two kings of the Am′or·ites who were in the region of the Jordan, from the torrent valley of Ar′non as far as Mount Her′mon; 9 (the Si·do′ni·ans used to call Her′mon Sir′i·on, and the Am′or·ites used to call it Se′nir,) 10 all the cities of the tableland and all Gil′e·ad and all Ba′shan as far as Sal′e·cah and Ed′re·i, the cities of the kingdom of Og in Ba′shan. 11 For only Og the king of Ba′shan remained of what was left of the Reph′a·im. Look! His bier was a bier of iron. Is it not in Rab′bah of the sons of Am′mon? Nine cubits is its length, and four cubits its width, by the cubit of a man. 12 And we took possession of this land at that particular time; from A·ro′er, which is by the torrent valley of Ar′non, and half of the mountainous region of Gil′e·ad, and its cities I have given to the Reu′ben·ites and the Gad′ites. 13 And the rest of Gil′e·ad and all Ba′shan of the kingdom of Og I have given to the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh. All the region of Ar′gob of all Ba′shan, is it not called the land of the Reph′a·im?

14 “Ja′ir the son of Ma·nas′seh took all the region of Ar′gob as far as the boundary of the Gesh′ur·ites and the Ma·ac′a·thites, and he proceeded to call those villages of Ba′shan by his own name, Hav′voth-ja′ir, to this day. 15 And to Ma′chir I have given Gil′e·ad. 16 And to the Reu′ben·ites and the Gad′ites I have given from Gil′e·ad to the torrent valley of Ar′non, the middle of the torrent valley being a boundary, and as far as Jab′bok, the torrent valley that is the boundary of the sons of Am′mon; 17 and the Ar′a·bah and the Jordan and the border, from Chin′ne·reth to the sea of the Ar′a·bah, the Salt Sea, at the base of the slopes of Pis′gah toward the sunrising.

18 “So I commanded YOU men at that particular time, saying, ‘Jehovah YOUR God has given YOU this land to take possession of it. YOU will pass over, equipped, before YOUR brothers, the sons of Israel, all the valiant men. 19 Only YOUR wives and YOUR little ones and YOUR livestock (I well know that YOU have a great deal of livestock) will continue dwelling in YOUR cities that I have given YOU, 20 until Jehovah gives YOUR brothers rest, as well as YOU, and they also have taken possession of the land that Jehovah YOUR God is giving them across the Jordan; after which YOU must come back, each one to his holding that I have given YOU.’

21 “And I commanded Joshua at that particular time, saying, ‘Your eyes are seeing all that Jehovah YOUR God has done to these two kings. The same way Jehovah will do to all the kingdoms to which you are passing over there. 22 YOU men must not be afraid of them, for Jehovah YOUR God is the One fighting for YOU.’

23 “And I proceeded to implore favor from Jehovah at that particular time, saying, 24 ‘O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, you yourself have started to make your servant see your greatness and your strong arm, for who is a god in the heavens or on the earth that does deeds like yours and mighty performances like yours? 25 Let me pass over, please, and see the good land that is across the Jordan, this good mountainous region and Leb′a·non.’ 26 And Jehovah continued to be furious against me on YOUR account and did not listen to me; but Jehovah said to me, ‘That is enough of you! Never speak to me further on this matter. 27 Go up to the top of Pis′gah and raise your eyes to the west and north and south and east and see with your eyes, for you will not pass over this Jordan. 28 And commission Joshua and encourage him and strengthen him, because he is the one to pass over before this people and he is the one to cause them to inherit the land that you will see.’ 29 All this while we were dwelling in the valley in front of Beth-pe′or.

Deuteronomy

9 “Hear, O Israel, you are today crossing the Jordan to go in and dispossess nations greater and mightier than you, cities great and fortified to the heavens, 2 a people great and tall, the sons of An′a·kim, about whom you yourself have known and you yourself have heard it said, ‘Who can make a firm stand before the sons of A′nak?’ 3 And you well know today that Jehovah your God is crossing before you. A consuming fire he is. He will annihilate them, and he himself will subdue them before you; and you must dispossess them and destroy them speedily, just as Jehovah has spoken to you.

4 “Do not say in your heart when Jehovah your God pushes them away from before you this, ‘It was for my own righteousness that Jehovah has brought me in to take possession of this land,’ whereas it is for the wickedness of these nations that Jehovah is driving them away from before you. 5 It is not for your righteousness or for the uprightness of your heart that you are going in to take possession of their land; in fact, it is for the wickedness of these nations that Jehovah your God is driving them away from before you, and in order to carry out the word that Jehovah swore to your forefathers, Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. 6 And you must know that it is not for your righteousness that Jehovah your God is giving you this good land to take possession of it; for you are a stiff-necked people.

7 “Remember: Do not forget how you have provoked Jehovah your God in the wilderness. From the day that you went out of the land of Egypt until YOUR coming to this place YOU people have proved rebellious in YOUR behavior with Jehovah. 8 Even in Ho′reb YOU provoked Jehovah to anger so that Jehovah got incensed at YOU to the point of annihilating YOU. 9 When I went up the mountain to receive the stone tablets, the tablets of the covenant that Jehovah had concluded with YOU, and I kept dwelling in the mountain forty days and forty nights, (I neither ate bread nor drank water,) 10 then Jehovah gave me the two tablets of stone written upon with God’s finger; and upon them were all the words that Jehovah had spoken with YOU in the mountain out of the middle of the fire in the day of the congregation. 11 And it came about that at the end of the forty days and forty nights Jehovah gave me the two tablets of stone, the tablets of the covenant; 12 and Jehovah proceeded to say to me, ‘Get up, go down quickly from here, because your people whom you brought out of Egypt have acted ruinously. They have turned aside quickly from the way about which I commanded them. They have made themselves a molten image.’ 13 And Jehovah went on to say this to me, ‘I have seen this people, and, look! it is a stiff-necked people. 14 Let me alone that I may annihilate them and wipe out their name from under the heavens, and let me make you a nation mightier and more populous than they are.’

15 “After that I turned and went down from the mountain, while the mountain was burning with fire; and the two tablets of the covenant were in both my hands. 16 Then I looked, and there YOU had sinned against Jehovah YOUR God! YOU had made yourselves a molten calf. YOU had turned aside quickly from the way about which Jehovah had commanded YOU. 17 At that I took hold of the two tablets and flung them down from both my hands and shattered them before YOUR eyes. 18 And I proceeded to prostrate myself before Jehovah, as at first, forty days and forty nights. I neither ate bread nor drank water, because of all YOUR sin that YOU had committed in doing evil in the eyes of Jehovah so as to offend him. 19 For I was scared because of the hot anger with which Jehovah had got indignant at YOU to the point of annihilating YOU. However, Jehovah listened to me also that time.

20 “At Aaron, too, Jehovah got very incensed to the point of annihilating him; but I made supplication also in behalf of Aaron at that particular time. 21 And YOUR sin that YOU had made, the calf, I took, and I proceeded to burn it in the fire and to crush it, grinding it thoroughly until it had become fine like dust; after which I threw its dust into the torrent that was descending from the mountain.

22 “Further, at Tab′e·rah and at Mas′sah and at Kib′roth-hat·ta′a·vah YOU proved yourselves provokers of Jehovah to anger. 23 And when Jehovah sent YOU out of Ka′desh-bar′ne·a, saying, ‘Go up and take possession of the land that I shall certainly give YOU!’ then YOU behaved rebelliously against the order of Jehovah YOUR God, and YOU did not exercise faith toward him and did not listen to his voice. 24 YOU have proved yourselves rebellious in behavior with Jehovah from the day of my knowing YOU.

25 “So I kept prostrating myself before Jehovah forty days and forty nights, for I prostrated myself thus because Jehovah talked of annihilating YOU. 26 And I began to make supplication to Jehovah and to say, ‘O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, do not bring to ruin your people, even your private property, whom you redeemed with your greatness, whom you brought out of Egypt with a strong hand. 27 Remember your servants Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. Do not turn your face to the hardness of this people and their wickedness and their sin, 28 for fear the land out of which you brought us may say: “Because Jehovah was unable to bring them into the land that he had promised them, and because he hated them he brought them out to put them to death in the wilderness.” 29 They are, too, your people and your private property whom you brought out with your great power and your outstretched arm.’

Deuteronomy

19 “When Jehovah your God cuts off the nations whose land Jehovah your God is giving you, and you have dispossessed them and have dwelt in their cities and their houses, 2 you will set apart three cities for yourself in the midst of your land that Jehovah your God is giving you to take possession of it. 3 You will prepare for yourself the way, and you must divide up the territory of your land that Jehovah your God proceeded to give you as a possession into three parts, and it must be for any manslayer to flee there.

4 “Now this is the case of the manslayer who may flee there and has to live: When he strikes his fellowman without knowing it and he was no hater of him formerly; 5 or when he goes with his fellowman into the woods to gather wood, and his hand has been raised to strike with the ax to cut the tree, and the iron has slipped off from the wooden handle, and it has hit his fellowman and he has died, he himself should flee to one of these cities and must live. 6 Otherwise, the avenger of blood may, because his heart is hot, chase after the manslayer and actually overtake him, since the way is great; and he may indeed strike his soul fatally, whereas there is no sentence of death for him, because he was no hater of him formerly. 7 That is why I am commanding you, saying, ‘Three cities you will set apart for yourself.’

8 “And if Jehovah your God widens out your territory according to what he swore to your forefathers, and he has given you all the land that he promised to give to your forefathers, 9 because you will keep all this commandment that I am commanding you today by doing it, to love Jehovah your God and to walk in his ways always, you must then add three other cities for yourself to these three, 10 that no innocent blood may be spilled in the midst of your land that Jehovah your God is giving you as an inheritance, and no bloodguilt has to be upon you.

11 “But in case there should happen to be a man hating his fellowman, and he has lain in wait for him and has risen up against him and struck his soul fatally and he has died, and the man has fled to one of these cities, 12 the older men of his city must then send and take him from there, and they must deliver him into the hand of the avenger of blood, and he must die. 13 Your eye should not feel sorry for him, and you must clear away the guilt of innocent blood out of Israel, that you may have good.

14 “You must not move back the boundary marks of your fellowman, when the ancestors will have set the boundaries in your inheritance that you will inherit in the land that Jehovah your God is giving you to take possession of it.

15 “No single witness should rise up against a man respecting any error or any sin, in the case of any sin that he may commit. At the mouth of two witnesses or at the mouth of three witnesses the matter should stand good. 16 In case a witness scheming violence should rise up against a man to bring a charge of revolt against him, 17 the two men who have the dispute must also stand before Jehovah, before the priests and the judges who will be acting in those days. 18 And the judges must search thoroughly, and if the witness is a false witness and has brought a false charge against his brother, 19 YOU must also do to him just as he had schemed to do to his brother, and you must clear away what is bad from your midst. 20 So those who remain will hear and be afraid, and they will never again do anything bad like this in your midst. 21 And your eye should not feel sorry: soul will be for soul, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.

Deuteronomy

22 “You must not see the bull of your brother or his sheep straying about and deliberately withdraw from them. You should by all means lead them back to your brother. 2 And if your brother is not near you and you have not got to know him, you must also bring it home into the midst of your house, and it must continue with you until your brother has searched for it. And you must return it to him. 3 That is the way too that you will do with his ass, and that is the way you will do with his mantle, and that is the way you will do with anything lost of your brother’s, which gets lost from him and which you have found. You will not be allowed to withdraw yourself.

4 “You must not see the ass of your brother or his bull fall down on the road and deliberately withdraw from them. You should by all means help him raise them up.

5 “No garb of an able-bodied man should be put upon a woman, neither should an able-bodied man wear the mantle of a woman; for anybody doing these things is something detestable to Jehovah your God.

6 “In case a bird’s nest happens to be before you in the way, in any tree or on the earth with young ones or eggs, and the mother is sitting upon the young ones or the eggs, you must not take the mother along with the offspring. 7 You should by all means send the mother away, but you may take the offspring for yourself; in order that it may go well with you, and you may indeed lengthen your days.

8 “In case you build a new house, you must also make a parapet for your roof, that you may not place bloodguilt upon your house because someone falling might fall from it.

9 “You must not sow your vineyard with two sorts of seed, for fear that the full produce of the seed that you might sow and the product of the vineyard may be forfeited to the sanctuary.

10 “You must not plow with a bull and an ass together.

11 “You must not wear mixed stuff of wool and linen together.

12 “You should make tassels for yourself on the four extremities of your clothing with which you cover yourself.

13 “In case a man takes a wife and actually has relations with her and has come to hate her, 14 and he has charged her with notorious deeds and brought forth a bad name upon her and has said, ‘This is the woman I have taken, and I proceeded to go near her, and I did not find evidence of virginity in her’; 15 the father of the girl and her mother must also take and bring forth the evidence of the girl’s virginity to the older men of the city at the gate of it; 16 and the girl’s father must say to the older men, ‘I gave my daughter to this man as a wife, and he went hating her. 17 And here he is charging her with notorious deeds, saying: “I have found your daughter does not have evidence of virginity.” Now this is the evidence of my daughter’s virginity.’ And they must spread out the mantle before the older men of the city. 18 And the older men of that city must take the man and discipline him. 19 And they must fine him a hundred silver shekels and give them to the girl’s father, because he brought forth a bad name upon a virgin of Israel; and she will continue to be his wife. He will not be allowed to divorce her all his days.

20 “If, though, this thing has proved to be the truth, evidence of virginity was not found in the girl, 21 they must also bring the girl out to the entrance of her father’s house, and the men of her city must pelt her with stones, and she must die, because she has committed a disgraceful folly in Israel by committing prostitution in the house of her father. So you must clear away what is bad from your midst.

22 “In case a man is found lying down with a woman owned by an owner, both of them must then die together, the man lying down with the woman and the woman. So you must clear away what is bad out of Israel.

23 “In case there happened to be a virgin girl engaged to a man, and a man actually found her in the city and lay down with her, 24 YOU must also bring them both out to the gate of that city and pelt them with stones, and they must die, the girl for the reason that she did not scream in the city, and the man for the reason that he humiliated the wife of his fellowman. So you must clear away what is evil from your midst.

25 “If, however, it is in the field that the man found the girl who was engaged, and the man grabbed hold of her and lay down with her, the man who lay down with her must also die by himself, 26 and to the girl you must do nothing. The girl has no sin deserving of death, because just as when a man rises up against his fellowman and indeed murders him, even a soul, so it is with this case. 27 For it was in the field that he found her. The girl who was engaged screamed, but there was no one to rescue her.

28 “In case a man finds a girl, a virgin who has not been engaged, and he actually seizes her and lies down with her, and they have been found out, 29 the man who lay down with her must also give the girl’s father fifty silver shekels, and she will become his wife due to the fact that he humiliated her. He will not be allowed to divorce her all his days.

30 “No man should take his father’s wife, that he may not uncover the skirt of his father.

Deuteronomy

25 “In case a dispute arises between men, and they have presented themselves for the judgment, they must also judge them and pronounce the righteous one righteous and pronounce the wicked one wicked. 2 And it must occur that if the wicked one deserves to be beaten, the judge must also have him laid prostrate and given strokes before him by number to correspond with his wicked deed. 3 With forty strokes he may beat him. He should add none, for fear he should continue to beat him with many strokes in addition to these and your brother is actually disgraced in your eyes.

4 “You must not muzzle a bull while it is threshing.

5 “In case brothers dwell together and one of them has died without his having a son, the wife of the dead one should not become a strange man’s outside. Her brother-in-law should go to her, and he must take her as his wife and perform brother-in-law marriage with her. 6 And it must occur that the firstborn whom she will bear should succeed to the name of his dead brother, that his name may not be wiped out of Israel.

7 “Now if the man finds no delight in taking his brother’s widow, his brother’s widow must then go up to the gate to the older men and say, ‘My husband’s brother has refused to preserve his brother’s name in Israel. He has not consented to perform brother-in-law marriage with me.’ 8 And the older men of his city must call him and speak to him, and he must stand and say, ‘I have found no delight in taking her.’ 9 At that his brother’s widow must approach him before the eyes of the older men and draw his sandal off his foot and spit in his face and answer and say, ‘That is the way it should be done to the man who will not build up his brother’s household.’ 10 And his name must be called in Israel ‘The house of the one who had his sandal drawn off.’

11 “In case men struggle together with one another, and the wife of the one has come near to deliver her husband out of the hand of the one striking him, and she has thrust out her hand and grabbed hold of him by his privates, 12 you must then amputate her hand. Your eye must feel no sorrow.

13 “You must not come to have in your bag two sorts of weights, a great one and a small one. 14 You must not come to have in your house two sorts of e′phahs, a great one and a small one. 15 A weight accurate and just you should continue to have. An e′phah accurate and just you should continue to have, in order that your days may become long on the soil that Jehovah your God is giving you. 16 For everyone doing these things, every doer of injustice, is something detestable to Jehovah your God.

17 “There should be a remembering of what Am′a·lek did to you in the way when YOU were coming out of Egypt, 18 how he met you in the way and proceeded to strike in the rear of you all those straggling after you, while you were exhausted and weary; and he did not fear God. 19 And it must occur that when Jehovah your God has given you rest from all your enemies round about in the land that Jehovah your God is giving you as an inheritance to take possession of it, you should wipe out the mention of Am′a·lek from under the heavens. You must not forget.

Deuteronomy

34 Then Moses proceeded to go up from the desert plains of Mo′ab into Mount Ne′bo, to the top of Pis′gah, which fronts toward Jer′i·cho. And Jehovah went showing him all the land, Gil′e·ad as far as Dan, 2 and all Naph′ta·li and the land of E′phra·im and Ma·nas′seh and all the land of Judah as far as the western sea, 3 and the Neg′eb and the District, the valley plain of Jer′i·cho, the city of the palm trees, as far as Zo′ar.

4 And Jehovah went on to say to him: “This is the land about which I have sworn to Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, saying, ‘To your seed I shall give it.’ I have caused you to see it with your own eyes, as you will not cross over there.”

5 After that Moses the servant of Jehovah died there in the land of Mo′ab at the order of Jehovah. 6 And he proceeded to bury him in the valley in the land of Mo′ab in front of Beth-pe′or, and nobody has come to know his grave down to this day. 7 And Moses was a hundred and twenty years old at his death. His eye had not grown dim, and his vital strength had not fled. 8 And the sons of Israel proceeded to weep for Moses on the desert plains of Mo′ab thirty days. At length the days of weeping of the mourning period for Moses were completed.

9 And Joshua the son of Nun was full of the spirit of wisdom, for Moses had laid his hand upon him; and the sons of Israel began to listen to him and they went doing just as Jehovah had commanded Moses. 10 But there has never yet risen up a prophet in Israel like Moses, whom Jehovah knew face to face, 11 as respects all the signs and the miracles that Jehovah sent him to do in the land of Egypt to Phar′aoh and all his servants and all his land, 12 and as regards all the strong hand and all the great awesomeness that Moses exercised before the eyes of all Israel.

Joshua

1 And it came about after the death of Moses the servant of Jehovah that Jehovah proceeded to say to Joshua the son of Nun, the minister of Moses: 2 “Moses my servant is dead; and now get up, cross this Jordan, you and all this people, into the land that I am giving to them, to the sons of Israel. 3 Every place upon which the sole of YOUR foot will tread, to YOU people I shall certainly give it, just as I promised to Moses. 4 From the wilderness and this Leb′a·non to the great river, the river Eu·phra′tes, that is, all the land of the Hit′tites, and to the Great Sea toward the setting of the sun YOUR territory will prove to be. 5 Nobody will take a firm stand before you all the days of your life. Just as I proved to be with Moses I shall prove to be with you. I shall neither desert you nor leave you entirely. 6 Be courageous and strong, for you are the one who will cause this people to inherit the land that I swore to their forefathers to give to them.

7 “Only be courageous and very strong to take care to do according to all the law that Moses my servant commanded you. Do not turn aside from it to the right or to the left, in order that you may act wisely everywhere you go. 8 This book of the law should not depart from your mouth, and you must in an undertone read in it day and night, in order that you may take care to do according to all that is written in it; for then you will make your way successful and then you will act wisely. 9 Have I not commanded you? Be courageous and strong. Do not suffer shock or be terrified, for Jehovah your God is with you wherever you go.”

10 And Joshua proceeded to command the officers of the people, saying: 11 “Pass through the midst of the camp and command the people, saying, ‘Get provisions ready for yourselves, because three days from now YOU are crossing this Jordan to go in and take possession of the land that Jehovah YOUR God is giving YOU to take possession of it.’”

12 And to the Reu′ben·ites and the Gad′ites and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh Joshua said: 13 “Let there be a remembering of the word that Moses the servant of Jehovah commanded YOU, saying, ‘Jehovah YOUR God is giving YOU rest and has given YOU this land. 14 YOUR wives, YOUR little ones and YOUR livestock will dwell in the land that Moses has given YOU on this side of the Jordan; but YOU men will pass over in battle formation before YOUR brothers, all the valiant mighty men, and YOU must help them. 15 First when Jehovah gives rest to YOUR brothers the same as to YOU and they also have taken possession of the land that Jehovah YOUR God is giving them, YOU must also return to the land of YOUR holding and take possession of it, the one that Moses the servant of Jehovah has given YOU on the side of the Jordan toward the rising of the sun.’”

16 Accordingly they answered Joshua, saying: “All that you have commanded us we shall do, and wherever you may send us we shall go. 17 As we listened to Moses in everything, so we shall listen to you. Only may Jehovah your God prove to be with you just as he proved to be with Moses. 18 Any man that behaves rebelliously against your order and does not listen to your words in all that you may command him will be put to death. Only be courageous and strong.”

Joshua

5 And it came about that as soon as all the kings of the Am′or·ites, who were on the side of the Jordan to the west, and all the kings of the Ca′naan·ites, who were by the sea, heard that Jehovah had dried up the waters of the Jordan from before the sons of Israel until they had passed over, then their hearts began to melt, and there proved to be no spiritedness in them anymore because of the sons of Israel.

2 At that particular time Jehovah said to Joshua: “Make for yourself flint knives and circumcise the sons of Israel again, the second time.” 3 Accordingly Joshua made flint knives for himself and circumcised the sons of Israel at Gib′e·ath-ha·ar′a·loth. 4 And this was the reason why Joshua did the circumcising: all the people that came out of Egypt, the males, all the men of war, had died in the wilderness on the road when they were coming out of Egypt. 5 For all the people who came out proved to be circumcised, but all the people born in the wilderness on the road when they were coming out of Egypt they had not circumcised. 6 For the sons of Israel had walked forty years in the wilderness, until all the nation of the men of war who came out of Egypt that did not listen to the voice of Jehovah had come to its finish, to whom Jehovah swore that he would never let them see the land that Jehovah had sworn to their forefathers to give to us, a land flowing with milk and honey. 7 And their sons he raised up instead of them. These Joshua circumcised, because they proved to be uncircumcised, for they had not circumcised them on the road.

8 And it came about that when they had completed circumcising all the nation, they kept sitting in their place in the camp until they revived.

9 Then Jehovah said to Joshua: “Today I have rolled away the reproach of Egypt from off YOU.” So the name of that place came to be called Gil′gal until this day.

10 And the sons of Israel continued to camp in Gil′gal, and they proceeded to carry out the passover on the fourteenth day of the month, in the evening, on the desert plains of Jer′i·cho. 11 And they began to eat some of the yield of the land the day after the passover, unfermented cakes and roasted grains, on this same day. 12 Then the manna ceased on the following day when they had eaten some of the yield of the land, and manna did not occur anymore for the sons of Israel, and they began to eat some of the produce of the land of Ca′naan in that year.

13 And it came about when Joshua happened to be by Jer′i·cho that he proceeded to raise his eyes and look, and there there was a man standing in front of him with his drawn sword in his hand. So Joshua walked up to him and said to him: “Are you for us or for our adversaries?” 14 To this he said: “No, but I—as prince of the army of Jehovah I have now come.” With that Joshua fell on his face to the earth and prostrated himself and said to him: “What is my lord saying to his servant?” 15 In turn the prince of the army of Jehovah said to Joshua: “Draw your sandals from off your feet, because the place on which you are standing is holy.” At once Joshua did so.

Joshua

10 And it came about that as soon as A·do′ni-ze′dek the king of Jerusalem heard that Joshua had captured A′i and then devoted it to destruction, that just as he had done to Jer′i·cho and its king, so he had done to A′i and its king, and that the inhabitants of Gib′e·on had made peace with Israel and were continuing in their midst, 2 he became very much afraid, because Gib′e·on was a great city, like one of the royal cities, and because it was greater than A′i, and all its men were mighty ones. 3 Consequently A·do′ni-ze′dek the king of Jerusalem sent to Ho′ham the king of He′bron and to Pi′ram the king of Jar′muth and to Ja·phi′a the king of La′chish and to De′bir the king of Eg′lon, saying, 4 “Come up to me and help me and let us strike Gib′e·on, because it has made peace with Joshua and the sons of Israel.” 5 At this they gathered together and went on up, five kings of the Am′or·ites, the king of Jerusalem, the king of He′bron, the king of Jar′muth, the king of La′chish, the king of Eg′lon, these and all their camps, and they proceeded to camp against Gib′e·on and to war against it.

6 Upon that the men of Gib′e·on sent to Joshua at the camp at Gil′gal, saying: “Do not let your hand relax from your slaves. Come up to us quickly and do save us and help us, for all the kings of the Am′or·ites inhabiting the mountainous region have collected together against us.” 7 So Joshua went on up from Gil′gal, he and all the people of war with him and all the valiant mighty men.

8 Then Jehovah said to Joshua: “Do not be afraid of them, for into your hand I have given them. Not a man of them will stand against you.” 9 And Joshua proceeded to come against them by surprise. All night long he had gone up from Gil′gal. 10 And Jehovah went throwing them into confusion before Israel, and they began to slay them with a great slaughter at Gib′e·on and went pursuing them by way of the ascent of Beth-ho′ron and slaying them as far as A·ze′kah and Mak·ke′dah. 11 And it came about that while they were fleeing from before Israel and were on the descent of Beth-ho′ron, Jehovah hurled great stones from the heavens upon them as far as A·ze′kah, so that they died. There were more who died from the hailstones than those whom the sons of Israel killed with the sword.

12 It was then that Joshua proceeded to speak to Jehovah on the day of Jehovah’s abandoning the Am′or·ites to the sons of Israel, and he went on to say before the eyes of Israel:

“Sun, be motionless over Gib′e·on,

And, moon, over the low plain of Ai′ja·lon.”

13 Accordingly the sun kept motionless, and the moon did stand still, until the nation could take vengeance on its enemies. Is it not written in the book of Ja′shar? And the sun kept standing still in the middle of the heavens and did not hasten to set for about a whole day. 14 And no day has proved to be like that one, either before it or after it, in that Jehovah listened to the voice of a man, for Jehovah himself was fighting for Israel.

15 After that Joshua and all Israel with him returned to the camp at Gil′gal.

16 Meantime these five kings fled and went hiding themselves in the cave at Mak·ke′dah. 17 Then the report was made to Joshua, saying: “The five kings have been found hidden in the cave at Mak·ke′dah.” 18 At that Joshua said: “ROLL great stones up to the mouth of the cave and assign men over it to guard them. 19 As for YOU men, do not stand still. Chase after YOUR enemies, and YOU must strike them in the rear. Do not allow them to enter into their cities, for Jehovah YOUR God has given them into YOUR hands.”

20 And it came about that as soon as Joshua and the sons of Israel had finished slaying them with a very great slaughter, until these came to their end, and those who did survive of them escaped and went entering into the fortified cities, 21 all the people then began to return to the camp, to Joshua, at Mak·ke′dah in peace. Not a man moved his tongue eagerly against the sons of Israel. 22 Then Joshua said: “OPEN the mouth of the cave and bring out these five kings from the cave to me.” 23 At that they did so and brought out to him from the cave these five kings, the king of Jerusalem, the king of He′bron, the king of Jar′muth, the king of La′chish, the king of Eg′lon. 24 And it came about that as soon as they had brought out these kings to Joshua, Joshua proceeded to call all the men of Israel and to say to the commanders of the men of war that had gone with him: “Come forward. Place YOUR feet on the back of the necks of these kings.” So they came forward and placed their feet on the back of their necks. 25 And Joshua went on to say to them: “Do not be afraid or be terrified. Be courageous and strong, for it is like this that Jehovah will do to all YOUR enemies against whom YOU are warring.”

26 And after that Joshua proceeded to strike them and put them to death and hang them upon five stakes, and they continued hanging upon the stakes until the evening. 27 And it came about that at the time of the setting of the sun Joshua commanded, and they went taking them down off the stakes and throwing them into the cave where they had hid themselves. Then they placed big stones at the mouth of the cave—until this very day.

28 And Joshua captured Mak·ke′dah on that day and went striking it with the edge of the sword. As for its king, he devoted him and every soul that was in it to destruction. He let no survivor remain. So he did to the king of Mak·ke′dah just as he had done to the king of Jer′i·cho.

29 Then Joshua and all Israel with him passed on from Mak·ke′dah to Lib′nah and warred against Lib′nah. 30 Accordingly Jehovah gave it also and its king into Israel’s hand, and they went striking it and every soul that was in it with the edge of the sword. They did not let a survivor remain in it. So they did to its king just as they had done to the king of Jer′i·cho.

31 Next Joshua and all Israel with him passed on from Lib′nah to La′chish and went camping against it and warring upon it. 32 Accordingly Jehovah gave La′chish into Israel’s hand so that they captured it on the second day, and they went striking it and every soul that was in it with the edge of the sword, according to all that they had done to Lib′nah.

33 It was then that Ho′ram the king of Ge′zer went up to help La′chish. So Joshua struck him and his people until he had let not a survivor of his remain.

34 Then Joshua and all Israel with him passed on from La′chish to Eg′lon and went camping against it and warring against it. 35 And they got to capture it on that day and began to smite it with the edge of the sword, and they devoted every soul that was in it to destruction on that day, according to all that they had done to La′chish.

36 Then Joshua and all Israel with him went up from Eg′lon to He′bron and began to war against it. 37 And they got to capture it and went striking it and its king and all its towns and every soul that was in it with the edge of the sword. He did not let a survivor remain, according to all that he had done to Eg′lon. So he devoted it and every soul that was in it to destruction.

38 Finally Joshua and all Israel with him came back to De′bir and began to war against it. 39 And he got to capture it and its king and all its towns, and they went striking them with the edge of the sword and devoting every soul that was in it to destruction. He did not let a survivor remain. Just as he had done to He′bron, so he did to De′bir and its king, and just as he had done to Lib′nah and its king.

40 And Joshua proceeded to strike all the land of the mountainous region and the Neg′eb and the She·phe′lah and the slopes and all their kings. He did not let a survivor remain, and everything that breathed he devoted to destruction, just as Jehovah the God of Israel had commanded. 41 And Joshua went striking them from Ka′desh-bar′ne·a to Ga′za and all the land of Go′shen and up to Gib′e·on. 42 And Joshua captured all these kings and their land at one time, because it was Jehovah the God of Israel who was fighting for Israel. 43 After that Joshua and all Israel with him returned to the camp at Gil′gal.

Joshua

13 Now Joshua was old, being advanced in years. So Jehovah said to him: “You yourself have grown old and have advanced in years, and to a very great extent the land yet remains to be taken in possession. 2 This is the land yet remaining: all the regions of the Phi·lis′tines and all the Gesh′ur·ites 3 (from the branch of the Nile that is in front of Egypt and up to the border of Ek′ron to the north, it used to be reckoned as belonging to the Ca′naan·ites); five axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines, the Ga′zites and the Ash′dod·ites, the Ash′ke·lon·ites, the Git′tites and the Ek′ron·ites; and the Av′vim. 4 To the south all the land of the Ca′naan·ites; and Me·ar′ah, which belongs to the Si·do′ni·ans, as far as A′phek, as far as the border of the Am′or·ites; 5 and the land of the Ge′bal·ites and all of Leb′a·non toward the rising of the sun, from Ba′al-gad at the base of Mount Her′mon as far as to the entering in of Ha′math; 6 all the inhabitants of the mountainous region, from Leb′a·non to Mis′re·photh-ma′im, all the Si·do′ni·ans; I myself shall dispossess them from before the sons of Israel. Only make it fall to Israel as an inheritance, just as I have commanded you. 7 And now apportion this land as an inheritance to the nine tribes and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh.”

8 With the other half tribe the Reu′ben·ites and the Gad′ites took their inheritance that Moses gave them on the side of the Jordan toward the east, just as Moses the servant of Jehovah had given them, 9 from A·ro′er, which is on the bank of the torrent valley of Ar′non, and the city that is in the middle of the torrent valley, and all the tableland of Med′e·ba as far as Di′bon; 10 and all the cities of Si′hon the king of the Am′or·ites, who reigned in Hesh′bon, up to the border of the sons of Am′mon; 11 and Gil′e·ad and the territory of the Gesh′ur·ites and the Ma·ac′a·thites and all of Mount Her′mon and all Ba′shan as far as Sal′e·cah; 12 all the royal realm of Og in Ba′shan, who reigned in Ash′ta·roth and in Ed′re·i—he it was who remained of what was left of the Reph′a·im—and Moses went striking them and dispossessing them. 13 And the sons of Israel did not dispossess the Gesh′ur·ites and the Ma·ac′a·thites, but Gesh′ur and Ma′a·cath keep dwelling in the midst of Israel down to this day.

14 It was only to the tribe of the Levites that he did not give an inheritance. The offerings made by fire of Jehovah the God of Israel are their inheritance, just as he has promised them.

15 Then Moses made a gift to the tribe of the sons of Reu′ben by their families, 16 and the territory came to be theirs from A·ro′er, which is on the bank of the torrent valley of Ar′non, and the city that is in the middle of the torrent valley, and all the tableland by Med′e·ba; 17 Hesh′bon and all its towns that are on the tableland, Di′bon and Ba′moth-ba′al and Beth-ba′al-me′on, 18 and Ja′haz and Ked′e·moth and Meph′a·ath, 19 and Kir·i·a·tha′im and Sib′mah and Ze′reth-sha′har in the mountain of the low plain, 20 and Beth-pe′or and the slopes of Pis′gah and Beth-jesh′i·moth, 21 and all the cities of the tableland and all the royal realm of Si′hon the king of the Am′or·ites, who reigned in Hesh′bon, and whom Moses struck, together with the chieftains of Mid′i·an, E′vi and Re′kem and Zur and Hur and Re′ba, the dukes of Si′hon, who were dwelling in the land. 22 And Ba′laam the son of Be′or, the diviner, was one whom the sons of Israel killed with the sword along with their slain ones. 23 And the boundary of the sons of Reu′ben came to be the Jordan; and this as a territory was the inheritance of the sons of Reu′ben by their families, with the cities and their settlements.

24 Furthermore, Moses made a gift to the tribe of Gad, the sons of Gad by their families, 25 and their territory came to be Ja′zer and all the cities of Gil′e·ad and half of the land of the sons of Am′mon as far as A·ro′er, which is in front of Rab′bah; 26 and from Hesh′bon to Ra′math-miz′peh and Bet′o·nim and from Ma·ha·na′im to the border of De′bir; 27 and in the low plain Beth-ha′ram and Beth-nim′rah and Suc′coth and Za′phon, the rest of the royal realm of Si′hon the king of Hesh′bon, the Jordan being the border as far as the extremity of the sea of Chin′ne·reth on the side of Jordan toward the east. 28 This was the inheritance of the sons of Gad by their families, with the cities and their settlements.

29 Further, Moses made a gift to the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh, and it came to be that of the half tribe of the sons of Ma·nas′seh by their families. 30 And their territory came to be from Ma·ha·na′im all of Ba′shan, all the royal realm of Og the king of Ba′shan, and all the tent villages of Ja′ir that are in Ba′shan, sixty towns. 31 And half of Gil′e·ad, and Ash′ta·roth and Ed′re·i, the cities of the royal realm of Og in Ba′shan, went to the sons of Ma′chir the son of Ma·nas′seh, to half of the sons of Ma′chir by their families.

32 These were what Moses caused them to inherit, on the desert plains of Mo′ab on the side of the Jordan, at Jer′i·cho, toward the east.

33 And to the tribe of the Levites Moses did not give an inheritance. Jehovah the God of Israel is their inheritance, just as he has promised them.

Joshua

16 And the lot came out for the sons of Joseph from the Jordan at Jer′i·cho to the waters of Jer′i·cho eastward, the wilderness going up from Jer′i·cho into the mountainous region of Beth′el. 2 And it went out from Beth′el belonging to Luz and passed over to the boundary of the Ar′chites at At′a·roth, 3 and it went down westward to the boundary of the Japh′le·tites as far as the boundary of Lower Beth-ho′ron and Ge′zer, and its termination proved to be at the sea.

4 And the sons of Joseph, Ma·nas′seh and E′phra·im, proceeded to take possession of land. 5 And the boundary of the sons of E′phra·im by their families came to be, yes, the boundary of their inheritance toward the east came to be At′a·roth-ad′dar, as far as Upper Beth-ho′ron; 6 and the boundary went out to the sea. Mich·me′thath was on the north, and the boundary went around eastward to Ta′a·nath-shi′loh, and passed over eastward to Ja·no′ah. 7 And it went down from Ja·no′ah to At′a·roth and Na′a·rah and reached to Jer′i·cho and went out to the Jordan. 8 From Tap′pu·ah the boundary moved on westward to the torrent valley of Ka′nah, and its termination proved to be at the sea. This is the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of E′phra·im by their families. 9 And the sons of E′phra·im had enclave cities in the midst of the inheritance of the sons of Ma·nas′seh, all the cities and their settlements.

10 And they did not drive away the Ca′naan·ites who were dwelling in Ge′zer, and the Ca′naan·ites continue dwelling in among E′phra·im down to this day and came to be subject to slavish forced labor.

Joshua

17 And the lot came to be for the tribe of Ma·nas′seh, because he was Joseph’s firstborn, for Ma′chir the firstborn of Ma·nas′seh, the father of Gil′e·ad, because he was one who proved to be a man of war; and Gil′e·ad and Ba′shan came to belong to him. 2 And there came to be a lot for the sons of Ma·nas′seh who were left over according to their families, for the sons of Abi-e′zer and the sons of He′lek and the sons of As′ri·el and the sons of She′chem and the sons of He′pher and the sons of She·mi′da. These were the sons of Ma·nas′seh the son of Joseph, the males according to their families. 3 As for Ze·lo′phe·had the son of He′pher, the son of Gil′e·ad, the son of Ma′chir, the son of Ma·nas′seh, he proved to have, not sons, but daughters, and these were the names of his daughters: Mah′lah and Noah, Hog′lah, Mil′cah and Tir′zah. 4 So they presented themselves before El·e·a′zar the priest and Joshua the son of Nun and the chieftains, saying: “Jehovah it was who commanded Moses to give us an inheritance in the midst of our brothers.” Accordingly he gave them, at the order of Jehovah, an inheritance in the midst of the brothers of their father.

5 And there were ten allotments falling to Ma·nas′seh apart from the land of Gil′e·ad and Ba′shan, which were on the other side of the Jordan; 6 for the daughters of Ma·nas′seh came into an inheritance in the midst of his sons; and the land of Gil′e·ad became the property of the sons of Ma·nas′seh who were left over.

7 And the boundary of Ma·nas′seh came to be from Ash′er to Mich·me′thath, which is in front of She′chem, and the boundary moved to the right to the inhabitants of En-Tap′pu·ah. 8 The land of Tap′pu·ah became Ma·nas′seh’s, but Tap′pu·ah at the boundary of Ma·nas′seh belonged to the sons of E′phra·im. 9 And the boundary went down to the torrent valley of Ka′nah, southward to the torrent valley of these cities of E′phra·im in the midst of the cities of Ma·nas′seh, and the boundary of Ma·nas′seh was on the north of the torrent valley, and its termination came to be at the sea. 10 To the south it was E′phra·im’s and to the north, Ma·nas′seh’s, and the sea came to be his boundary; and on the north they reach to Ash′er and on the east, to Is′sa·char.

11 And there came to belong to Ma·nas′seh in Is′sa·char and in Ash′er Beth-she′an and its dependent towns and Ib′le·am and its dependent towns and the inhabitants of Dor and its dependent towns and the inhabitants of En-dor and its dependent towns and the inhabitants of Ta′a·nach and its dependent towns and the inhabitants of Me·gid′do and its dependent towns, three of the heights.

12 And the sons of Ma·nas′seh did not prove able to take possession of these cities, but the Ca′naan·ites persisted in dwelling in this land. 13 And it turned out that when the sons of Israel had grown strong, they went putting the Ca′naan·ites at forced labor, and they did not dispossess them entirely.

14 And the sons of Joseph proceeded to speak with Joshua, saying: “Why is it that you have given me as an inheritance one lot and one allotment, whereas I am a numerous people for the reason that Jehovah has blessed me until now?” 15 At this Joshua said to them: “If you are a numerous people, go your way up to the forest, and you must cut it down for yourself there in the land of the Per′iz·zites and the Reph′a·im, because the mountainous region of E′phra·im has become too narrow for you.” 16 Then the sons of Joseph said: “The mountainous region is not enough for us, and there are war chariots with iron scythes among all the Ca′naan·ites dwelling in the land of the low plain, both those who are in Beth-she′an and its dependent towns and those who are in the low plain of Jez′re·el.” 17 So Joshua said this to the house of Joseph, to E′phra·im and Ma·nas′seh: “A numerous people you are, and great power is yours. You ought not to get one lot, 18 but the mountainous region should become yours. Because it is a forest, you must cut it down, and it must become the termination point for you. For you should drive away the Ca′naan·ites, although they have war chariots with iron scythes and they are strong.”

Joshua

19 Then the second lot came out for Sim′e·on, for the tribe of the sons of Sim′e·on by their families. And their inheritance came to be in the midst of the inheritance of the sons of Judah. 2 And they came to have in their inheritance Be′er-she′ba with She′ba, and Mo·la′dah, 3 and Ha′zar-shu′al and Ba′lah and E′zem, 4 and El·to′lad and Be′thul and Hor′mah, 5 and Zik′lag and Beth-mar′ca·both and Ha′zar-su′sah, 6 and Beth-le·ba′oth and Sha·ru′hen; thirteen cities and their settlements. 7 A′in, Rim′mon and E′ther and A′shan; four cities and their settlements, 8 and all the settlements that were all around these cities as far as Ba′al·ath-be′er, Ra′mah of the south. This was the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Sim′e·on by their families. 9 The inheritance of the sons of Sim′e·on was out of the allotment of the sons of Judah, because the share of the sons of Judah proved to be too large for them. So the sons of Sim′e·on got a possession in the midst of their inheritance.

10 Next the third lot came up for the sons of Zeb′u·lun by their families, and the boundary of their inheritance came to be as far as Sa′rid. 11 And their boundary went up westward also to Mar′e·al and reached to Dab′be·sheth and reached to the torrent valley that is in front of Jok′ne·am. 12 And it went back from Sa′rid eastward toward the rising of the sun to the border of Chis′loth-ta′bor and went out to Dab′e·rath and went up to Ja·phi′a. 13 And from there it passed over eastward toward the sunrise to Gath-he′pher, to Eth-ka′zin, and went out to Rim′mon and was marked out to Ne′ah. 14 And the boundary went around it on the north to Han′na·thon, and its terminations proved to be at the valley of Iph′tah-el, 15 and Kat′tath and Na·hal′al and Shim′ron and I′da·lah and Beth′le·hem; twelve cities and their settlements. 16 This was the inheritance of the sons of Zeb′u·lun by their families. These were the cities and their settlements.

17 It was for Is′sa·char that the fourth lot came out, for the sons of Is′sa·char by their families. 18 And their boundary came to be to Jez′re·el and Che·sul′loth and Shu′nem, 19 and Haph′a·ra′im and Shi′on and An·a·ha′rath, 20 and Rab′bith and Kish′i·on and E′bez, 21 and Re′meth and En-gan′nim and En-had′dah and Beth-paz′zez. 22 And the boundary reached to Ta′bor and Sha·ha·zu′mah and Beth-she′mesh, and the terminations of their border proved to be at the Jordan; sixteen cities and their settlements. 23 This was the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Is′sa·char by their families, the cities and their settlements.

24 Then the fifth lot came out for the tribe of the sons of Ash′er by their families. 25 And their boundary came to be Hel′kath and Ha′li and Be′ten and Ach′shaph, 26 and Al·lam′me·lech and A′mad and Mi′shal. And it reached westward to Car′mel and to Shi′hor-lib′nath, 27 and it went back toward the rising of the sun to Beth-da′gon and reached to Zeb′u·lun and the valley of Iph′tah-el to the north, to Beth-e′mek and Ne·i′el, and it went out to Ca′bul on the left, 28 and to E′bron and Re′hob and Ham′mon and Ka′nah as far as populous Si′don. 29 And the boundary went back to Ra′mah and as far as the fortified city of Tyre. And the boundary went back to Ho′sah, and its terminations came to be at the sea in the region of Ach′zib, 30 and Um′mah and A′phek and Re′hob; twenty-two cities and their settlements. 31 This was the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Ash′er by their families. These were the cities and their settlements.

32 It was for the sons of Naph′ta·li that the sixth lot came out, for the sons of Naph′ta·li by their families. 33 And their boundary came to be from He′leph, from the big tree in Za·a·nan′nim, and Ad′a·mi-ne′keb and Jab′ne·el as far as Lak′kum; and its terminations came to be at the Jordan. 34 And the boundary went back westward to Az′noth-ta′bor and went out from there to Huk′kok and reached to Zeb′u·lun on the south, and to Ash′er it reached on the west and to Judah at the Jordan toward the rising of the sun. 35 And the fortified cities were Zid′dim, Zer and Ham′math, Rak′kath and Chin′ne·reth, 36 and Ad′a·mah and Ra′mah and Ha′zor, 37 and Ke′desh and Ed′re·i and En-ha′zor, 38 and Yi′ron and Mig′dal-el, Ho′rem and Beth-a′nath and Beth-she′mesh; nineteen cities and their settlements. 39 This was the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Naph′ta·li by their families, the cities and their settlements.

40 It was for the tribe of the sons of Dan by their families that the seventh lot came out. 41 And the border of their inheritance came to be Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol and Ir-she′mesh, 42 and Sha·al·ab′bin and Ai′ja·lon and Ith′lah, 43 and E′lon and Tim′nah and Ek′ron, 44 and El′te·keh and Gib′be·thon and Ba′al·ath, 45 and Je′hud and Ben′e-be′rak and Gath-rim′mon, 46 and Me-jar′kon and Rak′kon, with the border in front of Jop′pa. 47 And the territory of the sons of Dan was too cramped for them. And the sons of Dan proceeded to go up and war against Le′shem and to capture it and strike it with the edge of the sword. Then they took possession of it and went dwelling in it, and they began to call Le′shem Dan, according to the name of Dan their forefather. 48 This was the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Dan by their families. These were the cities and their settlements.

49 Thus they finished dividing the land for a possession by its territories. Then the sons of Israel gave an inheritance to Joshua the son of Nun in their midst. 50 At the order of Jehovah they gave him the city for which he asked, namely, Tim′nath-se′rah, in the mountainous region of E′phra·im; and he began to build up the city and dwell in it.

51 These were the inheritances that El·e·a′zar the priest and Joshua the son of Nun and the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the sons of Israel distributed as a possession by lot in Shi′loh before Jehovah, at the entrance of the tent of meeting. So they left off from apportioning the land.

Joshua

21 The heads of the fathers of the Levites now approached El·e·a′zar the priest and Joshua the son of Nun and the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the sons of Israel, 2 and they proceeded to speak to them in Shi′loh in the land of Ca′naan, saying: “Jehovah by means of Moses commanded cities to be given us in which to dwell, together with their pasture grounds for our domestic animals.” 3 So the sons of Israel gave the Levites, at the order of Jehovah, these cities and their pasture grounds out of their inheritance.

4 Then the lot came out for the families of the Ko′hath·ites, and thirteen cities came to belong to the sons of Aaron the priest, of the Levites, by lot, out of the tribe of Judah and out of the tribe of the Sim′e·on·ites and out of the tribe of Benjamin.

5 And for the sons of Ko′hath that were left over there were by lot ten cities out of the families of the tribe of E′phra·im and out of the tribe of Dan and out of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh.

6 And for the sons of Ger′shon there were by lot thirteen cities out of the families of the tribe of Is′sa·char and out of the tribe of Ash′er and out of the tribe of Naph′ta·li and out of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh in Ba′shan.

7 For the sons of Me·rar′i by their families there were twelve cities out of the tribe of Reu′ben and out of the tribe of Gad and out of the tribe of Zeb′u·lun.

8 Thus the sons of Israel gave the Levites these cities and their pasture grounds by lot, just as Jehovah had commanded by means of Moses.

9 So out of the tribe of the sons of Judah and out of the tribe of the sons of Sim′e·on they gave these cities that were called by name, 10 and they came to belong to the sons of Aaron out of the families of the Ko′hath·ites of the sons of Le′vi, because the first lot became theirs. 11 Thus they gave them Kir′i·ath-ar′ba (said Ar′ba being the father of A′nak), that is to say, He′bron, in the mountainous region of Judah, and its pasture ground all around it; 12 and the field of the city and its settlements they gave to Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh as his possession.

13 And to the sons of Aaron the priest they gave the city of refuge for the manslayer, namely, He′bron, and its pasture ground, also Lib′nah and its pasture ground, 14 and Jat′tir and its pasture ground, and Esh·te·mo′a and its pasture ground, 15 and Ho′lon and its pasture ground, and De′bir and its pasture ground, 16 and A′in and its pasture ground, and Jut′tah and its pasture ground, Beth-she′mesh and its pasture ground; nine cities out of these two tribes.

17 And out of the tribe of Benjamin, Gib′e·on and its pasture ground, Ge′ba and its pasture ground, 18 An′a·thoth and its pasture ground, and Al′mon and its pasture ground; four cities.

19 All the cities of the sons of Aaron, the priests, were thirteen cities and their pasture grounds.

20 And for the families of the sons of Ko′hath, the Levites who were left over of the sons of Ko′hath, there came to be by their lot cities out of the tribe of E′phra·im. 21 Accordingly they gave them the city of refuge for the manslayer, namely, She′chem, and its pasture ground in the mountainous region of E′phra·im, and Ge′zer and its pasture ground, 22 and Kib′za·im and its pasture ground, and Beth-ho′ron and its pasture ground; four cities.

23 And from the tribe of Dan, El′te·ke and its pasture ground, Gib′be·thon and its pasture ground, 24 Ai′ja·lon and its pasture ground, Gath-rim′mon and its pasture ground; four cities.

25 And from the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh, Ta′a·nach and its pasture ground, and Gath-rim′mon and its pasture ground; two cities.

26 All the cities together with their pasture grounds that the families of the sons of Ko′hath who were left over had were ten.

27 And for the sons of Ger′shon, of the families of the Levites, there was out of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh the city of refuge for the manslayer, namely, Go′lan, in Ba′shan, and its pasture ground, and Be·esh′te·rah and its pasture ground; two cities.

28 And out of the tribe of Is′sa·char, Kish′i·on and its pasture ground, Dab′e·rath and its pasture ground, 29 Jar′muth and its pasture ground, En-gan′nim and its pasture ground; four cities.

30 And out of the tribe of Ash′er, Mi′shal and its pasture ground, Ab′don and its pasture ground, 31 Hel′kath and its pasture ground, and Re′hob and its pasture ground; four cities.

32 And out of the tribe of Naph′ta·li, the city of refuge for the manslayer, namely, Ke′desh in Gal′i·lee, and its pasture ground, and Ham′moth-dor and its pasture ground, and Kar′tan and its pasture ground; three cities.

33 All the cities of the Ger′shon·ites by their families were thirteen cities and their pasture grounds.

34 And the families of the sons of Me·rar′i, the Levites who were left over, had out of the tribe of Zeb′u·lun Jok′ne·am and its pasture ground, Kar′tah and its pasture ground, 35 Dim′nah and its pasture ground, Na·hal′al and its pasture ground; four cities.

36 And out of the tribe of Reu′ben, Be′zer and its pasture ground, and Ja′haz and its pasture ground, 37 Ked′e·moth and its pasture ground, and Meph′a·ath and its pasture ground; four cities.

38 And out of the tribe of Gad, the city of refuge for the manslayer, namely, Ra′moth in Gil′e·ad, and its pasture ground, and Ma·ha·na′im and its pasture ground, 39 Hesh′bon and its pasture ground, Ja′zer and its pasture ground; all the cities being four.

40 All the cities that came to belong to the sons of Me·rar′i by their families, who were left over from the families of the Levites, were, as their lot, twelve cities.

41 All the cities of the Levites in the midst of the possession of the sons of Israel were forty-eight cities together with their pasture grounds. 42 These cities came to be each a city together with its pasture ground all around it—thus as to all these cities.

43 So Jehovah gave Israel all the land that he had sworn to give to their forefathers, and they proceeded to take possession of it and to dwell in it. 44 Furthermore, Jehovah gave them rest all around, according to everything that he had sworn to their forefathers, and not one of all their enemies stood before them. All their enemies Jehovah gave into their hand. 45 Not a promise failed out of all the good promise that Jehovah had made to the house of Israel; it all came true.

Joshua

22 At that time Joshua proceeded to call the Reu′ben·ites and the Gad′ites and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh 2 and to say to them: “For YOUR part, YOU have kept all that Moses the servant of Jehovah commanded YOU, and YOU were obedient to my voice in all that I have commanded YOU. 3 YOU have not left YOUR brothers these many days down to this day, and YOU have kept the obligation of the commandment of Jehovah YOUR God. 4 And now Jehovah YOUR God has given YOUR brothers rest, just as he promised them. So now turn and go YOUR way to YOUR tents in the land of YOUR possession, which Moses the servant of Jehovah gave YOU on the other side of the Jordan. 5 Only be very careful to carry out the commandment and the law that Moses the servant of Jehovah commanded YOU by loving Jehovah YOUR God and by walking in all his ways and by keeping his commandments and by cleaving to him and by serving him with all YOUR heart and with all YOUR soul.”

6 With that Joshua blessed them and sent them away that they might go to their tents. 7 And to the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh Moses had made a gift in Ba′shan, and to the other half of it Joshua made a gift with their brothers on the side of the Jordan to the west. So, too, when Joshua sent them away to their tents, he proceeded to bless them. 8 And he went on to say to them: “Return to YOUR tents with many riches and with very much livestock, with silver and gold and copper and iron and garments in very great quantity. Take YOUR share of the spoil of YOUR enemies together with YOUR brothers.”

9 After that the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh returned and went away from the other sons of Israel, from Shi′loh, which is in the land of Ca′naan, so as to go to the land of Gil′e·ad, to the land of their possession in which they had been settled at the order of Jehovah by means of Moses. 10 When they came to the regions of the Jordan that were in the land of Ca′naan, then the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh built there an altar by the Jordan, an altar great in conspicuousness. 11 Later on the other sons of Israel heard it said: “Look! The sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh have built an altar on the frontier of the land of Ca′naan in the regions of the Jordan on the side belonging to the sons of Israel.” 12 When the sons of Israel got to hear of it, the whole assembly of the sons of Israel were then congregated at Shi′loh to go up for military action against them.

13 Then the sons of Israel sent to the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh in the land of Gil′e·ad Phin′e·has the son of El·e·a′zar the priest, 14 and ten chieftains with him, one chieftain of each paternal house of all the tribes of Israel, and they were each a head of the house of their fathers of the thousands of Israel. 15 In time they came to the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh in the land of Gil′e·ad and began to speak with them, saying:

16 “This is what all the assembly of Jehovah have said, ‘What is this act of unfaithfulness that YOU have perpetrated against the God of Israel in turning back today from following Jehovah by YOUR building for yourselves an altar, that YOU may rebel today against Jehovah? 17 Was the error of Pe′or too small for us, from which we have not cleansed ourselves down to this day, although the plague came to be upon the assembly of Jehovah? 18 And YOU—YOU would turn back today from following Jehovah; and it must occur that should YOU, for YOUR part, rebel today against Jehovah, then tomorrow it will be against the entire assembly of Israel that he will be indignant. 19 Now if it is indeed that the land of YOUR possession is unclean, make YOUR way across to the land of Jehovah’s possession where the tabernacle of Jehovah has resided, and get settled in our midst; and against Jehovah do not YOU rebel and do not make us the ones to rebel by YOUR building for yourselves an altar in addition to the altar of Jehovah our God. 20 Was it not A′chan the son of Ze′rah that perpetrated an act of unfaithfulness in the thing devoted to destruction, and was it not against all the assembly of Israel that there came indignation? And he was not the only man to expire in his error.’”

21 At this the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh answered and spoke with the heads of the thousands of Israel: 22 “Divine One, God, Jehovah, Divine One, God, Jehovah, he is knowing, and Israel, he too will know. If it is in rebellion and if it is in unfaithfulness against Jehovah, do not save us this day. 23 If it was to build for ourselves an altar so as to turn back from following Jehovah, and if it was to offer up burnt offerings and grain offerings on it, and if it was to render up communion sacrifices on it, Jehovah himself will search out; 24 or if it was not rather out of anxious care for something else that we did this, saying, ‘In a future day YOUR sons will say to our sons: “What do YOU have to do with Jehovah the God of Israel? 25 And there is a boundary that Jehovah has put between us and YOU, the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad, namely, the Jordan. YOU have no share in Jehovah.” And YOUR sons will certainly make our sons desist from fearing Jehovah.’

26 “Hence we said, ‘Let us take action in our behalf, please, by building the altar, not for burnt offering nor for sacrifice, 27 but that it may be a witness between us and YOU and our generations after us that we shall render the service of Jehovah before him with our burnt offerings and our sacrifices and our communion sacrifices, that YOUR sons may not say in a future day to our sons: “YOU have no share in Jehovah.”’ 28 So we said, ‘And it must occur that in case they should say that to us and to our generations in a future day, we must also say: “See the representation of Jehovah’s altar that our fathers made, not for burnt offering nor for sacrifice, but it is a witness between us and YOU.”’ 29 It is unthinkable, on our part, to rebel of our own accord against Jehovah and to turn back today from following Jehovah by building an altar for burnt offering, grain offering and sacrifice besides the altar of Jehovah our God that is before his tabernacle!”

30 Now when Phin′e·has the priest and the chieftains of the assembly and the heads of the thousands of Israel who were with him heard the words that the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad and the sons of Ma·nas′seh spoke, it came to be good in their eyes. 31 So Phin′e·has the son of El·e·a′zar the priest said to the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad and the sons of Ma·nas′seh: “Today we do know that Jehovah is in our midst, because YOU have not perpetrated against Jehovah this act of unfaithfulness. Now YOU have delivered the sons of Israel out of the hand of Jehovah.”

32 With that Phin′e·has the son of El·e·a′zar the priest and the chieftains returned from the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad in the land of Gil′e·ad to the land of Ca′naan to the other sons of Israel and brought back word to them. 33 And the word came to be good in the eyes of the sons of Israel; and the sons of Israel proceeded to bless God, and they did not talk of going up for army service against them to ruin the land in which the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad were dwelling.

34 And the sons of Reu′ben and the sons of Gad began to name the altar, because “it is a witness between us that Jehovah is the true God.”

Joshua

24 And Joshua proceeded to assemble all the tribes of Israel together at She′chem and to call the older men of Israel and its heads and its judges and its officers, and they went taking their stand before the true God. 2 And Joshua went on to say to all the people: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘It was on the other side of the River that YOUR forefathers dwelt a long time ago, Te′rah the father of Abraham and the father of Na′hor, and they used to serve other gods.

3 “‘In time I took YOUR forefather Abraham from the other side of the River and had him walk through all the land of Ca′naan and made his seed many. So I gave him Isaac. 4 Then to Isaac I gave Jacob and E′sau. Later to E′sau I gave Mount Se′ir to take possession of it; and Jacob and his sons went down to Egypt. 5 Later on I sent Moses and Aaron, and I went plaguing Egypt with what I did in its midst; and afterward I brought YOU out. 6 When I was bringing YOUR fathers out of Egypt and YOU came to the sea, then the Egyptians went chasing after YOUR fathers with war chariots and cavalrymen to the Red Sea. 7 And they began to cry out to Jehovah. So he placed a darkness between YOU and the Egyptians and brought the sea upon them and covered them, and YOUR eyes got to see what I did in Egypt; and YOU took up dwelling in the wilderness many days.

8 “‘Eventually I brought YOU to the land of the Am′or·ites who were dwelling on the other side of the Jordan, and they went fighting against YOU. At that I gave them into YOUR hand that YOU might take possession of their land, and I annihilated them from before YOU. 9 Then Ba′lak the son of Zip′por, the king of Mo′ab, got up and went fighting against Israel. So he sent and summoned Ba′laam the son of Be′or to call down evil upon YOU. 10 And I did not want to listen to Ba′laam. Consequently he blessed YOU repeatedly. Thus I delivered YOU out of his hand.

11 “‘Then YOU went crossing the Jordan and came to Jer′i·cho. And the landowners of Jer′i·cho, the Am′or·ites and the Per′iz·zites and the Ca′naan·ites and the Hit′tites and the Gir′ga·shites, the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites began fighting against YOU; but I gave them into YOUR hand. 12 So I sent the feeling of dejection ahead of YOU, and it gradually drove them out before YOU—two kings of the Am′or·ites—not with your sword and not with your bow. 13 Thus I gave YOU a land for which YOU had not toiled and cities that YOU had not built, and YOU took up dwelling in them. Vineyards and olive groves that YOU did not plant are what YOU are eating.’

14 “And now fear Jehovah and serve him in faultlessness and in truth, and remove the gods that YOUR forefathers served on the other side of the River and in Egypt, and serve Jehovah. 15 Now if it is bad in YOUR eyes to serve Jehovah, choose for yourselves today whom YOU will serve, whether the gods that YOUR forefathers who were on the other side of the River served or the gods of the Am′or·ites in whose land YOU are dwelling. But as for me and my household, we shall serve Jehovah.”

16 At this the people answered and said: “It is unthinkable, on our part, to leave Jehovah so as to serve other gods. 17 For it is Jehovah our God who brought us and our fathers up out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of slaves, and who performed these great signs before our eyes and who kept guarding us in all the way in which we walked and among all the peoples through the midst of whom we passed. 18 And Jehovah proceeded to drive out all the peoples, even the Am′or·ites, dwelling in the land from before us. As for us, too, we shall serve Jehovah, because he is our God.”

19 Then Joshua said to the people: “YOU are not able to serve Jehovah, for he is a holy God; he is a God exacting exclusive devotion. He will not pardon YOUR revolting and YOUR sins. 20 In case YOU should leave Jehovah and YOU do serve foreign gods, he also will certainly turn back and do YOU injury and exterminate YOU after he has done YOU good.”

21 In turn the people said to Joshua: “No, but Jehovah we shall serve!” 22 At this Joshua said to the people: “YOU are witnesses against yourselves that YOU of YOUR own accord have chosen Jehovah for yourselves, to serve him.” To this they said: “We are witnesses.”

23 “And now remove the foreign gods that are among YOU, and incline YOUR hearts to Jehovah the God of Israel.” 24 In turn the people said to Joshua: “Jehovah our God we shall serve, and to his voice we shall listen!”

25 And Joshua proceeded to conclude a covenant with the people on that day and to constitute for them a regulation and judicial decision in She′chem. 26 Then Joshua wrote these words in the book of God’s law and took a great stone and set it up there under the massive tree that is by the sanctuary of Jehovah.

27 And Joshua went on to say to all the people: “Look! This stone is what will serve as a witness against us, because it has itself heard all the sayings of Jehovah that he has spoken with us, and it must serve as a witness against YOU, that YOU may not deny YOUR God.” 28 With that Joshua sent the people away, each one to his inheritance.

29 And it came about that after these things Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of Jehovah, gradually died at the age of a hundred and ten years. 30 So they buried him in the territory of his inheritance in Tim′nath-se′rah, which is in the mountainous region of E′phra·im, north of Mount Ga′ash. 31 And Israel continued to serve Jehovah all the days of Joshua and all the days of the older men who extended their days after Joshua and who had known all the work of Jehovah that he did for Israel.

32 And Joseph’s bones, which the sons of Israel had brought up out of Egypt, they buried in She′chem in the tract of the field that Jacob had acquired from the sons of Ha′mor, She′chem’s father, for a hundred pieces of money; and it came to belong to the sons of Joseph as an inheritance.

33 Also, El·e·a′zar the son of Aaron died. So they buried him in the Hill of Phin′e·has his son, which he had given him in the mountainous region of E′phra·im.

Judges

3 Now these are the nations that Jehovah let stay so as by them to test Israel, that is, all those who had not experienced any of the wars of Ca′naan; 2 it was only in order for the generations of the sons of Israel to have the experience, so as to teach them war, that is, only those who before that had not experienced such things: 3 The five axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines, and all the Ca′naan·ites, even the Si·do′ni·ans and the Hi′vites inhabiting Mount Leb′a·non from Mount Ba′al-her′mon as far as to the entering in of Ha′math. 4 And they kept serving as agents to test Israel so as to know whether they would obey Jehovah’s commandments that he had commanded their fathers by means of Moses. 5 And the sons of Israel dwelt in among the Ca′naan·ites, the Hit′tites and the Am′or·ites and the Per′iz·zites and the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites. 6 And they proceeded to take their daughters as wives for themselves, and their own daughters they gave to their sons, and they took up serving their gods.

7 So the sons of Israel did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, and they were forgetful of Jehovah their God and went serving the Ba′als and the sacred poles. 8 At this Jehovah’s anger blazed against Israel, so that he sold them into the hand of Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im the king of Mes·o·po·ta′mi·a; and the sons of Israel continued to serve Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im eight years. 9 And the sons of Israel began to call to Jehovah for aid. Then Jehovah raised a savior up for the sons of Israel that he might save them, Oth′ni·el the son of Ke′naz, the younger brother of Ca′leb. 10 The spirit of Jehovah now came upon him, and he became the judge of Israel. When he went out to battle, then Jehovah gave Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im the king of Syria into his hand so that his hand overpowered Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im. 11 After that the land had no disturbance for forty years. Eventually Oth′ni·el the son of Ke′naz died.

12 And once again the sons of Israel went doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. At that Jehovah let Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab grow strong against Israel, because they did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. 13 Furthermore, he gathered against them the sons of Am′mon and Am′a·lek. Then they went and struck Israel and took possession of the city of palm trees. 14 And the sons of Israel continued to serve Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab eighteen years. 15 And the sons of Israel began to call to Jehovah for aid. So Jehovah raised up for them a savior, E′hud the son of Ge′ra, a Ben′ja·mite, a left-handed man. In time the sons of Israel sent tribute by his hand to Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab. 16 Meanwhile E′hud made a sword for himself, and it had two edges, its length being a cubit. Then he girded it underneath his garment upon his right thigh. 17 And he proceeded to present the tribute to Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab. Now Eg′lon was a very fat man.

18 And it came about that when he had finished presenting the tribute, he at once sent the people away, the bearers of the tribute. 19 And he himself turned back at the quarries that were at Gil′gal, and he proceeded to say: “I have a secret word for you, O king.” So he said: “Keep silence!” With that all those who were standing by him went on out from him. 20 And E′hud came to him as he was sitting in his cool roof chamber that he had to himself. And E′hud went on to say: “A word of God I have for you.” At that he rose up from his throne. 21 Then E′hud thrust in his left hand and took the sword off his right thigh and plunged it into his belly. 22 And the handle kept going in also after the blade so that the fat closed in over the blade, for he did not draw the sword out of his belly, and the fecal matter began to come out. 23 And E′hud proceeded to go out through the air hole, but he closed the doors of the roof chamber behind him and locked them. 24 And he himself went out.

And his servants came and began looking, and there the doors of the roof chamber were locked. So they said: “He is just easing nature in the cool interior room.” 25 And they kept waiting until they were ashamed, and, look! there was no one opening the doors of the roof chamber. At this they took the key and opened them, and, look! their lord was fallen to the earth dead!

26 As for E′hud, he escaped while they were lingering, and he himself passed by the quarries and made his escape to Se·i′rah. 27 And it came about that when he got there he began blowing the horn in the mountainous region of E′phra·im; and the sons of Israel began going down with him out of the mountainous region, he being at their head. 28 Then he said to them: “Follow me, because Jehovah has given YOUR enemies, the Mo′ab·ites, into YOUR hand.” And they went following him and got to capture the fords of the Jordan against the Mo′ab·ites, and they did not allow anybody to pass over. 29 And at that time they went striking down Mo′ab, about ten thousand men, every one robust and every one a valiant man; and not a single one escaped. 30 And Mo′ab came to be subdued on that day under Israel’s hand; and the land had no further disturbance for eighty years.

31 And after him there proved to be Sham′gar the son of A′nath, and he went striking down the Phi·lis′tines, six hundred men, with a cattle goad; and he too got to save Israel.

Judges

5 And on that day Deb′o·rah along with Ba′rak the son of A·bin′o·am broke out in song, saying:

2 “For letting the hair hang loose in Israel for war,

For the people’s volunteering,

BLESS Jehovah.

3 Listen, YOU kings; give ear, YOU high officials:

I to Jehovah, yes, I, will sing.

I shall make melody to Jehovah, Israel’s God.

4 Jehovah, at your going forth from Se′ir,

At your marching out of the field of E′dom,

Earth rocked, heavens also dripped,

Clouds also dripped with water.

5 Mountains flowed away from the face of Jehovah,

This Si′nai away from the face of Jehovah, Israel’s God.

6 In the days of Sham′gar the son of A′nath,

In the days of Ja′el, pathways had no traffic,

And the travelers of roadways would travel by roundabout pathways.

7 The dwellers in open country ceased, in Israel they ceased,

Until I, Deb′o·rah, rose up,

Until I rose up as a mother in Israel.

8 They proceeded to choose new gods.

It was then there was war in the gates.

A shield could not be seen, nor a lance,

Among forty thousand in Israel.

9 My heart is for the commanders of Israel,

Who were volunteers among the people.

BLESS Jehovah.

10 YOU riders on yellowish-red she-asses,

YOU who sit on rich carpets,

And YOU who walk on the road,

Consider!

11 Some of the voices of the water distributors among the places of drawing water,

There they began to recount the righteous acts of Jehovah,

The righteous acts of his dwellers in open country in Israel.

It was then Jehovah’s people made their way down to the gates.

12 Awake, awake, O Deb′o·rah;

Awake, awake, utter a song!

Rise up, Ba′rak, and lead your captives away, you son of A·bin′o·am!

13 It was then the survivors came down to the majestic ones;

Jehovah’s people came down to me against the mighty ones.

14 Out of E′phra·im was their origin in the low plain,

With you, O Benjamin, among your peoples.

Out of Ma′chir the commanders went down,

And out of Zeb′u·lun those handling the equipment of a scribe.

15 And the princes in Is′sa·char were with Deb′o·rah,

And as Is′sa·char, so was Ba′rak.

Into the low plain he was sent on foot.

Among the divisions of Reu′ben great were the searchings of the heart.

16 Why did you sit down between the two saddlebags,

To listen to the pipings for the flocks?

For the divisions of Reu′ben there were great searchings of the heart.

17 Gil′e·ad kept to his residence on the other side of the Jordan;

And Dan, why did he continue to dwell for the time in ships?

Ash′er sat idle at the seashore,

And by his landing places he kept residing.

18 Zeb′u·lun was a people that scorned their souls to the point of death;

Naph′ta·li also, on the heights of the field.

19 Kings came, they fought;

It was then that the kings of Ca′naan fought

In Ta′a·nach by the waters of Me·gid′do.

No gain of silver did they take.

20 From heaven did the stars fight,

From their orbits they fought against Sis′e·ra.

21 The torrent of Ki′shon washed them away,

The torrent of ancient days, the torrent of Ki′shon.

You went treading down strength, O my soul.

22 It was then that the hoofs of horses pawed

Because of dashings upon dashings of his stallions.

23 ‘CURSE Me′roz,’ said the angel of Jehovah,

‘CURSE its inhabitants incessantly,

For they did not come to the assistance of Jehovah,

To the assistance of Jehovah with the mighty ones.’

24 Ja′el the wife of He′ber the Ken′ite will be most blessed among women,

Among women in the tent she will be most blessed.

25 Water he asked, milk she gave;

In the large banquet bowl of majestic ones she presented curdled milk.

26 Her hand to the tent pin she then thrust out,

And her right hand to the mallet of hard workers.

And she hammered Sis′e·ra, she pierced his head through,

And she broke apart and cut up his temples.

27 Between her feet he collapsed, he fell, he lay down;

Between her feet he collapsed, he fell;

Where he collapsed, there he fell overcome.

28 From the window a woman looked out and kept watching for him,

The mother of Sis′e·ra from the lattice,

‘Why has his war chariot delayed in coming?

Why must the hoofbeats of his chariots be so late?’

29 The wise ones of her noble ladies would answer her,

Yes, she too would talk back to herself with her own sayings,

30 ‘Ought they not to find, ought they not to distribute spoil,

A womb—two wombs to every able-bodied man,

Spoil of dyed stuffs for Sis′e·ra, spoil of dyed stuffs,

An embroidered garment, dyed stuff, two embroidered garments

For the necks of men of spoil?’

31 Thus let all your enemies perish, O Jehovah,

And let your lovers be as when the sun goes forth in its mightiness.”

And the land had no further disturbance for forty years.

Judges

8 Then the men of E′phra·im said to him: “What sort of thing is this that you have done to us in not calling us when you went to fight against Mid′i·an?” And they vehemently tried to pick a quarrel with him. 2 Finally he said to them: “What now have I done in comparison with YOU? Are not the gleanings of E′phra·im better than the grape gathering of Abi-e′zer? 3 It was into YOUR hand that God gave Mid′i·an’s princes O′reb and Ze′eb, and what have I been able to do in comparison with YOU?” It was then that their spirit calmed down toward him when he spoke this word.

4 Eventually Gid′e·on came to the Jordan, crossing it, he and the three hundred men that were with him, tired but keeping up the pursuit. 5 Later he said to the men of Suc′coth: “Please give round loaves of bread to the people that are following my steps, for they are tired and I am chasing after Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na, the kings of Mid′i·an.” 6 But the princes of Suc′coth said: “Are the palms of Ze′bah and of Zal·mun′na already in your hand so that bread has to be given to your army?” 7 At this Gid′e·on said: “That is why when Jehovah gives Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na into my hand, I shall certainly give YOUR flesh a threshing with the thorns of the wilderness and the briers.” 8 And he continued on his way up from there to Pe·nu′el and went speaking to them in this same manner, but the men of Pe·nu′el answered him just as the men of Suc′coth had answered. 9 Hence he said also to the men of Pe·nu′el: “When I return in peace, I shall pull down this tower.”

10 Now Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na were in Kar′kor, and their camps with them, about fifteen thousand being all who were left over out of the entire camp of the Easterners; and those already fallen were a hundred and twenty thousand men who used to draw the sword. 11 And Gid′e·on continued on up by the way of those residing in tents to the east of No′bah and Jog′be·hah and began to strike the camp while the camp happened to be off guard. 12 When Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na took to flight, he at once went in pursuit of them and got to capture Mid′i·an’s two kings, Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na; and he drove all the camp into trembling.

13 And Gid′e·on the son of Jo′ash began his return from the war by the pass that goes up to He′res. 14 En route he captured a young man of the men of Suc′coth and made inquiries of him. So he wrote out for him the names of the princes of Suc′coth and its older men, seventy-seven men. 15 With that he went to the men of Suc′coth and said: “Here are Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na respecting whom YOU taunted me, saying, ‘Are the palms of Ze′bah and of Zal·mun′na already in your hand so that bread has to be given to your tired-out men?’” 16 Then he took the older men of the city and thorns of the wilderness and briers, and with them he put the men of Suc′coth through an experience. 17 And the tower of Pe·nu′el he pulled down, and he proceeded to kill the men of the city.

18 He now said to Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na: “What sort of men were they whom YOU killed in Ta′bor?” To this they said: “As you are, so were they, each one, like the sons of a king in form.” 19 At that he said: “They were my brothers, the sons of my mother. As Jehovah lives, if YOU had preserved them alive, I would not have to kill YOU.” 20 Then he said to Je′ther his firstborn: “Get up, kill them.” And the young man did not draw his sword, because he was afraid, for he was yet a young man. 21 So Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na said: “Get up yourself and assault us, for as a man is, so is his mightiness.” Accordingly Gid′e·on got up and killed Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na and took the moon-shaped ornaments that were on the necks of their camels.

22 Later the men of Israel said to Gid′e·on: “Rule over us, you and your son and your grandson as well, for you have saved us out of the hand of Mid′i·an.” 23 But Gid′e·on said to them: “I myself shall not rule over YOU, nor will my son rule over YOU. Jehovah is the one who will rule over YOU.” 24 And Gid′e·on went on to say to them: “Let me make a request of YOU: Give me, each one of YOU, the nose ring of his booty.” (For they had nose rings of gold, because they were Ish′ma·el·ites.) 25 Then they said: “We shall surely give them.” With that they spread out a mantle and went throwing each one the nose ring of his booty into it. 26 And the weight of the nose rings of gold that he had requested amounted to one thousand seven hundred gold shekels, besides the moon-shaped ornaments and the eardrops and the garments of wool dyed reddish purple that were upon the kings of Mid′i·an and besides the necklaces that were on the necks of the camels.

27 And Gid′e·on proceeded to make it into an eph′od and to exhibit it in his city Oph′rah; and all Israel began to have immoral intercourse with it there, so that it served as a snare to Gid′e·on and to his household.

28 Thus Mid′i·an was subdued before the sons of Israel, and they did not lift up their head anymore; and the land had no further disturbance for forty years in the days of Gid′e·on.

29 And Jer·ub·ba′al the son of Jo′ash went his way and continued to dwell in his house.

30 And Gid′e·on came to have seventy sons that issued out of his upper thigh, for he came to have many wives. 31 As for the concubine of his that was in She′chem, she too bore him a son. So he named him A·bim′e·lech. 32 Eventually Gid′e·on the son of Jo′ash died at a good old age and was buried in the burial place of Jo′ash his father in Oph′rah of the Abi-ez′rites.

33 And it came about that as soon as Gid′e·on had died the sons of Israel again took up having immoral intercourse with the Ba′als, so that they appointed Ba′al-be′rith as their god. 34 And the sons of Israel did not remember Jehovah their God, who had delivered them out of the hand of all their enemies round about; 35 and they did not exercise loving-kindness toward the household of Jer·ub·ba′al, Gid′e·on, in return for all the goodness that he had exercised toward Israel.

Judges

10 Now after A·bim′e·lech there rose up to save Israel To′la the son of Pu′ah, the son of Do′do, a man of Is′sa·char, and he was dwelling in Sha′mir in the mountainous region of E′phra·im. 2 And he continued to judge Israel for twenty-three years, after which he died and was buried in Sha′mir.

3 Then after him Ja′ir the Gil′e·ad·ite rose up, and he continued to judge Israel for twenty-two years. 4 And he came to have thirty sons who rode on thirty full-grown asses, and they had thirty cities. These they continue to call Hav′voth-ja′ir down to this day; they are in the land of Gil′e·ad. 5 After that Ja′ir died and was buried in Ka′mon.

6 And the sons of Israel again proceeded to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and they began to serve the Ba′als and the Ash′to·reth images and the gods of Syria and the gods of Si′don and the gods of Mo′ab and the gods of the sons of Am′mon and the gods of the Phi·lis′tines. So they left Jehovah and did not serve him. 7 At this Jehovah’s anger blazed against Israel, so that he sold them into the hand of the Phi·lis′tines and into the hand of the sons of Am′mon. 8 Hence they shattered and heavily oppressed the sons of Israel in that year—for eighteen years all the sons of Israel that were on the side of the Jordan in the land of the Am′or·ites that was in Gil′e·ad. 9 And the sons of Am′mon would cross the Jordan to fight even against Judah and Benjamin and the house of E′phra·im; and Israel was greatly distressed. 10 And the sons of Israel began to call to Jehovah for aid, saying: “We have sinned against you, because we have left our God and we serve the Ba′als.”

11 Then Jehovah said to the sons of Israel: “Was it not from Egypt and from the Am′or·ites and from the sons of Am′mon and from the Phi·lis′tines 12 and the Si·do′ni·ans and Am′a·lek and Mid′i·an, when they oppressed YOU and YOU went crying out to me, that I proceeded to save YOU out of their hand? 13 As for YOU, YOU abandoned me and took up serving other gods. That is why I shall not save YOU again. 14 Go and call for aid to the gods whom YOU have chosen. Let them be the ones to save YOU in the time of YOUR distress.” 15 But the sons of Israel said to Jehovah: “We have sinned. You yourself do to us according to anything that is good in your eyes. Only deliver us, please, this day.” 16 And they began to remove the foreign gods from their midst and to serve Jehovah, so that his soul became impatient because of the trouble of Israel.

17 In time the sons of Am′mon were called together and pitched camp in Gil′e·ad. So the sons of Israel gathered themselves together and pitched camp in Miz′pah. 18 And the people and the princes of Gil′e·ad began to say to one another: “Who is the man that will take the lead in fighting against the sons of Am′mon? Let him become the head of all the inhabitants of Gil′e·ad.”

Judges

12 Then the men of E′phra·im were called together and crossed over northward and said to Jeph′thah: “Why is it that you crossed over to fight against the sons of Am′mon, and to us you did not issue a call to go with you? Your very house we shall burn over you with fire.” 2 But Jeph′thah said to them: “I became a special contender, I and my people, with the sons of Am′mon. And I proceeded to call to YOU for aid, and YOU did not save me out of their hand. 3 When I got to see that you were no savior, then I determined to put my soul in my own palm and go over against the sons of Am′mon. At that Jehovah gave them into my hand. So why have YOU come up against me this day to fight against me?”

4 Immediately Jeph′thah collected all the men of Gil′e·ad together and fought E′phra·im; and the men of Gil′e·ad went striking E′phra·im down, for they had said: “Men escaped from E′phra·im is what YOU are, O Gil′e·ad, inside of E′phra·im, inside of Ma·nas′seh.” 5 And Gil′e·ad got to capture the fords of the Jordan ahead of E′phra·im; and it occurred that when the escaping men of E′phra·im would say: “Let me pass over,” then the men of Gil′e·ad would say to each one: “Are you an E′phra·im·ite?” When he would say: “No!” 6 then they would say to him: “Please say Shib′bo·leth.” And he would say: “Sib′bo·leth,” as he was unable to say the word correctly. And they would lay hold of him and slay him at the fords of the Jordan. So there fell at that time forty-two thousand out of E′phra·im.

7 And Jeph′thah continued to judge Israel for six years, after which Jeph′thah the Gil′e·ad·ite died and was buried in his city in Gil′e·ad.

8 And Ib′zan from Beth′le·hem began to judge Israel after him. 9 And he came to have thirty sons and thirty daughters. He sent outside and brought in thirty daughters for his sons from outside. And he continued to judge Israel for seven years. 10 Then Ib′zan died and was buried in Beth′le·hem.

11 And after him E′lon the Ze·bu′lu·nite began to judge Israel. And he continued to judge Israel ten years. 12 Then E′lon the Ze·bu′lu·nite died and was buried in Ai′ja·lon in the land of Zeb′u·lun.

13 And after him Ab′don the son of Hil′lel the Pir′a·thon·ite began to judge Israel. 14 And he came to have forty sons and thirty grandsons who rode on seventy full-grown asses. And he continued to judge Israel eight years. 15 Then Ab′don the son of Hil′lel the Pir′a·thon·ite died and was buried in Pir′a·thon in the land of E′phra·im in the mountain of the A·mal′ek·ite.

Judges

13 And the sons of Israel engaged again in doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, so that Jehovah gave them into the hand of the Phi·lis′tines for forty years.

2 Meanwhile there happened to be a certain man of Zo′rah of the family of the Dan′ites, and his name was Ma·no′ah. And his wife was barren and had borne no child. 3 In time Jehovah’s angel appeared to the woman and said to her: “Look, now, you are barren and have borne no child. And you will certainly become pregnant and give birth to a son. 4 And now watch yourself, please, and do not drink wine or intoxicating liquor, and do not eat anything unclean. 5 For, look! you will be pregnant, and you will certainly give birth to a son, and no razor should come upon his head, because a Naz′i·rite of God is what the child will become on leaving the belly; and he it is who will take the lead in saving Israel out of the hand of the Phi·lis′tines.”

6 Then the woman went and said to her husband: “There was a man of the true God that came to me, and his appearance was like the appearance of the angel of the true God, very fear-inspiring. And I did not ask him from just where he was, neither did he tell me his name. 7 But he said to me, ‘Look! You will be pregnant, and you will certainly give birth to a son. And now do not drink wine or intoxicating liquor, and do not eat any unclean thing, because a Naz′i·rite of God is what the child will become on leaving the belly until the day of his death.’”

8 And Ma·no′ah began to entreat Jehovah and say: “Excuse me, Jehovah. The man of the true God that you just sent, let him, please, come again to us and instruct us as to what we ought to do to the child that will be born.” 9 Accordingly the true God listened to the voice of Ma·no′ah, and the angel of the true God came again to the woman while she was sitting in the field, and Ma·no′ah her husband was not with her. 10 Immediately the woman hurried and ran and told her husband and said to him: “Look! The man that came the other day to me has appeared to me.”

11 At that Ma·no′ah got up and accompanied his wife and came to the man and said to him: “Are you the man that spoke to the woman?” to which he said: “I am.” 12 Then Ma·no′ah said: “Now let your words come true. What will become the child’s mode of life and his work?” 13 So Jehovah’s angel said to Ma·no′ah: “From everything that I mentioned to the woman she should keep herself. 14 Nothing at all that comes forth from the wine vine should she eat, and no wine or intoxicating liquor let her drink, and no unclean thing of any sort let her eat. Everything that I have commanded her let her keep.”

15 Ma·no′ah now said to Jehovah’s angel: “Let us, please, detain you and fix up a kid of the goats before you.” 16 But Jehovah’s angel said to Ma·no′ah: “If you detain me, I shall not feed myself on your bread; but if you will render up a burnt offering to Jehovah, you may offer it up.” For Ma·no′ah did not know that he was Jehovah’s angel. 17 Then Ma·no′ah said to Jehovah’s angel: “What is your name, that when your word comes true we shall certainly do you honor?” 18 However, Jehovah’s angel said to him: “Just why should you ask about my name, when it is a wonderful one?”

19 And Ma·no′ah proceeded to take the kid of the goats and the grain offering and to offer it upon the rock to Jehovah. And He was doing something in a wonderful way while Ma·no′ah and his wife were looking on. 20 So it came about that, as the flame ascended from off the altar heavenward, then Jehovah’s angel ascended in the flame of the altar while Ma·no′ah and his wife were looking on. At once they fell upon their faces to the earth. 21 And Jehovah’s angel did not repeat appearing to Ma·no′ah and his wife anymore. Then it was that Ma·no′ah knew that he had been Jehovah’s angel. 22 Consequently Ma·no′ah said to his wife: “We shall positively die, because it is God that we have seen.” 23 But his wife said to him: “If Jehovah had been delighted only to put us to death, he would not have accepted a burnt offering and grain offering from our hand, and he would not have shown us all these things, and he would not as now have let us hear anything like this.”

24 Later the woman gave birth to a son and called his name Samson; and the boy kept getting bigger, and Jehovah continued to bless him. 25 In time Jehovah’s spirit started to impel him in Ma′ha·neh-dan between Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol.

Judges

15 And it came about after a while, in the days of wheat harvest, that Samson went visiting his wife with a kid of the goats. So he said: “I will go in to my wife in the interior room.” And her father did not allow him to go in. 2 But her father said: “I really said to myself, ‘You must unquestionably hate her.’ Hence I gave her to your groomsman. Is not her younger sister better than she is? Let her, please, become yours instead of the other.” 3 However, Samson said to them: “This time I must be free of guilt against the Phi·lis′tines in case I am dealing with them to their injury.”

4 And Samson went his way and proceeded to catch three hundred foxes and to take torches and turn tail to tail and put one torch between two tails, right in the middle. 5 With that he set fire to the torches and sent them out into the fields of standing grain of the Phi·lis′tines. Thus he set on fire everything from sheaf to standing grain and the vineyards and the olive groves.

6 And the Phi·lis′tines began to say: “Who did this?” Then they said: “It was Samson the son-in-law of the Tim′nite, because he took his wife and then gave her to his groomsman.” At that the Phi·lis′tines went up and burned her and her father with fire. 7 In turn Samson said to them: “If YOU do like this, there is nothing but for me to avenge myself upon YOU, and afterward I shall quit.” 8 And he went smiting them, piling legs upon thighs with a great slaughter, after which he went down and began to dwell in a cleft of the crag E′tam.

9 Later the Phi·lis′tines came up and camped in Judah and went tramping about in Le′hi. 10 Then the men of Judah said: “Why have YOU come up against us?” to which they said: “It is to tie Samson that we have come up, to do to him just as he has done to us.” 11 So three thousand men of Judah went down to the cleft of the crag E′tam and said to Samson: “Do you not know that the Phi·lis′tines are ruling over us? So what does this mean that you have done to us?” Then he said to them: “Just as they did to me is the way I have done to them.” 12 But they said to him: “It is to tie you that we have come down, to give you into the hand of the Phi·lis′tines.” At that Samson said to them: “Swear to me that YOU yourselves will not assault me.” 13 And they went on to say to him: “No, but we shall merely tie you, and we will give you into their hand; but we shall by no means put you to death.”

Accordingly they bound him with two new ropes and brought him up out of the crag. 14 He, for his part, came as far as Le′hi, and the Phi·lis′tines, for their part, shouted exultantly at meeting him. And Jehovah’s spirit became operative upon him, and the ropes that were upon his arms came to be like linen threads that have been scorched with fire, so that his fetters melted off his hands. 15 He now found a moist jawbone of a male ass and thrust his hand out and took it and went striking down a thousand men with it. 16 Then Samson said:

“With the jawbone of a male ass—one heap, two heaps!

With the jawbone of a male ass I have struck down a thousand men.”

17 And it came about that when he finished speaking, he immediately threw the jawbone out of his hand and called that place Ra′math-le′hi. 18 Now he became very thirsty, and he began to call on Jehovah and say: “It was you that gave this great salvation into the hand of your servant, and now shall I die of thirst and must I fall into the hand of the uncircumcised?” 19 So God split open a mortar-shaped hollow that was in Le′hi, and water began to come out of it, and he proceeded to drink, after which his spirit returned and he revived. That is why he called its name En-hak·kor′e, which is in Le′hi down to this day.

20 And he continued to judge Israel in the days of the Phi·lis′tines twenty years.

Judges

18 In those days there was no king in Israel. And in those days the tribe of the Dan′ites was looking for an inheritance for itself to dwell there; because up to that day an inheritance had not fallen to them in the midst of the tribes of Israel.

2 Eventually the sons of Dan sent five men of their family, men from among them, men who were valiant fellows, out from Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol, to spy out the land and to explore it. So they said to them: “Go, explore the land.” In time they came into the mountainous region of E′phra·im as far as the house of Mi′cah and got to spend the night there. 3 While they were close by the house of Mi′cah, they recognized the voice of the young man, the Levite, so that they turned aside there. And they proceeded to say to him: “Who brought you here, and what are you doing in this place, and what interest do you have here?” 4 In turn he said to them: “Thus and so Mi′cah did for me that he might hire me, and that I might serve as priest for him.” 5 Then they said to him: “Inquire, please, of God that we may know whether our way on which we are going will be successful.” 6 So the priest said to them: “Go in peace. It is before Jehovah that YOUR way is in which YOU go.”

7 Accordingly the five men went on and came to La′ish and saw how the people that were within it were dwelling in self-reliance according to the custom of the Si·do′ni·ans, quiet and unsuspecting, and there was no oppressive conqueror that was molesting a thing in the land, while they were far off from the Si·do′ni·ans and they had nothing to do with mankind.

8 At length they came to their brothers at Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol, and their brothers began to say to them: “How was it with YOU?” 9 At this they said: “Do get up, and let us go up against them; for we have seen the land, and, look! it is very good. And YOU are hesitant. Do not be sluggish about walking to come in to take possession of the land. 10 When YOU come in, YOU will come to an unsuspecting people, and the land is quite wide; for God has given it into YOUR hand, a place where there is no lack of any sort of thing that is in the earth.”

11 Then six hundred men girded with weapons of war, out of the family of the Dan′ites, departed from there, that is, from Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol. 12 And they got on their way up and went camping at Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim in Judah. That is why they have called that place Ma′ha·neh-dan down to this day. Look! It is west of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim. 13 After that they passed along from there to the mountainous region of E′phra·im and came as far as the house of Mi′cah.

14 Then the five men that had gone to spy out the land of La′ish answered and said to their brothers: “Did YOU know that there are in these houses an eph′od and teraphim and a carved image and a molten statue? And now have in mind what YOU ought to do.” 15 So they turned aside there and came to the house of the young man, the Levite, at the house of Mi′cah, and began to ask how he was getting along. 16 All the while the six hundred men girded with their weapons of war, who were of the sons of Dan, were standing at the entrance of the gate. 17 The five men that had gone to spy out the land now went on up, that they might enter in there to take the carved image and the eph′od and the teraphim and the molten image. (And the priest was standing at the entrance of the gate with the six hundred men girded with weapons of war.) 18 And these went into the house of Mi′cah and proceeded to take the carved image, the eph′od and the teraphim and the molten image. At that the priest said to them: “What are YOU doing?” 19 But they said to him: “Be quiet. Put your hand over your mouth, and go with us and become a father and a priest for us. Which is better, for you to continue a priest to the house of one man or for you to become a priest to a tribe and family in Israel?” 20 At this the heart of the priest was pleased, and he now took the eph′od and the teraphim and the carved image and came into the midst of the people.

21 Then they turned and went their way and put the little ones and the livestock and the valuable things ahead of them. 22 They themselves had got a distance away from the house of Mi′cah when the men who were in the houses that were close by the house of Mi′cah were called together and tried to catch up with the sons of Dan. 23 When they kept crying out to the sons of Dan, then they turned their faces and said to Mi′cah: “What is the matter with you that you have been called together?” 24 So he said: “My gods that I made YOU have taken, the priest too, and YOU go YOUR way, and what do I have anymore? How, then, is it that YOU can say to me, ‘What is the matter with you?’” 25 At this the sons of Dan said to him: “Do not let your voice be heard close to us, for fear that men bitter of soul may assault YOU people, and you have to forfeit your own soul and the soul of your household.” 26 And the sons of Dan kept going on their way; and Mi′cah got to see that they were stronger than he was, and so he turned and went back to his house.

27 As for them, they took what Mi′cah had made and the priest that had become his, and they kept going toward La′ish, against a people quiet and unsuspecting. And they proceeded to strike them with the edge of the sword, and the city they burned with fire. 28 And there was no deliverer, for it was far away from Si′don, and they had nothing at all to do with mankind; and it was in the low plain that belonged to Beth-re′hob. Then they built the city and took up dwelling in it. 29 Furthermore, they called the name of the city Dan by the name of their father, Dan, who had been born to Israel. Nevertheless, La′ish was the city’s name at first. 30 After that the sons of Dan stood up the carved image for themselves; and Jon′a·than the son of Ger′shom, Moses’ son, he and his sons became priests to the tribe of the Dan′ites until the day of the land’s being taken into exile. 31 And they kept the carved image of Mi′cah, which he had made, set up for themselves all the days that the house of the true God continued in Shi′loh.

Judges

19 Now it happened in those days that there was no king in Israel. And it came about that a certain Levite was residing for a time in the remotest parts of the mountainous region of E′phra·im. In time he took as his wife a concubine from Beth′le·hem in Judah. 2 And his concubine began to commit fornication against him. Finally she went away from him to the house of her father at Beth′le·hem in Judah and continued there fully four months. 3 Then her husband got up and went after her to speak consolingly to her so as to bring her back; and there were with him his attendant and a couple of he-asses. So she had him come into her father’s house. When the father of the young woman got to see him, he at once rejoiced to meet him. 4 Consequently his father-in-law, the young woman’s father, took hold of him, so that he continued to dwell with him three days; and they would eat and drink, and he would stay overnight there.

5 And it came about on the fourth day, when they got up early in the morning as usual, he now rose to go, but the father of the young woman said to his son-in-law: “Sustain your heart with a bit of bread and afterward YOU people may go.” 6 So they sat down, and both of them began to eat and to drink together; after which the father of the young woman said to the man: “Come on, please, and stay overnight, and let your heart feel good.” 7 When the man rose to go, his father-in-law kept begging him, so that he stayed overnight there again.

8 When he got up early in the morning on the fifth day to go, the father of the young woman then said: “Please, take sustenance for your heart.” And they lingered until the fading away of the day. And both of them kept eating. 9 The man now rose to go, he and his concubine and his attendant; but his father-in-law, the young woman’s father, said to him: “Look, now! The day has declined toward becoming evening. Please, STAY overnight. Here the day is settling down. Stay here overnight, and let your heart feel good. And tomorrow YOU people must get up early for YOUR journey, and you must go to your tent.” 10 However, the man did not consent to stay overnight, but he rose and got on his way and came as far as in front of Je′bus, that is to say, Jerusalem; and with him there were the couple of he-asses saddled up, and his concubine and his attendant.

11 While they were close by Je′bus, as the daylight had gone down considerably, the attendant now said to his master: “O come, now, and let us turn aside to this city of the Jeb′u·sites and stay in it overnight.” 12 But his master said to him: “Let us not turn aside to a city of foreigners who are no part of the sons of Israel; and we have to pass on as far as Gib′e·ah.” 13 And he went on to say to his attendant: “Come and let us approach one of the places, and we must stay overnight either in Gib′e·ah or in Ra′mah.” 14 So they passed along and kept on their way, and the sun began to set upon them when near to Gib′e·ah, which belongs to Benjamin.

15 Consequently they turned aside there to go in to stay overnight in Gib′e·ah. And they proceeded to go in and sit down in the public square of the city, and there was nobody taking them on into the house to stay overnight. 16 Eventually, look! an old man coming in from his work in the field at evening, and the man was from the mountainous region of E′phra·im, and he was residing for a time in Gib′e·ah; but the men of the place were Ben′ja·mites. 17 When he raised his eyes he got to see the man, the traveler, in the public square of the city. So the old man said: “Where are you going, and where do you come from?” 18 In turn he said to him: “We are passing along from Beth′le·hem in Judah to the remotest parts of the mountainous region of E′phra·im. That is where I am from, but I went to Beth′le·hem in Judah; and it is to my own house that I am going, and there is nobody taking me on into the house. 19 And there are both straw and fodder for our he-asses, and there are both bread and wine for me and your slave girl and for the attendant with your servant. There is no lack of a single thing.” 20 However, the old man said: “May you have peace! Just let any lack of yours be upon me. Only do not stay overnight in the public square.” 21 With that he brought him into his house and threw mash to the he-asses. Then they washed their feet and began to eat and drink.

22 While they were making their hearts feel good, look! the men of the city, mere good-for-nothing men, surrounded the house, shoving one another against the door; and they kept saying to the old man, the owner of the house: “Bring out the man that came into your house, that we may have intercourse with him.” 23 At that the owner of the house went on out to them and said to them: “No, my brothers, do not do anything wrong, please, since this man has come into my house. Do not commit this disgraceful folly. 24 Here are my virgin daughter and his concubine. Let me bring them out, please, and YOU rape them and do to them what is good in YOUR eyes. But to this man YOU must not do this disgraceful, foolish thing.”

25 And the men did not want to listen to him. Hence the man took hold of his concubine and brought her forth to them outside; and they began to have intercourse with her, and kept on abusing her all night long until the morning, after which they sent her off at the ascending of the dawn. 26 Then the woman came as it was turning to morning, and fell down at the entrance of the man’s house where her master was,—until daylight. 27 Later her master rose up in the morning and opened the doors of the house and went out to get on his way, and, look! the woman, his concubine, fallen at the entrance of the house with her hands upon the threshold! 28 So he said to her: “Rise up, and let us go.” But there was no one answering. At that the man took her upon the ass and rose up and went to his place.

29 Then he entered his house and took the slaughtering knife and laid hold of his concubine and cut her up according to her bones into twelve pieces and sent her into every territory of Israel. 30 And it occurred that everybody seeing it said: “Such a thing as this has never been brought about or been seen from the day that the sons of Israel went up out of the land of Egypt down to this day. Set YOUR hearts upon it, take counsel and speak.”

Judges

20 Consequently all the sons of Israel went out and the assembly congregated themselves as one man, from Dan down to Be′er-she′ba along with the land of Gil′e·ad, to Jehovah at Miz′pah. 2 So the keymen of all the people and all the tribes of Israel took their station in the congregation of the people of the true God, four hundred thousand men on foot who drew the sword.

3 And the sons of Benjamin got to hear that the sons of Israel had gone up to Miz′pah.

Then the sons of Israel said: “SPEAK. How has this bad thing been brought about?” 4 At this the man, the Levite, the husband of the murdered woman, answered and said: “It was to Gib′e·ah, which belongs to Benjamin, that I came, I and my concubine, to stay overnight. 5 And the landowners of Gib′e·ah proceeded to rise up against me and to surround the house against me by night. It was I that they figured on killing, but it was my concubine that they raped, and she gradually died. 6 Hence I grasped my concubine and cut her up and sent her into every field of Israel’s inheritance, because they had carried on loose conduct and disgraceful folly in Israel. 7 Look! All YOU sons of Israel, give YOUR word and counsel here.”

8 So all the people rose up as one man, saying: “We shall not go any of us to his tent, nor shall we turn aside any of us to his house. 9 And now this is the thing that we shall do to Gib′e·ah. Let us go up by lot against it. 10 And we must take ten men out of a hundred of all the tribes of Israel, and a hundred out of a thousand, and a thousand out of ten thousand, to procure provisions for the people, that they may take action by going against Gib′e·ah of Benjamin, in view of all the disgraceful folly that they did in Israel.” 11 Thus all the men of Israel were gathered against the city as one man, as allies.

12 Accordingly the tribes of Israel sent men to all the tribesmen of Benjamin, saying: “What is this bad thing that has been brought about among YOU? 13 And now give over the men, the good-for-nothing men, that are in Gib′e·ah, that we may put them to death, and let us clear out what is bad from Israel.” And the sons of Benjamin did not want to listen to the voice of their brothers, the sons of Israel.

14 Then the sons of Benjamin went gathering together out of the cities to Gib′e·ah to go out to battle against the sons of Israel. 15 So the sons of Benjamin got to be mustered on that day from the cities, twenty-six thousand men drawing sword, apart from the inhabitants of Gib′e·ah, of whom seven hundred chosen men were mustered. 16 Out of all this people there were seven hundred chosen men left-handed. Every one of these was a slinger of stones to a hairbreadth and would not miss.

17 And the men of Israel were mustered apart from Benjamin, four hundred thousand men drawing sword. Every one of these was a man of war. 18 And they proceeded to rise up and go on up to Beth′el and to inquire of God. Then the sons of Israel said: “Who of us should go up in the lead to the battle against the sons of Benjamin?” To this Jehovah said: “Judah in the lead.”

19 After that the sons of Israel rose up in the morning and camped against Gib′e·ah.

20 The men of Israel now went out to battle against Benjamin; and the men of Israel proceeded to draw up in battle formation against them at Gib′e·ah. 21 So the sons of Benjamin came on out from Gib′e·ah and brought twenty-two thousand men in Israel down to ruin to the earth on that day. 22 However, the people, the men of Israel, showed themselves courageous and again went drawing up in battle formation in the place where they had drawn up in formation on the first day. 23 Then the sons of Israel went up and wept before Jehovah until the evening and inquired of Jehovah, saying: “Shall I again approach for battle against the sons of Benjamin my brother?” To this Jehovah said: “Go up against him.”

24 Accordingly the sons of Israel drew near to the sons of Benjamin on the second day. 25 In turn Benjamin came on out from Gib′e·ah to meet them on the second day and brought a further eighteen thousand men among the sons of Israel down to ruin to the earth, all of these drawing sword. 26 At that all the sons of Israel, even all the people, went on up and came to Beth′el and wept and sat there before Jehovah and fasted on that day until the evening and offered up burnt offerings and communion offerings before Jehovah. 27 After that the sons of Israel inquired of Jehovah, as it was there that the ark of the covenant of the true God was in those days. 28 Now Phin′e·has the son of El·e·a′zar, the son of Aaron, was standing before it in those days, saying: “Shall I go out yet again to battle against the sons of Benjamin my brother or shall I cease to?” To this Jehovah said: “Go up, because tomorrow I shall give him into your hand.” 29 Then Israel set men in ambush against Gib′e·ah all around.

30 And the sons of Israel proceeded to go up against the sons of Benjamin on the third day, and to draw up in formation against Gib′e·ah the same as at the other times. 31 When the sons of Benjamin went on out to meet the people, they were drawn away from the city. Then, the same as at the other times, they started to strike down some of the people mortally wounded on the highways, one of which goes up to Beth′el and the other to Gib′e·ah, in the field, about thirty men in Israel. 32 So the sons of Benjamin began to say: “They are suffering defeat before us the same as at the first.” As for the sons of Israel, they said: “Let us flee, and we shall certainly draw them away from the city onto the highways.” 33 And all the men of Israel rose up from their places and went drawing up in formation at Ba′al-ta′mar, while those of Israel in ambush were making a charge out of their places in the vicinity of Gib′e·ah. 34 Thus ten thousand chosen men out of all Israel came in front of Gib′e·ah, and the fighting was heavy; and the Ben′ja·mites did not know that calamity was impending over them.

35 And Jehovah proceeded to defeat Benjamin before Israel, so that the sons of Israel on that day brought down to ruin in Benjamin twenty-five thousand one hundred men, all of these drawing sword.

36 However, the sons of Benjamin imagined that the men of Israel faced defeat when they kept giving ground to Benjamin because they trusted in the ambush that they had set against Gib′e·ah. 37 As for the ambush, they acted quickly and went dashing toward Gib′e·ah. Then the ambush spread out and struck all the city with the edge of the sword.

38 Now the men of Israel had come to the arrangement with the ambush for them to make a smoke signal go up from the city.

39 When the sons of Israel turned around in the battle, Benjamin started to strike down about thirty men mortally wounded among the men of Israel, for they said: “They are unquestionably suffering nothing but defeat before us just as in the first battle.” 40 And the signal started to go up from the city as a pillar of smoke. So when Benjamin turned his face back, look! the whole city went up heavenward. 41 And the men of Israel made an about-face, and the men of Benjamin were disturbed, for they saw that calamity had reached them. 42 Hence they turned before the men of Israel in the direction of the wilderness, and the battle followed them up closely, while the men from out of the cities were bringing them down to ruin in their midst. 43 They surrounded Benjamin. They pursued him without a place to rest. They trampled him down directly in front of Gib′e·ah toward the rising of the sun. 44 Finally there fell eighteen thousand men of Benjamin, all of these being valiant men.

45 Thus they turned and went fleeing to the wilderness to the crag of Rim′mon. And they made a gleaning of five thousand men of them on the highways, and they kept following closely after them as far as Gi′dom and so struck down two thousand more men of them. 46 And all those of Benjamin that fell on that day amounted at last to twenty-five thousand men drawing sword, all these being valiant men. 47 But six hundred men turned and went fleeing to the wilderness to the crag of Rim′mon, and they continued to dwell on the crag of Rim′mon four months.

48 And the men of Israel came back against the sons of Benjamin and went striking with the edge of the sword those of the city, from men to domestic animal up to all that were found. Also, all the cities that were found they consigned to the fire.

Ruth

3 Na′o·mi her mother-in-law now said to her: “My daughter, ought I not to look for a resting-place for you, that it may go well with you? 2 And now, is not Bo′az, with whose young women you have continued, our kinsman? Look! He is winnowing barley at the threshing floor tonight. 3 And you must wash and rub yourself with oil and put your mantles upon you and go down to the threshing floor. Do not make yourself known to the man until he has finished eating and drinking. 4 And it should occur that when he lies down, you must also take note of the place where he lies down; and you must come and uncover him at his feet and lie down; and he, for his part, will tell you what you ought to do.”

5 At that she said to her: “All that you say to me I shall do.” 6 And she proceeded to go down to the threshing floor and to do according to all that her mother-in-law had commanded her. 7 Meantime Bo′az ate and drank, and his heart was feeling good. Then he went to lie down at the extremity of the grain heap. After that she came stealthily and uncovered him at his feet and lay down. 8 And it came about at midnight that the man began to tremble. So he bent himself forward, and, look! a woman lying at his feet! 9 Then he said: “Who are you?” In turn she said: “I am Ruth your slave girl, and you must spread out your skirt over your slave girl, for you are a repurchaser.” 10 At that he said: “Blessed may you be of Jehovah, my daughter. You have expressed your loving-kindness better in the last instance than in the first instance, in not going after the young fellows whether lowly or rich. 11 And now, my daughter, do not be afraid. All that you say I shall do for you, for everyone in the gate of my people is aware that you are an excellent woman. 12 And now while it is a fact that I am a repurchaser, there is also a repurchaser closer related than I am. 13 Lodge here tonight, and it must occur in the morning that if he will repurchase you, fine! Let him do the repurchasing. But if he does not take delight in repurchasing you, I will then repurchase you, I myself, as sure as Jehovah lives. Keep lying down until the morning.”

14 And she kept lying at his feet until the morning and then got up before anyone could recognize another. He now said: “Do not let it be known that a woman came to the threshing floor.” 15 And he went on to say: “Bring the cloak that is on you, and hold it open.” So she held it open, and he proceeded to measure out six measures of barley and to place it upon her, after which he went into the city.

16 And she went her way to her mother-in-law, who now said: “Who are you, my daughter?” Accordingly she told her everything that the man had done to her. 17 And she went on to say: “These six measures of barley he gave me, for he said to me, ‘Do not come empty-handed to your mother-in-law.’” 18 At that she said: “Sit still, my daughter, until you know how the matter will turn out, for the man will have no rest unless he has brought the matter to an end today.”

1 Samuel

4 And the word of Samuel continued to come to all Israel.

Then Israel went out to meet the Phi·lis′tines in battle; and they took up camping alongside Eb·en·e′zer, and the Phi·lis′tines themselves encamped in A′phek. 2 And the Phi·lis′tines proceeded to draw up in formation to meet Israel, and the battle went badly, so that Israel was defeated before the Phi·lis′tines, who went striking down about four thousand men in closed battle line in the field. 3 When the people came to the camp the older men of Israel began to say: “Why did Jehovah defeat us today before the Phi·lis′tines? Let us take to ourselves from Shi′loh the ark of Jehovah’s covenant, that it may come into our midst and may save us from the palm of our enemies.” 4 So the people sent to Shi′loh and carried from there the ark of the covenant of Jehovah of armies, who is sitting upon the cherubs. And the two sons of E′li were there with the ark of the covenant of the true God, namely, Hoph′ni and Phin′e·has.

5 And it came about that as soon as the ark of the covenant of Jehovah came into the camp, all the Israelites broke out into loud shouting, so that the earth was in a stir. 6 The Phi·lis′tines also got to hear the sound of the shouting and began saying: “What does the sound of this loud shouting in the camp of the Hebrews mean?” Finally they got to know that the ark of Jehovah itself had come into the camp. 7 And the Phi·lis′tines became afraid, because, they said: “God has come into the camp!” So they said: “Woe to us, for such a thing as this never occurred before! 8 Woe to us! Who will save us from the hand of this majestic God? This is the God that was the smiter of Egypt with every sort of slaughter in the wilderness. 9 Show yourselves courageous and prove yourselves men, YOU Phi·lis′tines, that YOU may not serve the Hebrews just as they have served YOU; and YOU must prove yourselves men and fight!” 10 Accordingly the Phi·lis′tines fought and Israel was defeated, and they went fleeing each one to his tent; and the slaughter came to be very great, so that out of Israel there fell thirty thousand men on foot. 11 And the ark of God itself was captured, and the two sons of E′li, Hoph′ni and Phin′e·has, died.

12 And a man of Benjamin went running from the battle line so that he arrived at Shi′loh on that day with his garments ripped apart and dirt on his head. 13 When he arrived, there was E′li sitting on the seat by the roadside, watching, because his heart had become atremble over the ark of the true God. And the man himself went in to report in the city, and the whole city began crying out. 14 And E′li got to hear the sound of the outcry. So he said: “What does the sound of this turmoil mean?” And the man himself hurried that he might go in and report to E′li. 15 (Now E′li was ninety-eight years old, and his eyes had set so that he was unable to see.) 16 And the man proceeded to say to E′li: “I am the one coming from the battle line, and I—it is from the battle line that I have fled today.” At this he said: “What is the thing that has happened, my son?” 17 So the news bearer answered and said: “Israel has fled before the Phi·lis′tines, and there has also occurred a great defeat among the people; and also your own two sons have died—Hoph′ni and Phin′e·has—and the very ark of the true God has been captured.”

18 And it came about that at the moment that he mentioned the ark of the true God, he began to fall from the seat backward beside the gate, and his neck got broken so that he died, because the man was old and heavy; and he himself had judged Israel forty years. 19 And his daughter-in-law, the wife of Phin′e·has, was pregnant near to giving birth, and she got to hear the report that the ark of the true God was captured and that her father-in-law and her husband had died. At that she bowed herself and began giving birth, because her pangs came unexpectedly upon her. 20 And about the time of her death, the women standing by her began to speak: “Do not be afraid, because it is a son that you have borne.” And she did not answer and did not set her heart on it. 21 But she called the boy Ich′a·bod, saying: “Glory has gone away from Israel into exile,” this with reference to the ark of the true God’s being captured and with reference to her father-in-law and her husband. 22 So she said: “Glory has gone away from Israel into exile, because the ark of the true God has been captured.”

1 Samuel

5 As for the Phi·lis′tines, they took the ark of the true God and then brought it from Eb·en·e′zer to Ash′dod. 2 And the Phi·lis′tines proceeded to take the ark of the true God and bring it into the house of Da′gon and station it beside Da′gon. 3 Then the Ash′dod·ites got up early the very next day, and there Da′gon was fallen upon his face to the earth before the ark of Jehovah. So they took Da′gon and returned him to his place. 4 When they got up early in the morning the very day after, there Da′gon was fallen upon his face to the earth before the ark of Jehovah, with the head of Da′gon and the palms of both his hands cut off, to the threshold. Only the fish part had been left upon him. 5 That is why the priests of Da′gon and all those going into the house of Da′gon do not tread upon the threshold of Da′gon in Ash′dod down to this day.

6 And the hand of Jehovah came to be heavy upon the Ash′dod·ites, and he began causing panic and striking them with piles, namely, Ash′dod and its territories. 7 And the men of Ash′dod came to see that it was so, and they said: “Do not let the ark of the God of Israel dwell with us, because his hand has been hard against us and against Da′gon our god.” 8 Consequently they sent and gathered all the axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines to them and said: “What shall we do to the ark of the God of Israel?” Finally they said: “Toward Gath let the ark of the God of Israel go around.” So they brought the ark of the God of Israel around to there.

9 And it came about that after they had brought it around to there, the hand of Jehovah came to be upon the city with a very great confusion, and he began striking the men of the city, from small to great, and piles began breaking out on them. 10 Hence they sent the ark of the true God to Ek′ron. And it came about that as soon as the ark of the true God came to Ek′ron, the Ek′ron·ites began to cry out, saying: “They have brought the ark of the God of Israel around to me to put me and my people to death!” 11 Consequently they sent and gathered all the axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines and said: “SEND the ark of the God of Israel away that it may return to its place and may not put me and my people to death.” For a death-dealing confusion had occurred in the whole city; the hand of the true God had been very heavy there, 12 and the men that did not die had been struck with piles. And the cry of the city for help kept ascending to the heavens.

1 Samuel

6 And the ark of Jehovah proved to be in the field of the Phi·lis′tines seven months. 2 And the Phi·lis′tines proceeded to call the priests and the diviners, saying: “What shall we do with the ark of Jehovah? Let us know with what we should send it away to its place.” 3 To this they said: “If YOU are sending the ark of the God of Israel away, do not send it away without an offering, for YOU should by all means return to him a guilt offering. Then it is that YOU will be healed, and it must become known to YOU why his hand would not turn away from YOU.” 4 At this they said: “What is the guilt offering that we ought to return to him?” Then they said: “According to the number of the axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines, five golden piles and five golden jerboas, for every one of YOU and YOUR axis lords have the same scourge. 5 And YOU must make images of YOUR piles and images of YOUR jerboas that are bringing the land to ruin, and YOU must give glory to the God of Israel. Perhaps he will lighten his hand from off YOU and YOUR god and YOUR land. 6 Also, why should YOU make YOUR heart unresponsive just the way Egypt and Phar′aoh made their heart unresponsive? Was it not as soon as He dealt severely with them that they proceeded to send them away, and they went their way? 7 And now take and make a new wagon, and two cows that are giving suck, upon which no yoke has come up, and YOU must hitch the cows to the wagon, and YOU must make their young ones go back home from following them. 8 And YOU must take the ark of Jehovah and place it on the wagon, and the golden articles that YOU must return to him as a guilt offering YOU should put into a box at the side of it. And YOU must send it away, and it must go. 9 And YOU must look: if it is the road to its territory that it goes up, to Beth-she′mesh, it is he that has done to us this great evil; but if not, we must know that it was not his hand that touched us; an accident it was that happened to us.”

10 And the men proceeded to do accordingly. So they took two cows that were giving suck and hitched them to the wagon, and their young ones they shut up at home. 11 Then they put the ark of Jehovah upon the wagon, and also the box and the golden jerboas and the images of their piles. 12 And the cows began to go straight ahead on the road to Beth-she′mesh. On the one highway they went, lowing as they went, and they did not turn aside to the right or to the left. All the while the axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines were walking after them as far as the boundary of Beth-she′mesh. 13 And people of Beth-she′mesh were reaping the wheat harvest in the low plain. When they raised their eyes and saw the Ark, they gave way to rejoicing at seeing it. 14 And the wagon itself came into the field of Joshua the Beth-she′mite and kept standing there, where there was a large stone. And they went splitting up the wood of the wagon, and the cows they offered up as a burnt offering to Jehovah.

15 And the Levites themselves took the ark of Jehovah down and the box that was with it, in which the golden articles were, and they proceeded to put it upon the large stone. And the men of Beth-she′mesh, for their part, offered up burnt offerings, and they continued rendering up sacrifices on that day to Jehovah.

16 And the five axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines themselves saw it and went their way back to Ek′ron on that day. 17 Now these are the golden piles that the Phi·lis′tines returned as a guilt offering to Jehovah: for Ash′dod one, for Ga′za one, for Ash′ke·lon one, for Gath one, for Ek′ron one. 18 And the golden jerboas were to the number of all the cities of the Phi·lis′tines belonging to the five axis lords, from the fortified city to the village of the open country.

And the great stone upon which they rested the ark of Jehovah is a witness down to this day in the field of Joshua the Beth-she′mite. 19 And he went striking down the men of Beth-she′mesh, because they had looked upon the ark of Jehovah. So he struck down among the people seventy men—fifty thousand men—and the people began mourning because Jehovah had struck down the people with a great slaughter. 20 Further, the men of Beth-she′mesh said: “Who will be able to stand before Jehovah this holy God, and to whom will he withdraw from off us?” 21 Finally they sent messengers to the inhabitants of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, saying: “The Phi·lis′tines have returned the ark of Jehovah. Come down. Take it up to yourselves.”

1 Samuel

7 Accordingly the men of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim came and brought the ark of Jehovah up and took it into the house of A·bin′a·dab on the hill, and El·e·a′zar his son was the one whom they sanctified to guard the ark of Jehovah.

2 And it came about that from the day of the Ark’s dwelling in Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim the days kept multiplying, so that they amounted to twenty years, and all the house of Israel went lamenting after Jehovah. 3 And Samuel proceeded to say to all the house of Israel: “If it is with all YOUR heart YOU are returning to Jehovah, put away the foreign gods from YOUR midst and also the Ash′to·reth images, and direct YOUR heart unswervingly to Jehovah and serve him alone, and he will deliver YOU from the hand of the Phi·lis′tines.” 4 At that the sons of Israel put away the Ba′als and the Ash′to·reth images and began serving Jehovah alone.

5 Then Samuel said: “Collect all Israel together at Miz′pah, that I may pray in YOUR behalf to Jehovah.” 6 So they were collected together at Miz′pah, and they went drawing water and pouring it out before Jehovah and kept a fast on that day. And they began saying there: “We have sinned against Jehovah.” And Samuel took up judging the sons of Israel in Miz′pah.

7 And the Phi·lis′tines came to hear that the sons of Israel had collected themselves together at Miz′pah, and the axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines got on their way up against Israel. When the sons of Israel heard of it, they began to be afraid on account of the Phi·lis′tines. 8 So the sons of Israel said to Samuel: “Do not keep silent for our sakes from calling to Jehovah our God for aid, that he may save us from the hand of the Phi·lis′tines.” 9 Then Samuel took a sucking lamb and offered it up as a burnt offering, a whole offering, to Jehovah; and Samuel began calling to Jehovah for aid in behalf of Israel, and Jehovah proceeded to answer him. 10 And it came about that while Samuel was offering up the burnt offering, the Phi·lis′tines themselves drew near for battle against Israel. And Jehovah now caused it to thunder with a loud noise on that day against the Phi·lis′tines, that he might throw them into confusion; and they got defeated before Israel. 11 At that the men of Israel sallied forth from Miz′pah and went in pursuit of the Phi·lis′tines and kept striking them down as far as south of Beth-car. 12 Then Samuel took a stone and set it between Miz′pah and Jesh′a·nah and began to call its name Eb·en·e′zer. Accordingly he said: “Till now Jehovah has helped us.” 13 Thus the Phi·lis′tines were subdued, and they did not come anymore into the territory of Israel; and the hand of Jehovah continued to be against the Phi·lis′tines all the days of Samuel. 14 And the cities that the Phi·lis′tines had taken from Israel kept coming back to Israel from Ek′ron to Gath, and the territory of them Israel delivered from the hand of the Phi·lis′tines.

And there came to be peace between Israel and the Am′or·ites.

15 And Samuel kept on judging Israel all the days of his life. 16 And he traveled from year to year and made the circuit of Beth′el and Gil′gal and Miz′pah and judged Israel at all these places. 17 But his return was to Ra′mah, because there was where his house was, and there he judged Israel. And he proceeded to build an altar there to Jehovah.

1 Samuel

9 Now there happened to be a man of Benjamin, and his name was Kish, the son of A·bi′el, the son of Ze′ror, the son of Be·co′rath, the son of A·phi′ah, a Ben′ja·min·ite, a man mighty in wealth. 2 And he happened to have a son whose name was Saul, young and handsome, and there was no man of the sons of Israel that was handsomer than he; from his shoulders upward he was taller than all the people.

3 And the she-asses belonging to Kish the father of Saul got lost. So Kish said to Saul his son: “Take, please, with you one of the attendants and get up, go, look for the she-asses.” 4 And he went passing through the mountainous region of E′phra·im and passing on through the land of Shal′i·shah, and they did not find them. And they went passing on through the land of Sha′a·lim, but they were not there. And he went passing on through the land of the Ben′ja·min·ites, and they did not find them.

5 They themselves came into the land of Zuph; and Saul, for his part, said to his attendant that was with him: “Do come, and let us return, that my father may not quit attending to the she-asses and actually become anxious about us.” 6 But he said to him: “Look, please! There is a man of God in this city, and the man is held in honor. All that he says comes true without fail. Let us go there now. Perhaps he can tell us our way that we must go.” 7 At this Saul said to his attendant: “And if we should go, what shall we bring to the man? because the bread itself has disappeared from our receptacles, and, as a gift, there is nothing to bring to the man of the true God. What is there with us?” 8 So the attendant answered Saul once more and said: “Look! There is a quarter of a shekel of silver found in my hand, and I shall have to give it to the man of the true God, and he will have to tell us our way.” 9 (In former times in Israel this was the way the man would have talked on his going to seek God: “COME, and let us go to the seer.” For the prophet of today used to be called a seer in former times.) 10 Then Saul said to his attendant: “Your word is good. Do come, let us go.” And they went their way to the city where the man of the true God was.

11 While they were going up on the ascent to the city, they themselves found girls going out to draw water. So they said to them: “Is the seer in this place?” 12 Then they answered them and said: “He is. Look! He is ahead of you. Hurry now, because today he has come to the city, for there is a sacrifice today for the people on the high place. 13 As soon as YOU men come into the city, YOU will directly find him before he goes up to the high place to eat; because the people may not eat until his coming, for he is the one that blesses the sacrifice. First after that those who are invited may eat. And now GO up, because him—just now YOU will find him.” 14 Accordingly they went on up to the city. As they were coming into the middle of the city, why, there was Samuel coming out to meet them to go up to the high place.

15 As for Jehovah, he had uncovered the ear of Samuel the day before Saul came, saying: 16 “Tomorrow about this time I shall send to you a man from the land of Benjamin, and you must anoint him as leader over my people Israel; and he must save my people from the hand of the Phi·lis′tines, because I have seen the affliction of my people, for their outcry has come to me.” 17 And Samuel himself saw Saul, and Jehovah, for his part, answered him: “Here is the man of whom I said to you, ‘This is the one that will keep my people within bounds.’”

18 Then Saul approached Samuel in the middle of the gate and said: “Do tell me, please, Just where is the house of the seer?” 19 And Samuel proceeded to answer Saul and say: “I am the seer. Go up before me to the high place, and YOU men must eat with me today, and I must send you away in the morning, and all that is in your heart I shall tell you. 20 As regards the she-asses that were lost to you three days ago, do not set your heart on them, for they have been found. And to whom does all that is desirable of Israel belong? Is it not to you and to the whole house of your father?” 21 At this Saul answered and said: “Am I not a Ben′ja·min·ite of the smallest of the tribes of Israel, and my family the most insignificant of all the families of the tribe of Benjamin? So why have you spoken to me a thing like this?”

22 Then Samuel took Saul and his attendant and brought them to the dining hall and gave them a place at the head of those invited; and they were about thirty men. 23 Later Samuel said to the cook: “Do give the portion that I have given to you, of which I said to you, ‘Put it away by you.’” 24 At that the cook lifted off the leg and what was on it, and put it before Saul. And he went on to say: “Here is what has been reserved. Put it before yourself. Eat, because to the appointed time they have reserved it for you that you may eat with those invited.” So Saul ate with Samuel on that day. 25 Subsequently they went down from the high place to the city, and he continued speaking with Saul on the housetop. 26 Then they rose early, and it came about that as soon as the dawn ascended Samuel proceeded to call to Saul on the housetop, saying: “Do get up, that I may send you away.” So Saul got up and both of them, he and Samuel, went forth out of doors. 27 While they were descending by the edge of the city Samuel himself said to Saul: “Say to the attendant that he should pass on ahead of us”—so he passed on—“and, as for you, stand still now that I may let you hear the word of God.”

1 Samuel

10 Samuel then took the flask of oil and poured it out upon his head and kissed him and said: “Is it not because Jehovah has anointed you as a leader over his inheritance? 2 On your going away from me today you will certainly find two men close by the tomb of Rachel in the territory of Benjamin at Zel′zah, and they will certainly say to you, ‘The she-asses that you have gone to look for have been found, but now your father has given up the matter of the she-asses and has become anxious about YOU men, saying: “What shall I do about my son?”’ 3 And you must pass on from there still farther and come as far as the big tree of Ta′bor, and there there must encounter you three men going up to the true God at Beth′el, one carrying three kids and one carrying three round loaves of bread and one carrying a large jar of wine. 4 And they will certainly ask about your welfare and give you two loaves, and you must accept them from their hand. 5 It is after that that you will come to the hill of the true God, where there is a garrison of the Phi·lis′tines. And it should come about that at the time of your coming there to the city, you will certainly meet a group of prophets coming down from the high place, and ahead of them a stringed instrument and tambourine and flute and harp, while they are speaking as prophets. 6 And the spirit of Jehovah will certainly become operative upon you, and you will certainly speak as a prophet along with them and be changed into another man. 7 And it must occur that when these signs come to you, do for yourself what your hand finds possible, because the true God is with you. 8 And you must go down ahead of me to Gil′gal; and, look! I am going down to you to offer up burnt sacrifices, to render up communion sacrifices. Seven days you should keep waiting until my coming to you, and I shall certainly let you know what you should do.”

9 And it occurred that as soon as he turned his shoulder to go from Samuel, God began changing the heart of his into another; and all these signs proceeded to come true on that day. 10 So they went from there to the hill, and here there was a group of prophets to meet him; at once the spirit of God became operative upon him, and he began to speak as a prophet in the middle of them. 11 And it came about that when all those knowing him formerly saw him, look! it was with prophets that he prophesied. Consequently the people said one to another: “What is this that has happened to the son of Kish? Is Saul also among the prophets?” 12 Then a man from there answered and said: “But who is their father?” That is why it has become a proverbial saying: “Is Saul also among the prophets?”

13 At length he finished speaking as a prophet and came to the high place. 14 Later the brother of Saul’s father said to him and to his attendant: “Where did YOU go?” Upon that he said: “To look for the she-asses, and we kept on going to see, but they were not there. So we came to Samuel.” 15 At this Saul’s uncle said: “Do tell me, please, What did Samuel say to YOU men?” 16 In turn Saul said to his uncle: “He told us unmistakably that the she-asses had been found.” And the matter of the kingship about which Samuel had talked, he did not tell him.

17 And Samuel proceeded to call the people together to Jehovah at Miz′pah 18 and to say to the sons of Israel: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘It was I who brought Israel up out of Egypt and who went delivering YOU from the hand of Egypt and from the hand of all the kingdoms that were oppressing YOU. 19 But YOU—today YOU have rejected YOUR God who was a savior to YOU out of all YOUR evils and YOUR distresses, and YOU went on to say: “No, but a king is what you should put over us.” And now take YOUR stand before Jehovah by YOUR tribes and by YOUR thousands.’”

20 Accordingly Samuel had all the tribes of Israel draw near, and the tribe of Benjamin came to be picked. 21 Then he had the tribe of Benjamin draw near by its families, and the family of the Mat′rites came to be picked. Finally Saul the son of Kish came to be picked. And they went looking for him, and he was not to be found. 22 Hence they inquired further of Jehovah: “Has the man come here as yet?” To this Jehovah said: “Here he is, hidden among the luggage.” 23 So they went running and took him from there. When he took his stand in the middle of the people, he was taller than all the other people from his shoulders upward. 24 Then Samuel said to all the people: “Have YOU seen the one whom Jehovah has chosen, that there is none like him among all the people?” And all the people began to shout and say: “Let the king live!”

25 Upon that Samuel spoke to the people about the rightful due of the kingship and wrote it in a book and deposited it before Jehovah. Then Samuel sent all the people away, each one to his house. 26 As for Saul himself, he went to his home at Gib′e·ah, and the valiant men whose heart God had touched proceeded to go with him. 27 As for the good-for-nothing men, they said: “How will this one save us?” Accordingly they despised him, and they did not bring any gift to him. But he continued like one grown speechless.

1 Samuel

12 Finally Samuel said to all Israel: “Here I have listened to YOUR voice as respects all that YOU have said to me, that I should cause a king to reign over YOU. 2 And now here is the king walking before YOU! As for me, I have grown old and gray, and my sons, here they are with YOU, and I—I have walked before YOU from my youth until this day. 3 Here I am. Answer against me in front of Jehovah and in front of his anointed one: Whose bull have I taken or whose ass have I taken or whom have I defrauded or whom have I crushed or from whose hand have I accepted hush money that I should hide my eyes with it? And I shall make restoration to YOU people.” 4 To this they said: “You have not defrauded us, nor have you crushed us, nor have you accepted anything at all from the hand of a single one.” 5 So he said to them: “Jehovah is a witness against YOU, and his anointed one is a witness this day that YOU have found nothing at all in my hand.” To this they said: “He is a witness.”

6 And Samuel went on to say to the people: “Jehovah is a witness, who used Moses and Aaron and who brought YOUR forefathers up out of the land of Egypt. 7 And now take YOUR stand, and I will judge YOU before Jehovah and recount to YOU all the righteous acts of Jehovah that he has done with YOU and with YOUR forefathers.

8 “As soon as Jacob had come into Egypt and YOUR forefathers began calling to Jehovah for aid, Jehovah proceeded to send Moses and Aaron, that they might lead YOUR forefathers out from Egypt and cause them to dwell in this place. 9 And they went forgetting Jehovah their God, so that he sold them into the hand of Sis′e·ra the chief of the army of Ha′zor and into the hand of the Phi·lis′tines and into the hand of the king of Mo′ab, and they kept fighting against them. 10 And they began to call to Jehovah for aid and say, ‘We have sinned, for we have left Jehovah that we might serve the Ba′als and the Ash′to·reth images; and now deliver us out of the hand of our enemies, that we may serve you.’ 11 And Jehovah proceeded to send Jer·ub·ba′al and Be′dan and Jeph′thah and Samuel and deliver YOU out of the hand of YOUR enemies all around, that YOU might dwell in security. 12 When YOU saw that Na′hash the king of the sons of Am′mon had come against YOU, YOU kept saying to me, ‘No, but a king is what should reign over us!’ all the while Jehovah YOUR God being YOUR King. 13 And now here is the king whom YOU have chosen, for whom YOU asked; and here Jehovah has put over YOU a king. 14 If YOU will fear Jehovah and actually serve him and obey his voice, and YOU will not rebel against the order of Jehovah, both YOU and the king who must reign over YOU will certainly prove to be followers of Jehovah YOUR God. 15 But if YOU will not obey the voice of Jehovah and YOU will actually rebel against the order of Jehovah, the hand of Jehovah will certainly prove to be against YOU and YOUR fathers. 16 Now, also, take YOUR stand and see this great thing that Jehovah is doing before YOUR eyes. 17 Is it not wheat harvest today? I shall call to Jehovah that he may give thunders and rain; then know and see that YOUR evil is abundant that YOU have done in the eyes of Jehovah in asking for yourselves a king.”

18 Upon that Samuel called to Jehovah, and Jehovah proceeded to give thunders and rain on that day, so that all the people were greatly in fear of Jehovah and of Samuel. 19 And all the people began to say to Samuel: “Pray in behalf of your servants to Jehovah your God, as we do not want to die; because we have added to all our sins an evil in asking for ourselves a king.”

20 So Samuel said to the people: “Do not be afraid. YOU—YOU have done all this evil. Only do not turn aside from following Jehovah, and YOU must serve Jehovah with all YOUR heart. 21 And YOU must not turn aside to follow the unrealities that are of no benefit and that do not deliver, because they are unrealities. 22 For Jehovah will not desert his people for the sake of his great name, because Jehovah has taken it upon himself to make YOU his people. 23 As for me also, it is unthinkable, on my part, to sin against Jehovah by ceasing to pray in YOUR behalf; and I must instruct YOU in the good and right way. 24 Only fear Jehovah, and YOU must serve him in truth with all YOUR heart; for see what great things he has done for YOU. 25 But if YOU flagrantly do what is bad, YOU will be swept away, both YOU and YOUR king.”

1 Samuel

16 Eventually Jehovah said to Samuel: “For how long will you be mourning for Saul, while I, on the other hand, have rejected him from ruling as king over Israel? Fill your horn with oil and go. I shall send you to Jes′se the Beth′le·hem·ite, because I have provided among his sons a king for myself.” 2 But Samuel said: “How can I go? Once Saul has heard of it he will certainly kill me.” And Jehovah went on to say: “A young cow of the herd you should take with you, and you must say, ‘To sacrifice to Jehovah is why I have come.’ 3 And you must call Jes′se to the sacrifice; and I, for my part, shall make known to you what you should do, and you must anoint for me the one whom I designate to you.”

4 And Samuel proceeded to do what Jehovah spoke. When he came to Beth′le·hem the older men of the city began to tremble at meeting him, and so they said: “Does your coming mean peace?” 5 To this he said: “It means peace. To sacrifice to Jehovah is why I have come. Sanctify yourselves, and YOU must come with me to the sacrifice.” Then he sanctified Jes′se and his sons, after which he called them to the sacrifice. 6 And it came about that, as they came in and he caught sight of E·li′ab, he at once said: “Surely his anointed one is before Jehovah.” 7 But Jehovah said to Samuel: “Do not look at his appearance and at the height of his stature, for I have rejected him. For not the way man sees is the way God sees, because mere man sees what appears to the eyes; but as for Jehovah, he sees what the heart is.” 8 Then Jes′se called A·bin′a·dab and had him pass before Samuel, but he said: “Neither has Jehovah chosen this one.” 9 Next Jes′se had Sham′mah pass by, but he said: “Neither has Jehovah chosen this one.” 10 So Jes′se had seven of his sons pass before Samuel; still Samuel said to Jes′se: “Jehovah has not chosen these.”

11 Finally Samuel said to Jes′se: “Are these all the boys?” To this he said: “The youngest one has till now been left out, and, look! he is pasturing the sheep.” At that Samuel said to Jes′se: “Do send and fetch him, because we shall not sit down to meal until his coming here.” 12 Accordingly he sent and had him come. Now he was ruddy, a young man with beautiful eyes and handsome in appearance. Then Jehovah said: “Get up, anoint him, for this is he!” 13 Accordingly Samuel took the horn of oil and anointed him in the midst of his brothers. And the spirit of Jehovah began to be operative upon David from that day forward. Later Samuel rose and went his way to Ra′mah.

14 And the very spirit of Jehovah departed from Saul, and a bad spirit from Jehovah terrorized him. 15 And the servants of Saul began to say to him: “Here, now, God’s bad spirit is terrorizing you. 16 Let our lord, please, command your servants before you that they should look for a skilled man playing upon the harp. And it must occur that, when God’s bad spirit comes to be upon you, he will have to play with his hand, and it will certainly be well with you.” 17 So Saul said to his servants: “Provide me, please, a man doing well at playing, and YOU must bring him to me.”

18 And one of the attendants proceeded to answer and say: “Look! I have seen how a son of Jes′se the Beth′le·hem·ite is skilled at playing, and he is a valiant, mighty man and a man of war and an intelligent speaker and a well-formed man, and Jehovah is with him.” 19 Then Saul sent messengers to Jes′se and said: “Do send to me David your son, who is with the flock.” 20 So Jes′se took an ass, bread and a skin bottle of wine and a kid of the goats and sent them by the hand of David his son to Saul. 21 Thus David came to Saul and attended upon him; and he got to loving him very much, and he came to be his armor-bearer. 22 Consequently Saul sent to Jes′se, saying: “Let David, please, keep attending upon me, for he has found favor in my eyes.” 23 And it occurred that, when God’s spirit came to be upon Saul, David took the harp and played with his hand; and there was relief for Saul and it was well with him, and the bad spirit departed from upon him.

1 Samuel

17 And the Phi·lis′tines went collecting their camps together for war. When they were collected together at So′coh, which belongs to Judah, then they took up camping between So′coh and A·ze′kah, in E′phes-dam′mim. 2 As for Saul and the men of Israel, they collected themselves together and took up camping in the low plain of E′lah, and they went drawing up in battle formation to meet the Phi·lis′tines. 3 And the Phi·lis′tines were standing on the mountain on this side, and the Israelites were standing on the mountain on that side, with the valley between them.

4 And a champion began to go out from the camps of the Phi·lis′tines, his name being Go·li′ath, from Gath, his height being six cubits and a span. 5 And there was a helmet of copper on his head, and he was clad with a coat of mail, of overlapping scales, and the weight of the coat of mail was five thousand shekels of copper. 6 And there were greaves of copper above his feet and a javelin of copper between his shoulders. 7 And the wooden shaft of his spear was like the beam of loom workers, and the blade of his spear was six hundred shekels of iron; and the bearer of the large shield was marching ahead of him. 8 Then he stood still and began to call to the battle lines of Israel and say to them: “Why do YOU come out to draw up in battle formation? Am I not the Phi·lis′tine and YOU servants belonging to Saul? Choose a man for yourselves, and let him come down to me. 9 If he is able to fight with me and he does strike me down, we must then become servants to YOU. But if I myself am a match for him and I do strike him down, YOU must also become servants to us, and YOU must serve us.” 10 And the Phi·lis′tine went on to say: “I myself do taunt the battle lines of Israel this day. Give me a man, and let us fight together!”

11 When Saul and all Israel heard these words of the Phi·lis′tine, then they became terrified and were greatly afraid.

12 Now David was the son of this Eph′rath·ite from Beth′le·hem of Judah whose name was Jes′se. And he had eight sons. And in the days of Saul the man was already old among men. 13 And the three oldest sons of Jes′se proceeded to go. They went after Saul to the war, and the names of his three sons that went into the war were E·li′ab the firstborn, and his second son A·bin′a·dab and the third Sham′mah. 14 And David was the youngest, and the three oldest themselves went after Saul.

15 And David was going and returning from Saul to tend the sheep of his father at Beth′le·hem. 16 And the Phi·lis′tine kept coming forward at early morning and at evening and taking his position for forty days.

17 Then Jes′se said to David his son: “Take, please, to your brothers this e′phah of roasted grain and these ten loaves of bread, and carry them quickly to the camp to your brothers. 18 And these ten portions of milk you should bring to the chief of the thousand; also, you should look after your own brothers as regards their welfare, and a token from them you should take.” 19 Meantime, Saul and they and all the other men of Israel were in the low plain of E′lah, fighting against the Phi·lis′tines.

20 Accordingly David got up early in the morning and left the sheep to the keeper’s charge and picked up and went just as Jes′se had commanded him. When he came to the camp enclosure, the military forces were going out to the battle line, and they raised a shout for the battle. 21 And Israel and the Phi·lis′tines began drawing up battle line to meet battle line. 22 Immediately David left the baggage from off him to the care of the keeper of the baggage and went running to the battle line. When he came, he began asking about the welfare of his brothers.

23 While he was speaking with them, why, here the champion, his name being Go·li′ath the Phi·lis′tine from Gath, was coming up from the battle lines of the Phi·lis′tines, and he began speaking the same words as before, and David got to listen in. 24 As for all the men of Israel, on their seeing the man, why, they went fleeing on account of him and were very much afraid. 25 And the men of Israel began to say: “Have YOU seen this man that is coming up? For it is to taunt Israel that he is coming up. And it must occur that, the man who strikes him down, the king will enrich him with great riches, and his own daughter he will give him, and the house of his father he will set free in Israel.”

26 And David began to say to the men that were standing close by him: “What will be done to the man that strikes down that Phi·lis′tine over there and actually turns away reproach from upon Israel? For who is this uncircumcised Phi·lis′tine that he has to taunt the battle lines of the living God?” 27 Then the people said to him the same words as before, saying: “This is the way it will be done to the man that strikes him down.” 28 And E·li′ab his oldest brother got to hear as he spoke to the men, and E·li′ab’s anger grew hot against David, so that he said: “Why is it that you have come down? And in whose charge did you leave those few sheep behind in the wilderness? I myself well know your presumptuousness and the badness of your heart, because you have come down for the purpose of seeing the battle.” 29 To this David said: “What have I done now? Was it not just a word?” 30 With that he turned about from beside him toward someone else and went saying the same word as before, and, in turn, the people gave him the same reply as formerly.

31 So the words that David spoke came to be heard, and they went telling them before Saul. Hence he fetched him. 32 And David proceeded to say to Saul: “Do not let the heart of any man collapse within him. Your servant himself will go and actually fight with this Phi·lis′tine.” 33 But Saul said to David: “You are not able to go against this Phi·lis′tine to fight with him, for you are but a boy, and he is a man of war from his boyhood.” 34 And David went on to say to Saul: “Your servant became a shepherd of his father among the flock, and there came a lion, and also a bear, and each carried off a sheep from the drove. 35 And I went out after it and struck it down and made the rescue from its mouth. When it began rising against me, I grabbed hold of its beard and struck it down and put it to death. 36 Both the lion and the bear your servant struck down; and this uncircumcised Phi·lis′tine must become like one of them, for he has taunted the battle lines of the living God.” 37 Then David added: “Jehovah, who delivered me from the paw of the lion and from the paw of the bear, he it is who will deliver me from the hand of this Phi·lis′tine.” At this Saul said to David: “Go, and may Jehovah himself prove to be with you.”

38 Saul now went clothing David with his garments, and he put a copper helmet upon his head, after which he clothed him with a coat of mail. 39 Then David girded his sword on over his garments and undertook to go but could not, because he had not tried them out. Finally David said to Saul: “I am unable to go in these things, for I have not tried them out.” So David removed them off him. 40 And he proceeded to take his staff in his hand and to choose for himself the five smoothest stones from the torrent valley and to place them in his shepherds’ bag that served him as a receptacle, and in his hand was his sling. And he began approaching the Phi·lis′tine.

41 And the Phi·lis′tine began to come, coming nearer and nearer to David, and the man carrying the large shield was ahead of him. 42 Now when the Phi·lis′tine looked and saw David, he began despising him because he proved to be a boy and ruddy, of beautiful appearance. 43 So the Phi·lis′tine said to David: “Am I a dog, so that you are coming to me with staves?” With that the Phi·lis′tine called down evil upon David by his gods. 44 And the Phi·lis′tine went on to say to David: “Just come to me, and I will give your flesh to the fowls of the heavens and to the beasts of the field.”

45 In turn David said to the Phi·lis′tine: “You are coming to me with a sword and with a spear and with a javelin, but I am coming to you with the name of Jehovah of armies, the God of the battle lines of Israel, whom you have taunted. 46 This day Jehovah will surrender you into my hand, and I shall certainly strike you down and remove your head off you; and I shall certainly give the carcasses of the camp of the Phi·lis′tines this day to the fowls of the heavens and to the wild beasts of the earth; and people of all the earth will know that there exists a God belonging to Israel. 47 And all this congregation will know that neither with sword nor with spear does Jehovah save, because to Jehovah belongs the battle, and he must give YOU men into our hand.”

48 And it occurred that the Phi·lis′tine rose and kept coming and drawing nearer to meet David, and David began hurrying and running toward the battle line to meet the Phi·lis′tine. 49 Then David thrust his hand into his bag and took a stone from there and slung it, so that he struck the Phi·lis′tine in his forehead and the stone sank into his forehead, and he went falling upon his face to the earth. 50 So David, with a sling and a stone, proved stronger than the Phi·lis′tine and struck the Phi·lis′tine down and put him to death; and there was no sword in David’s hand. 51 And David continued running and got to stand over the Phi·lis′tine. Then he took his sword and pulled it out of its sheath and definitely put him to death when he cut his head off with it. And the Phi·lis′tines got to see that their mighty one had died, and they took to flight.

52 At that the men of Israel and of Judah rose and broke into shouting and went in pursuit of the Phi·lis′tines clear to the valley and as far as the gates of Ek′ron, and the fatally wounded of the Phi·lis′tines kept falling on the way from Sha′a·ra′im, both as far as Gath and as far as Ek′ron. 53 Afterward the sons of Israel returned from hotly pursuing the Phi·lis′tines and went pillaging their camps.

54 Then David took the head of the Phi·lis′tine and brought it to Jerusalem, and his weapons he put in his tent.

55 Now at the moment that Saul saw David going out to meet the Phi·lis′tine, he said to Ab′ner the chief of the army: “Whose son is the boy, Ab′ner?” To this Ab′ner said: “By the life of your soul, O king, I do not know at all!” 56 So the king said: “You inquire whose son the lad is.” 57 Accordingly, as soon as David returned from striking the Phi·lis′tine down, Ab′ner proceeded to take him and bring him before Saul with the head of the Phi·lis′tine in his hand. 58 Saul now said to him: “Whose son are you, boy?” to which David said: “The son of your servant Jes′se the Beth′le·hem·ite.”

1 Samuel

19 At length Saul spoke to Jon′a·than his son and to all his servants of putting David to death. 2 As for Jon′a·than, Saul’s son, he took great delight in David. So Jon′a·than told David, saying: “Saul my father is seeking to have you put to death. And now be on your guard, please, in the morning, and you must dwell in secrecy and keep yourself hidden. 3 And I, for my part, shall go out and certainly stand at the side of my father in the field where you will be, and I myself shall speak for you to my father, and I shall certainly see what will happen, and I shall be sure to tell you.”

4 Accordingly Jon′a·than spoke well of David to Saul his father and said to him: “Do not let the king sin against his servant David, for he has not sinned toward you and his works have been very good toward you. 5 And he proceeded to put his soul in his palm and strike the Phi·lis′tine down, so that Jehovah performed a great salvation for all Israel. You saw it, and you gave way to rejoicing. So why should you sin against innocent blood in having David put to death for nothing?” 6 Then Saul obeyed the voice of Jon′a·than, and Saul swore: “As Jehovah is living, he will not be put to death.” 7 Afterward Jon′a·than called David and Jon′a·than told him all these words. Then Jon′a·than brought David to Saul, and he continued before him the same as formerly.

8 In time war broke out again and David went sallying forth and fighting against the Phi·lis′tines and striking them down with a great slaughter, and they took to flight from before him.

9 And Jehovah’s bad spirit came to be upon Saul when he was sitting in his house with his spear in his hand, while David was playing music with his hand. 10 Consequently Saul sought to pin David to the wall with the spear, but he dodged from before Saul, so that he struck the spear into the wall. And David himself fled that he might escape during that night. 11 Later Saul sent messengers to David’s house to watch it and to have him put to death in the morning; but Mi′chal his wife told David, saying: “If you are not letting your soul escape tonight, tomorrow you will be a man put to death.” 12 Immediately Mi′chal had David descend through the window, that he might go and run away and escape. 13 Then Mi′chal took the teraphim image and placed it on the couch, and a net of goats’ hair she put at the place of his head, after which she covered it with a garment.

14 Saul now sent messengers to take David, but she said: “He is sick.” 15 So Saul sent the messengers to see David, saying: “Bring him on his couch up to me to have him put to death.” 16 When the messengers came in, why, there was the teraphim image on the couch and a net of goats’ hair at the place of his head. 17 At this Saul said to Mi′chal: “Why did you trick me like this, so that you sent my enemy away that he might escape?” In turn Mi′chal said to Saul: “He himself said to me, ‘Send me away! Why should I put you to death?’”

18 As for David, he ran away and made his escape and got to come to Samuel at Ra′mah. And he proceeded to tell him all that Saul had done to him. Then he and Samuel went away, and they took up dwelling in Nai′oth. 19 In time the report got to Saul, saying: “Look! David is in Nai′oth in Ra′mah.” 20 At once Saul sent messengers to take David. When they got to see the elderly ones of the prophets prophesying, and Samuel standing in his position over them, the spirit of God came to be upon Saul’s messengers, and they began behaving like prophets, they also.

21 When they told it to Saul, he immediately sent other messengers, and they began behaving like prophets, they also. So Saul sent messengers again, the third set, and they began behaving like prophets, they also. 22 Finally he too went to Ra′mah. When he got as far as the great cistern that is in Se′cu, he began to inquire and say: “Where are Samuel and David?” To this they said: “There in Nai′oth in Ra′mah.” 23 And he kept on his way from there to Nai′oth in Ra′mah, and the spirit of God came to be upon him, yes, him, and he went on walking and continued behaving like a prophet until he came into Nai′oth in Ra′mah. 24 And he also proceeded to strip off his garments and behave, he also, like a prophet before Samuel, and he lay fallen naked all that day and all that night. That is why they came to say: “Is Saul also among the prophets?”

1 Samuel

23 In time they came reporting to David, saying: “Here the Phi·lis′tines are warring against Kei′lah, and they are pillaging the threshing floors.” 2 And David proceeded to inquire of Jehovah, saying: “Shall I go, and must I strike down these Phi·lis′tines?” In turn Jehovah said to David: “Go, and you must strike down the Phi·lis′tines and save Kei′lah.” 3 At this the men of David said to him: “Look! We are afraid while here in Judah, and how much more so in case we should go to Kei′lah against the battle lines of the Phi·lis′tines!” 4 So David inquired yet again of Jehovah. Jehovah now answered him and said: “Rise up, go down to Kei′lah, because I am giving the Phi·lis′tines into your hand.” 5 Accordingly David went with his men to Kei′lah and fought against the Phi·lis′tines and drove off with their livestock, but struck them down with a great slaughter; and David came to be the savior of the inhabitants of Kei′lah.

6 Now it came about that when A·bi′a·thar the son of A·him′e·lech ran away to David at Kei′lah, there was an eph′od that went down in his hand. 7 In time the report was made to Saul: “David has come to Kei′lah.” And Saul began to say: “God has sold him into my hand, for he has shut himself up by coming into a city with doors and bar.” 8 So Saul summoned all the people to war, to go down to Kei′lah, to besiege David and his men. 9 And David got to know that Saul was fabricating mischief against him. Hence he said to A·bi′a·thar the priest: “Do bring the eph′od near.” 10 And David went on to say: “O Jehovah the God of Israel, your servant has definitely heard that Saul is seeking to come to Kei′lah to lay the city in ruin on my account. 11 Will the landowners of Kei′lah surrender me into his hand? Will Saul come down just as your servant has heard? O Jehovah the God of Israel, tell your servant, please.” To this Jehovah said: “He will come down.” 12 And David went on to say: “Will the landowners of Kei′lah surrender me and my men into Saul’s hand?” In turn Jehovah said: “They will do the surrendering.”

13 At once David rose up with his men, about six hundred men, and they went out of Kei′lah and continued walking about wherever they could walk about. And to Saul it was reported that David had escaped from Kei′lah, and so he gave up going out. 14 And David took up dwelling in the wilderness in places difficult to approach, and he kept dwelling in the mountainous region in the wilderness of Ziph. And Saul kept looking for him always, and God did not give him into his hand. 15 And David continued in fear because Saul had gone out to look for his soul while David was in the wilderness of Ziph at Ho′resh.

16 Jon′a·than the son of Saul now rose up and went to David at Ho′resh, that he might strengthen his hand in regard to God. 17 And he went on to say to him: “Do not be afraid; for the hand of Saul my father will not find you, and you yourself will be king over Israel, and I myself shall become second to you; and Saul my father also has knowledge to that effect.” 18 Then the two of them concluded a covenant before Jehovah; and David kept dwelling in Ho′resh, and Jon′a·than himself went to his own home.

19 Later the men of Ziph went up to Saul at Gib′e·ah, saying: “Is not David concealing himself close by us in the places difficult to approach at Ho′resh, on the hill of Hach·i′lah, which is to the right side of Je·shi′mon? 20 And now in harmony with all the craving of your soul, O king, to come down, come down, and our part will be to surrender him into the hand of the king.” 21 At this Saul said: “Blessed are YOU of Jehovah, for YOU have had compassion on me. 22 Go, please, persevere some more and ascertain and see his place where his foot comes to be—whoever saw him there—for it has been said to me that he himself is surely cunning. 23 And see and ascertain about all the hiding places where he hides himself; and YOU must return to me with the evidence, and I will go with YOU; and it must occur that, if he is in the land, I will also search for him carefully among all the thousands of Judah.”

24 So they rose up and went to Ziph ahead of Saul, while David and his men were in the wilderness of Ma′on in the Ar′a·bah to the south of Je·shi′mon. 25 Later Saul came with his men to look for him. When they told David, he at once went down to the crag and continued dwelling in the wilderness of Ma′on. When Saul got to hear of it, he went chasing after David into the wilderness of Ma′on. 26 Eventually Saul came to this side of the mountain, and David and his men were on that side of the mountain. So David became hurried to go away because of Saul; all the while Saul and his men were closing in on David and his men to grab hold of them. 27 But there was a messenger that came to Saul, saying: “Do hasten and go, for the Phi·lis′tines have made a raid on the land!” 28 At that Saul turned back from chasing after David and went to meet the Phi·lis′tines. That is why they have called that place the Crag of the Divisions.

29 Then David made his way up from there and took up dwelling in the places difficult to approach at En-ge′di.

1 Samuel

24 And it came about that, as soon as Saul returned from following the Phi·lis′tines, they came reporting to him, saying: “Look! David is in the wilderness of En-ge′di.”

2 And Saul proceeded to take three thousand chosen men out of all Israel and to go looking for David and his men upon the bare rocks of the mountain goats. 3 At length he came to the stone sheepfolds along the road, where a cave was. So Saul came in to ease nature, while David and his men were in the parts of the cave farthest back, sitting down. 4 And David’s men began to say to him: “Here is the day on which Jehovah does say to you, ‘Look! I am giving your enemy into your hand, and you must do to him just as it may seem good in your eyes.’” So David rose up and quietly cut off the skirt of the sleeveless coat that belonged to Saul. 5 But it came about afterward that David’s heart kept striking him for the reason that he had cut off the skirt of the sleeveless coat that belonged to Saul. 6 Hence he said to his men: “It is unthinkable, on my part, from Jehovah’s standpoint, that I should do this thing to my lord, the anointed of Jehovah, by thrusting out my hand against him, for he is the anointed of Jehovah.” 7 Accordingly David dispersed his men with these words, and he did not allow them to rise up against Saul. As for Saul, he rose up from the cave and kept going on his way.

8 So David rose up afterward and went out from the cave and called out after Saul, saying: “My lord the king!” At this Saul looked behind him, and David proceeded to bow low with his face to the earth and prostrate himself. 9 And David went on to say to Saul: “Why do you listen to the words of man, saying, ‘Look! David is seeking your hurt’? 10 Here this day your eyes have seen how Jehovah gave you today into my hand in the cave; and someone said to kill you, but I felt sorry for you and said, ‘I shall not thrust out my hand against my lord, for he is the anointed of Jehovah.’ 11 And, my father, see, yes, see the skirt of your sleeveless coat in my hand, for when I cut off the skirt of your sleeveless coat I did not kill you. Know and see that there is no badness or revolt in my hand, and I have not sinned against you, while you are lying in wait for my soul to take it away. 12 May Jehovah judge between me and you; and Jehovah must take vengeance for me from you, but my own hand will not come to be upon you. 13 Just as the proverb of the ancients says, ‘From the wicked ones wickedness will go forth,’ but my own hand will not come to be upon you. 14 After whom has the king of Israel gone out? After whom are you chasing? After a dead dog? After a single flea? 15 And Jehovah must become judge, and he must judge between me and you, and he will see and he will conduct the legal case for me and judge me to free me from your hand.”

16 And it came about that, at the moment that David finished speaking these words to Saul, Saul proceeded to say: “Is this your voice, my son David?” And Saul began to raise his own voice and weep. 17 And he went on to say to David: “You are more righteous than I am, for it is you who have rendered me good, and it is I who have rendered you evil. 18 And you—you have told today what good you have done in connection with me in that Jehovah surrendered me into your hand and you did not kill me. 19 Now in the case where a man finds his enemy, will he send him away on a good road? So Jehovah himself will reward you with good, due to the fact that this day you have done it to me. 20 And now, look! I well know that you will, without fail, rule as king, and that in your hand the kingdom of Israel will certainly endure. 21 So now do swear to me by Jehovah that you will not cut off my seed after me and that you will not annihilate my name out of the house of my father.” 22 Accordingly David swore to Saul, after which Saul went to his home. As for David and his men, they went up to the place difficult to approach.

1 Samuel

29 And the Phi·lis′tines proceeded to collect all their camps together at A′phek, while the Israelites were camping by the spring that was in Jez′re·el. 2 And the axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines were passing along by hundreds and by thousands, and David and his men were passing along afterward with A′chish. 3 And the princes of the Phi·lis′tines began to say: “What do these Hebrews mean?” At this A′chish said to the princes of the Phi·lis′tines: “Is this not David the servant of Saul king of Israel, who happened to be with me here a year or two, and I have not found in him a single thing from the day of his deserting to me until this day?” 4 And the princes of the Phi·lis′tines became indignant at him; and the princes of the Phi·lis′tines went on to say to him: “Make the man go back, and let him go back to his place where you assigned him; and do not let him go down with us into the battle, that he may not become a resister of us in the battle. And with what should this person put himself in favor with his lord? Is it not with the heads of those our men? 5 Is this not David to whom they kept responding in the dances, saying, ‘Saul has struck down his thousands, and David his tens of thousands’?”

6 Consequently A′chish called David and said to him: “As Jehovah is living, you are upright, and your going out and your coming in with me in the camp has been good in my eyes; for I have not found badness in you from the day of your coming to me until this day. But in the eyes of the axis lords you are not good. 7 And now return and go in peace, that you may not do anything bad in the eyes of the axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines.” 8 However, David said to A′chish: “Why, what have I done, and what have you found in your servant from the day that I came to be before you until this day, that I should not come and actually fight against the enemies of my lord the king?” 9 At this A′chish answered and said to David: “I well know that you have been good in my own eyes, like an angel of God. Only it is the princes of the Phi·lis′tines that have said, ‘Let him not go up with us into the battle.’ 10 And now rise up early in the morning with the servants of your lord that came with you; and YOU men must rise up early in the morning when it has become light for YOU. Then go.”

11 Accordingly David rose up early, he and his men, to go in the morning and return to the land of the Phi·lis′tines; and the Phi·lis′tines themselves went up to Jez′re·el.

2 Samuel

2 And it came about afterward that David proceeded to inquire of Jehovah, saying: “Shall I go up into one of the cities of Judah?” At this Jehovah said to him: “Go up.” And David went on to say: “Where shall I go up?” Then he said: “To He′bron.” 2 Accordingly David went up there and also his two wives, A·hin′o·am the Jez′re·el·i·tess and Ab′i·gail the wife of Na′bal the Car′mel·ite. 3 And the men that were with him David brought up, each with his household; and they took up dwelling in the cities of He′bron territory. 4 Then the men of Judah came and anointed David there as king over the house of Judah.

And they came telling David, saying: “The men of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad were the ones that buried Saul.” 5 Hence David sent messengers to the men of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad and said to them: “Blessed may YOU be of Jehovah, because YOU exercised this loving-kindness toward YOUR lord, toward Saul, in that YOU buried him. 6 And now may Jehovah exercise toward YOU loving-kindness and trustworthiness, and I too shall exercise to YOU this goodness because YOU have done this thing. 7 And now let YOUR hands strengthen themselves and prove yourselves valiant men, because YOUR lord Saul is dead, and it is even I whom the house of Judah have anointed as king over them.”

8 As for Ab′ner the son of Ner the chief of the army that had belonged to Saul, he took Ish-bo′sheth, Saul’s son, and proceeded to bring him across to Ma·ha·na′im, 9 and to make him king over Gil′e·ad and the Ash′ur·ites and Jez′re·el and over E′phra·im and Benjamin and over Israel, all of it. 10 Forty years old Ish-bo′sheth, Saul’s son, was when he became king over Israel, and for two years he ruled as king. Only the house of Judah proved themselves followers of David. 11 And the number of the days that David proved to be king in He′bron over the house of Judah came to be seven years and six months.

12 In time Ab′ner the son of Ner and the servants of Ish-bo′sheth, Saul’s son, went out from Ma·ha·na′im to Gib′e·on. 13 As for Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah and the servants of David, they went out and later met together by the pool of Gib′e·on; and they kept sitting, these on this side of the pool and those on that side of the pool. 14 Finally Ab′ner said to Jo′ab: “Let the young men rise up, please, and let them put on a combat before us.” To this Jo′ab said: “Let them rise up.” 15 So they rose up and went across by number, twelve belonging to Benjamin and Ish-bo′sheth, Saul’s son, and twelve from the servants of David. 16 And they began grabbing hold of one another by the head, with the sword of each one in the side of the other, so that they fell down together. And that place came to be called Hel′kath-haz·zu′rim, which is in Gib′e·on.

17 And the fighting came to be extremely hard on that day, and Ab′ner and the men of Israel were finally defeated before the servants of David. 18 Now the three sons of Ze·ru′iah happened to be there, Jo′ab and A·bish′ai and As′a·hel; and As′a·hel was swift on his feet, like one of the gazelles that are in the open field. 19 And As′a·hel went chasing after Ab′ner, and he did not incline to go to the right or to the left from following Ab′ner. 20 At length Ab′ner looked behind him and said: “Is this you, As′a·hel?” to which he said: “It is I.” 21 Then Ab′ner said to him: “Veer to your right or to your left and seize one of the young men as yours and take what you strip off him as yours.” And As′a·hel did not want to turn aside from following him. 22 So Ab′ner said to As′a·hel yet again: “Turn your course aside from following me. Why should I strike you down to the earth? How, then, could I raise my face to Jo′ab your brother?” 23 But he kept refusing to turn aside; and Ab′ner got to strike him in the abdomen with the butt end of the spear, so that the spear came out from his back; and he fell there and died where he was. And it came about that all those who came to the place where As′a·hel fell and then died would stand still.

24 And Jo′ab and A·bish′ai went chasing after Ab′ner. As the sun was setting they themselves came to the hill of Am′mah, which is in front of Gi′ah on the way to the wilderness of Gib′e·on. 25 And the sons of Benjamin went collecting together behind Ab′ner, and they came to be one company and kept standing upon the top of one hill. 26 And Ab′ner began to call to Jo′ab and say: “Is the sword going to eat endlessly? Do you not really know that bitterness is what will develop at last? How long, then, will it be before you say to the people to turn back from following their brothers?” 27 At that Jo′ab said: “As the true God is living, if you had not spoken, then only by the morning would the people have been withdrawn, each one from following his brother.” 28 Jo′ab now blew the horn, and all the people came to a halt and did not continue chasing after Israel anymore, and they did not renew the fighting anymore.

29 As for Ab′ner and his men, they marched through the Ar′a·bah all that night and went crossing the Jordan and marching through the entire gully and finally came to Ma·ha·na′im. 30 As for Jo′ab, he turned back from following Ab′ner and began to collect all the people together. And there were missing from the servants of David nineteen men and As′a·hel. 31 And the servants of David, for their part, had struck down those of Benjamin and of the men of Ab′ner—there were three hundred and sixty men that died. 32 And they proceeded to carry As′a·hel and bury him in the burial place of his father, which is at Beth′le·hem. Then Jo′ab and his men went marching on all night long, and it became daylight for them at He′bron.

2 Samuel

4 When the son of Saul heard that Ab′ner had died in He′bron, then his hands became feeble and all the Israelites themselves were disturbed. 2 And there were two men, chiefs of the marauding bands, that happened to belong to the son of Saul, the name of the one being Ba′a·nah and the name of the other being Re′chab, the sons of Rim′mon the Be·er′oth·ite, of the sons of Benjamin; for Be·er′oth, too, used to be counted as part of Benjamin. 3 And the Be·er′oth·ites went running away to Git′ta·im, and they came to be alien residents there down to this day.

4 Now Jon′a·than, the son of Saul, had a son lame in the feet. Five years old he happened to be when the report about Saul and Jon′a·than came from Jez′re·el; and his nurse began to carry him and flee, but it came about that as she was running in panic to flee, he then had a fall and was lamed. And his name was Me·phib′o·sheth.

5 And the sons of Rim′mon the Be·er′oth·ite, Re′chab and Ba′a·nah, proceeded to go and come to the house of Ish-bo′sheth about when the day had heated up, as he was taking his noonday siesta. 6 And here they came into the middle of the house as men fetching wheat, and then struck him in the abdomen; and Re′chab and Ba′a·nah his brother themselves escaped detection. 7 When they went into the house, he was lying upon his couch in his inner bedroom, and then they struck him so that they put him to death, after which they removed his head and took his head and walked on the road to the Ar′a·bah all night long. 8 Eventually they came bringing the head of Ish-bo′sheth to David at He′bron and said to the king: “Here is the head of Ish-bo′sheth the son of Saul your enemy who looked for your soul; but Jehovah gives to my lord the king revenge this day upon Saul and his offspring.”

9 However, David answered Re′chab and Ba′a·nah his brother, the sons of Rim′mon the Be·er′oth·ite, and said to them: “As Jehovah who redeemed my soul out of all distress is living, 10 when there was one reporting to me, saying, ‘Here Saul is dead,’ and he himself in his own eyes became like a bringer of good news, I, however, took hold of him and killed him in Zik′lag when it was due for me to give him the messenger’s fee; 11 how much more so when wicked men themselves have killed a righteous man in his own house upon his bed? And now should I not require his blood from YOUR hands, and must I not clear YOU out of the earth?” 12 With that David commanded the young men and they killed them and cut off their hands and their feet and hanged them by the pool in He′bron; and the head of Ish-bo′sheth they took and then buried in the burial place of Ab′ner in He′bron.

2 Samuel

5 In time all the tribes of Israel came to David at He′bron and said: “Look! We ourselves are your bone and your flesh. 2 Both yesterday and previously while Saul happened to be king over us, you yourself became the one leading Israel out and bringing it in. And Jehovah proceeded to say to you, ‘You yourself will shepherd my people Israel, and you yourself will become leader over Israel.’” 3 So all the older men of Israel came to the king at He′bron, and King David concluded a covenant with them in He′bron before Jehovah; after which they anointed David as king over Israel.

4 Thirty years old was David when he became king. For forty years he ruled as king. 5 In He′bron he ruled as king over Judah for seven years and six months; and in Jerusalem he ruled as king for thirty-three years over all Israel and Judah. 6 Consequently the king and his men went to Jerusalem against the Jeb′u·sites inhabiting the land, and they began to say to David: “You will not come in here, but the blind and the lame ones will certainly turn you away,” they thinking: “David will not come in here.” 7 Just the same, David proceeded to capture the stronghold of Zion, that is, the City of David. 8 So David said on that day: “Anyone striking the Jeb′u·sites, let him, by means of the water tunnel, make contact with both the lame and the blind, hateful to the soul of David!” That is why they say: “The blind one and the lame one will not come into the house.” 9 And David took up dwelling in the stronghold, and it came to be called the City of David; and David began to build all around from the Mound and inward. 10 Thus David went on getting greater and greater, and Jehovah the God of armies was with him.

11 And Hi′ram the king of Tyre proceeded to send messengers to David, and also cedar trees and workers in wood and workers in stone for walls, and they began to build a house for David. 12 And David came to know that Jehovah had firmly established him as king over Israel and that he had exalted his kingdom for the sake of his people Israel.

13 Meantime, David went on taking more concubines and wives out of Jerusalem after he came from He′bron; and more sons and daughters continued to be born to David. 14 And these are the names of those born to him in Jerusalem: Sham·mu′a and Sho′bab and Nathan and Sol′o·mon, 15 and Ib′har and E·li′shu·a and Ne′pheg and Ja·phi′a, 16 and E·lish′a·ma and E·li′a·da and E·liph′e·let.

17 And the Phi·lis′tines got to hear that they had anointed David as king over Israel. At that all the Phi·lis′tines came up to look for David. When David heard of it, then he went down to the place hard to approach. 18 And the Phi·lis′tines, for their part, came in and kept tramping about in the low plain of Reph′a·im. 19 And David began to inquire of Jehovah, saying: “Shall I go up against the Phi·lis′tines? Will you give them into my hand?” At this Jehovah said to David: “Go up, for I shall without fail give the Phi·lis′tines into your hands.” 20 So David came to Ba′al-pe·ra′zim, and David got to strike them down there. At that he said: “Jehovah has broken through my enemies ahead of me, like a gap made by waters.” That is why he called the name of that place Ba′al-pe·ra′zim. 21 Consequently they left their idols there, and so David and his men took them away.

22 Later the Phi·lis′tines came up once again and tramped about in the low plain of Reph′a·im. 23 At that David inquired of Jehovah, but he said: “You must not go up. Go around to the rear of them, and you must come against them in front of the ba′ca bushes. 24 And let it occur that, when you hear the sound of a marching in the tops of the ba′ca bushes, at that time you act with decision, because at that time Jehovah will have gone out ahead of you to strike down the camp of the Phi·lis′tines.” 25 Accordingly David did that way, just as Jehovah had commanded him, and he went striking down the Phi·lis′tines from Ge′ba to as far as Ge′zer.

2 Samuel

8 And it came about afterward that David proceeded to strike the Phi·lis′tines down and subdue them, and David got to take Meth′eg-am′mah out of the hand of the Phi·lis′tines.

2 And he went on to strike down the Mo′ab·ites and measure them with a line, making them lie down on the earth, that he might measure two lines to put them to death, and a full line to preserve them alive; and the Mo′ab·ites came to be David’s servants to carry tribute.

3 And David went on to strike down Had·ad·e′zer the son of Re′hob the king of Zo′bah as he was going his way to put his control back again at the river Eu·phra′tes. 4 And David got to capture from him one thousand seven hundred horsemen and twenty thousand men on foot; and David proceeded to hamstring all the chariot horses, but he let a hundred chariot horses of them remain.

5 When Syria of Damascus came to help Had·ad·e′zer the king of Zo′bah, David then struck down among the Syrians twenty-two thousand men. 6 Further, David put garrisons in Syria of Damascus; and the Syrians came to be David’s servants to carry tribute. And Jehovah continued to save David wherever he went. 7 Moreover, David took the circular shields of gold that happened to be on the servants of Had·ad·e′zer and brought them to Jerusalem. 8 And from Be′tah and Be·ro′thai, cities of Had·ad·e′zer, King David took copper in very great quantity.

9 Now To′i the king of Ha′math got to hear that David had struck down all the military force of Had·ad·e′zer. 10 So To′i sent Jo′ram his son to King David to ask him about his welfare and congratulate him over the fact that he had fought against Had·ad·e′zer so that he struck him down (for Had·ad·e′zer had become trained in warfare against To′i); and in his hand there proved to be articles of silver and articles of gold and articles of copper. 11 These also King David sanctified to Jehovah, together with the silver and the gold that he had sanctified from all the nations that he had subdued, 12 from Syria and from Mo′ab and from the sons of Am′mon and from the Phi·lis′tines and from Am′a·lek and from the spoil of Had·ad·e′zer the son of Re′hob the king of Zo′bah. 13 And David proceeded to make a name when he came back from striking down the E′dom·ites in the Valley of Salt—eighteen thousand. 14 And he kept garrisons placed in E′dom. In all E′dom he placed garrisons, and all the E′dom·ites came to be servants of David; and Jehovah kept saving David wherever he went.

15 And David kept reigning over all Israel; and David was continually rendering judicial decision and righteousness for all his people. 16 And Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah was over the army; and Je·hosh′a·phat the son of A·hi′lud was recorder. 17 And Za′dok the son of A·hi′tub and A·him′e·lech the son of A·bi′a·thar were priests, and Se·rai′ah was secretary. 18 And Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da was over the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites. As for the sons of David, they became priests.

2 Samuel

11 And it came about at the return of the year, at the time that kings sally forth, that David proceeded to send Jo′ab and his servants with him and all Israel, that they might bring the sons of Am′mon to ruin and lay siege to Rab′bah, while David was dwelling in Jerusalem.

2 And it came about at the time of evening that David proceeded to rise from his bed and walk about on the rooftop of the king’s house; and from the rooftop he caught sight of a woman bathing herself, and the woman was very good in appearance. 3 Then David sent and inquired about the woman and someone said: “Is this not Bath-she′ba the daughter of E·li′am the wife of U·ri′ah the Hit′tite?” 4 After that David sent messengers that he might take her. So she came in to him and he lay down with her, while she was sanctifying herself from her uncleanness. Later she returned to her house.

5 And the woman became pregnant. Consequently she sent and told David and said: “I am pregnant.” 6 At this David sent to Jo′ab, saying: “Send to me U·ri′ah the Hit′tite.” So Jo′ab sent U·ri′ah to David. 7 When U·ri′ah came to him, David began to ask how Jo′ab was getting along and how the people were getting along and how the war was getting along. 8 Finally David said to U·ri′ah: “Go down to your house and bathe your feet.” Accordingly U·ri′ah went out from the king’s house, and the king’s courtesy gift went out following him. 9 However, U·ri′ah lay down at the entrance of the king’s house with all the other servants of his lord, and he did not go down to his own house. 10 So they told David, saying: “U·ri′ah did not go down to his own house.” Upon that David said to U·ri′ah: “It is from a journey that you have come in, is it not? Why have you not gone down to your own house?” 11 At this U·ri′ah said to David: “The Ark and Israel and Judah are dwelling in booths, and my lord Jo′ab and the servants of my lord are camping on the face of the field, and I—shall I go into my own house to eat and drink and to lie down with my wife? As you are living and as your soul is living, I shall not do this thing!”

12 Then David said to U·ri′ah: “Dwell here also today, and tomorrow I shall send you away.” Therefore U·ri′ah kept dwelling in Jerusalem on that day and the day following. 13 Further, David called him that he might eat before him and drink. So he got him drunk. Nevertheless, he went out in the evening to lie down on his bed with the servants of his lord, and to his own house he did not go down. 14 And it came about in the morning that David proceeded to write a letter to Jo′ab and send it by the hand of U·ri′ah. 15 So he wrote in the letter, saying: “PUT U·ri′ah in front of the heaviest battle charges, and YOU men must retreat from behind him, and he must be struck down and die.”

16 And it came about that while Jo′ab was keeping guard over the city he kept U·ri′ah put in the place where he knew that there were valiant men. 17 When the men of the city came on out and went fighting against Jo′ab, then some of the people, the servants of David, fell and U·ri′ah the Hit′tite also died. 18 Jo′ab now sent that he might report to David all the matters of the war. 19 And he went on to command the messenger, saying: “As soon as you finish speaking to the king about all the matters of the war, 20 then it must occur that if the rage of the king comes up and he does say to you, ‘Why did YOU have to go so near to the city to fight? Did YOU men not know that they would shoot from on top of the wall? 21 Who was it that struck down A·bim′e·lech the son of Je·rub′be·sheth? Was it not a woman that pitched an upper millstone upon him from on top of the wall so that he died at The′bez? Why did YOU men have to go so close to the wall?’ you must also say, ‘Your servant U·ri′ah the Hit′tite died too.’”

22 So the messenger went and came and told David all about which Jo′ab had sent him. 23 And the messenger went on to say to David: “The men proved superior to us, so that they came out against us into the field; but we kept pressing them right up to the entrance of the gate. 24 And the shooters kept shooting at your servants from on top of the wall, so that some of the servants of the king died; and your servant U·ri′ah the Hit′tite also died.” 25 At that David said to the messenger: “This is what you will say to Jo′ab, ‘Do not let this matter appear bad in your eyes, for the sword eats up one as well as another. Intensify your battle against the city and throw it down.’ And encourage him.”

26 And the wife of U·ri′ah got to hear that U·ri′ah her husband had died, and she began to wail over her owner. 27 When the mourning period was past, David immediately sent and took her home to his house, and she came to be his wife. In time she bore to him a son, but the thing that David had done appeared bad in the eyes of Jehovah.

2 Samuel

12 And Jehovah proceeded to send Nathan to David. So he came in to him and said to him: “There were two men that happened to be in one city, the one rich and the other of little means. 2 The rich man happened to have very many sheep and cattle; 3 but the man of little means had nothing but one female lamb, a small one, that he had bought. And he was preserving it alive, and it was growing up with him and with his sons, all together. From his morsel it would eat, and from his cup it would drink, and in his bosom it would lie, and it came to be as a daughter to him. 4 After a while a visitor came to the rich man, but he spared taking some from his own sheep and his own cattle to get such ready for the traveler that had come in to him. So he took the female lamb of the man of little means and got it ready for the man that had come in to him.”

5 At this David’s anger grew very hot against the man, so that he said to Nathan: “As Jehovah is living, the man doing this deserves to die! 6 And for the female lamb he should make compensation with four, as a consequence of the fact that he has done this thing and because he did not have compassion.”

7 Then Nathan said to David: “You yourself are the man! This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘I myself anointed you as king over Israel, and I myself delivered you out of the hand of Saul. 8 And I was willing to give you the house of your lord and the wives of your lord into your bosom, and to give you the house of Israel and of Judah. And if it were not enough, I was willing to add to you things like these as well as other things. 9 Why did you despise the word of Jehovah by doing what is bad in his eyes? U·ri′ah the Hit′tite you struck down with the sword, and his wife you took as your wife, and him you killed by the sword of the sons of Am′mon. 10 And now a sword will not depart from your own house to time indefinite, as a consequence of the fact that you despised me so that you took the wife of U·ri′ah the Hit′tite to become your wife.’ 11 This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am raising up against you calamity out of your own house; and I will take your wives under your own eyes and give them to your fellowman, and he will certainly lie down with your wives under the eyes of this sun. 12 Whereas you yourself acted in secret, I, for my part, shall do this thing in front of all Israel and in front of the sun.’”

13 David now said to Nathan: “I have sinned against Jehovah.” At this Nathan said to David: “Jehovah, in turn, does let your sin pass by. You will not die. 14 Notwithstanding this, because you have unquestionably treated Jehovah with disrespect by this thing, also the son himself, just born to you, will positively die.”

15 Then Nathan went to his own house.

And Jehovah proceeded to deal a blow to the child that the wife of U·ri′ah had borne to David so that it took sick. 16 And David began to seek the true God in behalf of the boy, and David went on a strict fast and came in and spent the night and lay down on the earth. 17 So the older men of his house stood up over him to raise him up from the earth, but he did not consent and did not take bread in company with them. 18 And it came about on the seventh day that the child gradually died. And the servants of David were afraid to tell him that the child had died; for they said: “Look! While the child continued alive we did speak to him, and he did not listen to our voice; so how can we say to him, ‘The child has died’? Then he will certainly do something bad.”

19 When David got to see that his servants were whispering together, David began to discern that the child had died. So David said to his servants: “Has the child died?” To this they said: “He has died.” 20 Then David got up from the earth and washed and rubbed himself with oil and changed his mantles and came to the house of Jehovah and prostrated himself; after which he came into his own house and asked, and they promptly set bread before him and he began to eat. 21 Consequently his servants said to him: “What does this thing mean that you have done? For the sake of the child while alive you fasted and kept weeping; and just as soon as the child had died you got up and began to eat bread.” 22 To this he said: “While the child was yet alive I did fast and I kept weeping, because I said to myself, ‘Who is there knowing whether Jehovah may show me favor, and the child will certainly live?’ 23 Now that he has died, why is it I am fasting? Am I able to bring him back again? I am going to him, but, as for him, he will not return to me.”

24 And David began to comfort Bath-she′ba his wife. Further, he came in to her and lay down with her. In time she bore a son, and his name came to be called Sol′o·mon. And Jehovah himself did love him. 25 So he sent by means of Nathan the prophet and called his name Jed·i·di′ah, for the sake of Jehovah.

26 And Jo′ab continued to fight against Rab′bah of the sons of Am′mon and got to capture the city of the kingdom. 27 So Jo′ab sent messengers to David and said: “I have fought against Rab′bah. I have also captured the city of waters. 28 And now gather the rest of the people and encamp against the city, and capture it; that I myself may not be the one to capture the city, and my name should not have to be called upon it.”

29 Accordingly David gathered all the people and went to Rab′bah and fought against it and captured it. 30 And he got to take the crown of Mal′cam off its head, the weight of which was a talent of gold, along with precious stones; and it came to be upon David’s head. And the spoil of the city that he brought out was very much. 31 And the people that were in it, he brought out that he might put them at sawing stones and at sharp instruments of iron and at axes of iron, and he made them serve at brickmaking. And that was the way he proceeded to do to all the cities of the sons of Am′mon. Finally David and all the people returned to Jerusalem.

2 Samuel

13 And it came about after such things that Ab′sa·lom the son of David had a beautiful sister whose name was Ta′mar, and Am′non the son of David fell in love with her. 2 And it was so distressing to Am′non that he felt sick on account of Ta′mar his sister, because she was a virgin, and it was difficult in the eyes of Am′non to do anything at all to her. 3 Now Am′non had a companion whose name was Je·hon′a·dab, the son of Shim′e·ah, David’s brother; and Je·hon′a·dab was a very wise man. 4 So he said to him: “Why are you, the son of the king, so downcast as this, morning by morning? Will you not tell me?” At this Am′non said to him: “With Ta′mar the sister of Ab′sa·lom my brother I am in love.” 5 Upon that Je·hon′a·dab said to him: “Lie down on your bed and play sick. And your father will certainly come to see you, and you must say to him, ‘Please, let Ta′mar my sister come in and give me bread as a patient, and she will have to make the bread of consolation under my eyes in order that I may see it, and I shall have to eat from her hand.’”

6 Accordingly Am′non lay down and played sick, and so the king came in to see him. Then Am′non said to the king: “Please, let Ta′mar my sister come in and bake two heart-shaped cakes under my eyes, that I may take bread as a patient from her hand.” 7 At that David sent to Ta′mar at the house, saying: “Go, please, to the house of Am′non your brother and make the bread of consolation for him.” 8 So Ta′mar went to the house of Am′non her brother while he was lying down. Then she took the flour dough and kneaded it and made the cakes under his eyes and cooked the heart-shaped cakes. 9 Finally she took the deep pan and poured it out before him, but Am′non refused to eat and said: “HAVE everybody go out from me!” Then everybody went out from him.

10 Am′non now said to Ta′mar: “Bring the bread of consolation to the interior room, that I may take it as a patient from your hand.” So Ta′mar took the heart-shaped cakes that she had made and brought them in to Am′non her brother in the interior room. 11 When she came near to him for him to eat, he at once grabbed hold of her and said to her: “Come, lie down with me, my sister.” 12 However, she said to him: “No, my brother! Do not humiliate me; for it is not usual to do that way in Israel. Do not do this disgraceful folly. 13 And I—where shall I cause my reproach to go? And you—you will become like one of the senseless men in Israel. And now speak, please, to the king; for he will not withhold me from you.” 14 And he did not consent to listen to her voice, but used strength superior to hers and humiliated her and lay down with her. 15 And Am′non began hating her with a very great hatred, because the hatred with which he hated her was greater than the love with which he had loved her, so that Am′non said to her: “Get up, go away!” 16 At this she said to him: “No, my brother; for this badness in sending me away is greater than the other that you have done with me!” And he did not consent to listen to her.

17 With that he called his attendant who waited upon him and said: “Send this person away from me, please, to the outside, and lock the door behind her.” 18 (Now upon her there was a striped robe; for that was the way the daughters of the king, the virgins, used to dress with sleeveless coats.) So his waiter proceeded to lead her clear outside, and he locked the door behind her. 19 Then Ta′mar placed ashes upon her head, and the striped robe that was upon her she ripped apart; and she kept her hands put upon her head and went walking away, crying out as she walked.

20 At this Ab′sa·lom her brother said to her: “Was it Am′non your brother that happened to be with you? And now, my sister, keep silent. He is your brother. Do not set your heart on this matter.” And Ta′mar began to dwell, while being kept from association with others, at the house of Ab′sa·lom her brother. 21 And King David himself heard about all these things, and he became very angry. 22 And Ab′sa·lom did not speak with Am′non either bad or good; for Ab′sa·lom hated Am′non over the fact that he had humiliated Ta′mar his sister.

23 And it turned out after two full years that Ab′sa·lom came to have sheepshearers at Ba′al-ha′zor, which is close by E′phra·im; and Ab′sa·lom proceeded to invite all the sons of the king. 24 So Ab′sa·lom came in to the king and said: “Here, now, your servant has sheepshearers! Let the king go, please, and also his servants, with your servant.” 25 But the king said to Ab′sa·lom: “No, my son! Do not let all of us go, please, that we may not be a burden upon you.” Although he kept urging him, he did not consent to go but blessed him. 26 Finally Ab′sa·lom said: “If not you, let Am′non my brother go with us, please.” At this the king said to him: “Why should he go with you?” 27 And Ab′sa·lom began to urge him, so that he sent Am′non and all the sons of the king with him.

28 Then Ab′sa·lom commanded his attendants, saying: “See, please, that just as soon as Am′non’s heart is in a merry mood with wine, and I shall certainly say to YOU, ‘Strike down Am′non!’ YOU must then put him to death. Do not be afraid. Have not I myself commanded YOU? Be strong and prove yourselves to be valiant men.” 29 And Ab′sa·lom’s attendants proceeded to do to Am′non just as Ab′sa·lom had commanded; and all the other sons of the king began to rise up and mount each one his mule and take to flight. 30 And it came about that, while they were on the way, the report itself came to David, saying: “Ab′sa·lom has struck down all the sons of the king, and not one of them has been left over.” 31 At this the king got up and ripped his clothes apart and lay upon the earth, and all his servants were standing by with their garments ripped apart.

32 However, Je·hon′a·dab the son of Shim′e·ah, David’s brother, answered and said: “Do not let my lord think that it is all the young men the sons of the king that they have put to death, for it is Am′non alone that has died, because at the order of Ab′sa·lom it has occurred as something appointed from the day that he humiliated Ta′mar his sister. 33 And now do not let my lord the king take to his heart the word, saying, ‘All the king’s sons themselves have died’; but it is Am′non alone that has died.”

34 Meantime, Ab′sa·lom went running away. Later the young man, the watchman, raised his eyes and saw, and, look! there were many people coming from the road behind him by the mountainside. 35 At this Je·hon′a·dab said to the king: “Look! The king’s sons themselves have come in. In accord with the word of your servant so it has taken place.” 36 And it came about that, as soon as he finished speaking, here the king’s sons themselves came in, and they began to raise their voice and weep; and even the king and all his servants wept with a very great weeping. 37 As for Ab′sa·lom, he ran off that he might go to Tal′mai the son of Am·mi′hud the king of Gesh′ur. And David continued to mourn over his son all the days. 38 As for Ab′sa·lom, he ran off and made his way to Gesh′ur; and he came to be there three years.

39 Finally the soul of David the king longed to go out to Ab′sa·lom; for he had comforted himself concerning Am′non, because he was dead.

2 Samuel

15 And it came about following such things that Ab′sa·lom proceeded to have a chariot made for himself, with horses and with fifty men running before him. 2 And Ab′sa·lom rose up early and stood at the side of the road to the gate. And it came about, when any man happened to have a legal case to come to the king for judgment, then Ab′sa·lom would call him and say: “From what city are you?” and he would say: “From one of the tribes of Israel your servant is.” 3 And Ab′sa·lom would say to him: “See, your matters are good and straight; but there is no one from the king giving you a hearing.” 4 And Ab′sa·lom would go on to say: “O that I were appointed judge in the land, that to me every man might come that happens to have a legal case or judgment! Then I should certainly do justice to him.”

5 It also occurred that, when a man drew near to bow down to him, he thrust his hand out and grabbed hold of him and kissed him. 6 And Ab′sa·lom kept doing a thing like this to all Israelites that would come in for judgment to the king; and Ab′sa·lom kept stealing the hearts of the men of Israel.

7 And it came about at the end of forty years that Ab′sa·lom proceeded to say to the king: “Let me go, please, and pay in He′bron my vow that I solemnly made to Jehovah. 8 For your servant made a solemn vow when I was dwelling in Gesh′ur in Syria, saying, ‘If Jehovah will without fail bring me back to Jerusalem, I must also render service to Jehovah.’” 9 So the king said to him: “Go in peace.” With that he rose up and went to He′bron.

10 Ab′sa·lom now sent spies through all the tribes of Israel, saying: “As soon as YOU hear the sound of the horn, YOU must also say, ‘Ab′sa·lom has become king in He′bron!’” 11 Now there had gone with Ab′sa·lom two hundred men from Jerusalem, being called and going unsuspectingly, and they did not know a single thing. 12 Further, when he offered the sacrifices, Ab′sa·lom sent for A·hith′o·phel the Gi′lon·ite, David’s counselor, from his city Gi′loh. And the conspiracy kept getting stronger, and the people were continually growing in number with Ab′sa·lom.

13 In time an informer came to David, saying: “The heart of the men of Israel has come to be behind Ab′sa·lom.” 14 At once David said to all his servants that were with him in Jerusalem: “Get up, and let us run away; for there will prove to be no escaping for us because of Ab′sa·lom! Go hurriedly, for fear he may hurry up and actually catch up with us and bring down upon us what is bad and strike the city with the edge of the sword!” 15 At this the king’s servants said to the king: “According to all that my lord the king may choose, here are your servants.” 16 So the king went out with all his household at his feet, and the king left ten women, concubines, to take care of the house. 17 And the king continued on his way out with all the people at his feet; and they came to a stop at Beth-mer′hak.

18 And all his servants were crossing at his side; and all the Cher′e·thites and all the Pel′e·thites and all the Git′tites, six hundred men that had followed him from Gath, were crossing before the king’s face. 19 Then the king said to It′tai the Git′tite: “Why should you yourself also go with us? Go back and dwell with the king; for you are a foreigner and, besides, you are an exile from your place. 20 Yesterday was when you came and today shall I make you wander with us, to go when I am going wherever I am going? Go back and take your brothers back with you, and may Jehovah exercise toward you loving-kindness and trustworthiness!” 21 But It′tai answered the king and said: “As Jehovah is living and as my lord the king is living, in the place where my lord the king may come to be, whether for death or for life, there is where your servant will come to be!” 22 At that David said to It′tai: “Go and cross over.” So It′tai the Git′tite crossed over, and also all his men and all the little ones that were with him.

23 And all the people of the land were weeping with a loud voice, and all the people were crossing over, and the king was standing by the torrent valley of Kid′ron, and all the people were crossing over upon the open road to the wilderness. 24 And here also there were Za′dok and with him all the Levites carrying the ark of the covenant of the true God; and they proceeded to set the ark of the true God down by A·bi′a·thar until all the people completed crossing over from the city. 25 But the king said to Za′dok: “Take the ark of the true God back to the city. If I shall find favor in the eyes of Jehovah, he will also certainly bring me back and let me see it and its abiding place. 26 But if this is what he should say, ‘I have found no delight in you,’ here I am, let him do to me just as it is good in his eyes.” 27 And the king went on to say to Za′dok the priest: “You are a seer, are you? Do return to the city in peace, and also A·him′a·az your son and Jon′a·than the son of A·bi′a·thar, the two sons of YOU men, with YOU. 28 See, I am lingering by the fords of the wilderness until word comes from YOU men to inform me.” 29 Accordingly Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar took the ark of the true God back to Jerusalem, and they continued to dwell there.

30 And David was going up by the ascent of the Olives, weeping as he went up, with his head covered; and he was walking barefoot, and all the people that were with him covered each one his head, and they went up weeping as they went up. 31 And to David the report was made, saying: “A·hith′o·phel himself is among those conspiring with Ab′sa·lom.” At this David said: “Turn, please, the counsel of A·hith′o·phel into foolishness, O Jehovah!”

32 And it came about that when David himself came to the summit where people used to bow down to God, here to meet him was Hu′shai the Ar′chite, with his robe ripped apart and dirt upon his head. 33 However, David said to him: “If you actually went across with me, you would then certainly become a load upon me. 34 But if you return to the city and you actually say to Ab′sa·lom, ‘I am your servant, O King. I used to prove myself the servant of your father, even I at that time, but now even I am your servant,’ you must then frustrate the counsel of A·hith′o·phel for me. 35 Are not Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar the priests there with you? And it must occur that everything that you may hear from the house of the king you should tell to Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar the priests. 36 Look! There with them are their two sons, A·him′a·az belonging to Za′dok and Jon′a·than belonging to A·bi′a·thar; and by means of them YOU men must send to me everything that YOU may hear.” 37 So Hu′shai, David’s companion, came into the city. As for Ab′sa·lom, he proceeded to come into Jerusalem.

2 Samuel

16 When David himself had crossed over a little beyond the summit, there was Zi′ba the attendant of Me·phib′o·sheth to meet him with a couple of asses saddled and upon them two hundred loaves of bread and a hundred cakes of raisins and a hundred loads of summer fruit and a large jar of wine. 2 Then the king said to Zi′ba: “What do these things mean on your part?” To this Zi′ba said: “The asses are for the household of the king to ride, and the bread and the load of summer fruit are for the young men to eat, and the wine is for the one tired out in the wilderness to drink.” 3 The king now said: “And where is the son of your master?” At this Zi′ba said to the king: “There he is dwelling in Jerusalem; for he said, ‘Today the house of Israel will give back to me the royal rule of my father.’” 4 The king then said to Zi′ba: “Look! Yours is everything that belongs to Me·phib′o·sheth.” Upon that Zi′ba said: “I do bow down. Let me find favor in your eyes, my lord the king.”

5 And King David came as far as Ba·hu′rim, and, look! coming out from there was a man of the family of Saul’s house, and his name was Shim′e·i, the son of Ge′ra, coming out and calling down evil as he came out. 6 And he began throwing stones at David and at all the servants of King David; and all the people and all the mighty men were at his right and at his left. 7 And this is what Shim′e·i said as he called down evil: “Get out, get out, you bloodguilty man and good-for-nothing man! 8 Jehovah has brought back upon you all the bloodguilt for the house of Saul in place of whom you have ruled as king; and Jehovah gives the kingship into the hand of Ab′sa·lom your son. And here you are in your calamity, because you are a bloodguilty man!”

9 Finally A·bish′ai the son of Ze·ru′iah said to the king: “Why should this dead dog call down evil upon my lord the king? Let me go over, please, and take off his head.” 10 But the king said: “What do I have to do with YOU men, YOU sons of Ze·ru′iah? Thus let him call down evil, because Jehovah himself has said to him, ‘Call down evil upon David!’ So who should say, ‘Why did you do that way?’” 11 And David went on to say to A·bish′ai and all his servants: “Here my own son, who has come forth out of my own inward parts, is looking for my soul; and how much more now a Ben′ja·min·ite! Let him alone that he may call down evil, for Jehovah has said so to him! 12 Perhaps Jehovah will see with his eye, and Jehovah will actually restore to me goodness instead of his malediction this day.” 13 With that David and his men kept going on in the road, while Shim′e·i was walking on the side of the mountain, walking abreast of him that he might call down evil; and he kept throwing stones while abreast of him, and he threw a lot of dust.

14 At length the king and all the people that were with him arrived tired. So they refreshed themselves there.

15 As for Ab′sa·lom and all the people, the men of Israel, they entered Jerusalem; and A·hith′o·phel was with him. 16 And it came about that, as soon as Hu′shai the Ar′chite, David’s companion, came in to Ab′sa·lom, Hu′shai proceeded to say to Ab′sa·lom: “Let the king live! Let the king live!” 17 At this Ab′sa·lom said to Hu′shai: “This is the loving-kindness of yours toward your companion, is it? Why did you not go with your companion?” 18 So Hu′shai said to Ab′sa·lom: “No; but the one whom Jehovah has chosen and also this people and all the men of Israel, his I shall become, and with him I shall dwell. 19 And for the second time I must say, Whom shall I myself serve? Is it not before his son? Just as I served before your father, so I shall prove to be before you.”

20 Later Ab′sa·lom said to A·hith′o·phel: “YOU men, give counsel on YOUR part. What shall we do?” 21 Then A·hith′o·phel said to Ab′sa·lom: “Have relations with the concubines of your father, whom he left behind to take care of the house. And all Israel will certainly hear that you have made yourself foul-smelling to your father, and the hands of all those who are with you will certainly become strong.” 22 Accordingly they pitched a tent for Ab′sa·lom upon the roof, and Ab′sa·lom began to have relations with the concubines of his father under the eyes of all Israel.

23 And the counsel of A·hith′o·phel, with which he counseled in those days, was just as when a man would inquire of the word of the true God. That was the way all the counsel of A·hith′o·phel was both to David and to Ab′sa·lom.

2 Samuel

17 And A·hith′o·phel proceeded to say to Ab′sa·lom: “Let me choose, please, twelve thousand men and rise up and chase after David tonight. 2 And I shall come upon him when he is weary and feeble in both hands, and I shall certainly drive him into trembling; and all the people that are with him will have to flee, and I shall certainly strike down the king by himself. 3 And let me bring all the people back to you. Equivalent to the returning of all is the man whom you are seeking; and all the people will themselves come to be at peace.” 4 And the word was just right in the eyes of Ab′sa·lom and in the eyes of all the older men of Israel.

5 However, Ab′sa·lom said: “Call, please, Hu′shai the Ar′chite also, and let us hear what is in his mouth, even his.” 6 So Hu′shai came in to Ab′sa·lom. Then Ab′sa·lom said to him: “According to this word is the way A·hith′o·phel spoke. Shall we act upon his word? If not, you yourself speak.” 7 At this Hu′shai said to Ab′sa·lom: “The counsel with which A·hith′o·phel has counseled is not good in this instance!”

8 And Hu′shai went on to say: “You yourself well know your father and the men of his, that they are mighty, and they are bitter of soul, like a female bear that has lost her cubs in the field; and your father is a warrior, and he will not spend the night with the people. 9 Look! Now he is in hiding in one of the hollows or in one of the other places; and it will certainly occur that, just as soon as he falls upon them at the start, the one hearing of it will then be bound to hear and say, ‘A defeat has taken place among the people that are following Ab′sa·lom!’ 10 And even the valiant man whose heart is as the heart of the lion will himself surely soften in weakness; for all Israel is aware that your father is a mighty man and so, too, are the valiant men that are with him. 11 I myself do say in counsel: Let all Israel without fail be gathered to you, from Dan to Be′er-she′ba, as the sand particles that are by the sea for multitude, with your own person going into the fight. 12 And we must come against him in one of the places where he is certain to be found, and we ourselves will be upon him just as the dew falls upon the ground; and there will certainly not be left even a single one among him and all the men that are with him. 13 And if it is into some city that he will withdraw, all Israel must also carry ropes to that city, and we shall certainly drag it down to the torrent valley, until there shall not be found there even a pebble.”

14 Then Ab′sa·lom and all the men of Israel said: “The counsel of Hu′shai the Ar′chite is better than the counsel of A·hith′o·phel!” And Jehovah himself had given command to frustrate the counsel of A·hith′o·phel although good, in order that Jehovah might bring calamity upon Ab′sa·lom.

15 Later Hu′shai said to Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar the priests: “This and that was the way that A·hith′o·phel counseled Ab′sa·lom and the older men of Israel; and this and that was the way that I myself counseled. 16 And now send speedily and tell David, saying, ‘Do not lodge in the desert plains of the wilderness tonight, but you also ought to cross over without fail, for fear that the king and all the people that are with him may be swallowed up.’”

17 As Jon′a·than and A·him′a·az were standing at En-ro′gel, a maidservant went off and told them. So they themselves went off, as they had to tell King David; for they were not able to appear entering the city. 18 However, a young man got to see them and told Ab′sa·lom. So the two of them went off speedily and came to the house of a man in Ba·hu′rim, who had a well in his courtyard; and they went down into it. 19 After that the woman took and spread out a screen over the face of the well and heaped up cracked grain upon it; and not a thing became known of it. 20 The servants of Ab′sa·lom now came to the woman at her house and said: “Where are A·him′a·az and Jon′a·than?” At this the woman said to them: “They passed on from here to the waters.” Then they kept on searching, and they did not find them and so returned to Jerusalem.

21 And it came about after their going away that then they came up out of the well and went on and told King David and said to David: “YOU people, rise up and speedily pass over the waters; for this is the way that A·hith′o·phel counseled against YOU.” 22 Immediately David rose up and also all the people that were with him, and they kept crossing the Jordan until the morning became light, until not a one was lacking that had not passed over the Jordan.

23 As for A·hith′o·phel, he saw that his counsel had not been acted upon, and he proceeded to saddle an ass and rise up and go off to his house at his own city. Then he gave commands to his household and strangled himself and thus died. So he was buried in the burial place of his forefathers.

24 As for David, he came to Ma·ha·na′im, and Ab′sa·lom himself crossed the Jordan, he and all the men of Israel with him. 25 And A·ma′sa was the one whom Ab′sa·lom put in the place of Jo′ab over the army; and A·ma′sa was the son of a man whose name was Ith′ra the Israelite, who had relations with Ab′i·gail the daughter of Na′hash, the sister of Ze·ru′iah, Jo′ab’s mother. 26 And Israel and Ab′sa·lom took up camping in the land of Gil′e·ad.

27 And it came about that, as soon as David came to Ma·ha·na′im, Sho′bi the son of Na′hash from Rab′bah of the sons of Am′mon, and Ma′chir the son of Am′mi·el from Lo-de′bar, and Bar·zil′lai the Gil′e·ad·ite from Ro·ge′lim 28 brought beds and basins and potter’s vessels, and wheat and barley and flour and roasted grain and broad beans and lentils and parched grain; 29 and honey and butter and sheep and curds of cattle they brought forward for David and the people that were with him to eat, for they said: “The people are hungry and tired and thirsty in the wilderness.”

2 Samuel

18 And David proceeded to number the people that were with him and to place over them chiefs of thousands and chiefs of hundreds. 2 Further, David sent one third of the people under the hand of Jo′ab and one third under the hand of A·bish′ai the son of Ze·ru′iah, Jo′ab’s brother, and one third under the hand of It′tai the Git′tite. Then the king said to the people: “I myself also shall without fail go out with YOU.” 3 But the people said: “You must not go out, for if we should at all flee, they would not set heart upon us; and if half of us would die, they would not set heart upon us, because you are worth ten thousand of us; and now it would be better if you would be of service to us to give help from the city.” 4 So the king said to them: “Whatever seems good in YOUR eyes I shall do.” And the king kept standing at the side of the gate, and all the people themselves went out by hundreds and by thousands. 5 And the king went on to command Jo′ab and A·bish′ai and It′tai, saying: “Deal gently for my sake with the young man Ab′sa·lom.” And all the people themselves heard when the king commanded all the chiefs over the matter of Ab′sa·lom.

6 And the people continued on their way out to the field to meet Israel; and the battle came to be in the forest of E′phra·im. 7 Finally the people of Israel were defeated there before the servants of David, and the slaughter there turned out to be great on that day, of twenty thousand men. 8 And the battle there got to be spread out over all the land that was in sight. Furthermore, the forest did more in eating up the people than the sword did in eating them up on that day.

9 Eventually Ab′sa·lom found himself before the servants of David. And Ab′sa·lom was riding upon a mule, and the mule got to come under the network of boughs of a massive big tree, so that his head got caught fast in the big tree, and he was taken up between the heavens and the earth, as the mule itself that was under him passed along. 10 Then a certain man saw it and told Jo′ab and said: “Look! I have seen Ab′sa·lom hung in a big tree.” 11 At this Jo′ab said to the man who was telling him: “And here you saw it, and why did you not strike him down to the earth there? Then it would have been my obligation to give you ten pieces of silver and a belt.” 12 But the man said to Jo′ab: “And although I were weighing upon my palms a thousand pieces of silver, I should not thrust my hand out against the king’s son; for in our hearing it was that the king commanded you and A·bish′ai and It′tai, saying, ‘WATCH, whoever you are, over the young man, over Ab′sa·lom.’ 13 Otherwise I should have dealt treacherously against his soul and the whole matter itself would not be hidden from the king, and you yourself would take a position off on the side.” 14 To this Jo′ab said: “Let me not hold myself up this way before you!” With that he took three shafts in his palm and proceeded to drive them through the heart of Ab′sa·lom while he was yet alive in the heart of the big tree. 15 Then ten attendants carrying Jo′ab’s weapons came around and struck Ab′sa·lom, that they might put him to death. 16 Jo′ab now blew the horn, that the people might return from chasing after Israel; for Jo′ab had held back the people. 17 Finally they took Ab′sa·lom and pitched him in the forest into a big hollow and raised up over him a very big pile of stones. As for all Israel, they fled each man to his home.

18 Now Ab′sa·lom himself, while he was alive, had taken and proceeded to raise up for himself a pillar, which is in the Low Plain of the King, for he said: “I have no son in order to keep my name in remembrance.” So he called the pillar by his own name, and it continues to be called Ab′sa·lom’s Monument down to this day.

19 Now as regards A·him′a·az the son of Za′dok, he said: “Let me run, please, and break the news to the king, because Jehovah has judged him to free him from the hand of his enemies.” 20 But Jo′ab said to him: “You are not a man of news this day, and you must break the news on another day; but this day you must not break the news, for the very reason that the king’s own son has died.” 21 Then Jo′ab said to the Cush′ite: “Go, tell the king what you have seen.” At that the Cush′ite bowed to Jo′ab and began to run. 22 A·him′a·az the son of Za′dok now said once again to Jo′ab: “Let, now, happen whatever will, let me also myself, please, run behind the Cush′ite.” However, Jo′ab said: “Why is it that you yourself have to run, my son, when there is no news being found for you?” 23 Still he said: “Let, now, happen whatever will, let me run.” So he said to him: “Run!” And A·him′a·az began to run by the way of the District, and he eventually passed by the Cush′ite.

24 Now David was sitting between the two gates. Meantime, the watchman went to the roof of the gate by the wall. At length he raised his eyes and saw and, look! there was a man running by himself. 25 So the watchman called and told the king, at which the king said: “If he is by himself, there is news in his mouth.” And he kept coming, steadily getting nearer. 26 The watchman now saw another man running. The watchman therefore called to the gatekeeper and said: “Look! Another man running by himself!” at which the king said: “This one also is a news bearer.” 27 And the watchman went on to say: “I am seeing that the running style of the first is like the running style of A·him′a·az the son of Za′dok,” at which the king said: “This is a good man, and with good news he should come.” 28 Eventually A·him′a·az called and said to the king: “It is well!” With that he bowed to the king with his face to the earth. And he went on to say: “Blessed be Jehovah your God, who has surrendered the men that lifted up their hand against my lord the king!”

29 However, the king said: “Is it well with the young man Ab′sa·lom?” To this A·him′a·az said: “I saw the great commotion at the time Jo′ab sent the king’s servant and your servant, and I did not know what it was.” 30 So the king said: “Step aside, take your position here.” At that he stepped aside and kept standing still.

31 And here was the Cush′ite coming in, and the Cush′ite began to say: “Let my lord the king accept news, for Jehovah has judged you today to free you from the hand of all those rising up against you.” 32 But the king said to the Cush′ite: “Is it well with the young man Ab′sa·lom?” To this the Cush′ite said: “May the enemies of my lord the king and all those who rose up against you for evil become as the young man.”

33 Then the king became disturbed and went up to the roof chamber over the gateway and gave way to weeping; and this is what he said as he walked: “My son Ab′sa·lom, my son, my son Ab′sa·lom! O that I might have died, I myself, instead of you, Ab′sa·lom my son, my son!”

2 Samuel

20 Now there happened to be there a good-for-nothing man, whose name was She′ba, the son of Bich′ri a Ben′ja·min·ite; and he proceeded to blow the horn and say: “We have no share in David, and we have no inheritance in the son of Jes′se. Every one to his gods, O Israel!” 2 At that all the men of Israel began to go up from following David to follow She′ba the son of Bich′ri; but as for the men of Judah, they stuck to their king from the Jordan to Jerusalem.

3 Eventually David came to his house at Jerusalem. Then the king took the ten women, the concubines whom he had left behind to take care of the house, and he put them in a house of confinement, but he kept on supplying food to them. And with them he did not have any relations, but they continued shut up closely until the day of their dying, in a widowhood with a living husband.

4 The king now said to A·ma′sa: “Call the men of Judah together to me within three days, and you yourself stand here.” 5 So A·ma′sa went to call Judah together; but he came later than the fixed time that he had appointed for him. 6 Then David said to A·bish′ai: “Now She′ba the son of Bich′ri will be worse for us than Ab′sa·lom. You yourself take the servants of your lord and chase after him, that he may not actually find for himself fortified cities and escape before our eyes.” 7 Accordingly the men of Jo′ab and the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites and all the mighty men went out after him; and they went on out of Jerusalem to chase after She′ba the son of Bich′ri. 8 They were close by the great stone that is in Gib′e·on, and A·ma′sa himself came to meet them. Now Jo′ab was girded, clothed with a garment; and upon him there was girded a sword attached to his hip, in its sheath. And he himself came forth, and so it fell out.

9 And Jo′ab proceeded to say to A·ma′sa: “Is it all right with you, my brother?” Then Jo′ab’s right hand took hold of A·ma′sa’s beard so as to kiss him. 10 As for A·ma′sa, he was not on guard against the sword that was in Jo′ab’s hand; so that he struck him with it in the abdomen, and his intestines spilled out to the earth, and he did not have to do it to him again. So he died. And Jo′ab and A·bish′ai his brother, for their part, chased after She′ba the son of Bich′ri.

11 And a certain one of Jo′ab’s young men stood over him and kept saying: “Whoever has found delight in Jo′ab and whoever belongs to David, let him follow Jo′ab!” 12 All the while A·ma′sa was wallowing in the blood in the middle of the highway. When the man saw that all the people stood still, then he moved A·ma′sa from the highway to the field. Finally he cast a garment over him, as he saw that everyone coming up to him stood still. 13 As soon as he had removed him from the highway, each man passed by following Jo′ab to chase after She′ba the son of Bich′ri.

14 And She′ba went passing through all the tribes of Israel to Abel of Beth-ma′a·cah. As for all the Bich′rites, they then congregated together and also went in after him.

15 And they proceeded to come and lay siege against him in Abel of Beth-ma′a·cah and cast up a siege rampart against the city, as it was standing within a rampart. And all the people that were with Jo′ab were undermining the wall, to throw it down. 16 And a wise woman began to call from the city: “Listen, men, listen! Say, please, to Jo′ab, ‘Come near as far as here, and let me speak to you.’” 17 So he went near to her, and the woman then said: “Are you Jo′ab?” to which he said: “I am.” At this she said to him: “Listen to the words of your slave girl.” In turn he said: “I am listening.” 18 And she went on to say: “Without exception they used to speak in former times, saying, ‘Let them but inquire in Abel, and thus they will certainly end the matter.’ 19 I represent the peaceable and faithful ones of Israel. You are seeking to put to death a city and a mother in Israel. Why should you swallow up the inheritance of Jehovah?” 20 To this Jo′ab answered and said: “It is altogether unthinkable on my part that I should swallow up and that I should bring to ruin. 21 The matter is not that way, but a man from the mountainous region of E′phra·im, whose name is She′ba the son of Bich′ri, has lifted up his hand against King David. YOU people, give him over by himself, and I will withdraw from the city.” Then the woman said to Jo′ab: “Look! His head will be pitched to you over the wall!”

22 At once the woman went in her wisdom to all the people, and they proceeded to cut off the head of She′ba the son of Bich′ri and pitch it to Jo′ab. Upon that he blew the horn, and so they were scattered from the city, each one to his home; and Jo′ab himself returned to Jerusalem to the king.

23 And Jo′ab was over all the army of Israel; and Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da was over the Cher′e·thites and over the Pel′e·thites. 24 And A·do′ram was over those conscripted for forced labor; and Je·hosh′a·phat the son of A·hi′lud was the recorder. 25 And She′va was secretary, and Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar were priests. 26 And I′ra the Ja′ir·ite also became a priest of David.

The First of Kings

or, according to the Greek Septuagint, THE THIRD OF KINGS

1 Now King David was old, advanced in days; and they would cover him with garments, but he would not feel warm. 2 So his servants said to him: “Let them look for a girl, a virgin, for my lord the king, and she will have to attend upon the king, that she may become his nurse; and she must lie in your bosom, and my lord the king will certainly feel warm.” 3 And they went looking for a beautiful girl throughout all the territory of Israel, and finally found Ab′i·shag the Shu′nam·mite and then brought her in to the king. 4 And the girl was beautiful in the extreme; and she came to be the king’s nurse and kept waiting upon him, and the king himself had no intercourse with her.

5 All the while Ad·o·ni′jah the son of Hag′gith was lifting himself up, saying: “I myself am going to rule as king!” And he proceeded to have a chariot made for himself with horsemen and fifty men running before him. 6 And his father did not hurt his feelings at any time by saying: “Why is this the way you have done?” And he was also very good-looking in form, and his mother had borne him after Ab′sa·lom. 7 And he came to have dealings with Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah and with A·bi′a·thar the priest, and they began offering help as followers of Ad·o·ni′jah. 8 As for Za′dok the priest and Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da and Nathan the prophet and Shim′e·i and Re′i and the mighty men that belonged to David, they did not become involved with Ad·o·ni′jah.

9 Eventually Ad·o·ni′jah held a sacrifice of sheep and cattle and fatlings close by the stone of Zo′he·leth, which is beside En-ro′gel, and he proceeded to invite all his brothers the king’s sons and all the men of Judah the king’s servants; 10 and Nathan the prophet and Be·nai′ah and the mighty men and Sol′o·mon his brother he did not invite. 11 Nathan now said to Bath-she′ba, Sol′o·mon’s mother: “Have you not heard that Ad·o·ni′jah the son of Hag′gith has become king, and our lord David does not know of it at all? 12 So now come, let me, please, solemnly counsel you. And provide escape for your own soul and for the soul of your son Sol′o·mon. 13 Go and enter in to King David, and you must say to him, ‘Was it not you, my lord the king, that swore to your slave girl, saying: “Sol′o·mon your son is the one that will become king after me, and he is the one that will sit upon my throne”? So why has Ad·o·ni′jah become king?’ 14 Look! While you are yet speaking there with the king, then I myself shall come in after you, and I shall certainly confirm your words.”

15 Accordingly Bath-she′ba went in to the king in the interior room, and the king was very old, and Ab′i·shag the Shu′nam·mite was waiting upon the king. 16 Then Bath-she′ba bowed low and prostrated herself to the king, upon which the king said: “What do you have to ask?” 17 At this she said to him: “My lord, it was you that swore by Jehovah your God to your slave girl, ‘Sol′o·mon your son is the one that will become king after me, and he is the one that will sit upon my throne.’ 18 And now, look! Ad·o·ni′jah himself has become king, and now my lord the king himself does not know of it at all. 19 So he sacrificed bulls and fatlings and sheep in great quantity and invited all the sons of the king and A·bi′a·thar the priest and Jo′ab the chief of the army; but Sol′o·mon your servant he has not invited. 20 And you my lord the king—the eyes of all Israel are upon you, to tell them who is going to sit upon the throne of my lord the king after him. 21 And it will certainly occur that as soon as my lord the king lies down with his forefathers, I myself and also my son Sol′o·mon shall certainly become offenders.”

22 And, look! while she was yet speaking with the king, Nathan the prophet himself came in. 23 At once they told the king, saying: “Here is Nathan the prophet!” After that he came in before the king and prostrated himself to the king with his face to the earth. 24 Then Nathan said: “My lord the king, did you yourself say, ‘Ad·o·ni′jah is the one that will become king after me, and he is the one that will sit upon my throne’? 25 For he has today gone down that he might sacrifice bulls and fatlings and sheep in great quantity and might invite all the sons of the king and the chiefs of the army and A·bi′a·thar the priest; and there they are eating and drinking before him and they keep saying, ‘Let King Ad·o·ni′jah live!’ 26 But as for me your servant, me and Za′dok the priest and Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da and Sol′o·mon your servant he has not invited. 27 If it is from my lord the king that this thing has been brought about, then you have not caused your servant to know who should sit upon the throne of my lord the king after him.”

28 King David now answered and said: “YOU men, call Bath-she′ba for me.” At that she came in before the king and stood before the king. 29 And the king proceeded to swear and say: “As Jehovah is living who redeemed my soul out of all distress, 30 just as I have sworn to you by Jehovah the God of Israel, saying, ‘Sol′o·mon your son is the one that will become king after me, and he is the one that will sit upon my throne in place of me!’ that is the way I shall do this day.” 31 Then Bath-she′ba bowed low with her face to the earth and prostrated herself to the king and said: “Let my lord King David live to time indefinite!”

32 Immediately King David said: “YOU men, call for me Za′dok the priest and Nathan the prophet and Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da.” So they came in before the king. 33 And the king went on to say to them: “Take with YOU the servants of YOUR lord, and YOU must make Sol′o·mon my son ride upon the she-mule that belongs to me and lead him down to Gi′hon. 34 And Za′dok the priest and Nathan the prophet must anoint him there as king over Israel; and YOU must blow the horn and say, ‘Let King Sol′o·mon live!’ 35 And YOU must come up following him, and he must come in and sit upon my throne; and he himself will be king in place of me, and him I shall have to commission to become leader over Israel and over Judah.” 36 At once Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da answered the king and said: “Amen! Thus may Jehovah the God of my lord the king say. 37 Just as Jehovah proved to be with my lord the king, so let him prove to be with Sol′o·mon, and may he make his throne greater than the throne of my lord King David.”

38 And Za′dok the priest and Nathan the prophet and Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da and the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites proceeded to go down and make Sol′o·mon ride upon the she-mule of King David, and then brought him to Gi′hon. 39 Za′dok the priest now took the horn of oil out of the tent and anointed Sol′o·mon; and they began to blow the horn, and all the people broke out saying: “Let King Sol′o·mon live!” 40 After that all the people came on up following him, and the people were playing on flutes and rejoicing with great joy, so that the earth was split by the noise of them.

41 And Ad·o·ni′jah and all the ones invited that were with him got to hear it, when they themselves had finished eating. When Jo′ab got to hear the sound of the horn, he at once said: “What does the noise of the town in an uproar mean?” 42 While he was yet speaking, why, here Jon′a·than the son of A·bi′a·thar the priest came. Then Ad·o·ni′jah said: “Come on in, for you are a valiant man, and you bring good news.” 43 But Jon′a·than answered and said to Ad·o·ni′jah: “No! Our lord King David himself has made Sol′o·mon king. 44 So the king sent with him Za′dok the priest and Nathan the prophet and Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da and the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites, and they made him ride upon the she-mule of the king. 45 Then Za′dok the priest and Nathan the prophet anointed him as king in Gi′hon; after which they came up from there rejoicing, and the town is in an uproar. That was the noise that YOU men heard. 46 And, besides, Sol′o·mon has sat down upon the throne of the kingship. 47 And, another thing, the servants of the king have come in to wish our lord King David well, saying, ‘May your God make Sol′o·mon’s name more splendid than your name, and may he make his throne greater than your throne!’ At that the king bowed down upon the bed. 48 And too this is what the king said, ‘Blessed be Jehovah the God of Israel, who has today given one to sit upon my throne, with my own eyes seeing it!’”

49 And all those invited that were with Ad·o·ni′jah began to tremble and rise up and go each one on his own way. 50 And Ad·o·ni′jah himself was afraid because of Sol′o·mon. So he rose up and went away and grabbed hold of the horns of the altar. 51 In time the report was made to Sol′o·mon, saying: “Here Ad·o·ni′jah himself has become afraid of King Sol′o·mon; and here he has taken hold on the horns of the altar, saying, ‘Let King Sol′o·mon first of all swear to me that he will not put his servant to death by the sword.’” 52 To this Sol′o·mon said: “If he will become a valiant man, there will not fall a single hair of his to the earth; but if what is bad should be found in him, he will also have to die.” 53 So King Sol′o·mon sent and they brought him down from off the altar. Then he came in and bowed down to King Sol′o·mon; after which Sol′o·mon said to him: “Go to your own house.”

1 Kings

2 And the days of David gradually drew near for him to die; and he proceeded to command Sol′o·mon his son, saying: 2 “I am going in the way of all the earth, and you must be strong and prove yourself to be a man. 3 And you must keep the obligation to Jehovah your God by walking in his ways, by keeping his statutes, his commandments and his judicial decisions and his testimonies, according to what is written in the law of Moses, in order that you may act prudently in everything that you do and everywhere that you turn; 4 in order that Jehovah may carry out his word that he spoke respecting me, saying, ‘If your sons will take care of their way by walking before me in truth with all their heart and with all their soul, there will not be cut off a man of yours from sitting upon the throne of Israel.’

5 “And you yourself also well know what Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah did to me in what he did to two chiefs of the armies of Israel, to Ab′ner the son of Ner and A·ma′sa the son of Je′ther, when he killed them and placed the blood of war in peacetime and put the blood of war on his belt that was about his hips and in his sandals that were on his feet. 6 And you must act according to your wisdom, and not let his gray hairs go down in peace to She′ol.

7 “And toward the sons of Bar·zil′lai the Gil′e·ad·ite you should exercise loving-kindness, and they must prove to be among those eating at your table; for that was the way they drew near to me when I ran away from before Ab′sa·lom your brother.

8 “And here there is with you Shim′e·i the son of Ge′ra the Ben′ja·min·ite from Ba·hu′rim, and he it was that called down evil upon me with a painful malediction on the day that I was going to Ma·ha·na′im; and he it was that came down to meet me at the Jordan, so that I swore to him by Jehovah, saying, ‘I shall not put you to death by the sword.’ 9 And now do not leave him unpunished, for you are a wise man and you well know what you ought to do to him, and you must bring his gray hairs down to She′ol with blood.”

10 Then David lay down with his forefathers and was buried in the City of David. 11 And the days that David had reigned over Israel were forty years. In He′bron he had reigned seven years, and in Jerusalem he had reigned thirty-three years.

12 As for Sol′o·mon, he sat down upon the throne of David his father; and gradually his kingship became very firmly established.

13 In time Ad·o·ni′jah the son of Hag′gith came to Bath-she′ba, Sol′o·mon’s mother. At this she said: “Is your coming peaceable?” to which he said: “It is peaceable.” 14 And he went on to say: “There is a matter I have for you.” So she said: “Speak.” 15 And he continued: “You yourself well know that the kingship was to have become mine, and it was toward me that all Israel had set their face for me to become king; but the kingship turned and came to be my brother’s, for it was from Jehovah that it became his. 16 And now there is one request that I am making of you. Do not turn my face away.” Accordingly she said to him: “Speak.” 17 And he went on to say: “Please, say to Sol′o·mon the king (for he will not turn your face away) that he should give me Ab′i·shag the Shu′nam·mite as a wife.” 18 To this Bath-she′ba said: “Good! I myself shall speak for you to the king.”

19 So Bath-she′ba came in to King Sol′o·mon to speak to him for Ad·o·ni′jah. At once the king rose to meet her and bowed down to her. Then he sat down upon his throne and had a throne set for the mother of the king, that she might sit at his right. 20 And she proceeded to say: “There is one little request that I am making of you. Do not turn my face away.” So the king said to her: “Make it, my mother; for I shall not turn your face away.” 21 And she went on to say: “Let Ab′i·shag the Shu′nam·mite be given to Ad·o·ni′jah your brother as a wife.” 22 At this King Sol′o·mon answered and said to his mother: “And why are you requesting Ab′i·shag the Shu′nam·mite for Ad·o·ni′jah? Request also for him the kingship (because he is my brother older than I am), even for him and for A·bi′a·thar the priest and for Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah.”

23 With that King Sol′o·mon swore by Jehovah, saying: “So may God do to me, and so may he add to it, if it was not against his own soul that Ad·o·ni′jah spoke this thing. 24 And now, as Jehovah is living who has firmly established me and keeps me seated upon the throne of David my father and who made a house for me just as he has spoken, today Ad·o·ni′jah will be put to death.” 25 Immediately King Sol′o·mon sent by means of Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da; and he proceeded to fall upon him, so that he died.

26 And to A·bi′a·thar the priest the king said: “Go to An′a·thoth to your fields! For you are deserving of death; but on this day I shall not put you to death, because you carried the ark of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah before David my father, and because you suffered affliction during all the time that my father suffered affliction.” 27 So Sol′o·mon drove out A·bi′a·thar from serving as a priest of Jehovah, to fulfill Jehovah’s word that he had spoken against the house of E′li in Shi′loh.

28 And the report itself came clear to Jo′ab—for Jo′ab himself had inclined to follow Ad·o·ni′jah, although Ab′sa·lom he had not inclined to follow—and Jo′ab went fleeing to the tent of Jehovah and began to hold fast to the horns of the altar. 29 Then King Sol′o·mon was told: “Jo′ab has fled to the tent of Jehovah, and there he is beside the altar.” So Sol′o·mon sent Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da, saying: “Go, fall upon him!” 30 Accordingly Be·nai′ah came to the tent of Jehovah and said to him: “This is what the king has said, ‘Come on out!’” But he said: “No! For here is where I shall die.” At that Be·nai′ah brought word back to the king, saying: “This is what Jo′ab spoke, and this is what he answered me.” 31 Then the king said to him: “Do just as he has spoken and fall upon him; and you must bury him and remove from off me and from off the house of my father the blood undeservedly shed that Jo′ab spilled. 32 And Jehovah will certainly bring back his blood upon his own head, because he fell upon two men more righteous and better than he was, and he proceeded to kill them with the sword, when my father David himself had not known of it, namely, Ab′ner the son of Ner the chief of the army of Israel and A·ma′sa the son of Je′ther the chief of the army of Judah. 33 And their blood must come back upon the head of Jo′ab and upon the head of his offspring to time indefinite; but for David and for his offspring and for his house and for his throne there will come to be peace to time indefinite from Jehovah.” 34 Then Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da went on up and fell upon him and put him to death; and he got to be buried at his own house in the wilderness. 35 Upon that the king put Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da in place of him over the army; and Za′dok the priest the king put in the place of A·bi′a·thar.

36 Finally the king sent and called Shim′e·i and said to him: “Build yourself a house in Jerusalem, and you must dwell there and not go out from there to this place and that. 37 And it must occur that on the day of your going out and when you do pass over the torrent valley of Kid′ron, you should unmistakably know that you will positively die. Bloodguilt for you will itself come to be upon your own head.” 38 At this Shim′e·i said to the king: “The word is good. Just as my lord the king has spoken is the way that your servant will do.” And Shim′e·i kept dwelling in Jerusalem many days.

39 And it came about at the end of three years that two slaves of Shim′e·i went running away to A′chish the son of Ma′a·cah the king of Gath; and people came telling Shim′e·i, saying: “Look! Your slaves are at Gath.” 40 Immediately Shim′e·i got up and saddled his ass and went to Gath to A′chish to look for his slaves; after which Shim′e·i went and brought his slaves from Gath. 41 Then Sol′o·mon was told: “Shim′e·i has gone out of Jerusalem to Gath and is back.” 42 At that the king sent and called Shim′e·i and said to him: “Did I not put you under oath by Jehovah that I might warn you, saying, ‘On the day of your going outside and when you do go here and there you should unmistakably know that you will positively die,’ and so did you not say to me, ‘Good is the word that I have heard’? 43 Why, then, did you not keep the oath of Jehovah and the commandment that I solemnly laid upon you?” 44 And the king went on to say to Shim′e·i: “You yourself certainly know all the injury which your heart well knows that you did to David my father; and Jehovah will certainly return the injury by you upon your own head. 45 But King Sol′o·mon will be blessed, and the throne of David itself will prove to be firmly established before Jehovah forever.” 46 With that the king commanded Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da, who then went out and fell upon him, so that he died.

And the kingdom was firmly established in the hand of Sol′o·mon.

1 Kings

3 And Sol′o·mon proceeded to form a marriage alliance with Phar′aoh the king of Egypt and to take Phar′aoh’s daughter and bring her to the City of David, until he finished building his own house and the house of Jehovah and Jerusalem’s wall all around. 2 Only the people were sacrificing on the high places, for a house had not been built to the name of Jehovah down to those days. 3 And Sol′o·mon continued to love Jehovah by walking in the statutes of David his father. Only it was on the high places that he was regularly sacrificing and making offerings smoke.

4 Accordingly the king went to Gib′e·on to sacrifice there, for that was the great high place. A thousand burnt sacrifices Sol′o·mon proceeded to offer upon that altar. 5 In Gib′e·on Jehovah appeared to Sol′o·mon in a dream by night; and God proceeded to say: “Request what I should give you.” 6 At this Sol′o·mon said: “You yourself have exercised great loving-kindness toward your servant David my father according as he walked before you in truth and in righteousness and in uprightness of heart with you; and you continued keeping toward him this great loving-kindness, so that you gave him a son to sit upon his throne as at this day. 7 And now, Jehovah my God, you yourself have made your servant king in the place of David my father, and I am but a little boy. I do not know how to go out and how to come in. 8 And your servant is in the middle of your people whom you have chosen, a multitudinous people that cannot be numbered or counted for multitude. 9 And you must give to your servant an obedient heart to judge your people, to discern between good and bad; for who is able to judge this difficult people of yours?”

10 And the thing was pleasing in the eyes of Jehovah, because Sol′o·mon had requested this thing. 11 And God went on to say to him: “For the reason that you have requested this thing and have not requested for yourself many days nor requested for yourself riches nor requested the soul of your enemies, and you have requested for yourself understanding to hear judicial cases, 12 look! I shall certainly do according to your words. Look! I shall certainly give you a wise and understanding heart, so that one like you there has not happened to be before you, and after you there will not rise up one like you. 13 And also what you have not requested I will give you, both riches and glory, so that there will not have happened to be any among the kings like you, all your days. 14 And if you will walk in my ways by keeping my regulations and my commandments, just as David your father walked, I will also lengthen your days.”

15 When Sol′o·mon awoke, why, here it had been a dream. Then he came to Jerusalem and stood before the ark of the covenant of Jehovah and offered up burnt sacrifices and rendered up communion offerings and spread a feast for all his servants.

16 At that time two women, prostitutes, got to come in to the king and stand before him. 17 Then the one woman said: “Excuse me, my lord, I and this woman are dwelling in one house, so that I gave birth close by her in the house. 18 And it came about on the third day after I gave birth, this woman also proceeded to give birth. And we were together. There was no stranger with us in the house, no one but the two of us in the house. 19 Later the son of this woman died at night, because she lay upon him. 20 So she got up in the middle of the night and took my son from beside me while your slave girl herself was asleep and laid him in her own bosom, and her dead son she laid in my bosom. 21 When I got up in the morning to nurse my son, why, there he was dead. So I examined him closely in the morning, and, look! he did not prove to be my son that I had borne.” 22 But the other woman said: “No, but my son is the living one and your son is the dead one!” All the while this woman was saying: “No, but your son is the dead one and my son is the living one.” And they kept on speaking before the king.

23 Finally the king said: “This one is saying, ‘This is my son, the living one, and your son is the dead one!’ and that one is saying, ‘No, but your son is the dead one and my son is the living one!’” 24 And the king went on to say: “YOU men, get me a sword.” So they brought the sword before the king. 25 And the king proceeded to say: “YOU men, sever the living child in two and give the one half to the one woman and the other half to the other.” 26 At once the woman whose son was the living one said to the king (for her inward emotions were excited toward her son, so that she said): “Excuse me, my lord! YOU men, give her the living child. Do not by any means put him to death.” All the while this other woman was saying: “Neither mine nor yours will he become. YOU men, do the severing!” 27 At that the king answered and said: “YOU men, give her the living child, and YOU must by no means put him to death. She is his mother.”

28 And all Israel got to hear of the judicial decision that the king had handed down; and they became fearful because of the king, for they saw that the wisdom of God was within him to execute judicial decision.

1 Kings

4 And King Sol′o·mon continued king over all Israel. 2 And these are the princes that he had: Az·a·ri′ah the son of Za′dok, the priest; 3 El·i·hor′eph and A·hi′jah, the sons of Shi′sha, secretaries; Je·hosh′a·phat the son of A·hi′lud, the recorder; 4 and Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da was over the army, and Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar were priests; 5 and Az·a·ri′ah the son of Nathan was over the deputies, and Za′bud the son of Nathan was a priest, the friend of the king; 6 and A·hi′shar was over the household, and Ad·o·ni′ram the son of Ab′da, over those conscripted for forced labor.

7 And Sol′o·mon had twelve deputies over all Israel, and they provided the king and his household with food. It would devolve upon each one to provide the food one month in the year. 8 And these were their names: The son of Hur, in the mountainous region of E′phra·im; 9 the son of De′ker, in Ma′kaz and in Sha·al′bim and Beth-she′mesh and E′lon-beth-ha′nan; 10 the son of He′sed, in A·rub′both (he had So′coh and all the land of He′pher); 11 the son of A·bin′a·dab, all the mountain ridge of Dor (Ta′phath, Sol′o·mon’s daughter, herself became his wife); 12 Ba′a·na the son of A·hi′lud, in Ta′a·nach and Me·gid′do and all Beth-she′an, which is beside Zar′e·than below Jez′re·el, from Beth-she′an to A′bel-me·ho′lah to the region of Jok′me·am; 13 the son of Ge′ber, in Ra′moth-gil′e·ad (he had the tent villages of Ja′ir the son of Ma·nas′seh, which are in Gil′e·ad; he had the region of Ar′gob, which is in Ba′shan: sixty large cities with wall and copper bar); 14 A·hin′a·dab the son of Id′do, in Ma·ha·na′im; 15 A·him′a·az, in Naph′ta·li (he, too, took Bas′e·math, Sol′o·mon’s daughter, as a wife); 16 Ba′a·na the son of Hu′shai, in Ash′er and Be·a′loth; 17 Je·hosh′a·phat the son of Pa·ru′ah, in Is′sa·char; 18 Shim′e·i the son of E′la, in Benjamin; 19 Ge′ber the son of U′ri, in the land of Gil′e·ad, the land of Si′hon the king of the Am′or·ites, and of Og the king of Ba′shan, and there was one deputy over all the other deputies that were in the land.

20 Judah and Israel were many, like the grains of sand that are by the sea for multitude, eating and drinking and rejoicing.

21 As for Sol′o·mon, he proved to be ruler over all the kingdoms from the River to the land of the Phi·lis′tines and to the boundary of Egypt. They were bringing gifts and serving Sol′o·mon all the days of his life.

22 And Sol′o·mon’s food for each day regularly proved to be thirty cor measures of fine flour and sixty cor measures of flour, 23 ten fat cattle and twenty pastured cattle and a hundred sheep, besides some stags and gazelles and roebucks and fattened cuckoos. 24 For he was holding in subjection everything this side of the River, from Tiph′sah to Ga′za, even all the kings this side of the River; and peace itself became his in every region of his, all around. 25 And Judah and Israel continued to dwell in security, everyone under his own vine and under his own fig tree, from Dan to Be′er-she′ba, all the days of Sol′o·mon.

26 And Sol′o·mon came to have forty thousand stalls of horses for his chariots and twelve thousand horsemen.

27 And these deputies supplied food to King Sol′o·mon and everyone approaching the table of King Sol′o·mon, each one in his month. They left nothing lacking. 28 And the barley and the straw for the horses and for the teams of horses they kept bringing to wherever the place might prove to be, each one according to his commission.

29 And God continued giving Sol′o·mon wisdom and understanding in very great measure and a broadness of heart, like the sand that is upon the seashore. 30 And Sol′o·mon’s wisdom was vaster than the wisdom of all the Orientals and than all the wisdom of Egypt. 31 And he was wiser than any other man, than E′than the Ez′ra·hite and He′man and Cal′col and Dar′da the sons of Ma′hol; and his fame came to be in all the nations all around. 32 And he could speak three thousand proverbs, and his songs came to be a thousand and five. 33 And he would speak about the trees, from the cedar that is in Leb′a·non to the hyssop that is coming forth on the wall; and he would speak about the beasts and about the flying creatures and about the moving things and about the fishes. 34 And they kept coming from all the peoples to hear Sol′o·mon’s wisdom, even from all the kings of the earth who had heard of his wisdom.

1 Kings

9 And it came about that, as soon as Sol′o·mon had finished building the house of Jehovah and the house of the king and every desirable thing of Sol′o·mon that he took delight in making, 2 then Jehovah appeared to Sol′o·mon the second time, the same as he had appeared to him in Gib′e·on. 3 And Jehovah went on to say to him: “I have heard your prayer and your request for favor with which you requested favor before me. I have sanctified this house that you have built by putting my name there to time indefinite; and my eyes and my heart will certainly prove to be there always. 4 And you, if you will walk before me, just as David your father walked, with integrity of heart and with uprightness by doing according to all that I have commanded you, and you will keep my regulations and my judicial decisions, 5 I also shall indeed establish the throne of your kingdom over Israel to time indefinite, just as I promised David your father, saying, ‘Not a man of yours will be cut off from sitting upon the throne of Israel.’ 6 If YOU yourselves and YOUR sons should definitely turn back from following me and not keep my commandments and my statutes that I have put before YOU men, and YOU actually go and serve other gods and bow down to them, 7 I will also cut Israel off from upon the surface of the ground that I have given to them; and the house that I have sanctified to my name I shall throw away from before me, and Israel will indeed become a proverbial saying and a taunt among all the peoples. 8 And this house itself will become heaps of ruins. Everyone passing by it will stare in amazement and will certainly whistle and say, ‘For what reason did Jehovah do like that to this land and this house?’ 9 And they will have to say, ‘For the reason that they left Jehovah their God who had brought their forefathers out from the land of Egypt, and they proceeded to take hold of other gods and bow down to them and serve them. That is why Jehovah brought upon them all this calamity.’”

10 And it came about at the end of twenty years, in which Sol′o·mon built the two houses, the house of Jehovah and the house of the king, 11 (Hi′ram the king of Tyre had himself assisted Sol′o·mon with timbers of cedar trees and timbers of juniper trees and with gold as much as he delighted in,) that at that time King Sol′o·mon proceeded to give to Hi′ram twenty cities in the land of Gal′i·lee. 12 Accordingly Hi′ram went out from Tyre to see the cities that Sol′o·mon had given him, and they were not just right in his eyes. 13 So he said: “What sort of cities are these that you have given me, my brother?” And they came to be called the Land of Ca′bul down to this day.

14 In the meantime Hi′ram sent to the king a hundred and twenty talents of gold.

15 Now this is the account of those conscripted for forced labor that King Sol′o·mon levied to build the house of Jehovah and his own house and the Mound and the wall of Jerusalem and Ha′zor and Me·gid′do and Ge′zer. 16 (Phar′aoh the king of Egypt himself had come up and then captured Ge′zer and burned it with fire, and the Ca′naan·ites dwelling in the city he had killed. So he gave it as a parting gift to his daughter, the wife of Sol′o·mon.) 17 And Sol′o·mon went on to build Ge′zer and Lower Beth-ho′ron, 18 and Ba′al·ath and Ta′mar in the wilderness, in the land, 19 and all the storage cities that became Sol′o·mon’s and the chariot cities and the cities for the horsemen, and the desirable things of Sol′o·mon that he had desired to build in Jerusalem and in Leb′a·non and in all the land of his dominion. 20 As for all the people remaining over from the Am′or·ites, the Hit′tites, the Per′iz·zites, the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites, who were no part of the sons of Israel, 21 their sons who had been left over after them in the land whom the sons of Israel had been unable to devote to destruction, Sol′o·mon kept levying them for slavish forced labor until this day. 22 And there were none of the sons of Israel that Sol′o·mon constituted slaves; for they were the warriors and his servants and his princes and his adjutants and chiefs of his charioteers and of his horsemen. 23 These were the chiefs of the deputies who were over the work of Sol′o·mon, five hundred and fifty, the foremen over the people who were active in the work.

24 However, Phar′aoh’s daughter herself came up out of the City of David to her own house that he had built for her. It was then that he built the Mound.

25 And Sol′o·mon continued three times in the year to offer up burnt sacrifices and communion sacrifices upon the altar that he had built for Jehovah, and there was a making of sacrificial smoke on the altar, which was before Jehovah; and he completed the house.

26 And there was a fleet of ships that King Sol′o·mon made in E′zi·on-ge′ber, which is by E′loth, upon the shore of the Red Sea in the land of E′dom. 27 And Hi′ram kept sending in the fleet of ships his own servants, seamen, having a knowledge of the sea, along with the servants of Sol′o·mon. 28 And they proceeded to go to O′phir and take from there four hundred and twenty talents of gold and bring it in to King Sol′o·mon.

1 Kings

11 And King Sol′o·mon himself loved many foreign wives along with the daughter of Phar′aoh, Mo′ab·ite, Am′mon·ite, E′dom·ite, Si·do′ni·an and Hit′tite women, 2 from the nations of whom Jehovah had said to the sons of Israel: “YOU must not go in among them, and they themselves should not come in among YOU; truly they will incline YOUR heart to follow their gods.” It was to them that Sol′o·mon clung to love them. 3 And he came to have seven hundred wives, princesses, and three hundred concubines; and his wives gradually inclined his heart. 4 And it came about in the time of Sol′o·mon’s growing old that his wives themselves had inclined his heart to follow other gods; and his heart did not prove to be complete with Jehovah his God like the heart of David his father. 5 And Sol′o·mon began going after Ash′to·reth the goddess of the Si·do′ni·ans and after Mil′com the disgusting thing of the Am′mon·ites. 6 And Sol′o·mon began to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and he did not follow Jehovah fully like David his father.

7 It was then that Sol′o·mon proceeded to build a high place to Che′mosh the disgusting thing of Mo′ab on the mountain that was in front of Jerusalem, and to Mo′lech the disgusting thing of the sons of Am′mon. 8 And that was the way he did for all his foreign wives who were making sacrificial smoke and sacrificing to their gods.

9 And Jehovah came to be incensed at Sol′o·mon, because his heart had inclined away from Jehovah the God of Israel, the one appearing to him twice. 10 And respecting this thing he commanded him not to go after other gods; but he had not kept that which Jehovah had commanded. 11 Jehovah now said to Sol′o·mon: “For the reason that this has taken place with you and you have not kept my covenant and my statutes that I laid in command upon you, I shall without fail rip the kingdom away from off you, and I shall certainly give it to your servant. 12 However, in your days I shall not do it, for the sake of David your father. Out of the hand of your son I shall rip it away. 13 Only it will not be all the kingdom that I shall rip away. One tribe I shall give to your son, for the sake of David my servant and for the sake of Jerusalem which I have chosen.”

14 And Jehovah began to raise up a resister to Sol′o·mon, namely, Ha′dad the E′dom·ite of the offspring of the king. He was in E′dom. 15 And it came about when David struck down E′dom, when Jo′ab the chief of the army came up to bury those slain, that he tried to strike down every male in E′dom. 16 (For it was six months that Jo′ab and all Israel dwelt there until he had cut off every male in E′dom.) 17 And Ha′dad went running away, he and some E′dom·ite men of the servants of his father with him, to come into Egypt, while Ha′dad was a young boy. 18 So they rose up out of Mid′i·an and came into Pa′ran and took men with them from Pa′ran and came into Egypt to Phar′aoh the king of Egypt, who then gave him a house. Also, bread he assigned to him, and land he gave him. 19 And Ha′dad continued to find favor in the eyes of Phar′aoh, so much that he gave him a wife, the sister of his own wife, the sister of Tah′pe·nes the lady. 20 In time the sister of Tah′pe·nes bore him Ge·nu′bath his son, and Tah′pe·nes got to wean him right inside the house of Phar′aoh; and Ge·nu′bath continued at the house of Phar′aoh right among the sons of Phar′aoh.

21 And Ha′dad himself heard in Egypt that David had lain down with his forefathers and that Jo′ab the chief of the army had died. So Ha′dad said to Phar′aoh: “Send me away, that I may go to my own land.” 22 But Phar′aoh said to him: “What are you in need of while with me that here you are seeking to go to your own land?” To this he said: “Nothing; but you ought to send me away without fail.”

23 And God proceeded to raise up to him another resister, namely, Re′zon the son of E·li′a·da, who had run away from Had·ad·e′zer the king of Zo′bah his lord. 24 And he kept collecting men to his side and came to be chief of a marauder band, when David killed them. So they went to Damascus and took up dwelling in it and began reigning in Damascus. 25 And he came to be a resister of Israel all the days of Sol′o·mon, and that along with the injury that Ha′dad did; and he had an abhorrence of Israel while he continued reigning over Syria.

26 And there was Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat an E′phra·im·ite from Zer′e·dah, a servant of Sol′o·mon, and his mother’s name was Ze·ru′ah, a widowed woman. He too began to lift up his hand against the king. 27 And this is the reason why he lifted up his hand against the king: Sol′o·mon himself had built the Mound. He had closed up the gap of the City of David his father. 28 Now the man Jer·o·bo′am was a valiant, mighty man. When Sol′o·mon got to see that the young man was a hard worker, he proceeded to make him overseer over all the compulsory service of the house of Joseph. 29 And it came about at that particular time that Jer·o·bo′am himself went out from Jerusalem, and A·hi′jah the Shi′lo·nite the prophet got to find him on the road, and A·hi′jah was covering himself with a new garment; and the two of them were by themselves in the field. 30 A·hi′jah now took hold of the new garment that was on him and ripped it into twelve pieces. 31 And he went on to say to Jer·o·bo′am:

“Take for yourself ten pieces; for this is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘Here I am ripping the kingdom out of the hand of Sol′o·mon, and I shall certainly give you ten tribes. 32 And the one tribe is what will continue his for the sake of my servant David and for the sake of Jerusalem, the city that I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel. 33 The reason why is that they have left me and begun to bow down to Ash′to·reth the goddess of the Si·do′ni·ans, to Che′mosh the god of Mo′ab and to Mil′com the god of the sons of Am′mon; and they have not walked in my ways by doing what is right in my eyes and my statutes and my judicial decisions like David his father. 34 But I shall not take the entire kingdom out of his hand, because a chieftain I shall set him for all the days of his life, for the sake of David my servant whom I chose, because he kept my commandments and my statutes. 35 And I shall certainly take the kingship out of the hand of his son and give it to you, even ten tribes. 36 And to his son I shall give one tribe, in order that David my servant may continue having a lamp always before me in Jerusalem, the city that I have chosen for myself to put my name there. 37 And you are the one that I shall take, and you will indeed reign over all that your soul craves, and you will certainly become king over Israel. 38 And it must occur that, if you obey all that I shall command you, and you do walk in my ways and actually do what is right in my eyes by keeping my statutes and my commandments, just as David my servant did, I will also prove to be with you, and I will build you a lasting house, just as I have built for David, and I will give you Israel. 39 And I shall humiliate the offspring of David on account of this, only not always.’”

40 And Sol′o·mon began seeking to put Jer·o·bo′am to death. So Jer·o·bo′am got up and went running off to Egypt to Shi′shak the king of Egypt, and he continued in Egypt until Sol′o·mon’s death.

41 As for the rest of the affairs of Sol′o·mon and all that he did and his wisdom, are they not written in the book of the affairs of Sol′o·mon? 42 And the days that Sol′o·mon had reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel were forty years. 43 Then Sol′o·mon lay down with his forefathers, and was buried in the City of David his father; and Re·ho·bo′am his son began to reign in place of him.

1 Kings

13 And here there was a man of God that had come out of Judah by the word of Jehovah to Beth′el, while Jer·o·bo′am was standing by the altar to make sacrificial smoke. 2 Then he called out against the altar by the word of Jehovah and said: “O altar, altar, this is what Jehovah has said, ‘Look! A son born to the house of David, whose name is Jo·si′ah! And he will certainly sacrifice upon you the priests of the high places that are making sacrificial smoke upon you, and men’s bones he will burn upon you.’” 3 And he gave a portent on that day, saying: “This is the portent of which Jehovah has spoken: Look! The altar is ripped apart, and the fatty ashes that are upon it will certainly be spilled out.”

4 And it came about that, as soon as the king heard the word of the man of the true God that he had called out against the altar in Beth′el, Jer·o·bo′am at once thrust out his hand from off the altar, saying: “YOU men, grab hold of him!” Immediately his hand that he had thrust out against him became dried up, and he was not able to draw it back to himself. 5 And the altar itself was ripped apart so that the fatty ashes were spilled out from the altar, according to the portent that the man of the true God had given by the word of Jehovah.

6 The king now answered and said to the man of the true God: “Soften, please, the face of Jehovah your God and pray in my behalf that my hand may be restored to me.” At this the man of the true God softened the face of Jehovah, so that the king’s hand was restored to him, and it came to be as at first. 7 And the king went on to say to the man of the true God: “Do come with me to the house and take sustenance, and let me give you a gift.” 8 But the man of the true God said to the king: “If you gave me half of your house I would not come with you and eat bread or drink water in this place. 9 For that is the way he commanded me by the word of Jehovah, saying, ‘You must not eat bread or drink water, and you must not return by the way that you went.’” 10 And he began to go by another way, and he did not return by the way by which he had come to Beth′el.

11 And a certain old prophet was dwelling in Beth′el, and his sons now came in and related to him all the work that the man of the true God had done that day in Beth′el and the words that he had spoken to the king, and they went on relating them to their father. 12 Then their father spoke to them: “Which way, then, did he go?” So his sons showed him the way that the man of the true God that had come out of Judah had gone. 13 He now said to his sons: “Saddle the ass for me.” Accordingly they saddled the ass for him, and he went riding on it.

14 And he went following the man of the true God and got to find him sitting under the big tree. Then he said to him: “Are you the man of the true God who has come out of Judah?” to which he said: “I am.” 15 And he went on to say to him: “Go with me to the house and eat bread.” 16 But he said: “I am not able to go back with you or to come in with you, and I may not eat bread or drink water with you in this place. 17 For it has been spoken to me by the word of Jehovah, ‘You must not eat bread or drink water there. You must not go back again by the way by which you went.’” 18 At this he said to him: “I too am a prophet like you, and an angel himself spoke to me by the word of Jehovah, saying, ‘Have him come back with you to your house that he may eat bread and drink water.’” (He deceived him.) 19 So he went back with him that he might eat bread in his house and drink water.

20 And it came about, while they were sitting at the table, that the word of Jehovah came to the prophet that had brought him back; 21 and he began to call out to the man of the true God that had come out of Judah, saying: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that you rebelled against the order of Jehovah and did not keep the commandment with which Jehovah your God commanded you, 22 but you went back that you might eat bread and drink water in the place about which he spoke to you: “Do not eat bread or drink water,” your dead body will not come into the burial place of your forefathers.’”

23 And it came about after his eating bread and after his drinking that he at once saddled for him the ass, that is, for the prophet whom he had brought back. 24 And he got on his way. Later a lion found him on the road and put him to death, and his dead body came to be thrown onto the road. And the ass was standing beside it, and the lion was standing beside the dead body. 25 And here there were men passing by, so that they got to see the dead body thrown onto the road and the lion standing beside the dead body. Then they came in and spoke of it in the city in which the old prophet was dwelling.

26 When the prophet that had brought him back from the way heard of it, he immediately said: “It is the man of the true God that rebelled against the order of Jehovah; and so Jehovah gave him to the lion, that he might crush him and put him to death, according to the word of Jehovah that he spoke to him.” 27 And he went on to speak to his sons, saying: “Saddle the ass for me.” So they saddled it. 28 Then he got on his way and found the dead body of him thrown onto the road with the ass and the lion standing beside the dead body. The lion had not eaten the dead body, nor had it crushed the ass. 29 And the prophet proceeded to lift up the dead body of the man of the true God and to deposit him upon the ass and to bring him back. Thus he came into the city of the old prophet to bewail and bury him. 30 Accordingly he deposited his dead body in his own burial place; and they kept wailing over him: “Too bad, my brother!” 31 And it came about after his burying him that he went on to say to his sons: “When I die YOU must bury me in the burial place in which the man of the true God is buried. Beside his bones deposit my own bones. 32 For without fail the word that he called out by the word of Jehovah against the altar that is in Beth′el and against all the houses of the high places that are in the cities of Sa·mar′i·a will take place.”

33 After this thing Jer·o·bo′am did not turn back from his bad way, but he again went making priests of high places from the people in general. As for anyone delighting in it, he would fill his hand with power, saying: “And let him become one of the priests of high places.” 34 And in this thing there came to be a cause of sin on the part of the household of Jer·o·bo′am and an occasion for effacing them and annihilating them off the surface of the ground.

1 Kings

17 And E·li′jah the Tish′bite from the inhabitants of Gil′e·ad proceeded to say to A′hab: “As Jehovah the God of Israel before whom I do stand is living, there will occur during these years neither dew nor rain, except at the order of my word!”

2 The word of Jehovah now came to him, saying: 3 “Go away from here, and you must turn your way eastward and conceal yourself at the torrent valley of Che′rith that is east of the Jordan. 4 And it must occur that from the torrent valley you should drink, and the ravens I shall certainly command to supply you food there.” 5 Immediately he went and did according to the word of Jehovah, and so went and took up dwelling by the torrent valley of Che′rith that is east of the Jordan. 6 And the ravens themselves were bringing him bread and meat in the morning and bread and meat in the evening, and from the torrent valley he kept drinking. 7 But it came about at the end of some days that the torrent valley became dry, because there had occurred no downpour upon the earth.

8 The word of Jehovah now came to him, saying: 9 “Rise up, go to Zar′e·phath, which belongs to Si′don, and you must dwell there. Look! I shall certainly command there a woman, a widow, to supply you food.” 10 Accordingly he rose up and went to Zar′e·phath and came into the entrance of the city; and, look! a woman, a widow, was there gathering up pieces of wood. So he called to her and said: “Please, get me a sip of water in a vessel that I may drink.” 11 When she began to go and get it, he went on to call to her and say: “Please, get me a bit of bread in your hand.” 12 At this she said: “As Jehovah your God is living, I have no round cake, but a handful of flour in the large jar and a little oil in the small jar; and here I am gathering up a few pieces of wood, and I must go in and make something for myself and my son, and we shall have to eat it and die.”

13 Then E·li′jah said to her: “Do not be afraid. Go in, do according to your word. Only from what is there make me a small round cake first, and you must bring it out to me, and for yourself and your son you can make something afterward. 14 For this is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘The large jar of flour itself will not get exhausted, and the small jar of oil itself will not fail until the day of Jehovah’s giving a downpour upon the surface of the ground.’” 15 So she went and did according to E·li′jah’s word; and she continued to eat, she together with him and her household, for days. 16 The large jar of flour itself did not get exhausted, and the small jar of oil itself did not fail, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken by means of E·li′jah.

17 And it came about after these things that the son of the woman, the mistress of the house, fell sick, and his sickness came to be so severe that there was no breath left in him. 18 At this she said to E·li′jah: “What do I have to do with you, O man of the true God? You have come to me to bring my error to mind and to put my son to death.” 19 But he said to her: “Give me your son.” Then he took him from her bosom and carried him up to the roof chamber, where he was dwelling, and laid him upon his own couch. 20 And he began calling to Jehovah and saying: “O Jehovah my God, is it also upon the widow with whom I am residing as an alien that you must bring injury by putting her son to death?” 21 And he proceeded to stretch himself upon the child three times and call to Jehovah and say: “O Jehovah my God, please, cause the soul of this child to come back within him.” 22 Finally Jehovah listened to E·li′jah’s voice, so that the soul of the child came back within him and he came to life. 23 E·li′jah now took the child and brought him down from the roof chamber into the house and gave him to his mother; and E·li′jah then said: “See, your son is alive.” 24 Upon that the woman said to E·li′jah: “Now, indeed, I do know that you are a man of God and that Jehovah’s word in your mouth is true.”

1 Kings

19 Then A′hab told Jez′e·bel all that E·li′jah had done and all about how he had killed all the prophets with the sword. 2 At that Jez′e·bel sent a messenger to E·li′jah, saying: “So may the gods do, and so may they add to it, if at this time tomorrow I shall not make your soul like the soul of each one of them!” 3 And he became afraid. Consequently he rose up and began to go for his soul and came to Be′er-she′ba, which belongs to Judah. Then he left his attendant behind there. 4 And he himself went into the wilderness a day’s journey, and at length came and sat down under a certain broom tree. And he began to ask that his soul might die and to say: “It is enough! Now, O Jehovah, take my soul away, for I am no better than my forefathers.”

5 Finally he lay down and fell asleep under the broom tree. But, look! now an angel was touching him. Then he said to him: “Rise up, eat.” 6 When he looked, why, there at his head was a round cake upon heated stones and a jug of water. And he began to eat and drink, after which he lay down again. 7 Later the angel of Jehovah came back a second time and touched him and said: “Rise up, eat, for the journey is too much for you.” 8 So he rose up and ate and drank, and he kept going in the power of that nourishment for forty days and forty nights as far as the mountain of the true God, Ho′reb.

9 There he finally entered into a cave, that he might spend the night there; and, look! there was Jehovah’s word for him, and it went on to say to him: “What is your business here, E·li′jah?” 10 To this he said: “I have been absolutely jealous for Jehovah the God of armies; for the sons of Israel have left your covenant, your altars they have torn down, and your prophets they have killed with the sword, so that I only am left; and they begin looking for my soul to take it away.” 11 But it said: “Go out, and you must stand on the mountain before Jehovah.” And, look! Jehovah was passing by, and a great and strong wind was rending mountains and breaking crags before Jehovah. (Jehovah was not in the wind.) And after the wind there was a quaking. (Jehovah was not in the quaking.) 12 And after the quaking there was a fire. (Jehovah was not in the fire.) And after the fire there was a calm, low voice. 13 And it came about that as soon as E·li′jah heard it, he immediately wrapped his face in his official garment and went out and stood at the entrance of the cave; and, look! there was a voice for him, and it proceeded to say to him: “What is your business here, E·li′jah?” 14 To this he said: “I have been absolutely jealous for Jehovah the God of armies; for the sons of Israel have left your covenant, your altars they have torn down, and your prophets they have killed with the sword, so that I only am left; and they begin looking for my soul to take it away.”

15 Jehovah now said to him: “Go, return on your way to the wilderness of Damascus; and you must come in and anoint Haz′a·el as king over Syria. 16 And Je′hu the grandson of Nim′shi you should anoint as king over Israel; and E·li′sha the son of Sha′phat from A′bel-me·ho′lah you should anoint as prophet in place of you. 17 And it must occur that the one escaping from Haz′a·el’s sword, Je′hu will put to death; and the one escaping from Je′hu’s sword, E·li′sha will put to death. 18 And I have let seven thousand remain in Israel, all the knees that have not bent down to Ba′al, and every mouth that has not kissed him.”

19 Accordingly he went from there and found E·li′sha the son of Sha′phat while he was plowing with twelve spans before him, and he with the twelfth. So E·li′jah crossed over to him and threw his official garment upon him. 20 At that he left the bulls and went running after E·li′jah and said: “Let me, please, kiss my father and my mother. Then I will go following you.” At this he said to him: “Go, return; for what have I done to you?” 21 So he returned from following him and then took a span of the bulls and sacrificed them, and with the implements of the bulls he boiled their flesh and then gave it to the people, and they proceeded to eat. After that he rose up and went following E·li′jah and began to minister to him.

2 Kings

2 And it came about that when Jehovah was to take E·li′jah in a windstorm up to the heavens, E·li′jah and E·li′sha proceeded to go from Gil′gal. 2 And E·li′jah began to say to E·li′sha: “Sit here, please, because Jehovah himself has sent me clear to Beth′el.” But E·li′sha said: “As Jehovah is living and as your soul is living, I will not leave you.” So they went down to Beth′el. 3 Then the sons of the prophets that were at Beth′el came out to E·li′sha and said to him: “Do you really know that today Jehovah is taking your master from headship over you?” At this he said: “I, too, well know it. BE silent.”

4 E·li′jah now said to him: “E·li′sha, sit here, please, because Jehovah himself has sent me to Jer′i·cho.” But he said: “As Jehovah is living and as your soul is living, I will not leave you.” So they came on to Jer′i·cho. 5 Then the sons of the prophets that were at Jer′i·cho approached E·li′sha and said to him: “Do you really know that today Jehovah is taking your master from headship over you?” At this he said: “I, too, well know it. BE silent.”

6 E·li′jah now said to him: “Sit here, please, because Jehovah himself has sent me to the Jordan.” But he said: “As Jehovah is living and as your soul is living, I will not leave you.” So both of them went on. 7 And there were fifty men of the sons of the prophets that went and kept standing in view at a distance; but, as for both of them, they stood by the Jordan. 8 Then E·li′jah took his official garment and wrapped it up and struck the waters, and gradually they were divided this way and that way, so that both of them went across on the dry ground.

9 And it came about that as soon as they had gone across E·li′jah himself said to E·li′sha: “Ask what I should do for you before I am taken from you.” To this E·li′sha said: “Please, that two parts in your spirit may come to me.” 10 At that he said: “You have asked a difficult thing. If you see me when taken from you, it will happen to you that way; but if you do not, it will not happen.”

11 And it came about that as they were walking along, speaking as they walked, why, look! a fiery war chariot and fiery horses, and they proceeded to make a separation between them both; and E·li′jah went ascending in the windstorm to the heavens. 12 All the while E·li′sha was seeing it, and he was crying out: “My father, my father, the war chariot of Israel and his horsemen!” And he did not see him anymore. Consequently he took hold of his own garments and ripped them into two pieces. 13 After that he picked up the official garment of E·li′jah that had fallen off him, and went back and stood by the shore of the Jordan. 14 Then he took the official garment of E·li′jah that had fallen off him and struck the waters and said: “Where is Jehovah the God of E·li′jah, even He?” When he struck the waters, then they were gradually divided this way and that way, so that E·li′sha went across.

15 When the sons of the prophets that were at Jer′i·cho saw him some way off, they began to say: “The spirit of E·li′jah has settled down upon E·li′sha.” Accordingly they came to meet him and bowed down to him to the earth. 16 And they went on to say to him: “Here, now, there are with your servants fifty men, valiant persons. Let them go, please, and look for your master. It may be that the spirit of Jehovah has lifted him up and then thrown him upon one of the mountains or in one of the valleys.” But he said: “YOU must not send them.” 17 And they kept urging him until he was embarrassed, so that he said: “Send.” They now sent fifty men; and they kept looking for three days, but they did not find him. 18 When they returned to him, he was dwelling in Jer′i·cho. Then he said to them: “Did I not say to YOU, ‘Do not go’?”

19 In time the men of the city said to E·li′sha: “Here, now, the situation of the city is good, just as my master is seeing; but the water is bad, and the land is causing miscarriages.” 20 At that he said: “Fetch me a small new bowl and put salt in it.” So they fetched it for him. 21 Then he went on out to the source of the water and threw salt in it and said: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘I do make this water healthful. No more will death or any causing of miscarriages result from it.’” 22 And the water continues healed down to this day, according to E·li′sha’s word that he spoke.

23 And he proceeded to go up from there to Beth′el. As he was going up on the way, there were small boys that came out from the city and began to jeer him and that kept saying to him: “Go up, you baldhead! Go up, you baldhead!” 24 Finally he turned behind him and saw them and called down evil upon them in the name of Jehovah. Then two she-bears came out from the woods and went tearing to pieces forty-two children of their number. 25 And he kept going from there to Mount Car′mel, and from there he returned to Sa·mar′i·a.

2 Kings

3 As for Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab, he became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a in the eighteenth year of Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah, and he continued to reign for twelve years. 2 And he kept on doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, only not like his father or like his mother, but he removed the sacred pillar of Ba′al that his father had made. 3 Only he stuck to the sins of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, with which he caused Israel to sin. He did not depart from them.

4 As regards Me′sha the king of Mo′ab, he became a sheep raiser, and he paid to the king of Israel a hundred thousand lambs and a hundred thousand unshorn male sheep. 5 And it came about that as soon as A′hab died, the king of Mo′ab began to revolt against the king of Israel. 6 Consequently King Je·ho′ram went out on that day from Sa·mar′i·a and mustered all Israel. 7 He went farther and now sent to Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah, saying: “The king of Mo′ab himself has revolted against me. Will you go with me to Mo′ab in war?” To this he said: “I shall go. I am the same as you are; my people are the same as your people; my horses are the same as your horses.” 8 And he went on to say: “By which particular way shall we go up?” So he said: “By the way of the wilderness of E′dom.”

9 And the king of Israel and the king of Judah and the king of E′dom proceeded to go, and they kept going their way around for seven days, and there proved to be no water for the camp and for the domestic animals that were following their steps. 10 At length the king of Israel said: “How unfortunate that Jehovah has called these three kings to give them into the hand of Mo′ab!” 11 At that Je·hosh′a·phat said: “Is there not here a prophet of Jehovah? Then let us inquire of Jehovah through him.” So one of the servants of the king of Israel answered and said: “There is here E·li′sha the son of Sha′phat, who poured out water upon the hands of E·li′jah.” 12 Then Je·hosh′a·phat said: “The word of Jehovah exists with him.” Accordingly the king of Israel and Je·hosh′a·phat and the king of E′dom went down to him.

13 And E·li′sha proceeded to say to the king of Israel: “What do I have to do with you? Go to the prophets of your father and to the prophets of your mother.” But the king of Israel said to him: “No, for Jehovah has called these three kings to give them into the hand of Mo′ab.” 14 To this E·li′sha said: “As Jehovah of armies before whom I do stand is living, if it were not that it is the face of Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah for which I am having consideration, I would not look at you or see you. 15 And now YOU men fetch me a string-instrument player.” And it occurred that, as soon as the string-instrument player played, the hand of Jehovah came to be upon him. 16 And he went on to say: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Let there be a making of this torrent valley full of ditches; 17 for this is what Jehovah has said: “YOU men will not see a wind, and YOU will not see a downpour; yet that torrent valley will be filled with water, and YOU men will certainly drink from it, YOU and YOUR livestock and YOUR domestic animals.”’ 18 And this will indeed be a trivial thing in the eyes of Jehovah, and he will certainly give Mo′ab into YOUR hand. 19 And YOU must strike down every fortified city and every choice city, and every good tree YOU should fell, and all the springs of water YOU should stop up, and every good tract of land YOU should mar with stones.”

20 And it came about in the morning, at the time of the going up of the grain offering, that, look! water was coming from the direction of E′dom, and the land came to be filled with the water.

21 As regards all the Mo′ab·ites, they heard that the kings had come up to fight against them. Consequently they called together men from as many as were girding on a belt and upward, and they began standing at the boundary. 22 When they got up early in the morning, the sun itself flashed upon the water, so that the Mo′ab·ites from the opposite side saw the water red like blood. 23 And they began to say: “This is blood! The kings have unquestionably been put to the sword, and they went striking one another down. So now, to the spoil, O Mo′ab!” 24 When they came into the camp of Israel, the Israelites immediately rose up and began striking the Mo′ab·ites down so that they took to flight from before them. Hence they came into Mo′ab, striking the Mo′ab·ites down as they came. 25 And the cities they went throwing down, and, as for every good tract of land, they would pitch each one his stone and actually fill it; and every spring of water they would stop up, and every good tree they would fell, until they left only the stones of Kir-har′e·seth remaining in it; and the slingers began going around it and striking it down.

26 When the king of Mo′ab saw that the battle had proved too strong for him, he at once took with him seven hundred men drawing sword to break through to the king of E′dom; but they were not able to. 27 Finally he took his firstborn son who was going to reign in place of him and offered him up as a burnt sacrifice upon the wall. And there came to be great indignation against Israel, so that they pulled away from against him and returned to their land.

2 Kings

4 Now there was a certain woman of the wives of the sons of the prophets that cried out to E·li′sha, saying: “Your servant, my husband, is dead; and you yourself well know that your own servant had continually feared Jehovah, and the creditor himself has come to take both my children for his slaves.” 2 At this E·li′sha said to her: “What shall I do for you? Tell me; what do you have in the house?” To this she said: “Your maidservant has nothing at all in the house but a spouted jar of oil.” 3 Then he said: “Go, ask for vessels for yourself from outside, from all your neighbors, empty vessels. Do not hold yourself to a few. 4 And you must go and close the door behind yourself and your sons, and you must pour out into all these vessels, and the full ones you should set aside.” 5 Upon that she went away from him.

When she closed the door behind herself and her sons, they were bringing the vessels near to her, and she was doing the pouring out. 6 And it came about that as soon as the vessels were full she went on to say to her son: “Do bring still another vessel near to me.” But he said to her: “There is no other vessel.” At that the oil stopped. 7 So she came in and told the man of the true God, and he now said: “Go, sell the oil and pay off your debts, and you and your sons should live from what is left.”

8 And it came about one day that E·li′sha went passing along to Shu′nem, where there was a prominent woman, and she began to constrain him to eat bread. And it came about that as often as he would pass by, he would turn aside there to eat bread. 9 At length she said to her husband: “Here, now, I well know that it is a holy man of God that is passing by us constantly. 10 Please, let us make a little roof chamber on the wall and put there for him a couch and a table and a chair and a lampstand; and it must occur that whenever he comes in to us he can turn aside there.”

11 And it came about one day that as usual he came in there and turned aside to the roof chamber and lay down there. 12 So he said to Ge·ha′zi his attendant: “Call this Shu′nam·mite woman.” At that he called her that she might stand before him. 13 Then he said to him: “Please, say to her, ‘Here you have restricted yourself for us with all this restriction. What is there to be done for you? Is there anything to speak to the king or to the chief of the army for you?’” To this she said: “In among my own people I am dwelling.” 14 And he went on to say: “What, then, is there to be done for her?” Ge·ha′zi now said: “For a fact, a son she does not have, and her husband is old.” 15 Immediately he said: “Call her.” So he called her, and she kept standing at the entrance. 16 Then he said: “At this appointed time next year you will be embracing a son.” But she said: “No, my master, O man of the true God! Do not tell lies in connection with your maidservant.”

17 However, the woman became pregnant and gave birth to a son at this appointed time the next year, just as E·li′sha had spoken to her. 18 And the child kept on growing up, and it came about one day that he went out as usual to his father with the reapers. 19 And he kept saying to his father: “My head, O my head!” At last he said to the attendant: “Carry him to his mother.” 20 Accordingly he carried him and brought him to his mother. And he kept sitting upon her knees until noon, and gradually he died. 21 Then she went up and laid him upon the couch of the man of the true God and closed the door upon him and went out. 22 She now called her husband and said: “Do send me, please, one of the attendants and one of the she-asses, and let me run as far as the man of the true God and return.” 23 But he said: “Why are you going to him today? It is not a new moon nor a sabbath.” However, she said: “It is all right.” 24 So she saddled up the she-ass and said to her attendant: “Drive and go ahead. Do not hold back for my sake from riding unless I shall have said so to you.”

25 And she proceeded to go and come to the man of the true God at Mount Car′mel. And it came about that, as soon as the man of the true God saw her out ahead, he immediately said to Ge·ha′zi his attendant: “Look! The Shu′nam·mite woman over there. 26 Now run, please, to meet her and say to her, ‘Is it all right with you? Is it all right with your husband? Is it all right with the child?’” To this she said: “It is all right.” 27 When she came to the man of the true God at the mountain, she at once took hold of him by his feet. At this Ge·ha′zi came near to push her away, but the man of the true God said: “Let her alone, for her soul is bitter within her; and Jehovah himself has hidden it from me and not told me.” 28 She now said: “Did I ask for a son through my lord? Did I not say, ‘You must not lead me to a false hope’?”

29 Immediately he said to Ge·ha′zi: “Gird up your loins and take my staff in your hand and go. In case you encounter anyone, you must not greet him; and in case anyone should greet you, you must not answer him. And you must place my staff upon the face of the boy.” 30 At this the mother of the boy said: “As Jehovah is living and as your soul is living, I will not leave you.” Therefore he got up and went with her. 31 And Ge·ha′zi himself passed along before them and then put the staff upon the boy’s face, but there was no voice nor paying of attention. So he went back to meet him and told him, saying: “The boy did not wake up.”

32 At last E·li′sha came into the house, and there the boy was dead, being laid upon his couch. 33 Then he came in and closed the door behind them both and began to pray to Jehovah. 34 Finally he went up and lay down upon the child and put his own mouth upon his mouth and his own eyes upon his eyes and his own palms upon his palms and kept bent over him, and gradually the child’s flesh grew warm. 35 Then he began walking again in the house, once this way and once that way, after which he went up and bent over him. And the boy began to sneeze as many as seven times, after which the boy opened his eyes. 36 He now called Ge·ha′zi and said: “Call this Shu′nam·mite woman.” So he called her and she came in to him. Then he said: “Lift up your son.” 37 And she proceeded to come in and fall at his feet and bow down to him to the earth, after which she lifted up her son and went out.

38 And E·li′sha himself returned to Gil′gal, and there was famine in the land. As the sons of the prophets were sitting before him, he in time said to his attendant: “Put the large cooking pot on and boil stew for the sons of the prophets.” 39 Accordingly a certain one went out to the field to pick mallows, and he got to find a wild vine and went picking wild gourds from it, his garment full, and then came and sliced them into the stewpot, for they were not acquainted with them. 40 Later they poured it out for the men to eat. And it came about that, as soon as they ate from the stew, they themselves cried out and began saying: “There is death in the pot, O man of the true God.” And they were not able to eat. 41 So he said: “FETCH, then, flour.” After he threw it into the pot, he went on to say: “Pour out for the people that they may eat.” And nothing injurious proved to be in the pot.

42 And there was a man that came from Ba′al-shal′i·shah, and he came bringing to the man of the true God bread of the first ripe fruits, twenty barley loaves, and new grain in his bread bag. Then he said: “Give it to the people that they may eat.” 43 However, his waiter said: “How shall I put this before a hundred men?” To this he said: “Give it to the people that they may eat, for this is what Jehovah has said, ‘There will be an eating and a having of leftovers.’” 44 At that he put it before them, and they began to eat, and they had leftovers according to the word of Jehovah.

2 Kings

7 E·li′sha now said: “Listen, YOU men, to the word of Jehovah. This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Tomorrow about this time a seah measure of fine flour will be worth a shekel, and two seah measures of barley worth a shekel in the gateway of Sa·mar′i·a.’” 2 At that the adjutant upon whose hand the king was supporting himself answered the man of the true God and said: “If Jehovah were making floodgates in the heavens, could this thing take place?” To this he said: “Here you are seeing it with your own eyes, but from it you will not eat.”

3 And there were four men, lepers, that happened to be at the entrance of the gate; and they began to say the one to the other: “Why are we sitting here until we have died? 4 If we had said, ‘Let us enter the city,’ when the famine is in the city, we would also have to die there. And if we do sit here, we shall also have to die. So now come and let us invade the camp of the Syrians. If they preserve us alive, we shall live; but if they put us to death, then we shall have to die.” 5 Accordingly they rose up in the evening darkness to enter the camp of the Syrians; and they got to come as far as the outskirts of the camp of the Syrians, and, look! nobody was there.

6 And Jehovah himself had caused the camp of the Syrians to hear the sound of war chariots, the sound of horses, the sound of a great military force, so that they said to one another: “Look! The king of Israel has hired against us the kings of the Hit′tites and the kings of Egypt to come against us!” 7 Immediately they got up and went fleeing in the evening darkness and leaving their tents and their horses and their asses—the camp just as it was—and they kept fleeing for their soul.

8 When these lepers came as far as the outskirts of the camp, they then entered into one tent and began to eat and drink and carry from there silver and gold and garments and go off and stick them away. After that they returned and entered into another tent and carried things from there and went off and stuck them away.

9 Finally they began to say the one to the other: “It is not right what we are doing. This day is a day of good news! If we are hesitating, and we actually wait until the morning light, guilt must also catch up with us. So now come and let us enter and make report at the king’s house.” 10 So they came and called to the gatekeepers of the city and reported to them, saying: “We came into the camp of the Syrians, and, look! there was nobody there nor sound of a man, but only the horses tied and the asses tied and the tents just as they were.” 11 At once the gatekeepers called out and they reported to the king’s house inside.

12 Immediately the king rose up by night and said to his servants: “Let me tell YOU, please, what the Syrians have done to us. They well know that we are hungry; and so they went out from the camp to hide themselves in the field, saying, ‘They will come out from the city, and we shall catch them alive, and into the city we shall enter.’” 13 Then one of his servants answered and said: “Let them take, please, five of the remaining horses that have remained in the city. Look! They are the same as all the crowd of Israel that have remained in it. Look! They are the same as all the crowd of Israel that have perished. And let us send out and see.” 14 Accordingly they took two chariots with horses and the king sent them out after the camp of the Syrians, saying: “Go and see.” 15 At that they went following them as far as the Jordan; and, look! all the way was full of garments and utensils that the Syrians had thrown away as they were hurrying away. Then the messengers returned and reported to the king.

16 And the people proceeded to go out and plunder the camp of the Syrians; and so a seah measure of fine flour came to be worth a shekel, and two seah measures of barley worth a shekel, according to the word of Jehovah. 17 And the king himself had appointed the adjutant upon whose hand he was supporting himself to have charge of the gateway; and the people kept trampling him in the gateway, so that he died, just as the man of the true God had spoken, when he spoke at the time that the king came down to him. 18 Thus it came about just as the man of the true God had spoken to the king, saying: “Two seah measures of barley worth a shekel and a seah measure of fine flour worth a shekel it will come to be tomorrow at this time in the gateway of Sa·mar′i·a.” 19 But the adjutant answered the man of the true God and said: “Even if Jehovah were making floodgates in the heavens, could it take place according to this word?” To this he said: “Here you are seeing it with your own eyes, but from it you will not eat.” 20 Thus it happened to him like that, when the people kept trampling him in the gateway, so that he died.

2 Kings

8 And E·li′sha himself had spoken to the woman whose son he had revived, saying: “Rise up and go, you with your household, and reside as an alien wherever you can reside as an alien; for Jehovah has called for a famine, and, besides, it must come upon the land for seven years.” 2 So the woman got up and did according to the word of the man of the true God and went, she with her household, and took up residence as an alien in the land of the Phi·lis′tines for seven years.

3 And it came about at the end of seven years that the woman proceeded to return from the land of the Phi·lis′tines and go forth to cry out to the king for her house and for her field. 4 Now the king was speaking to Ge·ha′zi the attendant of the man of the true God, saying: “Do relate to me, please, all the great things that E·li′sha has done.” 5 And it came about that as he was relating to the king how he had revived the dead one, why, here the woman whose son he had revived was crying out to the king for her house and for her field. At once Ge·ha′zi said: “My lord the king, this is the woman, and this is her son whom E·li′sha revived.” 6 At that the king asked the woman, and she went on to relate to him the story. Then the king gave her a court official, saying: “Return all that belongs to her and all the products of the field from the day of her leaving the land until now.”

7 And E·li′sha proceeded to come to Damascus; and Ben-ha′dad the king of Syria was sick. Accordingly the report was made to him, saying: “The man of the true God has come as far as here.” 8 At that the king said to Haz′a·el: “Take a gift in your hand and go and meet the man of the true God, and you must inquire of Jehovah through him, saying, ‘Shall I revive from this sickness?’” 9 So Haz′a·el went to meet him and took a gift in his hand, even every sort of good thing of Damascus, the load of forty camels, and came and stood before him and said: “Your son, Ben-ha′dad, the king of Syria, has sent me to you, saying, ‘Shall I revive from this sickness?’” 10 Then E·li′sha said to him: “Go, say to him, ‘You will positively revive,’ and Jehovah has shown me that he will positively die.” 11 And he kept a fixed look and kept it set to the point of embarrassment. Then the man of the true God gave way to weeping. 12 At this Haz′a·el said: “Why is my lord weeping?” To this he said: “Because I well know what injury you will do to the sons of Israel. Their fortified places you will consign to the fire, and their choice men you will kill with the sword, and their children you will dash to pieces, and their pregnant women you will rip up.” 13 Upon that Haz′a·el said: “What is your servant, who is a mere dog, that he could do this great thing?” But E·li′sha said: “Jehovah has shown me you as king over Syria.”

14 After that he went from E·li′sha and came to his own lord, who then said to him: “What did E·li′sha say to you?” To this he said: “He said to me, ‘You will positively revive.’” 15 And it came about on the next day that he proceeded to take a coverlet and dip it in water and spread it out over his face, so that he died. And Haz′a·el began to reign in place of him.

16 And in the fifth year of Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab the king of Israel, while Je·hosh′a·phat was king of Judah, Je·ho′ram the son of Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah became king. 17 Thirty-two years old he happened to be when he became king, and for eight years he reigned in Jerusalem. 18 And he went walking in the way of the kings of Israel, just as those of the house of A′hab had done; for it was A′hab’s daughter that became his wife, and he kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. 19 And Jehovah did not want to bring Judah to ruin for the sake of David his servant, just as he had promised him to give a lamp to him and to his sons always.

20 In his days E′dom revolted from under the hand of Judah, and then made a king reign over them. 21 Consequently Je·ho′ram passed over to Za′ir, also all the chariots with him. And it came about that he himself rose up by night and got to strike down the E′dom·ites that were surrounding him and the chiefs of the chariots; and the people went fleeing to their tents. 22 But E′dom kept up its revolt from under the hand of Judah down to this day. It was then that Lib′nah began to revolt at that time.

23 And the rest of the affairs of Je·ho′ram and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 24 Finally Je·ho′ram lay down with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David. And A·ha·zi′ah his son began to reign in place of him.

25 In the twelfth year of Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab the king of Israel, A·ha·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ram the king of Judah became king. 26 Twenty-two years old was A·ha·zi′ah when he began to reign, and for one year he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Ath·a·li′ah the granddaughter of Om′ri the king of Israel. 27 And he went walking in the way of the house of A′hab and kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, like the house of A′hab, for he was a relative of the house of A′hab by marriage. 28 Accordingly he went with Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab to the war against Haz′a·el the king of Syria at Ra′moth-gil′e·ad, but the Syrians struck down Je·ho′ram. 29 So Je·ho′ram the king returned to get healed at Jez′re·el from the wounds that the Syrians got to inflict upon him at Ra′mah when he fought Haz′a·el the king of Syria. As for A·ha·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ram the king of Judah, he went down to see Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab in Jez′re·el, for he was sick.

2 Kings

10 Now A′hab had seventy sons in Sa·mar′i·a. Therefore Je′hu wrote letters and sent them to Sa·mar′i·a to the princes of Jez′re·el, the older men and the caretakers of A′hab, saying: 2 “Now, then, at the very time that this letter comes to YOU there are with YOU the sons of YOUR lord, and there are with YOU the war chariots and the horses and a fortified city and the armor. 3 And YOU must see which is the best and most upright of the sons of YOUR lord and put him upon the throne of his father. Then fight for the house of YOUR lord.”

4 And they became very greatly afraid and began to say: “Look! Two kings themselves did not stand before him, and how shall we ourselves stand?” 5 Consequently the one who was over the house and the one who was over the city and the older men and the caretakers sent to Je′hu, saying: “We are your servants, and everything that you say to us we shall do. We shall not make anyone king. What is good in your own eyes do.”

6 At that he wrote them a second letter, saying: “If YOU belong to me, and it is my voice that YOU are obeying, take the heads of the men that are sons of YOUR lord and come to me tomorrow at this time at Jez′re·el.”

Now the sons of the king, seventy men, were with the distinguished men of the city that were bringing them up. 7 And it came about that as soon as the letter came to them, they went taking the sons of the king and slaughtering them, seventy men, after which they put their heads in baskets and sent them to him at Jez′re·el. 8 Then the messenger came in and told him, saying: “They have brought the heads of the sons of the king.” So he said: “PUT them in two heaps at the entrance of the gate until morning.” 9 And it came about in the morning that he proceeded to go out. Then he stood still and said to all the people: “YOU are righteous. Here I myself conspired against my lord, and I got to kill him; but who struck down all these? 10 Know, then, that nothing of Jehovah’s word will fall unfulfilled to the earth that Jehovah has spoken against the house of A′hab; and Jehovah himself has done what he spoke by means of his servant E·li′jah.” 11 Moreover, Je′hu went on to strike down all who were left over of the house of A′hab in Jez′re·el and all his distinguished men and his acquaintances and his priests, until he had let no survivor of his remain.

12 And he proceeded to rise and come in, then get on his way to Sa·mar′i·a. The binding house of the shepherds was on the way. 13 And Je′hu himself encountered the brothers of A·ha·zi′ah the king of Judah. When he said to them, “Who are YOU?” then they said: “We are the brothers of A·ha·zi′ah, and we are on our way down to ask if all is well with the sons of the king and the sons of the lady.” 14 Immediately he said: “Seize them alive, YOU men!” So they seized them alive and slaughtered them at the cistern of the binding house, forty-two men, and he did not let a single one of them remain.

15 As he was going along from there he got to encounter Je·hon′a·dab the son of Re′chab coming to meet him. When he blessed him, he accordingly said to him: “Is your heart upright with me, just as my own heart is with your heart?”

To this Je·hon′a·dab said: “It is.”

“If it is, do give me your hand.”

So he gave him his hand. At that he made him get up into the chariot with him. 16 Then he said: “Do go along with me and look upon my toleration of no rivalry toward Jehovah.” And they kept him riding with him in his war chariot. 17 Finally he came to Sa·mar′i·a. Now he went striking down all who were left over of A′hab’s in Sa·mar′i·a, until he had annihilated them, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken to E·li′jah.

18 Further, Je′hu collected all the people together and said to them: “A′hab, on the one hand, worshiped Ba′al a little. Je′hu, on the other hand, will worship him a great deal. 19 So now call all the prophets of Ba′al, all his worshipers and all his priests to me. Do not let a single one be missing, because I have a great sacrifice for Ba′al. Anyone that is missing will not keep living.” As for Je′hu, he acted slyly, for the purpose of destroying the worshipers of Ba′al.

20 And Je′hu went on to say: “Sanctify a solemn assembly for Ba′al.” Accordingly they proclaimed it. 21 After that Je′hu sent through all Israel, so that all the worshipers of Ba′al came in. And not a single one was left over that did not come in. And they kept coming into the house of Ba′al, and the house of Ba′al came to be full from end to end. 22 He now said to the one who was over the wardrobe: “Bring out garments for all the worshipers of Ba′al.” So he brought the attire out for them. 23 Then Je′hu entered with Je·hon′a·dab the son of Re′chab into the house of Ba′al. He now said to the worshipers of Ba′al: “Search carefully and see that there may be here with YOU none of the worshipers of Jehovah, but only the worshipers of Ba′al.” 24 Finally they came in to render up sacrifices and burnt offerings, and Je′hu himself stationed eighty men outside at his disposal and went on to say: “As for the man that escapes from the men whom I am bringing into YOUR hands, the one’s soul will go for the other’s soul.”

25 And it came about that as soon as he finished rendering up the burnt offering, Je′hu immediately said to the runners and the adjutants: “Come in, strike them down! Do not let a single one go out.” And the runners and the adjutants began to strike them down with the edge of the sword and to throw them out, and they kept going as far as the city of the house of Ba′al. 26 Then they brought out the sacred pillars of the house of Ba′al and burned each one. 27 Further, they pulled down the sacred pillar of Ba′al and pulled down the house of Ba′al, and they kept it set aside for privies down to this day.

28 Thus Je′hu annihilated Ba′al out of Israel. 29 It was only the sins of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, with which he caused Israel to sin, that Je′hu did not turn aside from following them, that is, the golden calves of which one was in Beth′el and one in Dan. 30 Consequently Jehovah said to Je′hu: “For the reason that you have acted well in doing what is right in my eyes, and according to all that was in my heart you have done to the house of A′hab, sons themselves to the fourth generation will sit for you upon the throne of Israel.” 31 And Je′hu himself did not take care to walk in the law of Jehovah the God of Israel with all his heart. He did not turn aside from the sins of Jer·o·bo′am with which he caused Israel to sin.

32 In those days Jehovah started to cut off Israel piece by piece; and Haz′a·el kept striking them in all the territory of Israel, 33 from the Jordan toward the rising of the sun, all the land of Gil′e·ad, the Gad′ites and the Reu′ben·ites and the Ma·nas′sites, from A·ro′er, which is by the torrent valley of Ar′non, even Gil′e·ad and Ba′shan.

34 And the rest of the affairs of Je′hu and all that he did and all his mightiness, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel? 35 Finally Je′hu lay down with his forefathers, and they buried him in Sa·mar′i·a; and Je·ho′a·haz his son began to reign in place of him. 36 And the days that Je′hu had reigned over Israel were twenty-eight years in Sa·mar′i·a.

2 Kings

11 Now as regards Ath·a·li′ah the mother of A·ha·zi′ah, she saw that her son had died. So she rose up and destroyed all the offspring of the kingdom. 2 However, Je·hosh′e·ba the daughter of King Je·ho′ram, the sister of A·ha·zi′ah, took Je·ho′ash the son of A·ha·zi′ah and stole him from among the sons of the king that were to be put to death, even him and his nursing woman, into the inner room for the couches, and they kept him concealed from the face of Ath·a·li′ah, and he was not put to death. 3 And he continued with her at the house of Jehovah in hiding for six years, while Ath·a·li′ah was reigning over the land.

4 And in the seventh year Je·hoi′a·da sent and then took the chiefs of hundreds of the Ca′ri·an bodyguard and of the runners and brought them to himself at the house of Jehovah and concluded a covenant with them and made them swear at the house of Jehovah, after which he showed them the son of the king. 5 And he went on to command them, saying: “This is the thing that YOU will do: One third of YOU are coming in on the sabbath and keeping strict watch over the king’s house; 6 and one third will be at the Gate of the Foundation, and one third will be at the gate behind the runners; and YOU must keep strict watch over the house by turns. 7 And there are two divisions among YOU that are all going out on the sabbath, and they must keep strict watch over the house of Jehovah in behalf of the king. 8 And YOU must encircle the king all around, each one with his weapons in his hand; and anyone entering within the rows will be put to death. And continue with the king when he goes out and when he comes in.”

9 And the chiefs of hundreds proceeded to do according to all that Je·hoi′a·da the priest had commanded. So they took each one his men that were coming in on the sabbath, together with those that were going out on the sabbath, and then came in to Je·hoi′a·da the priest. 10 The priest now gave the chiefs of hundreds the spears and the circular shields that had belonged to King David, which were in the house of Jehovah. 11 And the runners kept standing each one with his weapons in his hand, from the right side of the house clear to the left side of the house, by the altar and by the house, all around near the king. 12 Then he brought the son of the king out and put upon him the diadem and the Testimony; and so they made him king and anointed him. And they began to clap their hands and say: “Let the king live!”

13 When Ath·a·li′ah heard the sound of the people running, she at once came to the people at the house of Jehovah. 14 Then she saw, and there the king was standing by the pillar according to the custom, and the chiefs and the trumpets by the king, and all the people of the land rejoicing and blowing the trumpets. Immediately Ath·a·li′ah ripped her garments apart and began crying: “Conspiracy! Conspiracy!” 15 But Je·hoi′a·da the priest commanded the chiefs of hundreds, the appointed ones of the military force, and said to them: “Take her out from inside the rows, and, as for anyone coming after her, let there be an execution of death with the sword!” For the priest had said: “Do not let her be put to death in the house of Jehovah.” 16 So they laid their hands upon her and she came by the way of the horse entry of the king’s house, and she got put to death there.

17 Then Je·hoi′a·da concluded the covenant between Jehovah and the king and the people, that they should prove themselves the people of Jehovah; and also between the king and the people. 18 After that all the people of the land came to the house of Ba′al and pulled down his altars; and his images they broke up thoroughly, and Mat′tan the priest of Ba′al they killed before the altars.

And the priest proceeded to put overseers over the house of Jehovah. 19 Further, he took the chiefs of hundreds and the Ca′ri·an bodyguard and the runners and all the people of the land, that they might bring the king down from the house of Jehovah; and they came gradually by the way of the gate of the runners to the king’s house; and he began to sit upon the throne of the kings. 20 And all the people of the land continued to rejoice; and the city, for its part, had no disturbance, and Ath·a·li′ah herself they had put to death with the sword at the king’s house.

21 Seven years old Je·ho′ash was when he began to reign.

2 Kings

14 In the second year of Je·ho′ash the son of Je·ho′a·haz the king of Israel, Am·a·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ash the king of Judah became king. 2 Twenty-five years old he happened to be when he began to reign, and for twenty-nine years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Je·ho·ad′din of Jerusalem. 3 And he continued to do what was upright in Jehovah’s eyes, only not like David his forefather. According to all that Je·ho′ash his father had done, he did. 4 It was only the high places that did not disappear. The people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places. 5 And it came about that as soon as the kingdom had become firm in his hand, he began to strike down his servants that had struck down the king his father. 6 And the sons of the strikers he did not put to death, according to what is written in the book of Moses’ law that Jehovah gave in command, saying: “Fathers should not be put to death for sons, and sons themselves should not be put to death for fathers; but for his own sin should each one be put to death.” 7 He himself struck down the E′dom·ites in the Valley of Salt, ten thousand men, and got to seize Se′la in the war, and its name came to be called Jok′the·el down to this day.

8 Then it was that Am·a·zi′ah sent messengers to Je·ho′ash the son of Je·ho′a·haz the son of Je′hu the king of Israel, saying: “Do come. Let us look each other in the face.” 9 At that Je·ho′ash the king of Israel sent to Am·a·zi′ah the king of Judah, saying: “The thorny weed itself that was in Leb′a·non sent to the cedar that was in Leb′a·non, saying, ‘Do give your daughter to my son as a wife.’ However, a wild beast of the field that was in Leb′a·non passed by and trampled the thorny weed down. 10 You have unmistakably struck down E′dom, and your heart has lifted you up. Enjoy your honor and dwell in your own house. Why, then, should you engage in strife under unfavorable conditions and have to fall, you and Judah with you?” 11 And Am·a·zi′ah did not listen.

So Je·ho′ash the king of Israel came up, and they proceeded to look each other in the face, he and Am·a·zi′ah the king of Judah, at Beth-she′mesh, which belongs to Judah. 12 And Judah came to be defeated before Israel, so that they took to flight, each one to his tent. 13 And it was Am·a·zi′ah the king of Judah the son of Je·ho′ash the son of A·ha·zi′ah that Je·ho′ash the king of Israel captured at Beth-she′mesh, after which they came to Jerusalem and he made a breach in the wall of Jerusalem at the Gate of E′phra·im clear to the Corner Gate, four hundred cubits. 14 And he took all the gold and silver and all the articles to be found at the house of Jehovah and in the treasures of the house of the king and the hostages and then returned to Sa·mar′i·a.

15 As for the rest of the affairs of Je·ho′ash, what he did and his mightiness and how he fought against Am·a·zi′ah the king of Judah, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel? 16 Finally Je·ho′ash lay down with his forefathers and was buried in Sa·mar′i·a with the kings of Israel, and Jer·o·bo′am his son began to reign in place of him.

17 And Am·a·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ash the king of Judah continued to live after the death of Je·ho′ash the son of Je·ho′a·haz the king of Israel for fifteen years. 18 As for the rest of the affairs of Am·a·zi′ah, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 19 At length they leagued against him in a conspiracy at Jerusalem, and he went fleeing to La′chish; but they sent in pursuit of him to La′chish and put him to death there. 20 So they carried him upon horses and he was buried in Jerusalem with his forefathers in the City of David. 21 Then all the people of Judah took Az·a·ri′ah, he at the time being sixteen years old, and they made him king in place of his father Am·a·zi′ah. 22 He himself built E′lath and got to restore it to Judah after the king lay down with his forefathers.

23 In the fifteenth year of Am·a·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ash the king of Judah, Jer·o·bo′am the son of Je·ho′ash the king of Israel became king in Sa·mar′i·a for forty-one years. 24 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from all the sins of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, with which he caused Israel to sin. 25 He it was that restored the boundary of Israel from the entering in of Ha′math clear to the sea of the Ar′a·bah, according to the word of Jehovah the God of Israel who spoke by means of his servant Jo′nah the son of A·mit′tai, the prophet that was from Gath-he′pher. 26 For Jehovah had seen the very bitter affliction of Israel. There was neither any helpless one nor any worthless one, nor was there a helper for Israel. 27 And Jehovah had promised not to wipe out the name of Israel from under the heavens. Consequently he saved them by the hand of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Je·ho′ash.

28 As for the rest of the affairs of Jer·o·bo′am and all that he did and his mightiness, how he fought and how he restored Damascus and Ha′math to Judah in Israel, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Israel? 29 Finally Jer·o·bo′am lay down with his forefathers, with the kings of Israel, and Zech·a·ri′ah his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Kings

16 In the seventeenth year of Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah, A′haz the son of Jo′tham the king of Judah became king. 2 Twenty years old was A′haz when he began to reign, and for sixteen years he reigned in Jerusalem; and he did not do what was right in the eyes of Jehovah his God like David his forefather. 3 And he went walking in the way of the kings of Israel, and even his own son he made pass through the fire, according to the detestable things of the nations whom Jehovah drove out because of the sons of Israel. 4 And he kept sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places and upon the hills and under every luxuriant tree.

5 It was then that Re′zin the king of Syria and Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah the king of Israel proceeded to come up against Jerusalem in war and laid siege against A′haz, but they were not able to fight. 6 At that time Re′zin the king of Syria restored E′lath to E′dom, after which he cleared out the Jews from E′lath; and the E′dom·ites, for their part, entered E′lath and kept dwelling there down to this day. 7 So A′haz sent messengers to Tig′lath-pil·e′ser the king of As·syr′i·a, saying: “I am your servant and your son. Come up and save me out of the palm of the king of Syria and out of the palm of the king of Israel, who are rising up against me.” 8 Accordingly A′haz took the silver and the gold that was to be found at the house of Jehovah and in the treasures of the king’s house and sent the king of As·syr′i·a a bribe. 9 At that the king of As·syr′i·a listened to him and the king of As·syr′i·a went up to Damascus and captured it and led its people into exile at Kir, and Re′zin he put to death.

10 Then King A′haz went to meet Tig′lath-pil·e′ser the king of As·syr′i·a at Damascus, and he got to see the altar that was in Damascus. So King A′haz sent U·ri′jah the priest the design of the altar and its pattern as respects all its workmanship. 11 And U·ri′jah the priest proceeded to build the altar. According to all that King A′haz had sent from Damascus was the way that U·ri′jah the priest made it, pending the time that King A′haz came from Damascus. 12 When the king came from Damascus, the king got to see the altar; and the king began to go near to the altar and make offerings upon it. 13 And he continued to make his burnt offering and his grain offering smoke and to pour out his drink offering and to sprinkle the blood of the communion sacrifices that were his upon the altar. 14 And the copper altar that was before Jehovah he now brought near from in front of the house, from between his altar and the house of Jehovah, and put it at the north side of his altar. 15 And King A′haz went on to command him, even U·ri′jah the priest, saying: “Upon the great altar make the burnt offering of the morning smoke, also the grain offering of the evening and the burnt offering of the king and his grain offering and the burnt offering of all the people of the land and their grain offering and their drink offerings; and all the blood of burnt offering and all the blood of a sacrifice you should sprinkle upon it. As for the copper altar, it will become something for me to take under consideration.” 16 And U·ri′jah the priest went doing according to all that King A′haz had commanded.

17 Furthermore, King A′haz cut the sidewalls of the carriages in pieces and removed from off them the basins; and the sea he took down off the copper bulls that were underneath it and then put it upon a stone pavement. 18 And the covered structure for the sabbath that they had built in the house and the king’s outer entryway he shifted from the house of Jehovah because of the king of As·syr′i·a.

19 As for the rest of the affairs of A′haz, what he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 20 Finally A′haz lay down with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David; and Hez·e·ki′ah his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Kings

21 Twelve years old was Ma·nas′seh when he began to reign, and for fifty-five years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Heph′zi·bah. 2 And he proceeded to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to the detestable things of the nations that Jehovah had driven out from before the sons of Israel. 3 So he built again the high places that Hez·e·ki′ah his father had destroyed, and set up altars to Ba′al and made a sacred pole, just as A′hab the king of Israel had done; and he began to bow down to all the army of the heavens and to serve them. 4 And he built altars in the house of Jehovah, respecting which Jehovah had said: “In Jerusalem I shall put my name.” 5 And he went on to build altars to all the army of the heavens in two courtyards of the house of Jehovah. 6 And he made his own son pass through the fire, and he practiced magic and looked for omens and made spirit mediums and professional foretellers of events. He did on a large scale what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, to offend him.

7 Further, he put the carved image of the sacred pole that he had made in the house of which Jehovah had said to David and to Sol′o·mon his son: “In this house and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, I shall put my name to time indefinite. 8 And I shall not again make the foot of Israel wander from the ground that I gave to their forefathers, provided only they are careful to do according to all that I have commanded them, even concerning all the law that my servant Moses commanded them.” 9 And they did not listen, but Ma·nas′seh kept seducing them to do what was bad more than the nations whom Jehovah had annihilated from before the sons of Israel.

10 And Jehovah kept speaking by means of his servants the prophets, saying: 11 “For the reason that Ma·nas′seh the king of Judah has done these detestable things, he has acted more wickedly than all that the Am′or·ites did that were prior to him, and he proceeded to make even Judah sin with his dungy idols. 12 That is why this is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘Here I am bringing a calamity upon Jerusalem and Judah, of which if anyone hears both his ears will tingle. 13 And I shall certainly stretch upon Jerusalem the measuring line applied to Sa·mar′i·a and also the leveling instrument applied to the house of A′hab; and I shall simply wipe Jerusalem clean just as one wipes the handleless bowl clean, wiping it clean and turning it upside down. 14 And I shall indeed forsake the remnant of my inheritance and give them into the hand of their enemies, and they will simply become plunder and pillage to all their enemies, 15 for the reason that they did what was bad in my eyes and were continually offending me from the day that their forefathers came out from Egypt down to this day.’”

16 And there was also innocent blood that Ma·nas′seh shed in very great quantity, until he had filled Jerusalem from end to end, besides his sin with which he caused Judah to sin by doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah. 17 As for the rest of the affairs of Ma·nas′seh and all that he did and his sin with which he sinned, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 18 Finally Ma·nas′seh lay down with his forefathers and was buried in the garden of his house, in the garden of Uz′za; and A′mon his son began to reign in place of him.

19 Twenty-two years old was A′mon when he began to reign, and for two years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Me·shul′le·meth the daughter of Ha′ruz from Jot′bah. 20 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, just as Ma·nas′seh his father had done. 21 And he kept walking in all the way that his father had walked, and he continued serving the dungy idols that his father had served and bowing down to them. 22 Thus he left Jehovah the God of his forefathers, and he did not walk in the way of Jehovah. 23 Eventually servants of A′mon conspired against him and put the king to death in his own house. 24 But the people of the land struck down all the conspirators against King A′mon. Then the people of the land made Jo·si′ah his son king in place of him. 25 As for the rest of the affairs of A′mon, what he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 26 So they buried him in his grave in the garden of Uz′za; and Jo·si′ah his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Kings

24 In his days Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon came up, and so Je·hoi′a·kim became his servant for three years. However, he turned back and rebelled against him. 2 And Jehovah began to send against him marauder bands of Chal·de′ans and marauder bands of Syrians and marauder bands of Mo′ab·ites and marauder bands of the sons of Am′mon, and he kept sending them against Judah to destroy it, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken by means of his servants the prophets. 3 It was only by the order of Jehovah that it took place against Judah, to remove it from his sight for the sins of Ma·nas′seh, according to all that he had done; 4 and also for the innocent blood that he had shed, so that he filled Jerusalem with innocent blood, and Jehovah did not consent to grant forgiveness.

5 As for the rest of the affairs of Je·hoi′a·kim and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the affairs of the days of the kings of Judah? 6 Finally Je·hoi′a·kim lay down with his forefathers, and Je·hoi′a·chin his son began to reign in place of him.

7 And never again did the king of Egypt come out from his land, for the king of Babylon had taken all that happened to belong to the king of Egypt from the torrent valley of Egypt up to the river Eu·phra′tes.

8 Eighteen years old was Je·hoi′a·chin when he began to reign, and for three months he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Ne·hush′ta the daughter of El·na′than of Jerusalem. 9 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that his father had done. 10 During that time the servants of Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon came up to Jerusalem, so that the city came under siege. 11 And Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon proceeded to come against the city, while his servants were laying siege against it.

12 At length Je·hoi′a·chin the king of Judah went out to the king of Babylon, he with his mother and his servants and his princes and his court officials; and the king of Babylon got to take him in the eighth year of his being king. 13 Then he brought out from there all the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the king’s house, and went on to cut to pieces all the gold utensils that Sol′o·mon the king of Israel had made in the temple of Jehovah, just as Jehovah had spoken. 14 And he took into exile all Jerusalem and all the princes and all the valiant, mighty men—ten thousand he was taking into exile—and also every craftsman and builder of bulwarks. No one had been left behind except the lowly class of the people of the land. 15 Thus he took Je·hoi′a·chin into exile to Babylon; and the king’s mother and the king’s wives and his court officials and the foremost men of the land he led away as exiled people from Jerusalem to Babylon. 16 As for all the valiant men, seven thousand, and the craftsmen and the builders of bulwarks, a thousand, all the mighty men carrying on war, the king of Babylon proceeded to bring them as exiled people to Babylon. 17 Further, the king of Babylon made Mat·ta·ni′ah his uncle king in place of him. Then he changed his name to Zed·e·ki′ah.

18 Twenty-one years old was Zed·e·ki′ah when he began to reign, and for eleven years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Ha·mu′tal the daughter of Jeremiah from Lib′nah. 19 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that Je·hoi′a·kim had done. 20 For on account of the anger of Jehovah it took place in Jerusalem and in Judah, until he had cast them out of his sight. And Zed·e·ki′ah began to rebel against the king of Babylon.

The First of Chronicles

1 Adam,

Seth,

E′nosh,

2 Ke′nan,

Ma·hal′a·lel,

Ja′red,

3 E′noch,

Me·thu′se·lah,

La′mech,

4 Noah,

Shem, Ham and Ja′pheth.

5 The sons of Ja′pheth were Go′mer and Ma′gog and Ma′da·i and Ja′van and Tu′bal and Me′shech and Ti′ras.

6 And the sons of Go′mer were Ash′ke·naz and Ri′phath and To·gar′mah.

7 And the sons of Ja′van were E·li′shah and Tar′shish, Kit′tim and Ro′da·nim.

8 The sons of Ham were Cush and Miz′ra·im, Put and Ca′naan.

9 And the sons of Cush were Se′ba and Hav′i·lah and Sab′tah and Ra′a·mah and Sab′te·ca.

And the sons of Ra′a·mah were She′ba and De′dan.

10 And Cush himself became father to Nim′rod. He it was that made the start in becoming a mighty one in the earth.

11 As for Miz′ra·im, he became father to Lu′dim and An′a·mim and Le·ha′bim and Naph·tu′him 12 and Path·ru′sim and Cas·lu′him (from among whom the Phi·lis′tines went forth) and Caph′to·rim.

13 As for Ca′naan, he became father to Si′don his firstborn and Heth 14 and the Jeb′u·site and the Am′or·ite and the Gir′ga·shite 15 and the Hi′vite and the Ark′ite and the Si′nite 16 and the Ar′vad·ite and the Zem′a·rite and the Ha′math·ite.

17 The sons of Shem were E′lam and As′shur and Ar·pach′shad and Lud and A′ram,

And Uz and Hul and Ge′ther and Mash.

18 As for Ar·pach′shad, he became father to She′lah, and She′lah himself became father to E′ber.

19 And to E′ber two sons were born. The name of the one was Pe′leg, because in his days the earth was divided; and the name of his brother was Jok′tan.

20 As for Jok′tan, he became father to Al·mo′dad and She′leph and Ha·zar·ma′veth and Je′rah 21 and Ha·do′ram and U′zal and Dik′lah 22 and O′bal and A·bim′a·el and She′ba 23 and O′phir and Hav′i·lah and Jo′bab; all these were the sons of Jok′tan.

24 Shem,

Ar·pach′shad,

She′lah,

25 E′ber,

Pe′leg,

Re′u,

26 Se′rug,

Na′hor,

Te′rah,

27 A′bram, that is to say, Abraham.

28 The sons of Abraham were Isaac and Ish′ma·el.

29 These are their family origins: Ish′ma·el’s firstborn Ne·ba′ioth and Ke′dar and Ad′be·el and Mib′sam, 30 Mish′ma and Du′mah, Mas′sa, Ha′dad and Te′ma, 31 Je′tur, Na′phish and Ked′e·mah. These were the sons of Ish′ma·el.

32 As for the sons of Ke·tu′rah, Abraham’s concubine, she gave birth to Zim′ran and Jok′shan and Me′dan and Mid′i·an and Ish′bak and Shu′ah.

And the sons of Jok′shan were She′ba and De′dan.

33 And the sons of Mid′i·an were E′phah and E′pher and Ha′noch and A·bi′da and El·da′ah.

All these were the sons of Ke·tu′rah.

34 And Abraham came to be father to Isaac. The sons of Isaac were E′sau and Israel.

35 The sons of E′sau were El′i·phaz, Reu′el and Je′ush and Ja′lam and Ko′rah.

36 The sons of El′i·phaz were Te′man and O′mar, Ze′pho and Ga′tam, Ke′naz and Tim′na and Am′a·lek.

37 The sons of Reu′el were Na′hath, Ze′rah, Sham′mah and Miz′zah.

38 And the sons of Se′ir were Lo′tan and Sho′bal and Zib′e·on and A′nah and Di′shon and E′zer and Di′shan.

39 And the sons of Lo′tan were Ho′ri and Ho′mam. And Lo′tan’s sister was Tim′na.

40 The sons of Sho′bal were Al′van and Man′a·hath and E′bal, She′pho and O′nam.

And the sons of Zib′e·on were A′iah and A′nah.

41 The sons of A′nah were Di′shon.

And the sons of Di′shon were Hem′dan and Esh′ban and Ith′ran and Che′ran.

42 The sons of E′zer were Bil′han and Za′a·van and A′kan.

The sons of Di′shan were Uz and A′ran.

43 And these are the kings that reigned in the land of E′dom before any king reigned over the sons of Israel: Be′la the son of Be′or, the name of whose city was Din′ha·bah. 44 Eventually Be′la died, and Jo′bab the son of Ze′rah from Boz′rah began to reign in place of him. 45 Eventually Jo′bab died, and Hu′sham from the land of the Te′man·ites began to reign in place of him. 46 Eventually Hu′sham died, and Ha′dad the son of Be′dad, who defeated Mid′i·an in the field of Mo′ab, began to reign in place of him. And the name of his city was A′vith. 47 Eventually Ha′dad died, and Sam′lah from Mas·re′kah began to reign in place of him. 48 Eventually Sam′lah died, and Sha′ul from Re·ho′both by the River began to reign in place of him. 49 Eventually Sha′ul died, and Ba′al-ha′nan the son of Ach′bor began to reign in place of him. 50 Eventually Ba′al-ha′nan died, and Ha′dad began to reign in place of him; and the name of his city was Pa′u, and the name of his wife was Me·het′a·bel, the daughter of Ma′tred, the daughter of Me′za·hab. 51 Eventually Ha′dad died.

And the sheiks of E′dom came to be sheik Tim′na, sheik Al′vah, sheik Je′theth, 52 sheik O·hol·i·ba′mah, sheik E′lah, sheik Pi′non, 53 sheik Ke′naz, sheik Te′man, sheik Mib′zar, 54 sheik Mag′di·el, sheik I′ram. These were the sheiks of E′dom.

1 Chronicles

3 And these became the sons of David that were born to him in He′bron: the firstborn Am′non, of A·hin′o·am the Jez′re·el·i·tess, the second, Daniel, of Ab′i·gail the Car′mel·it·ess, 2 the third, Ab′sa·lom the son of Ma′a·cah the daughter of Tal′mai the king of Gesh′ur, the fourth, Ad·o·ni′jah the son of Hag′gith, 3 the fifth, Sheph·a·ti′ah, of A·bi′tal, the sixth, Ith′re·am, of Eg′lah his wife. 4 There were six born to him in He′bron; and he continued to reign there seven years and six months, and for thirty-three years he reigned in Jerusalem.

5 And there were these born to him in Jerusalem: Shim′e·a and Sho′bab and Nathan and Sol′o·mon, four of Bath-she′ba the daughter of Am′mi·el, 6 and Ib′har and E·lish′a·ma and E·liph′e·let, 7 and No′gah and Ne′pheg and Ja·phi′a, 8 and E·lish′a·ma and E·li′a·da and E·liph′e·let, nine, 9 all the sons of David besides the sons of the concubines, and Ta′mar their sister.

10 And the son of Sol′o·mon was Re·ho·bo′am, A·bi′jah his son, A′sa his son, Je·hosh′a·phat his son, 11 Je·ho′ram his son, A·ha·zi′ah his son, Je·ho′ash his son, 12 Am·a·zi′ah his son, Az·a·ri′ah his son, Jo′tham his son, 13 A′haz his son, Hez·e·ki′ah his son, Ma·nas′seh his son, 14 A′mon his son, Jo·si′ah his son. 15 And the sons of Jo·si′ah were the firstborn Jo·ha′nan, the second, Je·hoi′a·kim, the third, Zed·e·ki′ah, the fourth, Shal′lum. 16 And the sons of Je·hoi′a·kim were Jec·o·ni′ah his son, Zed·e·ki′ah his son. 17 And the sons of Jec·o·ni′ah as prisoner were She·al′ti·el his son 18 and Mal·chi′ram and Pe·dai′ah and She·naz′zar, Jek·a·mi′ah, Hosh′a·ma and Ned·a·bi′ah. 19 And the sons of Pe·dai′ah were Ze·rub′ba·bel and Shim′e·i; and the sons of Ze·rub′ba·bel were Me·shul′lam and Han·a·ni′ah (and She·lo′mith was their sister); 20 and Ha·shu′bah and O′hel and Ber·e·chi′ah and Has·a·di′ah, Ju′shab-he′sed, five. 21 And the sons of Han·a·ni′ah were Pel·a·ti′ah and Je·sha′iah, the sons of Je·sha′iah Re·pha′iah, the sons of Re·pha′iah Ar′nan, the sons of Ar′nan O·ba·di′ah, the sons of O·ba·di′ah Shec·a·ni′ah; 22 and the sons of Shec·a·ni′ah, She·mai′ah, and the sons of She·mai′ah, Hat′tush and I′gal and Ba·ri′ah and Ne·a·ri′ah and Sha′phat, six. 23 And the sons of Ne·a·ri′ah were Eli·o·e′nai and Hiz·ki′ah and Az·ri′kam, three. 24 And the sons of Eli·o·e′nai were Hod·a·vi′ah and E·li′a·shib and Pe·la′iah and Ak′kub and Jo·ha′nan and De·la′iah and A·na′ni, seven.

1 Chronicles

6 The sons of Le′vi were Ger′shon, Ko′hath and Me·rar′i. 2 And the sons of Ko′hath were Am′ram, Iz′har and He′bron and Uz′zi·el. 3 And the sons of Am′ram were Aaron and Moses, and there was Mir′i·am. And the sons of Aaron were Na′dab and A·bi′hu, El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar. 4 As for El·e·a′zar, he became father to Phin′e·has. Phin′e·has himself became father to Ab·i·shu′a. 5 Ab·i·shu′a, in turn, became father to Buk′ki; Buk′ki, in turn, became father to Uz′zi. 6 Uz′zi, in turn, became father to Zer·a·hi′ah; Zer·a·hi′ah, in turn, became father to Me·ra′ioth. 7 Me·ra′ioth himself became father to Am·a·ri′ah; Am·a·ri′ah, in turn, became father to A·hi′tub. 8 A·hi′tub, in turn, became father to Za′dok; Za′dok, in turn, became father to A·him′a·az. 9 A·him′a·az, in turn, became father to Az·a·ri′ah. Az·a·ri′ah, in turn, became father to Jo·ha′nan. 10 Jo·ha′nan, in turn, became father to Az·a·ri′ah. He was the one that acted as priest in the house that Sol′o·mon built in Jerusalem.

11 And Az·a·ri′ah came to be father to Am·a·ri′ah. Am·a·ri′ah, in turn, became father to A·hi′tub. 12 A·hi′tub, in turn, became father to Za′dok. Za′dok, in turn, became father to Shal′lum. 13 Shal′lum, in turn, became father to Hil·ki′ah. Hil·ki′ah, in turn, became father to Az·a·ri′ah. 14 Az·a·ri′ah, in turn, became father to Se·rai′ah. Se·rai′ah, in turn, became father to Je·hoz′a·dak. 15 And Je·hoz′a·dak it was that went away when Jehovah took Judah and Jerusalem into exile by the hand of Neb·u·chad·nez′zar.

16 The sons of Le′vi were Ger′shom, Ko′hath and Me·rar′i. 17 And these are the names of the sons of Ger′shom: Lib′ni and Shim′e·i. 18 And the sons of Ko′hath were Am′ram and Iz′har and He′bron and Uz′zi·el. 19 The sons of Me·rar′i were Mah′li and Mu′shi.

And these were the families of the Levites by their forefathers: 20 Of Ger′shom, Lib′ni his son, Ja′hath his son, Zim′mah his son, 21 Jo′ah his son, Id′do his son, Ze′rah his son, Je·ath′e·rai his son. 22 The sons of Ko′hath were Am·min′a·dab his son, Ko′rah his son, As′sir his son, 23 El·ka′nah his son and E·bi′a·saph his son and As′sir his son; 24 Ta′hath his son, U·ri′el his son, Uz·zi′ah his son, and Sha′ul his son. 25 And the sons of El·ka′nah were A·ma′sai and A·hi′moth. 26 As for El·ka′nah, the sons of El·ka′nah were Zo′phai his son and Na′hath his son, 27 E·li′ab his son, Je·ro′ham his son, El·ka′nah his son. 28 And the sons of Samuel were the firstborn Joel and the second A·bi′jah. 29 The sons of Me·rar′i were Mah′li, Lib′ni his son, Shim′e·i his son, Uz′zah his son, 30 Shim′e·a his son, Hag·gi′ah his son, A·sai′ah his son.

31 And these were the ones to whom David gave positions for the direction of the singing at the house of Jehovah after the Ark had a resting-place. 32 And they came to be ministers in the singing before the tabernacle of the tent of meeting until Sol′o·mon built the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem; and they kept attending upon their service according to their commission. 33 And these were those in attendance and also their sons: Of the sons of the Ko′hath·ites He′man the singer, the son of Joel, the son of Samuel, 34 the son of El·ka′nah, the son of Je·ro′ham, the son of E′li·el, the son of To′ah, 35 the son of Zuph, the son of El·ka′nah, the son of Ma′hath, the son of A·ma′sai, 36 the son of El·ka′nah, the son of Joel, the son of Az·a·ri′ah, the son of Zeph·a·ni′ah, 37 the son of Ta′hath, the son of As′sir, the son of E·bi′a·saph, the son of Ko′rah, 38 the son of Iz′har, the son of Ko′hath, the son of Le′vi, the son of Israel.

39 As for his brother A′saph, who was attending at his right, A′saph was the son of Ber·e·chi′ah, the son of Shim′e·a, 40 the son of Mi′cha·el, the son of Ba·a·se′iah, the son of Mal·chi′jah, 41 the son of Eth′ni, the son of Ze′rah, the son of A·dai′ah, 42 the son of E′than, the son of Zim′mah, the son of Shim′e·i, 43 the son of Ja′hath, the son of Ger′shom, the son of Le′vi.

44 As regards the sons of Me·rar′i their brothers on the left hand, there was E′than the son of Kish′i, the son of Ab′di, the son of Mal′luch, 45 the son of Hash·a·bi′ah, the son of Am·a·zi′ah, the son of Hil·ki′ah, 46 the son of Am′zi, the son of Ba′ni, the son of She′mer, 47 the son of Mah′li, the son of Mu′shi, the son of Me·rar′i, the son of Le′vi.

48 And their brothers the Levites were the ones given for all the service of the tabernacle of the house of the true God. 49 And Aaron and his sons were making sacrificial smoke upon the altar of burnt offering and upon the altar of incense for all the work of the most holy things and to make atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of the true God had commanded. 50 And these were the sons of Aaron: El·e·a′zar his son, Phin′e·has his son, Ab·i·shu′a his son, 51 Buk′ki his son, Uz′zi his son, Zer·a·hi′ah his son, 52 Me·ra′ioth his son, Am·a·ri′ah his son, A·hi′tub his son, 53 Za′dok his son, A·him′a·az his son.

54 And these were their dwelling places by their walled camps in their territory, for the sons of Aaron belonging to the family of the Ko′hath·ites, for the lot had come to be theirs. 55 Accordingly they gave them He′bron in the land of Judah, with its pasture grounds all around it. 56 And the field of the city and its settlements they gave to Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh. 57 And to the sons of Aaron they gave the cities of refuge, He′bron, and Lib′nah with its pasture grounds and Jat′tir and Esh·te·mo′a with its pasture grounds, 58 and Hi′len with its pasture grounds, De′bir with its pasture grounds, 59 and A′shan with its pasture grounds and Beth-she′mesh with its pasture grounds; 60 and from the tribe of Benjamin Ge′ba with its pasture grounds and Al′e·meth with its pasture grounds and An′a·thoth with its pasture grounds. All their cities were thirteen cities among their families.

61 And to the sons of Ko′hath that were left over they gave from the family of the tribe, from the half tribe, the half of Ma·nas′seh, by the lot ten cities.

62 And to the sons of Ger′shom by their families they gave from the tribe of Is′sa·char and from the tribe of Ash′er and from the tribe of Naph′ta·li and from the tribe of Ma·nas′seh in Ba′shan, thirteen cities.

63 To the sons of Me·rar′i by their families they gave from the tribe of Reu′ben and from the tribe of Gad and from the tribe of Zeb′u·lun by the lot twelve cities.

64 Thus the sons of Israel gave the Levites the cities with their pasture grounds. 65 Furthermore, by the lot they gave from the tribe of the sons of Judah and from the tribe of the sons of Sim′e·on and from the tribe of the sons of Benjamin these cities, which they proceeded to call by names.

66 And some of the families of the sons of Ko′hath came to have the cities of their territory from the tribe of E′phra·im. 67 Accordingly they gave them the cities of refuge, She′chem with its pasture grounds in the mountainous region of E′phra·im, and Ge′zer with its pasture grounds, 68 and Jok′me·am with its pasture grounds and Beth-ho′ron with its pasture grounds, 69 and Ai′ja·lon with its pasture grounds and Gath-rim′mon with its pasture grounds; 70 and from half of the tribe of Ma·nas′seh, A′ner with its pasture grounds and Bil′e·am with its pasture grounds, to the family of the sons of Ko′hath that were left over.

71 And to the sons of Ger′shom they gave from the family of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh Go′lan in Ba′shan with its pasture grounds and Ash′ta·roth with its pasture grounds; 72 and from the tribe of Is′sa·char, Ke′desh with its pasture grounds and Dab′e·rath with its pasture grounds, 73 and Ra′moth with its pasture grounds and A′nem with its pasture grounds; 74 and from the tribe of Ash′er, Ma′shal with its pasture grounds and Ab′don with its pasture grounds, 75 and Hu′kok with its pasture grounds and Re′hob with its pasture grounds; 76 and from the tribe of Naph′ta·li, Ke′desh in Gal′i·lee with its pasture grounds and Ham′mon with its pasture grounds and Kir·i·a·tha′im with its pasture grounds.

77 To the sons of Me·rar′i that were left over they gave from the tribe of Zeb′u·lun Rim′mo·no with its pasture grounds, Ta′bor with its pasture grounds, 78 and in the region of the Jordan at Jer′i·cho to the east of the Jordan, from the tribe of Reu′ben, Be′zer in the wilderness with its pasture grounds and Ja′haz with its pasture grounds, 79 and Ked′e·moth with its pasture grounds and Meph′a·ath with its pasture grounds; 80 and from the tribe of Gad, Ra′moth in Gil′e·ad with its pasture grounds and Ma·ha·na′im with its pasture grounds, 81 and Hesh′bon with its pasture grounds and Ja′zer with its pasture grounds.

1 Chronicles

8 As for Benjamin, he became father to Be′la his firstborn, Ash′bel the second and A·har′ah the third, 2 No′hah the fourth and Ra′pha the fifth. 3 And Be′la came to have sons, Ad′dar and Ge′ra and A·bi′hud, 4 and Ab·i·shu′a and Na′a·man and A·ho′ah, 5 and Ge′ra and She·phu′phan and Hu′ram. 6 And these were the sons of E′hud. These were the heads of the houses of forefathers belonging to the inhabitants of Ge′ba, and they proceeded to take them into exile at Man′a·hath. 7 And Na′a·man and A·hi′jah; and Ge′ra—he was the one that took them into exile, and he became father to Uz′za and A·hi′hud. 8 As for Sha·ha·ra′im, he became father to children in the field of Mo′ab after he sent them away. Hu′shim and Ba′a·ra were his wives. 9 And by Ho′desh his wife he came to be father to Jo′bab and Zib′i·a and Me′sha and Mal′cam, 10 and Je′uz and Sa·chi′a and Mir′mah. These were his sons, heads of the houses of forefathers.

11 And by Hu′shim he became father to A·bi′tub and El·pa′al. 12 And the sons of El·pa′al were E′ber and Mi′sham and She′med, who built O′no and Lod and its dependent towns, 13 and Be·ri′ah and She′ma. These were heads of the houses of forefathers, belonging to the inhabitants of Ai′ja·lon. These were the ones that chased away the inhabitants of Gath. 14 And there were A·hi′o, Sha′shak and Jer′e·moth, 15 and Zeb·a·di′ah and A′rad and E′der, 16 and Mi′cha·el and Ish′pah and Jo′ha, the sons of Be·ri′ah, 17 and Zeb·a·di′ah and Me·shul′lam and Hiz′ki and He′ber, 18 and Ish′me·rai and Iz·li′ah and Jo′bab, the sons of El·pa′al, 19 and Ja′kim and Zich′ri and Zab′di, 20 and E·li·e′nai and Zil′le·thai and E′li·el, 21 and A·dai′ah and Be·ra′iah and Shim′rath, the sons of Shim′e·i, 22 and Ish′pan and E′ber and E′li·el, 23 and Ab′don and Zich′ri and Ha′nan, 24 and Han·a·ni′ah and E′lam and An·tho·thi′jah, 25 and Iph·de′iah and Pe·nu′el, the sons of Sha′shak, 26 and Sham′she·rai and She·ha·ri′ah and Ath·a·li′ah, 27 and Ja·a·re·shi′ah and E·li′jah and Zich′ri, the sons of Je·ro′ham. 28 These were heads of the houses of forefathers by their descendants, headmen. These were the ones that dwelt in Jerusalem.

29 And it was in Gib′e·on that the father of Gib′e·on, Je·i′el, dwelt, and his wife’s name was Ma′a·cah. 30 And his son, the firstborn, was Ab′don, and Zur and Kish and Ba′al and Na′dab, 31 and Ge′dor and A·hi′o and Ze′cher. 32 As for Mik′loth, he became father to Shim′e·ah. And these really were the ones that dwelt in front of their brothers in Jerusalem along with brothers of theirs.

33 As for Ner, he became father to Kish; Kish, in turn, became father to Saul; Saul, in turn, became father to Jon′a·than and Mal′chi-shu′a and A·bin′a·dab and Esh·ba′al. 34 And Jon′a·than’s son was Mer′ib-ba′al. As for Mer′ib-ba′al, he became father to Mi′cah. 35 And the sons of Mi′cah were Pi′thon and Mel′ech and Ta·re′a and A′haz. 36 As for A′haz, he became father to Je·ho′ad·dah; Je·ho′ad·dah, in turn, became father to Al′e·meth and Az′ma·veth and Zim′ri. Zim′ri, in turn, became father to Mo′za; 37 Mo′za, in turn, became father to Bin′e·a, Ra′phah his son, El·e·a′sah his son, A′zel his son. 38 And A′zel had six sons, and these were their names: Az·ri′kam, Bo′che·ru and Ish′ma·el and She·a·ri′ah and O·ba·di′ah and Ha′nan. All these were the sons of A′zel. 39 And the sons of E′shek his brother were U′lam his firstborn, Je′ush the second and E·liph′e·let the third. 40 And the sons of U′lam came to be valiant, mighty men, bending the bow, and having many sons and grandsons, a hundred and fifty. All these were from the sons of Benjamin.

1 Chronicles

12 And these are the ones that came to David at Zik′lag while he was still under restrictions because of Saul the son of Kish; and they were among the mighty men, the helpers in the warfare, 2 armed with the bow, using the right hand and using the left hand with stones or with arrows in the bow. They were of the brothers of Saul, of Benjamin. 3 There was the head A·hi·e′zer and Jo′ash the sons of She·ma′ah the Gib′e·ath·ite, and Je′zi·el and Pel′et the sons of Az′ma·veth, and Ber′a·cah and Je′hu the An′a·thoth·ite, 4 and Ish·ma′iah the Gib′e·on·ite, a mighty man among the thirty and over the thirty; and Jeremiah and Ja·ha·zi′el and Jo·ha′nan and Jo′za·bad the Ge·de′rath·ite, 5 E·lu′zai and Jer′i·moth and Be·a·li′ah and Shem·a·ri′ah and Sheph·a·ti′ah the Har′i·phite, 6 El·ka′nah and Is·shi′ah and Az′ar·el and Jo·e′zer and Ja·sho′be·am, the Ko′rah·ites, 7 and Jo·e′lah and Zeb·a·di′ah the sons of Je·ro′ham of Ge′dor.

8 And there were some of the Gad′ites that separated themselves to David’s side at the place difficult to approach in the wilderness, valiant, mighty men, army men for the war, keeping the large shield and the lance ready, whose faces were the faces of lions, and they were like the gazelles upon the mountains for speed. 9 E′zer was the head, O·ba·di′ah the second, E·li′ab the third, 10 Mish·man′nah the fourth, Jeremiah the fifth, 11 At′tai the sixth, E′li·el the seventh, 12 Jo·ha′nan the eighth, El·za′bad the ninth, 13 Jeremiah the tenth, Mach′ban·nai the eleventh. 14 These were of the sons of Gad, heads of the army. The least one was equal to a hundred, and the greatest to a thousand. 15 These are the ones that crossed the Jordan in the first month when it was overflowing all its banks, and they then chased away all those of the low plains, to the east and to the west.

16 And some of the sons of Benjamin and Judah proceeded to come clear to the place difficult to approach, to David. 17 Then David went out before them and answered and said to them: “If it is for peace that YOU have come to me to help me, my own heart will become at unity with YOU. But if it is to betray me to my adversaries when there is no wrong on my palms, let the God of our forefathers see to it and set it in order.” 18 And spirit itself enveloped A·ma′sai, the head of the thirty:

“Yours we are, O David, and with you we are, O son of Jes′se.

Peace, peace be yours, and peace to the one helping you,

For your God has helped you.”

So David received them and put them among the heads of the troops.

19 And there were some of Ma·nas′seh that deserted to David when he came with the Phi·lis′tines against Saul for battle; but he did not help them, for on counsel the axis lords of the Phi·lis′tines sent him away, saying: “At the risk of our own heads he will desert to his lord Saul.” 20 When he came to Zik′lag there deserted to him from Ma·nas′seh Ad′nah and Jo′za·bad and Je·di′a·el and Mi′cha·el and Jo′za·bad and E·li′hu and Zil′le·thai, heads of the thousands that belonged to Ma·nas′seh. 21 And they, for their part, were of help to David against the marauder band, because all of them were mighty men of valor, and they came to be chiefs in the army; 22 for day by day people kept coming to David to help him, until it was a great camp, like the camp of God.

23 And these were the numbers of the heads of those equipped for the army that came to David at He′bron to turn the kingship of Saul over to him according to Jehovah’s order. 24 The sons of Judah carrying the large shield and the lance were six thousand eight hundred, equipped for the army. 25 Of the sons of Sim′e·on the mighty men of valor of the army were seven thousand one hundred.

26 Of the sons of the Levites four thousand six hundred. 27 And Je·hoi′a·da was the leader of the sons of Aaron, and with him there were three thousand seven hundred. 28 Also Za′dok a young man, mighty in valor, and the house of his forefathers, twenty-two chiefs.

29 And of the sons of Benjamin, the brothers of Saul, there were three thousand, and up till then the greater number of them were keeping strict watch of the house of Saul. 30 And of the sons of E′phra·im there were twenty thousand eight hundred, mighty men of valor, men of fame, by the house of their forefathers.

31 And of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh there were eighteen thousand that had been designated by name to come to make David king. 32 And of the sons of Is′sa·char having a knowledge of how to discern the times to know what Israel ought to do, there were two hundred head ones of theirs, and all their brothers were at their orders. 33 Of Zeb′u·lun those going out to the army, drawing up in battle formation with all the weapons of war, there were fifty thousand, and for flocking together to David they were not of a double heart. 34 And of Naph′ta·li there were a thousand chiefs, and with them with the large shield and the spear there were thirty-seven thousand. 35 And of the Dan′ites those drawing up in battle formation were twenty-eight thousand six hundred. 36 And of Ash′er those going out to the army for drawing up in battle formation were forty thousand.

37 And from across the Jordan of the Reu′ben·ites and the Gad′ites and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh with all the weapons of the military army there were a hundred and twenty thousand. 38 All these were men of war, flocking together in battle line; with a complete heart they came to He′bron to make David king over all Israel; and also all the remainder of Israel were of one heart for making David king. 39 And they continued there with David three days, eating and drinking, for their brothers had made preparation for them. 40 And also those near to them, as far as Is′sa·char and Zeb′u·lun and Naph′ta·li, were bringing food upon asses and upon camels and upon mules and upon cattle, eatables of flour, cakes of pressed figs and cakes of raisins and wine and oil and cattle and sheep in great quantity, for there was rejoicing in Israel.

1 Chronicles

13 And David proceeded to consult with the chiefs of the thousands and of the hundreds and with every leader; 2 and David went on to say to all the congregation of Israel: “If it seems good to YOU and it is acceptable with Jehovah our God, let us send to our brothers that are left over in all the lands of Israel and with them to the priests and the Levites in their cities with pasture grounds, that they may collect themselves together to us. 3 And let us bring the ark of our God around to ourselves.” For they had not cared for it in the days of Saul. 4 So all the congregation said to do that way, for the thing seemed right in the eyes of all the people. 5 Accordingly David congregated all Israel from the river of Egypt as far as the entering of Ha′math, to bring the ark of the true God from Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim.

6 And David and all Israel proceeded to go up to Ba′al·ah, to Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, which belongs to Judah, to bring up from there the ark of the true God, Jehovah, sitting on the cherubs, where his name is called on. 7 However, they had the ark of the true God ride upon a new wagon from the house of A·bin′a·dab, and Uz′zah and A·hi′o were leading the wagon. 8 And David and all Israel were celebrating before the true God with full power and with songs and with harps and with stringed instruments and with tambourines and with cymbals and with trumpets. 9 And they came gradually as far as the threshing floor of Chi′don, and Uz′zah now thrust his hand out to grab hold of the Ark, for the bulls nearly caused an upset. 10 At that Jehovah’s anger blazed against Uz′zah, so that he struck him down because he had thrust his hand out upon the Ark, and he died there before God. 11 And David became angry because Jehovah had broken through in a rupture against Uz′zah; and that place came to be called Pe′rez-uz′zah down to this day.

12 And David became afraid of the true God on that day, saying: “How shall I bring the ark of the true God to me?” 13 And David did not remove the Ark to himself at the City of David, but he carried it aside to the house of O′bed-e′dom the Git′tite. 14 And the ark of the true God kept dwelling with the household of O′bed-e′dom, at his house three months; and Jehovah kept blessing the household of O′bed-e′dom and all that was his.

1 Chronicles

14 And Hi′ram the king of Tyre proceeded to send messengers to David and cedar timbers and builders of walls and workers in wood to build him a house. 2 And David came to know that Jehovah had firmly established him as king over Israel, for his kingship was highly exalted on account of his people Israel.

3 And David went on to take more wives in Jerusalem, and David came to be father to more sons and daughters. 4 And these are the names of the children that became his in Jerusalem: Sham·mu′a and Sho′bab, Nathan and Sol′o·mon, 5 and Ib′har and E·li′shu·a and El′pe·let, 6 and No′gah and Ne′pheg and Ja·phi′a, 7 and E·lish′a·ma and Be·e·li′a·da and E·liph′e·let.

8 And the Phi·lis′tines got to hear that David had been anointed as king over all Israel. At that all the Phi·lis′tines came up to look for David. When David heard of it, then he went out against them. 9 And the Phi·lis′tines, for their part, came in and kept making raids in the low plain of Reph′a·im. 10 And David began to inquire of God, saying: “Shall I go up against the Phi·lis′tines, and will you certainly give them into my hand?” At this Jehovah said to him: “Go up, and I shall certainly give them into your hand.” 11 So David went up to Ba′al-pe·ra′zim and there got to strike them down. At that David said: “The true God has broken through my enemies by my hand like a gap made by waters.” That is why they called the name of that place Ba′al-pe·ra′zim. 12 Consequently they left their gods there. Then David said the word, and so they were burned in the fire.

13 Later the Phi·lis′tines once again made a raid in the low plain. 14 At that David inquired again of God, and the true God now said to him: “You must not go up after them. Go around from directly against them, and you must come at them in front of the ba′ca bushes. 15 And let it occur that, when you hear the sound of the marching in the tops of the ba′ca bushes, then you go out into the fight, because the true God will have gone out before you to strike the camp of the Phi·lis′tines down.” 16 So David did just as the true God had commanded him, and they went striking down the camp of the Phi·lis′tines from Gib′e·on to Ge′zer. 17 And David’s fame began to go out into all the lands, and Jehovah himself put the dread of him upon all the nations.

1 Chronicles

15 And he continued building houses for himself in the City of David; and he went on to prepare a place for the ark of the true God and pitch a tent for it. 2 It was then that David said: “No one is to carry the ark of the true God but the Levites, for they are the ones whom Jehovah has chosen to carry the ark of Jehovah and to minister to him to time indefinite.” 3 Then David congregated all Israel at Jerusalem to bring the ark of Jehovah up to its place that he had prepared for it.

4 And David proceeded to gather the sons of Aaron and the Levites; 5 of the sons of Ko′hath, U·ri′el the chief and his brothers, a hundred and twenty; 6 of the sons of Me·rar′i, A·sai′ah the chief and his brothers, two hundred and twenty; 7 of the sons of Ger′shom, Joel the chief and his brothers, a hundred and thirty; 8 of the sons of E·li·za′phan, She·mai′ah the chief and his brothers, two hundred; 9 of the sons of He′bron, E′li·el the chief and his brothers, eighty; 10 of the sons of Uz′zi·el, Am·min′a·dab the chief and his brothers, a hundred and twelve. 11 Furthermore, David called Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar the priests, and the Levites U·ri′el, A·sai′ah and Joel, She·mai′ah and E′li·el and Am·min′a·dab, 12 and he went on to say to them: “YOU are the heads of the fathers of the Levites. Sanctify yourselves, YOU and YOUR brothers, and YOU must bring the ark of Jehovah the God of Israel up to the place that I have prepared for it. 13 Because at the first time YOU did not, Jehovah our God broke through against us, for we did not search after him according to the custom.” 14 So the priests and the Levites sanctified themselves to bring up the ark of Jehovah the God of Israel.

15 Then the sons of the Levites began to carry the ark of the true God, just as Moses had commanded by Jehovah’s word, upon their shoulders with the rods upon them. 16 David now said to the chiefs of the Levites to station their brothers the singers with the instruments of song, stringed instruments and harps and cymbals, playing aloud to cause a sound of rejoicing to arise.

17 Accordingly the Levites stationed He′man the son of Joel and, of his brothers, A′saph the son of Ber·e·chi′ah; and, of the sons of Me·rar′i their brothers, E′than the son of Kush·a′iah; 18 and with them their brothers of the second division, Zech·a·ri′ah, Ben and Ja·a′zi·el and She·mir′a·moth and Je·hi′el and Un′ni, E·li′ab and Be·nai′ah and Ma·a·sei′ah and Mat·ti·thi′ah and E·liph′e·le·hu and Mik·ne′iah, and O′bed-e′dom and Je·i′el the gatekeepers, 19 and the singers He′man, A′saph and E′than, with the copper cymbals to play aloud; 20 and Zech·a·ri′ah and A′zi·el and She·mir′a·moth and Je·hi′el and Un′ni and E·li′ab and Ma·a·sei′ah and Be·nai′ah with stringed instruments tuned to Al′a·moth, 21 and Mat·ti·thi′ah and E·liph′e·le·hu and Mik·ne′iah and O′bed-e′dom and Je·i′el and Az·a·zi′ah with harps tuned to Shem′i·nith, to act as directors; 22 and Chen·a·ni′ah the chief of the Levites in carrying, he giving instruction in carrying, for he was expert; 23 and Ber·e·chi′ah and El·ka′nah the gatekeepers for the Ark; 24 and Sheb·a·ni′ah and Josh′a·phat and Ne·than′el and A·ma′sai and Zech·a·ri′ah and Be·nai′ah and E·li·e′zer the priests loudly sounding the trumpets before the ark of the true God, and O′bed-e′dom and Je·hi′ah the gatekeepers for the Ark.

25 And David and the older men of Israel and the chiefs of the thousands came to be the ones walking along to bring up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah from the house of O′bed-e′dom with rejoicing. 26 And it came about when the true God helped the Levites while carrying the ark of the covenant of Jehovah that they proceeded to sacrifice seven young bulls and seven rams. 27 And David was dressed in a sleeveless coat of fine fabric, and also all the Levites carrying the Ark and the singers and Chen·a·ni′ah the chief of the carrying by the singers; but upon David there was an eph′od of linen. 28 And all the Israelites were bringing up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah with joyful shouting and with the sounding of the horn and with trumpets and with cymbals, playing aloud on stringed instruments and harps.

29 And it came about that, when the ark of the covenant of Jehovah came as far as the City of David, Mi′chal, Saul’s daughter, herself looked down through the window and got to see King David skipping about and celebrating; and she began to despise him in her heart.

1 Chronicles

16 Thus they brought the ark of the true God in and placed it inside the tent that David had pitched for it; and they began to present burnt offerings and communion sacrifices before the true God. 2 When David finished offering up the burnt offering and the communion sacrifices, he went on to bless the people in the name of Jehovah. 3 Further, he apportioned to all the Israelites, man as well as woman, to each one a round loaf of bread and a date cake and a raisin cake. 4 Then he put before the ark of Jehovah some of the Levites as ministers, both to call to remembrance and to thank and praise Jehovah the God of Israel, 5 A′saph the head, and second to him Zech·a·ri′ah, and Je·i′el and She·mir′a·moth and Je·hi′el and Mat·ti·thi′ah and E·li′ab and Be·nai′ah and O′bed-e′dom and Je·i′el, with instruments of the string type and with harps, and A′saph with the cymbals playing aloud, 6 and Be·nai′ah and Ja·ha·zi′el the priests with the trumpets constantly before the ark of the covenant of the true God.

7 It was then on that day that David made a contribution for the first time to thank Jehovah by means of A′saph and his brothers:

8 “Give thanks to Jehovah, YOU people; call upon his name,

Make his deeds known among the peoples!

9 Sing to him, make melody to him,

Concern yourselves with all his wonderful acts.

10 Make YOUR boast in his holy name,

Let the heart of those seeking Jehovah rejoice.

11 Search after Jehovah and his strength,

Seek his face constantly.

12 Remember his wonderful acts that he has performed,

His miracles and the judicial decisions of his mouth,

13 O offspring of Israel his servant,

YOU sons of Jacob, his chosen ones.

14 He is Jehovah our God; in all the earth are his judicial decisions.

15 Remember his covenant even to time indefinite,

The word that he commanded, to a thousand generations,

16 Which covenant he concluded with Abraham,

And his sworn statement to Isaac.

17 And which statement he kept standing as a regulation even to Jacob,

As an indefinitely lasting covenant even to Israel,

18 Saying, ‘To you I shall give the land of Ca′naan,

As the allotment of YOUR inheritance.’

19 This was when YOU happened to be few in number,

Yes, very few, and alien residents in it.

20 And they kept walking about from nation to nation,

And from one kingdom to another people.

21 He did not allow anyone to defraud them,

But on their account he reproved kings,

22 Saying, ‘Do not YOU men touch my anointed ones,

And to my prophets do nothing bad.’

23 Sing to Jehovah, all YOU of the earth!

Announce from day to day the salvation he gives!

24 Relate among the nations his glory,

Among all the peoples his wonderful acts.

25 For Jehovah is great and very much to be praised,

And he is to be feared more than all other gods.

26 For all the gods of the peoples are valueless gods.

As for Jehovah, he made the heavens.

27 Dignity and splendor are before him,

Strength and joy are at his place.

28 Attribute to Jehovah, O families of peoples,

Attribute to Jehovah glory and strength.

29 Attribute to Jehovah the glory of his name,

Carry a gift and come in before him.

Bow down to Jehovah in holy adornment.

30 Be in severe pains on account of him, all YOU people of the earth!

Also the productive land is firmly established:

Never will it be made to totter.

31 Let the heavens rejoice, and let the earth be joyful,

And let them say among the nations, ‘Jehovah himself has become king!’

32 Let the sea thunder and also that which fills it,

Let the field exult and all that is in it.

33 At the same time let the trees of the forest break out joyfully on account of Jehovah,

For he has come to judge the earth.

34 Give thanks to Jehovah, YOU people, for he is good,

For to time indefinite is his loving-kindness.

35 And say, ‘Save us, O God of our salvation,

And collect us together and deliver us from the nations,

To give thanks to your holy name, to speak exultingly in your praise.

36 Blessed be Jehovah the God of Israel from time indefinite to time indefinite.’”

And all the people proceeded to say, “Amen!” and a praise to Jehovah.

37 Then he left there before the ark of the covenant of Jehovah A′saph and his brothers to minister before the Ark constantly, according to the requirement of each day; 38 and O′bed-e′dom and his brothers, sixty-eight, and O′bed-e′dom the son of Je·du′thun and Ho′sah as gatekeepers; 39 and Za′dok the priest and his brothers the priests before the tabernacle of Jehovah on the high place that was at Gib′e·on, 40 to offer up burnt offerings to Jehovah on the altar of burnt offering constantly morning and evening and for all that is written in the law of Jehovah that he laid in command upon Israel; 41 and with them He′man and Je·du′thun and the rest of the select men that were designated by names to thank Jehovah, because “to time indefinite is his loving-kindness”; 42 and with them He′man and Je·du′thun, to sound forth the trumpets and cymbals and instruments of the song of the true God; and the sons of Je·du′thun at the gate. 43 And all the people proceeded to go each one to his own house. Accordingly David went around to bless his own house.

1 Chronicles

17 And it came about that as soon as David had begun dwelling in his own house, David proceeded to say to Nathan the prophet: “Here I am dwelling in a house of cedars, but the ark of the covenant of Jehovah is under tent cloths.” 2 Upon that Nathan said to David: “Everything that is in your heart do, for the true God is with you.”

3 And it came about on that night that the word of God came to Nathan, saying: 4 “Go, and you must say to David my servant, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “It will not be you that will build me the house in which to dwell. 5 For I have not dwelt in a house from the day that I brought Israel up until this day, but I continued from tent to tent and from one tabernacle to another. 6 During all the time that I walked about in all Israel, did I speak a single word with one of the judges of Israel whom I commanded to shepherd my people, saying, ‘Why have YOU men not built me a house of cedars?’”’

7 “And now this is what you will say to my servant David, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies has said: “I myself took you from the pasture ground from following the flock to become a leader over my people Israel. 8 And I shall prove to be with you wherever you do walk, and I shall cut off all your enemies from before you, and I shall certainly make for you a name like the name of the great ones that are upon the earth. 9 And I shall certainly appoint a place for my people Israel and plant them, and they will indeed reside where they are and no more will they be disturbed; and the sons of unrighteousness will not wear them out again, just as they did at the first, 10 even since the days that I put judges in command over my people Israel. And I shall certainly humble all your enemies. And I tell you, ‘Also a house Jehovah will build for you.’

11 “‘“And it must occur that when your days have come to the full for you to go to be with your forefathers, I shall certainly raise up your seed after you that will come to be one of your sons, and I shall indeed firmly establish his kingship. 12 He is the one that will build me a house, and I shall certainly establish his throne firmly to time indefinite. 13 I myself shall become his father, and he himself will become my son; and my loving-kindness I shall not remove from him the way I removed it from the one that happened to be prior to you. 14 And I will cause him to stand in my house and in my kingship to time indefinite, and his throne will itself become one lasting to time indefinite.”’”

15 According to all these words and according to all this vision was the way that Nathan spoke to David.

16 After that King David came in and sat down before Jehovah and said: “Who am I, O Jehovah God, and what is my house that you have brought me thus far? 17 As though this should be something little in your eyes, O God, yet you speak concerning the house of your servant down to a distant future time, and you have looked on me according to the opportunity of the man in the ascendancy, O Jehovah God. 18 What more could David say to you as to honoring your servant, when you yourself know your servant well? 19 O Jehovah, for the sake of your servant and in agreement with your own heart you have done all these great things by making all the great achievements known. 20 O Jehovah, there is none like you, and there is no God except you in connection with all that we have heard with our ears. 21 And what other nation in the earth is like your people Israel, whom the true God went to redeem to himself as a people, to assign to yourself a name of great achievements and fear-inspiring things by driving out nations from before your people whom you have redeemed from Egypt? 22 And you proceeded to constitute your people Israel as your people to time indefinite, and you yourself, O Jehovah, became their God. 23 And now, O Jehovah, let the word that you have spoken concerning your servant and concerning his house prove faithful to time indefinite, and do just as you have spoken. 24 And let your name prove faithful and become great to time indefinite, saying, ‘Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, is God to Israel,’ and let the house of David your servant be one lasting before you. 25 For you yourself, my God, have revealed to your servant the purpose to build him a house. That is why your servant has found occasion to pray before you. 26 And now, O Jehovah, you are the true God, and you promise this goodness concerning your servant. 27 And now you must take it upon yourself and bless the house of your servant for it to continue to time indefinite before you; for you yourself, O Jehovah, have blessed, and it is blessed to time indefinite.”

1 Chronicles

19 And it came about afterward that Na′hash the king of the sons of Am′mon came to die, and his son began to reign in place of him. 2 At that David said: “I shall exercise loving-kindness toward Ha′nun the son of Na′hash, because his father exercised loving-kindness toward me.” Accordingly David sent messengers to comfort him over his father, and the servants of David proceeded to come into the land of the sons of Am′mon to Ha′nun to comfort him. 3 However, the princes of the sons of Am′mon said to Ha′nun: “Is David honoring your father in your eyes in that he has sent comforters to you? Is it not for the sake of making a thorough search and causing an overthrow and for spying out the land that his servants have come in to you?” 4 So Ha′nun took the servants of David and shaved them and cut their garments in half to their buttocks and sent them away. 5 Later people went and told David about the men; and he at once sent to meet them, because they had become men very much humiliated; and the king went on to say: “Dwell in Jer′i·cho until YOUR beards grow abundantly. Then YOU must return.”

6 In time the sons of Am′mon saw that they had become foul-smelling to David, and Ha′nun and the sons of Am′mon proceeded to send a thousand silver talents to hire for themselves chariots and horsemen from Mes·o·po·ta′mi·a and from A′ram-ma′a·cah and from Zo′bah. 7 Thus they hired for themselves thirty-two thousand chariots and the king of Ma′a·cah and his people. Then they came in and camped before Med′e·ba; and as for the sons of Am′mon, they gathered together from their cities and now came in for the war.

8 When David heard of it, he immediately sent Jo′ab and all the army and the mighty men. 9 And the sons of Am′mon began to go out and draw up in battle formation at the entrance of the city, and the kings that had come were by themselves in the open field.

10 When Jo′ab saw that the battle charges had come to be against him from the front and from the rear, he at once chose some of all the choice men in Israel and drew them up in formation to meet the Syrians. 11 And the rest of the people he gave into the hand of A·bish′ai his brother, that they might draw up in formation to meet the sons of Am′mon. 12 And he went on to say: “If the Syrians become too strong for me, you must also serve as a salvation for me; but if the sons of Am′mon themselves become too strong for you, I must also save you. 13 Be strong, that we may show ourselves courageous in behalf of our people and in behalf of the cities of our God; and as for Jehovah, what is good in his own eyes he will do.”

14 Then Jo′ab and the people that were with him advanced before the Syrians to the battle, and they took to flight from before him. 15 As for the sons of Am′mon, they saw that the Syrians had fled, and they themselves also took to flight from before A·bish′ai his brother and then came into the city. Later Jo′ab came into Jerusalem.

16 When the Syrians saw that they had been defeated before Israel, they proceeded to send messengers and bring out the Syrians that were in the region of the River, with Sho′phach the chief of the army of Had·ad·e′zer before them.

17 When the report was made to David, he immediately gathered all Israel together and crossed the Jordan and came to them and drew up in formation against them. When David drew up in battle formation to meet the Syrians, they began to fight against him. 18 But the Syrians took to flight because of Israel; and David went killing of the Syrians seven thousand charioteers and forty thousand men on foot, and Sho′phach the chief of the army himself he put to death. 19 When the servants of Had·ad·e′zer saw that they had been defeated before Israel, they promptly made peace with David and began to serve him; and Syria did not want to try saving the sons of Am′mon anymore.

1 Chronicles

24 Now the sons of Aaron had their divisions. The sons of Aaron were Na′dab and A·bi′hu, El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar. 2 However, Na′dab and A·bi′hu died before their father, and they did not happen to have any sons, but El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar continued to act as priests. 3 And David, and Za′dok from the sons of El·e·a′zar, and A·him′e·lech from the sons of Ith′a·mar proceeded to make divisions of them for their office in their service. 4 But the sons of El·e·a′zar were found to be more numerous in headmen than the sons of Ith′a·mar. So they distributed them to the sons of El·e·a′zar, as heads for their paternal houses, sixteen, and to the sons of Ith′a·mar, as heads for their paternal houses, eight.

5 Further, they distributed them by lots, these along with those, for there had to be chiefs of the holy place and chiefs of the true God from the sons of El·e·a′zar and from the sons of Ith′a·mar. 6 Then She·mai′ah the son of Ne·than′el the secretary of the Levites wrote them down before the king and the princes and Za′dok the priest and A·him′e·lech the son of A·bi′a·thar and the heads of the fathers of the priests and of the Levites, one paternal house being picked out for El·e·a′zar and one being picked out for Ith′a·mar.

7 And the lot proceeded to come out: the first for Je·hoi′a·rib; for Je·da′iah the second, 8 for Ha′rim the third, for Se·o′rim the fourth, 9 for Mal·chi′jah the fifth, for Mij′a·min the sixth, 10 for Hak′koz the seventh, for A·bi′jah the eighth, 11 for Jesh′u·a the ninth, for Shec·a·ni′ah the tenth, 12 for E·li′a·shib the eleventh, for Ja′kim the twelfth, 13 for Hup′pah the thirteenth, for Je·sheb′e·ab the fourteenth, 14 for Bil′gah the fifteenth, for Im′mer the sixteenth, 15 for He′zir the seventeenth, for Hap′piz·zez the eighteenth, 16 for Peth·a·hi′ah the nineteenth, for Je·hez′kel the twentieth, 17 for Ja′chin the twenty-first, for Ga′mul the twenty-second, 18 for De·la′iah the twenty-third, for Ma·a·zi′ah the twenty-fourth.

19 These were their offices for their service, to come into the house of Jehovah according to their due right by the hand of Aaron their forefather, just as Jehovah the God of Israel had commanded him.

20 And of the sons of Le′vi that were left over, of the sons of Am′ram there was Shu′ba·el; of the sons of Shu′ba·el, Jeh·de′iah; 21 of Re·ha·bi′ah: of the sons of Re·ha·bi′ah, Is·shi′ah the head; 22 of the Iz′har·ites, She·lo′moth; of the sons of She·lo′moth, Ja′hath; 23 and the sons of He′bron, Je·ri′ah the head, Am·a·ri′ah the second, Ja·ha·zi′el the third, Jek·a·me′am the fourth. 24 The sons of Uz′zi·el, Mi′cah; of the sons of Mi′cah, Sha′mir. 25 The brother of Mi′cah was Is·shi′ah; of the sons of Is·shi′ah, Zech·a·ri′ah.

26 The sons of Me·rar′i were Mah′li and Mu′shi; the sons of Ja·a·zi′ah, Be′no. 27 The sons of Me·rar′i: Of Ja·a·zi′ah, Be′no and Sho′ham and Zac′cur and Ib′ri. 28 Of Mah′li, El·e·a′zar, who did not come to have any sons. 29 Of Kish: the sons of Kish were Je·rah′me·el. 30 And the sons of Mu′shi were Mah′li and E′der and Jer′i·moth.

These were the sons of the Levites by their paternal houses. 31 And they themselves also proceeded to cast lots exactly as their brothers the sons of Aaron did before David the king and Za′dok and A·him′e·lech and the heads of the paternal houses of the priests and of the Levites. As respects paternal houses, the head one was exactly as his younger brother.

1 Chronicles

26 For the divisions of gatekeepers: Of the Ko′rah·ites, Me·shel·e·mi′ah the son of Ko′re of the sons of A′saph. 2 And Me·shel·e·mi′ah had sons: Zech·a·ri′ah the firstborn, Je·di′a·el the second, Zeb·a·di′ah the third, Jath′ni·el the fourth, 3 E′lam the fifth, Je·ho·ha′nan the sixth, El′ie·ho-e′nai the seventh. 4 And O′bed-e′dom had sons: She·mai′ah the firstborn, Je·hoz′a·bad the second, Jo′ah the third and Sa′car the fourth and Ne·than′el the fifth, 5 Am′mi·el the sixth, Is′sa·char the seventh, Pe·ul′le·thai the eighth; for God had blessed him.

6 And to She·mai′ah his son there were sons born that were rulers of the house of their father, for they were capable, mighty men. 7 The sons of She·mai′ah, Oth′ni and Reph′a·el and O′bed, El·za′bad, whose brothers were capable men, E·li′hu and Sem·a·chi′ah. 8 All these were of the sons of O′bed-e′dom, they and their sons and their brothers, capable men with the power for the service, sixty-two belonging to O′bed-e′dom. 9 And Me·shel·e·mi′ah had sons and brothers, capable men, eighteen. 10 And Ho′sah of the sons of Me·rar′i had sons. Shim′ri was the head, for he did not happen to be the firstborn but his father appointed him as head; 11 Hil·ki′ah the second, Teb·a·li′ah the third, Zech·a·ri′ah the fourth. All the sons and brothers of Ho′sah were thirteen.

12 Of these divisions of the gatekeepers, the headmen had duties exactly as their brothers did, to minister at the house of Jehovah. 13 So they cast lots for the small the same as for the great by their paternal houses, for the different gates. 14 Then the lot to the east fell to Shel·e·mi′ah. For Zech·a·ri′ah his son, a counselor with discretion, they cast the lots, and his lot got to come out to the north. 15 O′bed-e′dom had his to the south, and his sons had the storehouses. 16 Shup′pim and Ho′sah had theirs to the west close by the Gate Shal′lech·eth by the highway that goes up, guard group corresponding with guard group; 17 to the east there were six Levites; to the north for a day, four; to the south for a day, four; and for the stores, two by two; 18 for the portico to the west, four at the highway, two at the portico. 19 These were the divisions of the gatekeepers of the sons of the Ko′rah·ites and of the sons of Me·rar′i.

20 As regards the Levites, A·hi′jah was over the treasures of the house of the true God and over the treasures of the things made holy. 21 The sons of La′dan, the sons of the Ger′shon·ite belonging to La′dan; the heads of the paternal houses belonging to La′dan the Ger′shon·ite, Je·hi′e·li. 22 The sons of Je·hi′e·li, Ze′tham and Joel his brother, were over the treasures of the house of Jehovah. 23 For the Am′ram·ites, for the Iz′har·ites, for the He′bron·ites, for the Uz·zi′el·ites, 24 even Sheb′u·el the son of Ger′shom the son of Moses was a leader over the stores. 25 As regards his brothers, of E·li·e′zer there was Re·ha·bi′ah his son and Je·sha′iah his son and Jo′ram his son and Zich′ri his son and She·lo′moth his son. 26 This She·lo′moth and his brothers were over all the treasures of the things made holy, that David the king and the heads of the paternal houses, and the chiefs of the thousands and of the hundreds, and the chiefs of the army had made holy. 27 From the wars and from the spoil they had made things holy to maintain the house of Jehovah. 28 And also all that Samuel the seer and Saul the son of Kish and Ab′ner the son of Ner and Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah had made holy. What anyone made holy was under the control of She·lo′mith and his brothers.

29 Of the Iz′har·ites, Chen·a·ni′ah and his sons were for the outside business as officers and as judges over Israel.

30 Of the He′bron·ites, Hash·a·bi′ah and his brothers, capable men, a thousand seven hundred, were over the administration of Israel in the region of the Jordan to the west for all the work of Jehovah and for the king’s service. 31 Of the He′bron·ites, Je·ri′jah was the head of the He′bron·ites by its generations by forefathers. In the fortieth year of David’s kingship they were sought out, and valiant, mighty men came to be found among them in Ja′zer in Gil′e·ad. 32 And his brothers, capable men, were two thousand seven hundred, heads of the paternal houses. So David the king assigned them over the Reu′ben·ites and the Gad′ites and the half tribe of the Ma·nas′sites, for every matter of the true God and matter of the king.

1 Chronicles

27 As for the sons of Israel by their number, the heads of the paternal houses and the chiefs of the thousands and of the hundreds and their officers that were ministering to the king in every matter of the divisions of those that came in and that went out month by month for all the months of the year, each division was twenty-four thousand.

2 Over the first division of the first month there was Ja·sho′be·am the son of Zab′di·el, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand. 3 Some of the sons of Pe′rez the head of all the chiefs of the service groups were for the first month. 4 And over the division of the second month there was Do′dai the A·ho′hite with his division, and Mik′loth was the leader, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand. 5 The chief of the third service group for the third month was Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da the chief priest, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand. 6 This Be·nai′ah was a mighty man of the thirty and over the thirty; and over his division there was Am·miz′a·bad his son. 7 The fourth for the fourth month was As′a·hel, Jo′ab’s brother, and Zeb·a·di′ah his son after him, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand. 8 The fifth chief for the fifth month was Sham′huth the Iz′rah·ite, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand. 9 The sixth for the sixth month was I′ra the son of Ik′kesh the Te·ko′ite, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand. 10 The seventh for the seventh month was He′lez the Pel′o·nite of the sons of E′phra·im, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand. 11 The eighth for the eighth month was Sib′be·cai the Hu′shath·ite of the Ze′rah·ites, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand. 12 The ninth for the ninth month was Abi-e′zer the An′a·thoth·ite of the Ben′ja·min·ites, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand. 13 The tenth for the tenth month was Ma′ha·rai the Ne·toph′a·thite of the Ze′rah·ites, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand. 14 The eleventh for the eleventh month was Be·nai′ah the Pir′a·thon·ite of the sons of E′phra·im, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand. 15 The twelfth for the twelfth month was Hel′dai the Ne·toph′a·thite, of Oth′ni·el, and in his division there were twenty-four thousand.

16 And over the tribes of Israel, of the Reu′ben·ites, E·li·e′zer the son of Zich′ri was leader; of the Sim′e·on·ites, Sheph·a·ti′ah the son of Ma′a·cah; 17 of Le′vi, Hash·a·bi′ah the son of Kem·u′el; of Aaron, Za′dok; 18 of Judah, E·li′hu, one of David’s brothers; of Is′sa·char, Om′ri the son of Mi′cha·el; 19 of Zeb′u·lun, Ish·ma′iah the son of O·ba·di′ah; of Naph′ta·li, Jer′i·moth the son of Az′ri·el; 20 of the sons of E′phra·im, Ho·she′a the son of Az·a·zi′ah; of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh, Joel the son of Pe·dai′ah; 21 of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh in Gil′e·ad, Id′do the son of Zech·a·ri′ah; of Benjamin, Ja·a·si′el the son of Ab′ner; 22 of Dan, Az′ar·el the son of Je·ro′ham. These were the princes of the tribes of Israel.

23 And David did not take the number of those from twenty years of age and under, because Jehovah had promised to make Israel as many as the stars of the heavens. 24 Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah had himself started to take the count, but he did not finish; and for this there came to be indignation against Israel, and the number did not come up into the account of the affairs of the days of King David.

25 And over the treasures of the king there was Az′ma·veth the son of Ad′i·el. And over the treasures in the field, in the cities and in the villages and in the towers there was Jon′a·than the son of Uz·zi′ah. 26 And over the doers of work in the field, for the cultivation of the soil, there was Ez′ri the son of Che′lub. 27 And over the vineyards there was Shim′e·i the Ra′math·ite; and over that which was in the vineyards for the wine supplies there was Zab′di the Shiph′mite. 28 And over the olive groves and the sycamore trees that were in the She·phe′lah there was Ba′al-ha′nan the Ge·de′rite; and over the oil supplies there was Jo′ash. 29 And over the herds that were grazing in Shar′on there was Shit′rai the Shar′on·ite; and over the herds in the low plains there was Sha′phat the son of Ad′lai. 30 And over the camels there was O′bil the Ish′ma·el·ite; and over the she-asses there was Jeh·de′iah the Me·ron′o·thite. 31 And over the flocks there was Ja′ziz the Hag′rite. All these were the chiefs of the goods that belonged to King David.

32 And Jon′a·than, David’s nephew, was a counselor, a man of understanding, he being also a secretary; and Je·hi′el the son of Hach′mo·ni was with the king’s sons. 33 And A·hith′o·phel was a counselor of the king; and Hu′shai the Ar′chite was the king’s companion. 34 And after A·hith′o·phel there were Je·hoi′a·da the son of Be·nai′ah and A·bi′a·thar; and Jo′ab was chief of the army of the king.

2 Chronicles

4 Then he made the copper altar, twenty cubits being its length, and twenty cubits its width, and ten cubits its height.

2 And he proceeded to make the molten sea ten cubits from its one brim to its other brim, circular all around, and its height was five cubits, and it took a line of thirty cubits to circle all around it. 3 And there was the likeness of gourd-shaped ornaments under it clear around, surrounding it, ten in a cubit, enclosing the sea all around. The gourd-shaped ornaments were in two rows, being cast in its casting. 4 It was standing upon twelve bulls, three facing the north and three facing the west and three facing the south and three facing the east; and the sea was above upon them, and all their hind parts were inward. 5 And its thickness was a handbreadth; and its brim was like the workmanship of the brim of a cup, a lily blossom. As a receptacle, three thousand bath measures were what it could contain.

6 Further, he made ten basins, and put five to the right and five to the left, to wash in them. Things having to do with the burnt offering they would rinse in them. But the sea was for the priests to wash in it.

7 He then made lampstands of gold, ten of them of the same plan, and put them in the temple, five to the right and five to the left.

8 Further, he made ten tables, and stationed them in the temple, five to the right and five to the left, and made a hundred bowls of gold.

9 Then he made the courtyard of the priests and the great enclosure and the doors belonging to the enclosure, and their doors he overlaid with copper. 10 And the sea he placed at the right side, to the east, toward the south.

11 Finally Hi′ram made the cans and the shovels and the bowls.

So Hi′ram finished doing the work that he did for King Sol′o·mon on the house of the true God. 12 The two pillars and the round capitals upon the top of the two pillars and the two networks to cover the two round capitals that were upon the top of the pillars 13 and the four hundred pomegranates for the two networks, two rows of pomegranates for each network to cover the two round capitals that were upon the pillars, 14 and the ten carriages and the ten basins upon the carriages; 15 the one sea and the twelve bulls under it, 16 and the cans and the shovels and the forks and all their utensils Hi′ram-a′biv made for King Sol′o·mon for the house of Jehovah, of polished copper. 17 In the District of the Jordan the king cast them in the thick ground between Suc′coth and Zer′e·dah. 18 Thus Sol′o·mon made all these utensils in very great quantity, for the weight of the copper was not ascertained.

19 And Sol′o·mon proceeded to make all the utensils that were at the house of the true God and the golden altar and the tables with the showbread upon them, 20 and the lampstands and their lamps of pure gold, to light them up before the innermost room according to the rule; 21 and the blossoms and the lamps and the snuffers, of gold, (it was the purest gold,) 22 and the extinguishers and the bowls and the cups and the fire holders, of pure gold, and the entrance of the house, its inner doors for the Most Holy and the doors of the house of the temple, of gold.

2 Chronicles

8 And it came about at the end of twenty years, in which Sol′o·mon had built the house of Jehovah and his own house, 2 that the cities that Hi′ram had given to Sol′o·mon—Sol′o·mon rebuilt them and then caused the sons of Israel to dwell there. 3 Furthermore, Sol′o·mon went to Ha′math-zo′bah and prevailed over it. 4 Then he rebuilt Tad′mor in the wilderness and all the storage cities that he had built in Ha′math. 5 And he went on to build Upper Beth-ho′ron and Lower Beth-ho′ron, fortified cities with walls, doors and bar, 6 and Ba′al·ath and all the storage cities that had become Sol′o·mon’s and all the chariot cities and the cities for the horsemen and every desirable thing of Sol′o·mon that he had desired to build in Jerusalem and in Leb′a·non and in all the land of his dominion.

7 As for all the people that were left over of the Hit′tites and the Am′or·ites and the Per′iz·zites and the Hi′vites and the Jeb′u·sites, who were no part of Israel, 8 from their sons that had been left behind them in the land, whom the sons of Israel had not exterminated, Sol′o·mon kept levying men for forced labor until this day. 9 But there were none out of the sons of Israel that Sol′o·mon constituted slaves for his work; for they were warriors and chiefs of his adjutants and chiefs of his charioteers and of his horsemen. 10 These were the chiefs of the deputies that belonged to King Sol′o·mon, two hundred and fifty, the foremen over the people.

11 And Phar′aoh’s daughter Sol′o·mon brought up out of the City of David to the house that he had built for her, for he said: “Although a wife of mine, she should not dwell in the house of David the king of Israel, for the places to which the ark of Jehovah has come are something holy.”

12 It was then that Sol′o·mon offered up burnt sacrifices to Jehovah upon the altar of Jehovah that he had built before the porch, 13 even as a daily matter of course to make offerings according to the commandment of Moses for the sabbaths and for the new moons and for the appointed festivals three times in the year, at the festival of unfermented cakes and at the festival of the weeks and at the festival of the booths. 14 Further, he set the divisions of the priests over their services according to the rule of David his father, and the Levites at their posts of duty, to praise and to minister in front of the priests as a daily matter of course, and the gatekeepers in their divisions for the different gates, for such was the commandment of David the man of the true God. 15 And they did not turn aside from the king’s commandment to the priests and the Levites concerning any matter and concerning the supplies. 16 So Sol′o·mon’s work was all in a prepared state from the day of the foundation-laying of the house of Jehovah until it was finished. So the house of Jehovah was complete.

17 It was then that Sol′o·mon went to E′zi·on-ge′ber and to E′loth upon the shore of the sea in the land of E′dom. 18 And Hi′ram regularly sent to him by means of his servants ships and servants having a knowledge of the sea, and they would come with Sol′o·mon’s servants to O′phir and take from there four hundred and fifty talents of gold and bring it to King Sol′o·mon.

2 Chronicles

12 And it came about that, as soon as the kingship of Re·ho·bo′am was firmly established and as soon as he was strong, he left the law of Jehovah, and also all Israel with him. 2 And it came about in the fifth year of King Re·ho·bo′am that Shi′shak the king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, (for they had behaved unfaithfully toward Jehovah,) 3 with twelve hundred chariots and with sixty thousand horsemen; and there was no number to the people that came with him out of Egypt—Lib′y·ans, Suk′ki·im and E·thi·o′pi·ans. 4 And he got to capture the fortified cities that belonged to Judah and finally came as far as Jerusalem.

5 Now as for She·mai′ah the prophet, he came to Re·ho·bo′am and the princes of Judah who had gathered themselves at Jerusalem because of Shi′shak, and he proceeded to say to them: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘YOU, for YOUR part, have left me, and I, too, for my part, have left YOU to the hand of Shi′shak.’” 6 At that the princes of Israel and the king humbled themselves and said: “Jehovah is righteous.” 7 And when Jehovah saw that they had humbled themselves, the word of Jehovah came to She·mai′ah, saying: “They have humbled themselves. I shall not bring them to ruin, and in a little while I shall certainly give them an escape, and my rage will not pour forth upon Jerusalem by the hand of Shi′shak. 8 But they will become servants of his, that they may know the difference between my service and the service of the kingdoms of the lands.”

9 So Shi′shak the king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem and took the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the king’s house. Everything he took; and so he took the gold shields that Sol′o·mon had made. 10 Consequently King Re·ho·bo′am made in their place copper shields, and he committed them to the control of the chiefs of the runners, the guards of the entrance of the king’s house. 11 And it would occur that as often as the king came to the house of Jehovah, the runners came in and carried them and returned them to the guard chamber of the runners. 12 And because he humbled himself, Jehovah’s anger turned back from him, and he did not think of bringing them to ruin completely. And, besides, there happened to be good things in Judah.

13 And King Re·ho·bo′am continued to make his position strong in Jerusalem and kept reigning; for Re·ho·bo′am was forty-one years old when he began to reign, and for seventeen years he reigned in Jerusalem, the city that Jehovah had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel to put his name there. And his mother’s name was Na′a·mah the Am′mon·it·ess. 14 But he did what was bad, for he had not firmly established his heart to search for Jehovah.

15 As for Re·ho·bo′am’s affairs, the first and the last, are they not written among the words of She·mai′ah the prophet and of Id′do the visionary by genealogical enrollment? And there were wars between Re·ho·bo′am and Jer·o·bo′am all the time. 16 Finally Re·ho·bo′am lay down with his forefathers and was buried in the City of David; and A·bi′jah his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Chronicles

13 In the eighteenth year of King Jer·o·bo′am it was that A·bi′jah began to reign over Judah. 2 Three years he reigned in Jerusalem, and his mother’s name was Mi·cai′ah the daughter of U·ri′el of Gib′e·ah. And war itself took place between A·bi′jah and Jer·o·bo′am.

3 So A·bi′jah engaged in the war with a military force of four hundred thousand mighty men of war, chosen men. And Jer·o·bo′am himself drew up in battle formation against him with eight hundred thousand chosen men, valiant, mighty men. 4 A·bi′jah now rose up upon Mount Zem·a·ra′im, which is in the mountainous region of E′phra·im, and said: “Hear me, O Jer·o·bo′am and all Israel. 5 Is it not for YOU to know that Jehovah the God of Israel himself gave a kingdom to David over Israel to time indefinite, to him and to his sons, by a covenant of salt? 6 And Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, the servant of Sol′o·mon the son of David, proceeded to rise up and rebel against his lord. 7 And idle men, good-for-nothing fellows, kept collecting themselves together by him. Finally they proved superior to Re·ho·bo′am the son of Sol′o·mon, when Re·ho·bo′am himself happened to be young and fainthearted, and he did not hold his own against them.

8 “And now YOU men are thinking of holding YOUR own against the kingdom of Jehovah in the hand of the sons of David, when YOU are a large crowd and there are with YOU the golden calves that Jer·o·bo′am made for YOU as gods. 9 Have YOU not driven out Jehovah’s priests, the sons of Aaron, and the Levites, and do YOU not keep making priests for yourselves like the peoples of the lands? As for anyone that came and filled his hand with power by means of a young bull and seven rams, he became a priest of what are no gods. 10 As for us, Jehovah is our God, and we have not left him; but priests are ministering to Jehovah, the sons of Aaron, and also the Levites in the work. 11 And they are making burnt offerings smoke to Jehovah morning by morning and evening by evening and also perfumed incense; and the layers of bread are upon the table of pure gold, and there are the golden lampstand and its lamps to light up evening by evening; because we are keeping the obligation to Jehovah our God, but YOU yourselves have left him. 12 And, look! with us there is at the head the true God with his priests and the signal trumpets for sounding the battle alarm against YOU. O sons of Israel, do not fight against Jehovah the God of YOUR forefathers, for YOU will not prove successful.”

13 And Jer·o·bo′am, for his part, dispatched an ambush around to come behind them, so that they proved to be in front of Judah and the ambush behind them. 14 When those of Judah turned around, why, there they had the battle in front and behind. And they began to cry out to Jehovah, while the priests were loudly sounding the trumpets. 15 And the men of Judah broke out shouting a war cry. And it came about that, when the men of Judah shouted a war cry, then the true God himself defeated Jer·o·bo′am and all Israel before A·bi′jah and Judah. 16 And the sons of Israel took to flight from before Judah, and then God gave them into their hand. 17 And A·bi′jah and his people went striking them down with a vast slaughter; and the slain of Israel kept falling down, five hundred thousand chosen men. 18 Thus the sons of Israel were humbled at that time, but the sons of Judah proved superior because they leaned upon Jehovah the God of their forefathers. 19 And A·bi′jah kept chasing after Jer·o·bo′am and got to capture cities from him, Beth′el and its dependent towns, and Jesh′a·nah and its dependent towns, and E′phra·in and its dependent towns. 20 And Jer·o·bo′am did not retain any more power in the days of A·bi′jah; but Jehovah dealt him a blow, so that he died.

21 And A·bi′jah continued to strengthen himself. In time he got fourteen wives for himself, and became father to twenty-two sons and sixteen daughters. 22 And the rest of A·bi′jah’s affairs, even his ways and his words, are written in the exposition of the prophet Id′do.

2 Chronicles

19 Then Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah returned in peace to his own house at Jerusalem. 2 Je′hu the son of Ha·na′ni the visionary now went out before him and said to King Je·hosh′a·phat: “Is it to the wicked that help is to be given, and is it for those hating Jehovah that you should have love? And for this there is indignation against you from the person of Jehovah. 3 Nevertheless, there are good things that have been found with you, because you have cleared out the sacred poles from the land and you have prepared your heart to search for the true God.”

4 And Je·hosh′a·phat continued dwelling in Jerusalem; and he began to go out again among the people from Be′er-she′ba to the mountainous region of E′phra·im, that he might bring them back to Jehovah the God of their forefathers. 5 And he proceeded to station judges throughout the land in all the fortified cities of Judah, city by city. 6 And he went on to say to the judges: “See what YOU are doing, because it is not for man that YOU judge but it is for Jehovah; and he is with YOU in the matter of judgment. 7 And now let the dread of Jehovah come to be upon YOU. Be careful and act, for with Jehovah our God there is no unrighteousness or partiality or taking of a bribe.”

8 And in Jerusalem also Je·hosh′a·phat stationed some of the Levites and the priests and some of the heads of the paternal houses of Israel for the judgment of Jehovah and for the legal cases of the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 9 Further, he laid a command upon them, saying: “This is how YOU should do in the fear of Jehovah with faithfulness and with a complete heart. 10 As for every legal case that will come to YOU of YOUR brothers who are dwelling in their cities, involving the shedding of blood, involving law and commandment and regulations and judicial decisions, YOU must warn them that they may not do wrong against Jehovah and indignation may not have to take place against YOU and against YOUR brothers. This is how YOU should do that YOU may not incur guilt. 11 And here is Am·a·ri′ah the chief priest over YOU for every matter of Jehovah; and Zeb·a·di′ah the son of Ish′ma·el the leader of the house of Judah for every matter of the king; and as officers the Levites are available for YOU. Be strong and act, and let Jehovah prove to be with what is good.”

2 Chronicles

21 Finally Je·hosh′a·phat lay down with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David; and Je·ho′ram his son began to reign in place of him. 2 And he had brothers, Je·hosh′a·phat’s sons, Az·a·ri′ah and Je·hi′el and Zech·a·ri′ah and Az·a·ri′ah and Mi′cha·el and Sheph·a·ti′ah, all these being the sons of Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Israel. 3 Consequently their father gave them many gifts in silver and in gold and in choice things along with fortified cities in Judah; but the kingdom he gave to Je·ho′ram, for he was the firstborn.

4 When Je·ho′ram rose up over the kingdom of his father he proceeded to make his position strong, and so he killed all his brothers with the sword and also some of the princes of Israel. 5 Thirty-two years old was Je·ho′ram when he began to reign, and for eight years he reigned in Jerusalem. 6 And he went on walking in the way of the kings of Israel, just as those of the house of A′hab had done; for A′hab’s own daughter had become his wife, and he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. 7 And Jehovah did not want to bring the house of David to ruin, for the sake of the covenant that he had concluded with David, and just as he had said he would give him and his sons a lamp always.

8 In his days E′dom revolted from under the hand of Judah and then made a king to reign over them. 9 So Je·ho′ram together with his chiefs passed over and also all the chariots with him. And it came about that he rose up by night and went striking down the E′dom·ites that were surrounding him and also the chiefs of the chariots. 10 But E′dom kept up its revolt from under the hand of Judah down to this day. It was then that Lib′nah began to revolt at the same time from under his hand, because he had left Jehovah the God of his forefathers. 11 He himself also had made high places on the mountains of Judah, that he might cause the inhabitants of Jerusalem to have immoral intercourse, and that he might drive Judah away.

12 Eventually there came a writing to him from E·li′jah the prophet, saying: “This is what Jehovah the God of David your forefather has said, ‘Due to the fact that you have not walked in the ways of Je·hosh′a·phat your father or in the ways of A′sa the king of Judah, 13 but you walk in the way of the kings of Israel and cause Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to have immoral intercourse the same way that the house of A′hab caused the having of immoral intercourse, and even your own brothers, the household of your father, who were better than you, you have killed; 14 look! Jehovah is dealing a great blow to your people and to your sons and to your wives and to all your goods. 15 And you will be with many sicknesses, with a malady of your intestines, until your intestines have come out because of the sickness day by day.’”

16 Accordingly Jehovah aroused against Je·ho′ram the spirit of the Phi·lis′tines and the Arabs that were by the side of the E·thi·o′pi·ans. 17 So they came up into Judah and forced it open and took captive all the goods that were to be found in the king’s house and also his sons and his wives, and there was not left to him a son but Je·ho′a·haz, his youngest son. 18 And after all this Jehovah plagued him in his intestines with a sickness for which there was no healing. 19 And it came about that in the days to come, even when the term of two full years had expired, his intestines came out during his sickness, and he gradually died in his bad maladies; and his people did not make a burning for him like the burning for his forefathers. 20 Thirty-two years old he happened to be when he began to reign, and for eight years he reigned in Jerusalem. Finally he went away without being desired. So they buried him in the City of David, but not in the burial places of the kings.

2 Chronicles

22 Then the inhabitants of Jerusalem made A·ha·zi′ah his youngest son king in place of him, (for the marauder band that came with the Arabs to the camp had killed all the older ones,) and A·ha·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ram began to reign as king of Judah. 2 Twenty-two years old was A·ha·zi′ah when he began to reign, and for one year he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Ath·a·li′ah the granddaughter of Om′ri.

3 He himself also walked in the ways of the house of A′hab, for his mother herself became his counselor in doing wickedly. 4 And he went on doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, the same as the house of A′hab, for they themselves became counselors to him after the death of his father, to his ruination. 5 It was also in their counsel that he walked, so that he went with Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab the king of Israel to the war against Haz′a·el the king of Syria at Ra′moth-gil′e·ad, at which the shooters got to strike Je·ho′ram. 6 Hence he returned to get healed at Jez′re·el from the wounds that they had inflicted upon him at Ra′mah when he fought Haz′a·el the king of Syria.

As for Az·a·ri′ah the son of Je·ho′ram the king of Judah, he went down to see Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab in Jez′re·el, for he was sick. 7 But it was from God that the downfall of A·ha·zi′ah occurred by his coming to Je·ho′ram; and when he came, he went out with Je·ho′ram to Je′hu the grandson of Nim′shi, whom Jehovah had anointed to cut off the house of A′hab. 8 And it came about that as soon as Je′hu had entered into controversy with the house of A′hab, he got to find the princes of Judah and the sons of the brothers of A·ha·zi′ah, ministers of A·ha·zi′ah, and he proceeded to kill them. 9 Then he went looking for A·ha·zi′ah, and they finally captured him, as he was hiding in Sa·mar′i·a, and brought him to Je′hu. Then they put him to death and buried him, for they said: “He is the grandson of Je·hosh′a·phat, who searched for Jehovah with all his heart.” And there was no one of the house of A·ha·zi′ah to retain power for the kingdom.

10 As regards Ath·a·li′ah the mother of A·ha·zi′ah, she saw that her son had died. So she rose up and destroyed all the royal offspring of the house of Judah. 11 However, Je·ho·shab′e·ath the daughter of the king took Je·ho′ash the son of A·ha·zi′ah and stole him away from among the sons of the king that were to be put to death, and put him and his nursing woman in the inner room for the couches. And Je·ho·shab′e·ath the daughter of King Je·ho′ram, the wife of Je·hoi′a·da the priest, (for she herself happened to be the sister of A·ha·zi′ah,) kept him concealed because of Ath·a·li′ah, and she did not put him to death. 12 And he continued with them in the house of the true God hidden for six years, while Ath·a·li′ah was ruling as queen over the land.

2 Chronicles

24 Seven years old was Je·ho′ash when he began to reign, and for forty years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Zib′i·ah from Be′er-she′ba. 2 And Je·ho′ash kept doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes all the days of Je·hoi′a·da the priest. 3 And Je·hoi′a·da proceeded to get two wives for him, and he came to be father to sons and daughters.

4 Now it occurred afterward that it became close to the heart of Je·ho′ash to renovate the house of Jehovah. 5 Accordingly he collected the priests and the Levites together and said to them: “Go out to the cities of Judah and collect money from all Israel to repair the house of YOUR God from year to year; and YOU, for YOUR part, should act quickly in the matter.” And the Levites did not act quickly. 6 So the king called Je·hoi′a·da the head and said to him: “Why is it that you have not required an account of the Levites for bringing in from Judah and Jerusalem the sacred tax ordered by Moses the servant of Jehovah, even that of the congregation of Israel, for the tent of the Testimony? 7 For as regards Ath·a·li′ah the wicked woman, her sons themselves had broken into the house of the true God, and even all the holy things of the house of Jehovah they had rendered up to the Ba′als.” 8 Then the king said the word, and so they made a chest and put it outside at the gate of the house of Jehovah. 9 After that they issued a call throughout Judah and Jerusalem to bring to Jehovah the sacred tax ordered by Moses the servant of the true God upon Israel in the wilderness. 10 And all the princes and all the people began to rejoice, and they kept bringing and casting it into the chest until they all had given.

11 And it came about at the proper time he would bring the chest to the care of the king by the hand of the Levites, and, as soon as they saw that there was plenty of money, the secretary of the king and the commissioner of the chief priest came and then emptied the chest and lifted it up and returned it to its place. That was the way they did from day to day, so that they gathered money in abundance. 12 Then the king and Je·hoi′a·da would give it to the doers of the work of the service of Jehovah’s house, and they came to be hirers of the stonecutters and of the craftsmen for renovating Jehovah’s house, and also of the workers in iron and copper for repairing Jehovah’s house. 13 And the doers of the work began operations, and the repair work kept advancing by their hand, and finally they made the house of the true God stand as it structurally should and made it strong. 14 And as soon as they had finished they brought before the king and Je·hoi′a·da the rest of the money, and they proceeded to make utensils for the house of Jehovah, utensils for the ministry and for making offerings and cups and utensils of gold and of silver; and they came to be offerers of burnt sacrifices in the house of Jehovah constantly all the days of Je·hoi′a·da.

15 And Je·hoi′a·da got to be old and satisfied with years and gradually died, being a hundred and thirty years old at his death. 16 So they buried him in the City of David along with the kings, because he had done good in Israel and with the true God and His house.

17 And after Je·hoi′a·da’s death the princes of Judah came in and proceeded to bow down to the king. At that time the king listened to them. 18 And gradually they left the house of Jehovah the God of their forefathers and began serving the sacred poles and the idols, so that there came to be indignation against Judah and Jerusalem because of this guilt of theirs. 19 And he kept sending prophets among them to bring them back to Jehovah; and they kept bearing witness against them, but they did not give ear.

20 And God’s spirit itself enveloped Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da the priest, so that he stood up above the people and said to them: “This is what the true God has said, ‘Why are YOU overstepping the commandments of Jehovah, so that YOU cannot prove successful? Because YOU have left Jehovah, he will, in turn, leave YOU.’” 21 Finally they conspired against him and pelted him with stones at the king’s commandment in the courtyard of Jehovah’s house. 22 And Je·ho′ash the king did not remember the loving-kindness that Je·hoi′a·da his father had exercised toward him, so that he killed his son, who, when he was at the point of dying, said: “Let Jehovah see to it and ask it back.”

23 And it came about at the turn of the year a military force of Syria came up against him, and they began to invade Judah and Jerusalem. Then they brought all the princes of the people to ruin from among the people, and all their spoil they sent to the king of Damascus. 24 For it was with a small number of men that the military force of the Syrians made an invasion, and Jehovah himself gave into their hand a military force of very great number, because they had left Jehovah the God of their forefathers; and upon Je·ho′ash they executed acts of judgment. 25 And when they went away from him (for they left him with many diseases), his own servants conspired against him because of the blood of the sons of Je·hoi′a·da the priest; and they got to kill him upon his own couch, so that he died. Then they buried him in the City of David, but they did not bury him in the burial places of the kings.

26 And these were the conspirators against him: Za′bad the son of Shim′e·ath the Am′mon·it·ess and Je·hoz′a·bad the son of Shim′rith the Mo′ab·i·tess. 27 As for his sons and the abundance of the pronouncement against him and the founding of the house of the true God, there they are written in the exposition of the Book of the Kings. And Am·a·zi′ah his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Chronicles

26 Then all the people of Judah took Uz·zi′ah, he being sixteen years old, and they made him king in place of his father Am·a·zi′ah. 2 He it was that rebuilt E′loth and then restored it to Judah after the king had lain down with his forefathers. 3 Sixteen years old was Uz·zi′ah when he began to reign, and for fifty-two years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Je·co·li′ah of Jerusalem. 4 And he kept doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that Am·a·zi′ah his father had done. 5 And he continually tended to search for God in the days of Zech·a·ri′ah, the instructor in the fear of the true God; and, in the days of his searching for Jehovah, the true God made him prosperous.

6 And he proceeded to go out and fight against the Phi·lis′tines and break through the wall of Gath and the wall of Jab′neh and the wall of Ash′dod, after which he built cities in Ash′dod territory and among the Phi·lis′tines. 7 And the true God continued to help him against the Phi·lis′tines and against the Arabians that were dwelling in Gur·ba′al and the Me·u′nim. 8 And the Am′mon·ites began to give tribute to Uz·zi′ah. Eventually his fame went even as far as Egypt, for he displayed strength to an extraordinary degree. 9 Moreover, Uz·zi′ah built towers in Jerusalem by the Corner Gate and by the Valley Gate and by the Buttress, and made them strong. 10 Further, he built towers in the wilderness, and hewed out many cisterns (for there was a great deal of livestock that became his), and also in the She·phe′lah and on the tableland. There were farmers and vinedressers in the mountains and in Car′mel, for a lover of agriculture he proved to be.

11 Moreover, Uz·zi′ah came to have a force engaging in war, those going out on military service in troops, by the number of their registration by the hand of Je·i′el the secretary and Ma·a·sei′ah the officer under the control of Han·a·ni′ah of the king’s princes. 12 The entire number of the heads of the paternal houses, of the valiant, mighty men, was two thousand six hundred. 13 And under their control the army forces were three hundred and seven thousand five hundred men engaging in war with the power of a military force to help the king against the enemy. 14 And Uz·zi′ah continued to prepare for them, for the entire army, shields and lances and helmets and coats of mail and bows and slingstones. 15 Further, he made in Jerusalem engines of war, the invention of engineers, that they might come to be upon the towers and upon the corners, to shoot arrows and great stones. Consequently his fame went out to a great distance, for he was helped wonderfully until he was strong.

16 However, as soon as he was strong, his heart became haughty even to the point of causing ruin, so that he acted unfaithfully against Jehovah his God and came into the temple of Jehovah to burn incense upon the altar of incense. 17 Immediately Az·a·ri′ah the priest and with him priests of Jehovah, eighty valiant men, came in after him. 18 Then they stood up against Uz·zi′ah the king and said to him: “It is not your business, O Uz·zi′ah, to burn incense to Jehovah, but it is the business of the priests the sons of Aaron, the ones sanctified, to burn incense. Go out from the sanctuary; for you have acted unfaithfully, and it is not for any glory to you on the part of Jehovah God.”

19 But Uz·zi′ah became enraged while in his hand there was a censer for burning incense, and, during his rage against the priests, leprosy itself flashed up in his forehead before the priests in the house of Jehovah beside the altar of incense. 20 When Az·a·ri′ah the chief priest and all the priests turned toward him, why, there he was stricken with leprosy in his forehead! So they excitedly began to remove him from there, and he himself also hastened to go out, because Jehovah had smitten him.

21 And Uz·zi′ah the king continued to be a leper until the day of his death, and he kept dwelling in a house exempt from duties, as a leper; for he had been severed from the house of Jehovah, while Jo′tham his son was over the king’s house, judging the people of the land.

22 And the rest of the affairs of Uz·zi′ah, the first and the last, Isaiah the son of A′moz the prophet has written. 23 Finally Uz·zi′ah lay down with his forefathers; and so they buried him with his forefathers, but in the burial field that belonged to the kings, for they said: “He is a leper.” And Jo′tham his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Chronicles

27 Twenty-five years old was Jo′tham when he began to reign, and for sixteen years he reigned in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Je·ru′shah the daughter of Za′dok. 2 And he kept doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that Uz·zi′ah his father had done. Only he did not invade the temple of Jehovah. However, the people were yet acting ruinously. 3 He himself built the upper gate of Jehovah’s house, and on the wall of O′phel he did a great deal of building. 4 And cities he built in the mountainous region of Judah, and in the woodlands he built fortified places and towers. 5 And he himself warred against the king of the sons of Am′mon and eventually proved stronger than they were, so that the sons of Am′mon gave him in that year a hundred silver talents and ten thousand cor measures of wheat and ten thousand of barley. This was what the sons of Am′mon paid to him, also in the second year and the third. 6 So Jo′tham kept strengthening himself, for he prepared his ways before Jehovah his God.

7 As for the rest of the affairs of Jo′tham and all his wars and his ways, there they are written in the Book of the Kings of Israel and of Judah. 8 Twenty-five years old he happened to be when he began to reign, and for sixteen years he reigned in Jerusalem. 9 Finally Jo′tham lay down with his forefathers, and they buried him in the City of David. And A′haz his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Chronicles

28 Twenty years old was A′haz when he began to reign, and for sixteen years he reigned in Jerusalem, and he did not do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes like David his forefather. 2 But he walked in the ways of the kings of Israel, and even molten statues he made of the Ba′als. 3 And he himself made sacrificial smoke in the valley of the son of Hin′nom and proceeded to burn up his sons in the fire, according to the detestable things of the nations that Jehovah had driven out from before the sons of Israel. 4 And he regularly sacrificed and made sacrificial smoke on the high places and upon the hills and under every sort of luxuriant tree.

5 Consequently Jehovah his God gave him into the hand of the king of Syria, so that they struck him and carried off from him a great number of captives and brought them to Damascus. And also into the hand of the king of Israel he was given, so that he struck him with a great slaughter. 6 Accordingly Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah killed in Judah a hundred and twenty thousand in one day, all valiant men, because of their leaving Jehovah the God of their forefathers. 7 Further, Zich′ri, a mighty man of E′phra·im, killed Ma·a·sei′ah the son of the king and Az·ri′kam the leader of the household and El·ka′nah the one next to the king. 8 Moreover, the sons of Israel took two hundred thousand of their brothers captive, women, sons and daughters; and also a great deal of spoil they took from them as plunder, after which they brought the spoil to Sa·mar′i·a.

9 And there happened to be a prophet of Jehovah there whose name was O′ded. So he went out before the army that was coming to Sa·mar′i·a and said to them: “Look! It was because of the rage of Jehovah the God of YOUR forefathers against Judah that he gave them into YOUR hand, so that YOU did a killing among them with a raging that has reached clear to the heavens. 10 And now the sons of Judah and of Jerusalem YOU are thinking of reducing to menservants and maidservants for yourselves. Nevertheless, are there not with YOU yourselves cases of guilt against Jehovah YOUR God? 11 And now listen to me and return the captives that YOU have captured from YOUR brothers, for Jehovah’s burning anger is against YOU.”

12 At that certain men of the heads of the sons of E′phra·im, Az·a·ri′ah the son of Je·ho·ha′nan, Ber·e·chi′ah the son of Me·shil′le·moth and Je·hiz·ki′ah the son of Shal′lum and A·ma′sa the son of Had′lai, rose up against those coming in from the military campaign, 13 and they said to them: “YOU must not bring in the captives here, for it will result in guilt against Jehovah on our part. YOU are thinking of adding to our sins and to our guilt, for abundant is the guilt we have, and there is burning anger against Israel.” 14 Accordingly the armed men left the captives and the plunder before the princes and all the congregation. 15 Then the men that were designated by their names rose up and took hold of the captives, and all their naked ones they clothed from the spoil. So they clothed them and furnished them with sandals and fed them and gave them drink and greased them. Furthermore, in the case of anyone tottering, they gave them transportation on the asses and brought them to Jer′i·cho, the city of palm trees, beside their brothers. After that they returned to Sa·mar′i·a.

16 At that time King A′haz sent to the kings of As·syr′i·a for them to help him. 17 And once again the E′dom·ites themselves came in and went striking down Judah and carrying off captives. 18 As for the Phi·lis′tines, they made a raid upon the cities of the She·phe′lah and the Neg′eb of Judah and got to capture Beth-she′mesh and Ai′ja·lon and Ge·de′roth and So′co and its dependent towns and Tim′nah and its dependent towns and Gim′zo and its dependent towns; and they took up dwelling there. 19 For Jehovah humbled Judah on account of A′haz the king of Israel, because he let unrestraint grow in Judah, and there was an acting with great unfaithfulness toward Jehovah.

20 Eventually Til′gath-pil·ne′ser the king of As·syr′i·a came against him and caused him distress, and did not strengthen him. 21 For A′haz stripped the house of Jehovah and the house of the king and of the princes and thus made a gift to the king of As·syr′i·a; but it was of no assistance to him. 22 However, at the time that he was causing him distress, he acted unfaithfully still more toward Jehovah, that is, King A′haz did. 23 And he began to sacrifice to the gods of Damascus that were striking him, and he went on to say: “Because the gods of the kings of Syria are helping them, to them I shall sacrifice, that they may help me.” And they themselves became to him a cause for making him and all Israel stumble. 24 Furthermore, A′haz gathered together the utensils of the house of the true God and cut to pieces the utensils of the house of the true God, and closed the doors of the house of Jehovah, and made altars for himself at every corner in Jerusalem. 25 And in all cities, even the cities of Judah, he made high places for making sacrificial smoke to other gods, so that he offended Jehovah the God of his forefathers.

26 As for the rest of his affairs and all his ways, the first and the last, there they are written in the Book of the Kings of Judah and of Israel. 27 Finally A′haz lay down with his forefathers, and they buried him in the city, in Jerusalem, for they did not bring him into the burial places of the kings of Israel. And Hez·e·ki′ah his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Chronicles

31 And as soon as they finished all this, all the Israelites that were found there went out to the cities of Judah, and they proceeded to break up the sacred pillars and cut down the sacred poles and pull down the high places and the altars out of all Judah and Benjamin and in E′phra·im and Ma·nas′seh until they had finished; after which all the sons of Israel returned to their cities, each one to his own possession.

2 Then Hez·e·ki′ah set the divisions of the priests and of the Levites in their divisions, each one in accordance with its service for the priests and for the Levites as regards the burnt offering and the communion sacrifices to minister and to give thanks and praise in the gates of the camps of Jehovah. 3 And there was a portion of the king from his own goods for the burnt offerings, for the burnt offerings of the morning and the evening, and also the burnt offerings for the sabbaths and for the new moons and for the festival seasons, according to what is written in the law of Jehovah.

4 Furthermore, he said to the people, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, to give the portion of the priests and of the Levites, in order that they might adhere strictly to the law of Jehovah. 5 And as soon as the word broke forth, the sons of Israel increased the firstfruits of the grain, new wine, and oil and honey and all the produce of the field, and the tenth of everything they brought in abundantly. 6 And the sons of Israel and of Judah that were dwelling in the cities of Judah, even they themselves brought in the tenth of cattle and sheep and the tenth of the holy things, the things sanctified to Jehovah their God. They brought in and so gave heaps upon heaps. 7 In the third month they started the heaps by laying the lowest layer, and in the seventh month they finished. 8 When Hez·e·ki′ah and the princes came and saw the heaps, they proceeded to bless Jehovah and his people Israel.

9 In time Hez·e·ki′ah inquired of the priests and the Levites concerning the heaps. 10 Then Az·a·ri′ah the chief priest of the house of Za′dok said to him, yes, he said: “From the time they started to bring the contribution into the house of Jehovah there has been an eating and getting satisfied and having a surplus in abundance; for Jehovah himself has blessed his people, and what has been left over is this great plenty.”

11 At this Hez·e·ki′ah said to prepare dining rooms in the house of Jehovah. Accordingly they prepared them. 12 And they kept bringing in the contribution and the tenth and the holy things in faithfulness; and Con·a·ni′ah the Levite was in charge of them as leader, and Shim′e·i his brother was second. 13 And Je·hi′el and Az·a·zi′ah and Na′hath and As′a·hel and Jer′i·moth and Jo′za·bad and E′li·el and Is·ma·chi′ah and Ma′hath and Be·nai′ah were commissioners at the side of Con·a·ni′ah and Shim′e·i his brother, by the order of Hez·e·ki′ah the king, and Az·a·ri′ah was the leading one of the house of the true God. 14 And Ko′re the son of Im′nah the Levite was the gatekeeper to the east, in charge of the voluntary offerings of the true God, to give Jehovah’s contribution and the most holy things. 15 And under his control there were E′den and Mi·ni′a·min and Jesh′u·a and She·mai′ah, Am·a·ri′ah and Shec·a·ni′ah, in the cities of the priests, in office of trust, to give to their brothers in the divisions, equally to great and small; 16 apart from their genealogical enrollment of the males from three years of age upward, of all those coming to the house of Jehovah as a daily matter of course, for their service by their obligations according to their divisions.

17 This is the genealogical enrollment of the priests by the house of their fathers and also of the Levites, from the age of twenty years upward, by their obligations in their divisions; 18 both for the genealogical enrollment among all their little ones, their wives and their sons and their daughters, for all the congregation, because in their office of trust they proceeded to sanctify themselves for what was holy; 19 and for the sons of Aaron, the priests, in the fields of pasture ground of their cities. In all the different cities there were men that had been designated by their names, to give portions to every male among the priests and to the entire genealogical enrollment among the Levites.

20 And Hez·e·ki′ah proceeded to do like this in all Judah, and he continued to do what was good and right and faithful before Jehovah his God. 21 And in every work that he started in the service of the house of the true God and in the law and in the commandment to search for his God, it was with all his heart that he acted, and he proved successful.

2 Chronicles

32 After these things and this faithful course Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a came and proceeded to invade Judah and camp against the fortified cities, and kept thinking of making them his by a breakthrough.

2 When Hez·e·ki′ah saw that Sen·nach′er·ib had come with his face set for war against Jerusalem, 3 then he decided with his princes and his mighty men to stop up the waters of the springs that were outside the city; and so they helped him. 4 Accordingly many people were collected together, and they went stopping up all the fountains and the torrent that floods through the middle of the land, saying: “Why should the kings of As·syr′i·a come and actually find a great deal of water?”

5 Furthermore, he took courage and built up all the broken-down wall and raised towers upon it, and on the outside another wall, and repaired the Mound of the City of David, and made missiles in abundance and shields. 6 And he proceeded to put military chiefs over the people and collect them to him at the public square of the gate of the city and speak to the heart of them, saying: 7 “Be courageous and strong. Do not be afraid nor be terrified because of the king of As·syr′i·a and on account of all the crowd that is with him; for with us there are more than there are with him. 8 With him there is an arm of flesh, but with us there is Jehovah our God to help us and to fight our battles.” And the people began to brace themselves upon the words of Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah.

9 It was after this that Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a sent his servants to Jerusalem, while he was at La′chish and all his imperial might with him, to Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah and to all the Ju·de′ans that were in Jerusalem, saying:

10 “This is what Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a has said, ‘In what is it that YOU are trusting while sitting quiet under siege in Jerusalem? 11 Is not Hez·e·ki′ah alluring YOU so as to give YOU over to die by famine and by thirst, saying: “Jehovah our God himself will deliver us out of the palm of the king of As·syr′i·a”? 12 Is it not Hez·e·ki′ah himself that removed his high places and his altars and then said to Judah and to Jerusalem: “Before one altar YOU should bow and upon it YOU should make sacrificial smoke”? 13 Do YOU not know what I myself and my forefathers did to all the peoples of the lands? Did the gods of the nations of the lands at all prove able to deliver their land out of my hand? 14 Who was there among all the gods of these nations that my forefathers devoted to destruction that proved able to deliver his people out of my hand, so that YOUR God should be able to deliver YOU out of my hand? 15 And now do not let Hez·e·ki′ah deceive YOU or allure YOU like this and do not put faith in him, for no god of any nation or kingdom was able to deliver his people out of my hand and out of the hand of my forefathers. How much less, then, will YOUR own God deliver YOU out of my hand!’”

16 And his servants spoke yet further against Jehovah the true God and against Hez·e·ki′ah his servant. 17 Even letters he wrote to reproach Jehovah the God of Israel and to talk against him, saying: “Like the gods of the nations of the lands who did not deliver their people out of my hand, so the God of Hez·e·ki′ah will not deliver his people out of my hand.” 18 And they kept calling with a loud voice in the Jews’ language to the people of Jerusalem that were upon the wall, to make them afraid and to disturb them, in order that they might capture the city. 19 And they went on speaking against the God of Jerusalem the same way as against the gods of the peoples of the earth, the work of man’s hands. 20 But Hez·e·ki′ah the king and Isaiah the son of A′moz, the prophet, kept praying over this and crying to the heavens for aid.

21 And Jehovah proceeded to send an angel and efface every valiant, mighty man and leader and chief in the camp of the king of As·syr′i·a, so that he went back with shame of face to his own land. Later on he entered the house of his god and there certain ones that had come out of his own inward parts felled him with the sword. 22 Thus Jehovah saved Hez·e·ki′ah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem out of the hand of Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a and out of the hand of all others and gave them rest all around. 23 And there were many bringing gifts to Jehovah at Jerusalem and choice things to Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah, and he came to be exalted in the eyes of all the nations after that.

24 In those days Hez·e·ki′ah fell sick to the point of dying, and he began to pray to Jehovah. So He talked to him, and a portent He gave him. 25 But according to the benefit rendered him Hez·e·ki′ah made no return, for his heart became haughty and there came to be indignation against him and against Judah and Jerusalem. 26 However, Hez·e·ki′ah humbled himself for the haughtiness of his heart, he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and Jehovah’s indignation did not come upon them in the days of Hez·e·ki′ah.

27 And Hez·e·ki′ah came to have riches and glory to a very great amount; and storehouses he made for himself for silver and for gold and for precious stones and for balsam oil and for shields and for all the desirable articles; 28 and also storage places for the produce of grain and new wine and oil, and also stalls for all the different sorts of beasts and stalls for the droves. 29 And cities he acquired for himself, and also livestock of the flock and of the herd in abundance; for God gave him very many goods. 30 And Hez·e·ki′ah was the one that stopped up the upper source of the waters of Gi′hon and kept them directed straight along down to the west to the City of David, and Hez·e·ki′ah continued to prove successful in every work of his. 31 And thus it was that by the spokesmen of the princes of Babylon that were sent to him to inquire about the portent that had happened in the land, the true God left him to put him to the test, to get to know everything in his heart.

32 As for the rest of the affairs of Hez·e·ki′ah and his acts of loving-kindness, there they are written in the vision of Isaiah the prophet, the son of A′moz, in the Book of the Kings of Judah and Israel. 33 Finally Hez·e·ki′ah lay down with his forefathers, and they buried him in the ascent to the burial places of the sons of David; and honor was what all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem rendered to him at his death. And Ma·nas′seh his son began to reign in place of him.

2 Chronicles

35 Then Jo·si′ah held in Jerusalem a passover to Jehovah and they slaughtered the passover victim on the fourteenth day of the first month. 2 So he stationed the priests over the things under their care and encouraged them in the service of the house of Jehovah. 3 And he went on to say to the Levites, the instructors of all Israel, those holy to Jehovah: “Put the holy Ark in the house that Sol′o·mon the son of David the king of Israel built; it is not YOURS as a burden upon the shoulder. Now serve Jehovah YOUR God and his people Israel. 4 And make preparation by the house of YOUR forefathers according to YOUR divisions, by the writing of David the king of Israel and by the writing of Sol′o·mon his son. 5 And stand in the holy place by the classes of the house of the forefathers for YOUR brothers, the sons of the people, and the portion of a paternal house belonging to the Levites. 6 And slaughter the passover victim and sanctify yourselves and make preparation for YOUR brothers to do according to the word of Jehovah by means of Moses.”

7 Jo·si′ah now contributed to the sons of the people flocks, male lambs and male kids, the whole for the passover victims for all who were to be found, to the number of thirty thousand, and cattle, three thousand. These were from the goods of the king. 8 And his princes themselves made a contribution as a voluntary offering for the people, for the priests and for the Levites. Hil·ki′ah and Zech·a·ri′ah and Je·hi′el themselves as leaders of the house of the true God gave to the priests for the passover victims two thousand six hundred, and three hundred cattle. 9 And Con·a·ni′ah and She·mai′ah and Ne·than′el his brothers and Hash·a·bi′ah and Je·i′el and Jo′za·bad, the chiefs of the Levites, contributed to the Levites for passover victims five thousand, and five hundred cattle.

10 And the service was prepared and the priests kept standing at their places, and the Levites by their divisions, according to the king’s commandment. 11 And they proceeded to slaughter the passover victim and the priests sprinkled the blood from their hand, while the Levites were stripping the skins off. 12 Further, they prepared the burnt offerings so as to give them to the classes by the paternal house, to the sons of the people, so as to make a presentation to Jehovah according to what is written in the book of Moses; and thus also with the cattle. 13 And they went cooking the passover offering over the fire according to the custom; and the things made holy they cooked in cooking pots and in round-bottomed pots and in banquet bowls, after which they brought it quickly to all the sons of the people. 14 And afterward they prepared for themselves and for the priests, because the priests the sons of Aaron were engaged in offering up the burnt sacrifices and the fat pieces until night, and the Levites, for their part, prepared for themselves and for the priests the sons of Aaron.

15 And the singers the sons of A′saph were at their office according to the commandment of David and of A′saph and of He′man and of Je·du′thun the visionary of the king; and the gatekeepers were at the different gates. There was no need for them to turn aside from their service, because their brothers the Levites themselves prepared for them. 16 And all the service of Jehovah was prepared on that day to hold the passover and to offer up the burnt offerings upon the altar of Jehovah, according to the commandment of King Jo·si′ah.

17 And the sons of Israel that were to be found proceeded to hold the passover at that time and also the festival of the unfermented cakes for seven days. 18 And there had never been held a passover like it in Israel since the days of Samuel the prophet, neither had any of the other kings of Israel themselves held a passover like that which Jo·si′ah and the priests and the Levites and all Judah and Israel that were to be found and the inhabitants of Jerusalem held. 19 In the eighteenth year of Jo·si′ah’s reign this passover was held.

20 After all this when Jo·si′ah had prepared the house, Ne′cho the king of Egypt came up to fight at Car′che·mish by the Eu·phra′tes. Then Jo·si′ah went out to an encounter with him. 21 At that he sent messengers to him, saying: “What do I have to do with you, O king of Judah? It is not against you that I am coming today, but it is against another house that my fight is and that God himself said that I should cause disturbance. Refrain for your own sake because of God, who is with me, and do not let him bring you to ruin.” 22 And Jo·si′ah did not turn his face away from him, but to fight against him he disguised himself and did not listen to the words of Ne′cho from the mouth of God. So he came to fight in the valley plain of Me·gid′do.

23 And the shooters got to shoot at King Jo·si′ah, so that the king said to his servants: “Take me down, for I have been very severely wounded.” 24 Accordingly his servants took him down from the chariot and had him ride in the second war chariot that was his and brought him to Jerusalem. Thus he died and was buried in the graveyard of his forefathers; and all Judah and Jerusalem were mourning over Jo·si′ah. 25 And Jeremiah began to chant over Jo·si′ah; and all the male singers and female singers keep talking about Jo·si′ah in their dirges down till today; and they have them set as a regulation over Israel, and there they are written among the dirges.

26 As for the rest of the affairs of Jo·si′ah and his acts of loving-kindness, according to what is written in the law of Jehovah, 27 and his affairs, the first and the last, there they are written in the Book of the Kings of Israel and Judah.

Ezra

1 And in the first year of Cyrus the king of Persia, that Jehovah’s word from the mouth of Jeremiah might be accomplished, Jehovah roused the spirit of Cyrus the king of Persia so that he caused a cry to pass through all his realm, and also in writing, saying:

2 “This is what Cyrus the king of Persia has said, ‘All the kingdoms of the earth Jehovah the God of the heavens has given me, and he himself has commissioned me to build him a house in Jerusalem, which is in Judah. 3 Whoever there is among YOU of all his people, may his God prove to be with him. So let him go up to Jerusalem, which is in Judah, and rebuild the house of Jehovah the God of Israel—he is the true God—which was in Jerusalem. 4 As for anyone that is left from all the places where he is residing as an alien, let the men of his place assist him with silver and with gold and with goods and with domestic animals along with the voluntary offering for the house of the true God, which was in Jerusalem.’”

5 Then the heads of the fathers of Judah and of Benjamin and the priests and the Levites rose up, even everyone whose spirit the true God had roused, to go up and rebuild the house of Jehovah, which was in Jerusalem. 6 As for all those round about them, they strengthened their hands with utensils of silver, with gold, with goods and with domestic animals and with choice things, besides all that which was voluntarily offered.

7 Also, King Cyrus himself brought forth the utensils of the house of Jehovah, which Neb·u·chad·nez′zar had brought out from Jerusalem and then put in the house of his god. 8 And Cyrus the king of Persia proceeded to bring them forth under the control of Mith′re·dath the treasurer and to number them out to Shesh·baz′zar the chieftain of Judah.

9 Now these are the numbers of them: thirty basket-shaped vessels of gold, a thousand basket-shaped vessels of silver, twenty-nine replacement vessels, 10 thirty small bowls of gold, four hundred and ten small secondary bowls of silver, a thousand other utensils. 11 All the utensils of gold and of silver were five thousand four hundred. Everything Shesh·baz′zar brought up, along with the bringing up of the exiled people out of Babylon to Jerusalem.

Ezra

4 When the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin heard that the sons of the Exile were building a temple to Jehovah the God of Israel, 2 they immediately approached Ze·rub′ba·bel and the heads of the paternal houses and said to them: “Let us build along with YOU; for, just like YOU, we search for YOUR God and to him we are sacrificing since the days of E′sar-had′don the king of As·syr′i·a, who brought us up here.” 3 However, Ze·rub′ba·bel and Jesh′u·a and the rest of the heads of the paternal houses of Israel said to them: “YOU have nothing to do with us in building a house to our God, for we ourselves shall together build to Jehovah the God of Israel, just as King Cyrus the king of Persia has commanded us.”

4 At that the people of the land were continually weakening the hands of the people of Judah and disheartening them from building, 5 and hiring counselors against them to frustrate their counsel all the days of Cyrus the king of Persia down till the reign of Da·ri′us the king of Persia. 6 And in the reign of A·has·u·e′rus, at the start of his reign, they wrote an accusation against the inhabitants of Judah and Jerusalem. 7 Also, in the days of Ar·ta·xerx′es, Bish′lam, Mith′re·dath, Tab′e·el and the rest of his colleagues wrote to Ar·ta·xerx′es the king of Persia, and the writing of the letter was written in Ar·a·ma′ic characters and translated into the Ar·a·ma′ic language.

8 Re′hum the chief government official and Shim′shai the scribe wrote a letter against Jerusalem to Ar·ta·xerx′es the king, as follows: 9 Then Re′hum the chief government official and Shim′shai the scribe and the rest of their colleagues, the judges and the lesser governors across the River, the secretaries, the people of E′rech, the Babylonians, the inhabitants of Su′sa, that is, the E′lam·ites, 10 and the rest of the nations whom the great and honorable As′e·nap·par took into exile and settled in the cities of Sa·mar′i·a, and the rest beyond the River, ——; and now 11 this is a copy of the letter that they sent concerning it:

“To Ar·ta·xerx′es the king your servants, the men beyond the River: And now 12 let it become known to the king that the Jews who came up here from you to us have come to Jerusalem. They are building the rebellious and bad city, and they proceed to finish the walls and to repair the foundations. 13 Now let it become known to the king that, if this city should be rebuilt and its walls be finished, neither tax nor tribute nor toll will they give, and it will cause loss to the treasuries of the kings. 14 Now inasmuch as we do eat the salt of the palace, and it is not proper for us to see the denuding of the king, on this account we have sent and made it known to the king, 15 that there may be an investigation of the book of records of your ancestors. Then you will find in the book of records and learn that that city is a city rebellious and causing loss to kings and jurisdictional districts, and within it there were movers of revolt from the days of old. For this reason that city has been laid waste. 16 We are making known to the king that, if that city should be rebuilt and its walls be finished, you also will certainly have no share beyond the River.”

17 The king sent word to Re′hum the chief government official and Shim′shai the scribe and the rest of their colleagues who were dwelling in Sa·mar′i·a and the rest beyond the River:

“Greetings! And now 18 the official document that YOU have sent us has been distinctly read before me. 19 So an order has been put through by me, and they have investigated and found that that city has from the days of old been one rising up against kings and one in which rebellion and revolt have been carried on. 20 And there proved to be strong kings over Jerusalem and governing all beyond the River, and tax, tribute and toll were being given to them. 21 Now PUT an order through for these able-bodied men to stop, that that city may not be rebuilt until the order is put through by me. 22 So be careful that there be no negligence about acting in this regard, that the harm may not increase to the injury of kings.”

23 Now after the copy of the official document of Ar·ta·xerx′es the king had been read before Re′hum and Shim′shai the scribe and their colleagues, they went in a hurry to Jerusalem to the Jews and stopped them by force of arms. 24 It was then that the work on the house of God, which was in Jerusalem, stopped; and it continued stopped until the second year of the reign of Da·ri′us the king of Persia.

Nehemiah

2 And it came about in the month Ni′san, in the twentieth year of Ar·ta·xerx′es the king, that wine was before him, and I as usual took up the wine and gave it to the king. But never had I happened to be gloomy before him. 2 So the king said to me: “Why is your face gloomy when you yourself are not sick? This is nothing but a gloominess of heart.” At this I became very much afraid.

3 Then I said to the king: “Let the king himself live to time indefinite! Why should not my face become gloomy when the city, the house of the burial places of my forefathers, is devastated, and its very gates have been eaten up with fire?” 4 In turn the king said to me: “What is this that you are seeking to secure?” At once I prayed to the God of the heavens. 5 After that I said to the king: “If to the king it does seem good, and if your servant seems good before you, that you would send me to Judah, to the city of the burial places of my forefathers, that I may rebuild it.” 6 At this the king said to me, as his queenly consort was sitting beside him: “How long will your journey come to be and when will you return?” So it seemed good before the king that he should send me, when I gave him the appointed time.

7 And I went on to say to the king: “If to the king it does seem good, let letters be given me to the governors beyond the River, that they may let me pass until I come to Judah; 8 also a letter to A′saph the keeper of the park that belongs to the king, that he may give me trees to build with timber the gates of the Castle that belongs to the house, and for the wall of the city and for the house into which I am to enter.” So the king gave them to me, according to the good hand of my God upon me.

9 Eventually I came to the governors beyond the River and gave them the letters of the king. Moreover, the king sent with me chiefs of the military force and horsemen. 10 When San·bal′lat the Hor′o·nite and To·bi′ah the servant, the Am′mon·ite, got to hear of it, then it seemed to them something very bad that a man had come to seek something good for the sons of Israel.

11 At length I came to Jerusalem, and I continued there for three days. 12 Then I rose up by night, I and a few men with me, and I did not tell a man what my God was putting into my heart to do for Jerusalem, and there was no domestic animal with me except the domestic animal on which I was riding. 13 And I proceeded to go out by the Valley Gate by night and in front of the Fountain of the Big Snake and to the Gate of the Ash-heaps, and I was constantly examining the walls of Jerusalem, how they were broken down and the gates of it had been eaten up by fire. 14 And I went passing along to the Fountain Gate and to the King’s Pool, and there was no place for the domestic animal under me to pass along. 15 But I kept on ascending in the torrent valley by night, and I kept on examining the wall; after which I came back and entered by the Valley Gate, and so got back.

16 And the deputy rulers themselves did not know where I had gone and what I was doing; and to the Jews and the priests and the nobles and the deputy rulers and the rest of the doers of the work I had not yet told anything. 17 Finally I said to them: “YOU are seeing the bad plight in which we are, how Jerusalem is devastated and its gates have been burned with fire. Come and let us rebuild the wall of Jerusalem, that we may no longer continue to be a reproach.” 18 And I went on to tell them of the hand of my God, how it was good upon me, and also of the king’s words that he had said to me. At this they said: “Let us get up, and we must build.” So they strengthened their hands for the good work.

19 Now when San·bal′lat the Hor′o·nite and To·bi′ah the servant, the Am′mon·ite, and Ge′shem the Arabian heard of it, they began to deride us and look on us despisingly and say: “What is this thing that YOU are doing? Is it against the king that YOU are rebelling?” 20 However, I replied to them and said to them: “The God of the heavens is the One that will grant us success, and we ourselves, his servants, shall get up, and we must build; but YOU yourselves have no share, nor just claim, nor memorial in Jerusalem.”

Nehemiah

3 And E·li′a·shib the high priest and his brothers, the priests, proceeded to get up and build the Sheep Gate. They themselves sanctified it and went setting up its doors; and as far as the Tower of Me′ah they sanctified it, as far as the Tower of Ha·nan′el. 2 And at their side the men of Jer′i·cho did building. And at their side Zac′cur the son of Im′ri did building.

3 And the Fish Gate was what the sons of Has·se·na′ah built; they themselves timbered it and then set up its doors, its bolts and its bars. 4 And at their side Mer′e·moth the son of U·ri′jah the son of Hak′koz did repair work, and at their side Me·shul′lam the son of Ber·e·chi′ah the son of Me·shez′a·bel did repair work; and at their side Za′dok the son of Ba′a·na did repair work. 5 And at their side the Te·ko′ites did repair work; but their majestic ones themselves did not bring the back of their neck into the service of their masters.

6 And the Gate of the Old City was what Joi′a·da the son of Pa·se′ah and Me·shul′lam the son of Bes·o·dei′ah repaired; they themselves timbered it and then set up its doors and its bolts and its bars. 7 And at their side Mel·a·ti′ah the Gib′e·on·ite and Ja′don the Me·ron′o·thite, did repair work, men of Gib′e·on and Miz′pah, belonging to the throne of the governor beyond the River. 8 At his side Uz′zi·el the son of Har·hai′ah, goldsmiths, did repair work; and at his side Han·a·ni′ah a member of the ointment mixers did repair work; and they proceeded to flagstone Jerusalem as far as the Broad Wall. 9 And at their side Re·pha′iah the son of Hur, a prince of half the district of Jerusalem, did repair work. 10 And at their side Je·da′iah the son of Ha·ru′maph did repair work in front of his own house; and at his side Hat′tush the son of Hash·ab·nei′ah did repair work.

11 Another measured section was what Mal·chi′jah the son of Ha′rim and Has′shub the son of Pa′hath-mo′ab repaired, and also the Tower of the Bake Ovens. 12 And at his side Shal′lum the son of Hal·lo′hesh, a prince of half the district of Jerusalem, did repair work, he and his daughters.

13 The Valley Gate was what Ha′nun and the inhabitants of Za·no′ah repaired; they themselves built it and then set up its doors, its bolts and its bars, also a thousand cubits in the wall as far as the Gate of the Ash-heaps. 14 And the Gate of the Ash-heaps was what Mal·chi′jah the son of Re′chab, a prince of the district of Beth-hac·che′rem, repaired; he himself went building it and setting up its doors, its bolts and its bars.

15 And the Fountain Gate was what Shal′lun the son of Col·ho′zeh, a prince of the district of Miz′pah, repaired; he himself proceeded to build it and to roof it over and to set up its doors, its bolts and its bars, and also the wall of the Pool of the Canal to the King’s Garden and as far as the Stairway that goes down from the City of David.

16 After him Ne·he·mi′ah the son of Az′buk, a prince of half the district of Beth-zur, did repair work as far as in front of the Burial Places of David and as far as the pool that had been made and as far as the House of the Mighty Ones.

17 After him the Levites did repair work, Re′hum the son of Ba′ni; at his side Hash·a·bi′ah, a prince of half the district of Kei′lah, did repair work for his district. 18 After him their brothers did repair work, Bav′vai the son of Hen′a·dad, a prince of half the district of Kei′lah.

19 And E′zer the son of Jesh′u·a, a prince of Miz′pah, proceeded at his side to repair another measured section in front of the going up to the Armory at the Buttress.

20 After him Bar′uch the son of Zab′bai worked with fervor and repaired another measured section, from the Buttress as far as the entrance of the house of E·li′a·shib the high priest.

21 After him Mer′e·moth the son of U·ri′jah the son of Hak′koz repaired another measured section, from the entrance of the house of E·li′a·shib as far as the end of E·li′a·shib’s house.

22 And after him the priests, men of the Jordan District, did repair work. 23 After them Benjamin and Has′shub did repair work in front of their own house. After them Az·a·ri′ah the son of Ma·a·sei′ah the son of A·na·ni′ah did repair work close by his own house. 24 After him Bin′nu·i the son of Hen′a·dad repaired another measured section, from the house of Az·a·ri′ah as far as the Buttress and as far as the corner.

25 After him Pa′lal the son of U′zai did repair work in front of the Buttress and the tower that goes out from the King’s House, the upper one that belongs to the Courtyard of the Guard. After him there was Pe·dai′ah the son of Pa′rosh.

26 And the Neth′i·nim themselves happened to be dwellers in O′phel; they did repair work as far as in front of the Water Gate on the east and the protruding tower.

27 After them the Te·ko′ites repaired another measured section, from in front of the great protruding tower as far as the wall of O′phel.

28 Above the Horse Gate the priests did repair work, each one in front of his own house.

29 After them Za′dok the son of Im′mer did repair work in front of his own house.

And after him She·mai′ah the son of Shec·a·ni′ah, the keeper of the East Gate, did repair work.

30 After him Han·a·ni′ah the son of Shel·e·mi′ah and Ha′nun the sixth son of Za′laph repaired another measured section.

After him Me·shul′lam the son of Ber·e·chi′ah did repair work in front of his own hall.

31 After him Mal·chi′jah, a member of the goldsmith guild, did repair work as far as the house of the Neth′i·nim and the traders, in front of the Inspection Gate and as far as the roof chamber of the corner.

32 And between the roof chamber of the corner and the Sheep Gate the goldsmiths and the traders did repair work.

Nehemiah

7 And it came about that, as soon as the wall had been rebuilt, I at once set up the doors. Then there were appointed the gatekeepers and the singers and the Levites. 2 And I went on to put in command of Jerusalem Ha·na′ni my brother and Han·a·ni′ah the prince of the Castle, for he was such a trustworthy man and feared the true God more than many others. 3 So I said to them: “The gates of Jerusalem should not be opened until the sun gets hot; and while they are standing by they should shut the doors and bolt them. And station guards of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, each one at his own guardpost and each one in front of his own house.” 4 Now the city was wide and great, and there were few people inside it, and there were no houses built.

5 But my God put it into my heart that I should collect together the nobles and the deputy rulers and the people to get themselves enrolled genealogically. Then I found the book of genealogical enrollment of those who came up at the first, and found written in it:

6 These are the sons of the jurisdictional district who came up out of the captivity of the exiled people whom Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon had taken into exile and who later returned to Jerusalem and to Judah, each to his own city; 7 those who came in with Ze·rub′ba·bel, Jesh′u·a, Ne·he·mi′ah, Az·a·ri′ah, Ra·a·mi′ah, Na·ham′a·ni, Mor′de·cai, Bil′shan, Mis′pe·reth, Big′vai, Ne′hum, Ba′a·nah.

The number of the men of the people of Israel: 8 The sons of Pa′rosh, two thousand one hundred and seventy-two; 9 the sons of Sheph·a·ti′ah, three hundred and seventy-two; 10 the sons of A′rah, six hundred and fifty-two; 11 the sons of Pa′hath-mo′ab, of the sons of Jesh′u·a and Jo′ab, two thousand eight hundred and eighteen; 12 the sons of E′lam, a thousand two hundred and fifty-four; 13 the sons of Zat′tu, eight hundred and forty-five; 14 the sons of Zac′cai, seven hundred and sixty; 15 the sons of Bin′nu·i, six hundred and forty-eight; 16 the sons of Be′bai, six hundred and twenty-eight; 17 the sons of Az′gad, two thousand three hundred and twenty-two; 18 the sons of Ad·o·ni′kam, six hundred and sixty-seven; 19 the sons of Big′vai, two thousand and sixty-seven; 20 the sons of A′din, six hundred and fifty-five; 21 the sons of A′ter, of Hez·e·ki′ah, ninety-eight; 22 the sons of Ha′shum, three hundred and twenty-eight; 23 the sons of Be′zai, three hundred and twenty-four; 24 the sons of Ha′riph, a hundred and twelve; 25 the sons of Gib′e·on, ninety-five; 26 the men of Beth′le·hem and Ne·to′phah, a hundred and eighty-eight; 27 the men of An′a·thoth, a hundred and twenty-eight; 28 the men of Beth-az′ma·veth, forty-two; 29 the men of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, Che·phi′rah and Be·er′oth, seven hundred and forty-three; 30 the men of Ra′mah and Ge′ba, six hundred and twenty-one; 31 the men of Mich′mas, a hundred and twenty-two; 32 the men of Beth′el and A′i, a hundred and twenty-three; 33 the men of the other Ne′bo, fifty-two; 34 the sons of the other E′lam, a thousand two hundred and fifty-four; 35 the sons of Ha′rim, three hundred and twenty; 36 the sons of Jer′i·cho, three hundred and forty-five; 37 the sons of Lod, Ha′did and O′no, seven hundred and twenty-one; 38 the sons of Se·na′ah, three thousand nine hundred and thirty.

39 The priests: The sons of Je·da′iah of the house of Jesh′u·a, nine hundred and seventy-three; 40 the sons of Im′mer, a thousand and fifty-two; 41 the sons of Pash′hur, a thousand two hundred and forty-seven; 42 the sons of Ha′rim, a thousand and seventeen.

43 The Levites: The sons of Jesh′u·a, of Kad′mi·el, of the sons of Ho′de·vah, seventy-four. 44 The singers, the sons of A′saph, a hundred and forty-eight. 45 The gatekeepers, the sons of Shal′lum, the sons of A′ter, the sons of Tal′mon, the sons of Ak′kub, the sons of Ha·ti′ta, the sons of Sho′bai, a hundred and thirty-eight.

46 The Neth′i·nim: The sons of Zi′ha, the sons of Ha·su′pha, the sons of Tab·ba′oth, 47 the sons of Ke′ros, the sons of Si′a, the sons of Pa′don, 48 the sons of Le·ba′nah, the sons of Hag′a·bah, the sons of Sal′mai, 49 the sons of Ha′nan, the sons of Gid′del, the sons of Ga′har, 50 the sons of Re·a′iah, the sons of Re′zin, the sons of Ne·ko′da, 51 the sons of Gaz′zam, the sons of Uz′za, the sons of Pa·se′ah, 52 the sons of Be′sai, the sons of Me·u′nim, the sons of Ne·phush′e·sim, 53 the sons of Bak′buk, the sons of Ha·ku′pha, the sons of Har′hur, 54 the sons of Baz′lith, the sons of Me·hi′da, the sons of Har′sha, 55 the sons of Bar′kos, the sons of Sis′e·ra, the sons of Te′mah, 56 the sons of Ne·zi′ah, the sons of Ha·ti′pha.

57 The sons of the servants of Sol′o·mon: The sons of So′tai, the sons of So·phe′reth, the sons of Pe·ri′da, 58 the sons of Ja′a·la, the sons of Dar′kon, the sons of Gid′del, 59 the sons of Sheph·a·ti′ah, the sons of Hat′til, the sons of Po′che·reth-haz·ze·ba′im, the sons of A′mon. 60 All the Neth′i·nim and the sons of the servants of Sol′o·mon were three hundred and ninety-two.

61 And these were the ones going up from Tel-me′lah, Tel-har′sha, Che′rub, Ad′don and Im′mer, and they were not able to tell the house of their fathers and their origin, whether they were of Israel: 62 the sons of De·la′iah, the sons of To·bi′ah, the sons of Ne·ko′da, six hundred and forty-two. 63 And of the priests: the sons of Ha·bai′ah, the sons of Hak′koz, the sons of Bar·zil′lai, who took a wife from the daughters of Bar·zil′lai the Gil′e·ad·ite and came to be called by their name. 64 These were the ones that looked for their register, to establish their genealogy publicly, and it was not found, so that they were barred as polluted from the priesthood. 65 Consequently the Tir·sha′tha said to them that they should not eat from the most holy things until the priest with U′rim and Thum′mim stood up.

66 The entire congregation as one group was forty-two thousand three hundred and sixty, 67 apart from their men slaves and their slave girls, these being seven thousand three hundred and thirty-seven; and they had two hundred and forty-five male singers and female singers. 68 Their horses were seven hundred and thirty-six, their mules two hundred and forty-five. 69 The camels were four hundred and thirty-five. The asses were six thousand seven hundred and twenty.

70 And there was a part of the heads of the paternal houses that gave to the work. The Tir·sha′tha himself gave to the treasure a thousand gold drachmas, fifty bowls, five hundred and thirty priests’ robes. 71 And there were some of the heads of the paternal houses that gave to the treasure for the work twenty thousand gold drachmas and two thousand two hundred silver mi′nas. 72 And what the rest of the people gave was twenty thousand gold drachmas and two thousand silver mi′nas and sixty-seven priests’ robes.

73 And the priests and the Levites and the gatekeepers and the singers and some of the people and the Neth′i·nim and all Israel took up dwelling in their cities. When the seventh month arrived, the sons of Israel were then in their cities.

Nehemiah

12 And these were the priests and the Levites that went up with Ze·rub′ba·bel the son of She·al′ti·el and Jesh′u·a: Se·rai′ah, Jeremiah, Ez′ra, 2 Am·a·ri′ah, Mal′luch, Hat′tush, 3 Shec·a·ni′ah, Re′hum, Mer′e·moth, 4 Id′do, Gin′ne·thoi, A·bi′jah, 5 Mij′a·min, Ma·a·di′ah, Bil′gah, 6 She·mai′ah, and Joi′a·rib, Je·da′iah, 7 Sal′lu, A′mok, Hil·ki′ah, Je·da′iah. These were the heads of the priests and their brothers in the days of Jesh′u·a.

8 And the Levites were Jesh′u·a, Bin′nu·i, Kad′mi·el, She·re·bi′ah, Judah, Mat·ta·ni′ah, over the giving of thanks, he and his brothers. 9 And Bak·bu·ki′ah and Un′ni their brothers were opposite them for guard duties. 10 Jesh′u·a himself became father to Joi′a·kim, and Joi′a·kim himself became father to E·li′a·shib, and E·li′a·shib to Joi′a·da. 11 And Joi′a·da himself became father to Jon′a·than, and Jon′a·than himself became father to Jad′du·a.

12 And in the days of Joi′a·kim there happened to be priests, the heads of the paternal houses: for Se·rai′ah, Me·rai′ah; for Jeremiah, Han·a·ni′ah; 13 for Ez′ra, Me·shul′lam; for Am·a·ri′ah, Je·ho·ha′nan; 14 for Mal′lu·chi, Jon′a·than; for Sheb·a·ni′ah, Joseph; 15 for Ha′rim, Ad′na; for Me·ra′ioth, Hel′kai; 16 for Id′do, Zech·a·ri′ah; for Gin′ne·thon, Me·shul′lam; 17 for A·bi′jah, Zich′ri; for Mi·ni′a·min, ——; for Mo·a·di′ah, Pil′tai; 18 for Bil′gah, Sham·mu′a; for She·mai′ah, Je·hon′a·than; 19 and for Joi′a·rib, Mat·te′nai; for Je·da′iah, Uz′zi; 20 for Sal·la′i, Kal′lai; for A′mok, E′ber; 21 for Hil·ki′ah, Hash·a·bi′ah; for Je·da′iah, Ne·than′el.

22 The Levites in the days of E·li′a·shib, Joi′a·da and Jo·ha′nan and Jad′du·a were recorded as heads of paternal houses, also the priests, down till the kingship of Da·ri′us the Persian.

23 The sons of Le′vi as heads of the paternal houses were recorded in the book of the affairs of the times, even down till the days of Jo·ha′nan the son of E·li′a·shib. 24 And the heads of the Levites were Hash·a·bi′ah, She·re·bi′ah and Jesh′u·a the son of Kad′mi·el and their brothers opposite them to offer praise and give thanks according to the commandment of David the man of the true God, guard group corresponding with guard group. 25 Mat·ta·ni′ah and Bak·bu·ki′ah, O·ba·di′ah, Me·shul′lam, Tal′mon, Ak′kub were keeping guard as gatekeepers, a guard group by the stores of the gates. 26 These were in the days of Joi′a·kim the son of Jesh′u·a the son of Jo′za·dak and in the days of Ne·he·mi′ah the governor and Ez′ra the priest, the copyist.

27 And at the inauguration of the wall of Jerusalem they looked for the Levites, to bring them out of all their places to Jerusalem to carry on an inauguration and a rejoicing even with thanksgivings and with song, cymbals and stringed instruments and with harps. 28 And the sons of the singers proceeded to gather themselves even from the District, from all around Jerusalem and from the settlements of the Ne·toph′a·thites, 29 and from Beth-gil′gal and from the fields of Ge′ba and Az′ma·veth, for there were settlements that the singers had built for themselves all around Jerusalem. 30 And the priests and the Levites proceeded to cleanse themselves and cleanse the people and the gates and the wall.

31 Then I brought up the princes of Judah upon the wall. Further, I appointed two large thanksgiving choirs and processions, and the one was walking to the right upon the wall to the Gate of the Ash-heaps. 32 And Ho·shai′ah and half of the princes of Judah began to walk behind them, 33 also Az·a·ri′ah, Ez′ra and Me·shul′lam, 34 Judah and Benjamin and She·mai′ah and Jeremiah; 35 also of the sons of the priests with the trumpets Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Jon′a·than the son of She·mai′ah the son of Mat·ta·ni′ah the son of Mi·cai′ah the son of Zac′cur the son of A′saph, 36 and his brothers She·mai′ah and Az′ar·el, Mil′a·lai, Gil′a·lai, Ma′ai, Ne·than′el and Judah, Ha·na′ni, with the instruments of song of David the man of the true God; and Ez′ra the copyist before them. 37 And at the Fountain Gate and straight ahead of them they went up on the Stairway of the City of David by the ascent of the wall above the House of David and clear to the Water Gate to the east.

38 And the other thanksgiving choir was walking in front, and I after it, also half of the people, upon the wall up over the Tower of the Bake Ovens and on to the Broad Wall, 39 and up over the Gate of E′phra·im and on to the Gate of the Old City and clear to the Fish Gate and the Tower of Ha·nan′el and the Tower of Me′ah and on to the Sheep Gate; and they came to a stand at the Gate of the Guard.

40 At length the two thanksgiving choirs came to a stand at the house of the true God, also I and half of the deputy rulers with me, 41 and the priests E·li′a·kim, Ma·a·sei′ah, Mi·ni′a·min, Mi·cai′ah, Eli·o·e′nai, Zech·a·ri′ah, Han·a·ni′ah with the trumpets, 42 and Ma·a·sei′ah and She·mai′ah, and El·e·a′zar and Uz′zi and Je·ho·ha′nan and Mal·chi′jah and E′lam and E′zer. And the singers with Iz·ra·hi′ah the overseer kept making themselves heard.

43 And they proceeded to sacrifice on that day great sacrifices and to rejoice, for the true God himself caused them to rejoice with great joy. And also the women and the children themselves rejoiced, so that the rejoicing of Jerusalem could be heard far away.

44 Further, there were appointed on that day men over the halls for the stores, for the contributions, for the firstfruits and for the tenths, to gather into them out of the fields of the cities the portions called for by the law for the priests and the Levites; for the rejoicing of Judah was because of the priests and of the Levites who were in attendance. 45 And they began taking care of the obligation of their God and the obligation of the purification, also the singers and the gatekeepers, according to the commandment of David and Sol′o·mon his son. 46 For in the days of David and A′saph in bygone time there were heads of the singers and the song of praise and thanksgivings to God. 47 And all Israel during the days of Ze·rub′ba·bel and during the days of Ne·he·mi′ah were giving the portions of the singers and of the gatekeepers according to the daily need and were sanctifying them to the Levites; and the Levites were sanctifying them to the sons of Aaron.

Nehemiah

13 On that day there was a reading from the book of Moses in the ears of the people; and there was found written in it that the Am′mon·ite and the Mo′ab·ite should not come into the congregation of the true God to time indefinite, 2 for they had not met the sons of Israel with bread and with water, but went hiring against them Ba′laam to call down evil upon them. However, our God changed the malediction into a benediction. 3 So it came about that, as soon as they heard the law, they began to separate all the mixed company from Israel.

4 Now before this, E·li′a·shib the priest in charge of a dining hall of the house of our God was a relative of To·bi′ah; 5 and he proceeded to make for him a large dining hall, where previously they were regularly putting the grain offering, the frankincense and the utensils and the tenth of the grain, the new wine and the oil, to which the Levites and the singers and the gatekeepers are entitled, and the contribution for the priests.

6 And during all this time I did not happen to be in Jerusalem, for in the thirty-second year of Ar·ta·xerx′es the king of Babylon I came to the king, and sometime later I asked leave of absence from the king. 7 Then I came to Jerusalem and got to notice the badness that E·li′a·shib had committed for To·bi′ah by making for him a hall in the courtyard of the house of the true God. 8 And it seemed very bad to me. So I threw all the furniture of To·bi′ah’s house outside the dining hall. 9 After that I said the word and they cleansed the dining halls; and I proceeded to put back there the utensils of the house of the true God, with the grain offering and the frankincense.

10 And I got to find out that the very portions of the Levites had not been given them, so that the Levites and the singers doing the work went running off, each one to his own field. 11 And I began to find fault with the deputy rulers and say: “Why has the house of the true God been neglected?” Consequently I collected them together and stationed them at their standing place. 12 And all Judah, for their part, brought in the tenth of the grain and of the new wine and of the oil to the stores. 13 Then I put Shel·e·mi′ah the priest and Za′dok the copyist and Pe·dai′ah of the Levites in charge of the stores; and under their control there was Ha′nan the son of Zac′cur the son of Mat·ta·ni′ah, for they were considered faithful; and upon them it devolved to do the distributing to their brothers.

14 Do remember me, O my God, concerning this, and do not wipe out my acts of loving-kindness that I have performed in connection with the house of my God and the guardianship of it.

15 In those days I saw in Judah people treading winepresses on the sabbath and bringing in grain heaps and loading them upon asses, and also wine, grapes and figs and every sort of burden, and bringing them into Jerusalem on the sabbath day; and I proceeded to bear witness against them on the day of their selling provisions. 16 And the Tyr′i·ans themselves dwelt in the city, bringing in fish and every sort of merchandise and making sales on the sabbath to the sons of Judah and in Jerusalem. 17 So I began to find fault with the nobles of Judah and say to them: “What is this bad thing that YOU are doing, even profaning the sabbath day? 18 Was it not this way that YOUR forefathers did, so that our God brought upon us all this calamity, and also upon this city? Yet YOU are adding to the burning anger against Israel by profaning the sabbath.”

19 And it came about that, as soon as the gates of Jerusalem had grown shadowy before the sabbath, I immediately said the word and the doors began to be closed. I said further that they should not open them until after the sabbath; and some of my own attendants I stationed at the gates that no burden might come in on the sabbath day. 20 Consequently the traders and the sellers of every sort of merchandise spent the night outside Jerusalem once and a second time. 21 Then I proceeded to bear witness against them and say to them: “Why are YOU spending the night in front of the wall? If YOU do it again, a hand I shall lay on YOU.” From that time on they did not come on the sabbath.

22 And I went on to say to the Levites that they should be regularly purifying themselves and coming in, keeping guard of the gates to sanctify the sabbath day. This, also, do remember to my account, O my God, and do feel sorry for me according to the abundance of your loving-kindness.

23 Also, in those days I saw the Jews that had given a dwelling to Ash′dod·ite, Am′mon·ite and Mo′ab·ite wives. 24 And as for their sons, half were speaking Ash′dod·ite, and there were none of them knowing how to speak Jewish, but in the tongue of the different peoples. 25 And I began to find fault with them and call down evil upon them and strike some men of them and pull out their hair and make them swear by God: “YOU should not give YOUR daughters to their sons, and YOU should not accept any of their daughters for YOUR sons or yourselves. 26 Was it not because of these that Sol′o·mon the king of Israel sinned? And among the many nations there proved to be no king like him; and loved of his God he happened to be, so that God constituted him king over all Israel. Even him the foreign wives caused to sin. 27 And is it not something unheard of for YOU to commit all this great badness in acting unfaithfully against our God by giving a dwelling to foreign wives?”

28 And one of the sons of Joi′a·da the son of E·li′a·shib the high priest was a son-in-law of San·bal′lat the Hor′o·nite. So I chased him away from me.

29 Do remember them, O my God, on account of the defilement of the priesthood and the covenant of the priesthood and of the Levites.

30 And I purified them from everything foreign and proceeded to assign duties to the priests and to the Levites, each one in his own work, 31 even for the supply of the wood at appointed times and for the first ripe fruits.

Do remember me, O my God, for good.

Esther

3 After these things King A·has·u·e′rus magnified Ha′man the son of Ham·me·da′tha the Ag′ag·ite and proceeded to exalt him and to put his throne above all the other princes that were with him. 2 And all the king’s servants that were in the king’s gate were bowing low and prostrating themselves to Ha′man, for so the king had commanded respecting him. But as for Mor′de·cai, he would neither bow low nor prostrate himself. 3 And the king’s servants who were in the king’s gate began to say to Mor′de·cai: “Why are you sidestepping the king’s commandment?” 4 And it came about that, as they talked to him day by day, and he did not listen to them, then they told Ha′man to see whether Mor′de·cai’s affairs would stand; for he had told them that he was a Jew.

5 Now Ha′man kept seeing that Mor′de·cai was not bowing low and prostrating himself to him, and Ha′man became filled with rage. 6 But it was despicable in his eyes to lay hand upon Mor′de·cai alone, for they had told him about Mor′de·cai’s people; and Ha′man began seeking to annihilate all the Jews who were in all the realm of A·has·u·e′rus, Mor′de·cai’s people.

7 In the first month, that is, the month Ni′san, in the twelfth year of King A·has·u·e′rus, someone cast Pur, that is, the Lot, before Ha′man from day to day and from month to month, to the twelfth, that is, the month A′dar. 8 And Ha′man proceeded to say to King A·has·u·e′rus: “There is one certain people scattered and separated among the peoples in all the jurisdictional districts of your realm; and their laws are different from all other people’s, and the king’s own laws they are not performing, and for the king it is not appropriate to let them alone. 9 If to the king it does seem good, let there be a writing that they be destroyed; and ten thousand silver talents I shall pay into the hands of those doing the work by bringing it into the king’s treasury.”

10 At that the king removed his signet ring from his own hand and gave it to Ha′man the son of Ham·me·da′tha the Ag′ag·ite, the one showing hostility to the Jews. 11 And the king went on to say to Ha′man: “The silver is given to you, also the people, to do with them according to what is good in your own eyes.” 12 The king’s secretaries were then called in the first month on the thirteenth day of it, and writing went on according to all that Ha′man commanded the king’s satraps and the governors who were over the different jurisdictional districts, and the princes of the different peoples, of each jurisdictional district, in its own style of writing, and each people in its own tongue; in the name of King A·has·u·e′rus it was written and it was sealed with the king’s signet ring.

13 And there was a sending of the letters by means of couriers to all the king’s jurisdictional districts, to annihilate, to kill and to destroy all the Jews, young man as well as old man, little ones and women, on one day, on the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, that is, the month A′dar, and to plunder the spoil of them. 14 A copy of the writing to be given as law in all the different jurisdictional districts was being published to all the peoples, for them to become ready for this day. 15 The couriers themselves went out, being moved to speed because of the king’s word, and the law itself was given in Shu′shan the castle. As for the king and Ha′man, they sat down to drink; but as for the city of Shu′shan, it was in confusion.

Esther

4 And Mor′de·cai himself got knowledge of everything that had been done; and Mor′de·cai proceeded to rip his garments apart and put on sackcloth and ashes and go out into the middle of the city and cry out with a loud and bitter outcry. 2 Finally he came as far as in front of the king’s gate, for no one was to come into the king’s gate in clothing of sackcloth. 3 And in all the different jurisdictional districts, wherever the king’s word and his law were reaching, there was great mourning among the Jews, and fasting and weeping and wailing. Sackcloth and ashes themselves came to be spread out as a couch for many. 4 And Esther’s young women and her eunuchs began to come in and tell her. And the queen was very much pained. Then she sent garments to clothe Mor′de·cai and to remove his sackcloth off him. And he did not accept them. 5 At this Esther called Ha′thach, one of the king’s eunuchs, whom he had made to attend upon her, and she proceeded to give him a command concerning Mor′de·cai, to know what this meant and what this was all about.

6 So Ha′thach went out to Mor′de·cai into the public square of the city that was before the king’s gate. 7 Then Mor′de·cai told him about all the things that had befallen him and the exact statement of the money that Ha′man had said to pay to the king’s treasury against the Jews, to destroy them. 8 And a copy of the writing of the law that had been given in Shu′shan to have them annihilated he gave him to show Esther and to tell her and to lay the command upon her to come in to the king and implore favor of him and make request directly before him for her own people.

9 Ha′thach now came in and told Esther Mor′de·cai’s words. 10 Then Esther said to Ha′thach and commanded him concerning Mor′de·cai: 11 “All the king’s servants and the people of the king’s jurisdictional districts are aware that, as regards any man or woman that comes in to the king at the inner courtyard who is not called, his one law is to have him put to death; only in case the king holds out to him the golden scepter, he will also certainly stay alive. As for me, I have not been called to come in to the king now for thirty days.”

12 And they proceeded to tell Mor′de·cai the words of Esther. 13 Then Mor′de·cai said to reply to Esther: “Do not imagine within your own soul that the king’s household will escape any more than all the other Jews. 14 For if you are altogether silent at this time, relief and deliverance themselves will stand up for the Jews from another place; but as for you and your father’s house, YOU people will perish. And who is there knowing whether it is for a time like this that you have attained to royal dignity?”

15 Accordingly Esther said to reply to Mor′de·cai: 16 “Go, gather all the Jews that are to be found in Shu′shan and fast in my behalf and neither eat nor drink for three days, night and day. I too with my young women, I shall fast likewise, and upon that I shall come in to the king, which is not according to the law; and in case I must perish, I must perish.” 17 At this Mor′de·cai passed along and proceeded to do according to all that Esther had laid in command upon him.

Esther

5 And it came about on the third day that Esther went dressing up royally, after which she took her stand in the inner courtyard of the king’s house opposite the king’s house, while the king was sitting on his royal throne in the royal house opposite the entrance of the house. 2 And it came about that, as soon as the king saw Esther the queen standing in the courtyard, she gained favor in his eyes, so that the king held out to Esther the golden scepter that was in his hand. Esther now came near and touched the top of the scepter.

3 Then the king said to her: “What do you have, O Esther the queen, and what is your request? To the half of the kingship—let it even be given to you!” 4 In turn Esther said: “If to the king it does seem good, let the king with Ha′man come today to the banquet that I have made for him.” 5 Accordingly the king said: “YOU men, have Ha′man act quickly on the word of Esther.” Later the king and Ha′man came to the banquet that Esther had made.

6 In time the king said to Esther during the banquet of wine: “What is your petition? Let it even be granted you! And what is your request? To the half of the kingship—let it even be done!” 7 To this Esther answered and said: “My petition and my request is, 8 If I have found favor in the king’s eyes and if to the king it does seem good to grant my petition and to act on my request, let the king and Ha′man come to the banquet that I shall hold for them tomorrow, and tomorrow I shall do according to the king’s word.”

9 Consequently Ha′man went out on that day joyful and merry of heart; but as soon as Ha′man saw Mor′de·cai in the king’s gate and that he did not rise and did not quake on account of him, Ha′man was immediately filled with rage against Mor′de·cai. 10 However, Ha′man kept control of himself and came into his house. Then he sent and had his friends and Ze′resh his wife brought in; 11 and Ha′man proceeded to declare to them the glory of his riches and the large number of his sons and everything with which the king had magnified him and how he had exalted him over the princes and the servants of the king.

12 And Ha′man went on to say: “What is more, Esther the queen brought in with the king to the banquet that she had made no one but me, and tomorrow also I am invited to her with the king. 13 But all this—none of it suits me as long as I am seeing Mor′de·cai the Jew sitting in the king’s gate.” 14 At that Ze′resh his wife and all his friends said to him: “Let them make a stake fifty cubits high. Then in the morning say to the king that they should hang Mor′de·cai on it. Then go in with the king to the banquet joyful.” So the thing seemed good before Ha′man, and he proceeded to have the stake made.

Esther

6 During that night the king’s sleep fled. Therefore he said to bring the book of the records of the affairs of the times. Thus there came to be a reading of them before the king. 2 At length there was found written what Mor′de·cai had reported concerning Big·tha′na and Te′resh, two court officials of the king, doorkeepers, who had sought to lay hand on King A·has·u·e′rus. 3 Then the king said: “What honor and great thing has been done to Mor′de·cai for this?” To this the king’s attendants, his ministers, said: “Nothing has been done with him.”

4 Later the king said: “Who is in the courtyard?” Now Ha′man himself had come into the outer courtyard of the king’s house to say to the king to hang Mor′de·cai on the stake that he had prepared for him. 5 Accordingly the king’s attendants said to him: “Here is Ha′man standing in the courtyard.” So the king said: “Let him come in.”

6 When Ha′man came in, the king proceeded to say to him: “What is to be done to the man in whose honor the king himself has taken a delight?” At this Ha′man said in his heart: “To whom would the king take delight in rendering an honor more than me?” 7 So Ha′man said to the king: “As for the man in whose honor the king himself has taken a delight, 8 let them bring royal apparel with which the king does clothe himself and a horse upon which the king does ride and on the head of which the royal headdress has been put. 9 And let there be a putting of the apparel and the horse into the charge of one of the king’s noble princes; and they must clothe the man in whose honor the king himself has taken a delight, and they must make him ride on the horse in the public square of the city, and they must call out before him, ‘This is how it is done to the man in whose honor the king himself has taken a delight.’” 10 At once the king said to Ha′man: “Quickly, take the apparel and the horse, just as you have said, and do that way to Mor′de·cai the Jew who is sitting in the king’s gate. Do not let anything go unfulfilled of all that you have spoken.”

11 And Ha′man proceeded to take the apparel and the horse and clothe Mor′de·cai and make him ride in the public square of the city and call out before him: “This is how it is done to the man in whose honor the king himself has taken a delight.” 12 Afterward Mor′de·cai returned to the king’s gate. As for Ha′man, he hurried to his house, mourning and with his head covered. 13 And Ha′man went on to relate to Ze′resh his wife and to all his friends everything that had befallen him. At that his wise men and Ze′resh his wife said to him: “If it is from the seed of the Jews that Mor′de·cai is before whom you have started to fall, you will not prevail against him, but you will without fail fall before him.”

14 While they were yet speaking with him the king’s court officials themselves arrived and proceeded hastily to bring Ha′man to the banquet that Esther had made.

Esther

8 On that day King A·has·u·e′rus gave to Esther the queen the house of Ha′man, the one showing hostility to the Jews; and Mor′de·cai himself came in before the king, because Esther had told what he was to her. 2 Then the king removed his signet ring that he had taken away from Ha′man and gave it to Mor′de·cai; and Esther went on to place Mor′de·cai over the house of Ha′man.

3 Moreover, Esther spoke again before the king and fell down before his feet and wept and implored favor of him to turn away the badness of Ha′man the Ag′ag·ite and his scheme that he had schemed against the Jews. 4 Then the king held the golden scepter out to Esther, at which Esther rose and stood before the king. 5 She now said: “If to the king it does seem good, and if I have found favor before him and the thing is proper before the king and I am good in his eyes, let it be written to undo the written documents, the scheme of Ha′man the son of Ham·me·da′tha the Ag′ag·ite, which he wrote to destroy the Jews that are in all the king’s jurisdictional districts. 6 For how can I bear it when I must look upon the calamity that will find my people, and how can I bear it when I must look upon the destruction of my relatives?”

7 So King A·has·u·e′rus said to Esther the queen and to Mor′de·cai the Jew: “Look! The house of Ha′man I have given to Esther, and him they have hanged on the stake, for the reason that he thrust out his hand against the Jews. 8 And YOU yourselves write in behalf of the Jews according to what is good in YOUR own eyes in the king’s name and seal it with the king’s signet ring; for a writing that is written in the king’s name and sealed with the king’s signet ring it is not possible to undo.”

9 Accordingly the secretaries of the king were called at that time in the third month, that is, the month of Si′van, on the twenty-third day of it; and writing went on according to all that Mor′de·cai commanded to the Jews and to the satraps and the governors and the princes of the jurisdictional districts that were from In′di·a to E·thi·o′pi·a, a hundred and twenty-seven jurisdictional districts, to each jurisdictional district in its own style of writing and to each people in its own tongue, and to the Jews in their own style of writing and in their own tongue.

10 And he proceeded to write in the name of King A·has·u·e′rus and do the sealing with the king’s signet ring and send written documents by the hand of the couriers on horses, riding post-horses used in the royal service, sons of speedy mares, 11 that the king granted to the Jews that were in all the different cities to congregate themselves and stand for their souls, to annihilate and kill and destroy all the force of the people and jurisdictional district that were showing hostility to them, little ones and women, and to plunder their spoil, 12 on the one day in all the jurisdictional districts of King A·has·u·e′rus, on the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, that is, the month of A′dar. 13 A copy of the writing was to be given as law throughout all the different jurisdictional districts, published to all the peoples, that the Jews should become ready for this day to avenge themselves upon their enemies. 14 The couriers themselves, riding post-horses used in the royal service, went forth, being urged forward and being moved with speed by the king’s word; and the law itself was given out in Shu′shan the castle.

15 As for Mor′de·cai, he went forth from before the king in royal apparel of blue and linen, with a great crown of gold, and a fine-fabric cloak, even of wool dyed reddish purple. And the city of Shu′shan itself cried out shrilly and was joyful. 16 For the Jews there occurred light and rejoicing and exultation and honor. 17 And in all the different jurisdictional districts and in all the different cities wherever the word of the king and his law were reaching there were rejoicing and exultation for the Jews, a banquet and a good day; and many of the peoples of the land were declaring themselves Jews, for the dread of the Jews had fallen upon them.

Esther

9 And in the twelfth month, that is, the month of A′dar, on the thirteenth day of it, when the king’s word and his law came due to be performed, on the day for which the enemies of the Jews had waited to domineer over them, there was even a turning to the contrary, in that the Jews themselves domineered over those hating them. 2 The Jews congregated themselves in their cities in all the jurisdictional districts of King A·has·u·e′rus to lay hand on those seeking their injury, and not a man stood his ground before them, for the dread of them had fallen upon all the peoples. 3 And all the princes of the jurisdictional districts and the satraps and the governors and the doers of the business that belonged to the king were assisting the Jews, for the dread of Mor′de·cai had fallen upon them. 4 For Mor′de·cai was great in the king’s house and his fame was traveling throughout all the jurisdictional districts, because the man Mor′de·cai was steadily growing greater.

5 And the Jews went striking down all their enemies with a slaughter by the sword and with a killing and destruction, and they went doing to those hating them according to their liking. 6 And in Shu′shan the castle the Jews killed and there was a destroying of five hundred men. 7 Also, Par·shan·da′tha and Dal′phon and As·pa′tha 8 and Po·ra′tha and A·da′li·a and A·ri·da′tha 9 and Par·mash′ta and Ar′i·sai and Ar′i·dai and Vai·za′tha, 10 the ten sons of Ha′man the son of Ham·me·da′tha, the one showing hostility to the Jews, they killed; but on the plunder they did not lay their hand.

11 On that day the number of those killed in Shu′shan the castle came before the king.

12 And the king proceeded to say to Esther the queen: “In Shu′shan the castle the Jews have killed, and there has been a destroying of five hundred men and the ten sons of Ha′man. In the rest of the jurisdictional districts of the king what have they done? And what is your petition? Let it even be given to you. And what is your further request? Let it even be done.” 13 Accordingly Esther said: “If to the king it does seem good, let it be granted tomorrow also to the Jews that are in Shu′shan to do according to the law of today; and let the ten sons of Ha′man be hanged upon the stake.” 14 So the king said for it to be done that way. Then a law was given out in Shu′shan, and the ten sons of Ha′man were hanged.

15 And the Jews that were in Shu′shan proceeded to congregate themselves also on the fourteenth day of the month A′dar, and they got to kill in Shu′shan three hundred men; but on the plunder they did not lay their hand.

16 As for the rest of the Jews that were in the jurisdictional districts of the king, they congregated themselves, and there was a stand for their souls, and there was an avenging of themselves upon their enemies and a killing among those hating them of seventy-five thousand; but on the plunder they did not lay their hand, 17 on the thirteenth day of the month A′dar; and there was a rest on the fourteenth day of it, and there was a making of it a day of banqueting and of rejoicing.

18 As for the Jews that were in Shu′shan, they congregated themselves on the thirteenth day of it and on the fourteenth day of it, and there was a rest on the fifteenth day of it, and there was a making of it a day of banqueting and of rejoicing. 19 That is why the country Jews, inhabiting the cities of the outlying districts, were making the fourteenth day of the month A′dar a rejoicing and a banqueting and a good day and a sending of portions to one another.

20 And Mor′de·cai proceeded to write these things and send written documents to all the Jews that were in all the jurisdictional districts of King A·has·u·e′rus, the nearby and the distant ones, 21 to impose upon them the obligation to be regularly holding the fourteenth day of the month A′dar and the fifteenth day of it in each and every year, 22 according to the days on which the Jews had rested from their enemies and the month that was changed for them from grief to rejoicing and from mourning to a good day, to hold them as days of banqueting and rejoicing and sending of portions to one another and of gifts to the poor people.

23 And the Jews accepted what they had started to do and what Mor′de·cai had written to them. 24 For Ha′man the son of Ham·me·da′tha, the Ag′ag·ite, the one showing hostility to all the Jews, had himself schemed against the Jews to destroy them, and he had had Pur, that is, the Lot, cast, to disquiet them and destroy them. 25 But when Esther came in before the king he said with the written document: “Let his bad scheme that he has schemed against the Jews come back upon his own head”; and they hanged him and his sons upon the stake. 26 That is why they called these days Pu′rim, by the name of the Pur. That is why, according to all the words of this letter and what they had seen as to this and what had come upon them, 27 the Jews imposed and accepted upon themselves and upon their offspring and upon all those joining themselves to them, that it should not pass away, the obligation to be regularly holding these two days according to what was written concerning them and according to their appointed time in each and every year. 28 And these days were to be remembered and held in each and every generation, each family, each jurisdictional district and each city, and these days of Pu′rim themselves should not pass away from the midst of the Jews and the commemoration itself of them not come to an end among their offspring.

29 And Esther the queen, the daughter of Ab′i·ha·il, and Mor′de·cai the Jew proceeded to write with all forcefulness to confirm this second letter concerning Pu′rim. 30 Then he sent written documents to all the Jews in the one hundred and twenty-seven jurisdictional districts, the realm of A·has·u·e′rus, in words of peace and truth, 31 to confirm these days of Pu′rim at their appointed times, just as Mor′de·cai the Jew and Esther the queen had imposed upon them, and just as they had imposed upon their own soul and upon their offspring, the matters of the fasts and their cry for aid. 32 And the very saying of Esther confirmed these matters of Pu′rim, and it was written down in a book.

Job

2 Afterward it came to be the day when the sons of the true God entered to take their station before Jehovah, and Satan also proceeded to enter right among them to take his station before Jehovah.

2 Then Jehovah said to Satan: “Just where do you come from?” At that Satan answered Jehovah and said: “From roving about in the earth and from walking about in it.” 3 And Jehovah went on to say to Satan: “Have you set your heart upon my servant Job, that there is no one like him in the earth, a man blameless and upright, fearing God and turning aside from bad? Even yet he is holding fast his integrity, although you incite me against him to swallow him up without cause.” 4 But Satan answered Jehovah and said: “Skin in behalf of skin, and everything that a man has he will give in behalf of his soul. 5 For a change, thrust out your hand, please, and touch as far as his bone and his flesh and see whether he will not curse you to your very face.”

6 Accordingly Jehovah said to Satan: “There he is in your hand! Only watch out for his soul itself!” 7 So Satan went out away from the person of Jehovah and struck Job with a malignant boil from the sole of his foot to the crown of his head. 8 And he proceeded to take for himself a fragment of earthenware with which to scrape himself; and he was sitting in among the ashes.

9 Finally his wife said to him: “Are you yet holding fast your integrity? Curse God and die!” 10 But he said to her: “As one of the senseless women speaks, you speak also. Shall we accept merely what is good from the true God and not accept also what is bad?” In all this Job did not sin with his lips.

11 And three companions of Job got to hear of all this calamity that had come upon him, and they proceeded to come, each one from his own place, El′i·phaz the Te′man·ite and Bil′dad the Shu′hite and Zo′phar the Na′a·ma·thite. So they met together by appointment to come and sympathize with him and comfort him. 12 When they raised their eyes from far off they did not then recognize him. And they proceeded to raise their voice and weep and rip each one his sleeveless coat apart and toss dust toward the heavens upon their heads. 13 And they kept sitting with him on the earth seven days and seven nights, and there was no one speaking a word to him, for they saw that the pain was very great.

Job

10 “My soul certainly feels a loathing toward my life.

I will give vent to my concern about myself.

I will speak in the bitterness of my soul!

2 I shall say to God, ‘Do not pronounce me wicked.

Cause me to know why it is that you are contending with me.

3 Is it good for you that you should do wrong,

That you should reject the product of the hard work of your hands,

And that upon the counsel of wicked ones you should actually beam?

4 Do you have eyes of flesh,

Or is it as a mortal man sees that you see?

5 Are your days like the days of mortal man,

Or your years just like the days of an able-bodied man,

6 That you should try to find my error

And for my sin you should keep looking?

7 This in spite of your own knowledge that I am not in the wrong,

And there is no one delivering out of your own hand?

8 Your own hands have shaped me so that they made me

In entirety round about, and yet you would swallow me up.

9 Remember, please, that out of clay you have made me

And to dust you will make me return.

10 Did you not proceed to pour me out as milk itself

And like cheese to curdle me?

11 With skin and flesh you proceeded to clothe me

And with bones and sinews to weave me together.

12 Life and loving-kindness you have worked with me;

And your own care has guarded my spirit.

13 And these things you have concealed in your heart.

I well know that these things are with you.

14 If I have sinned and you have kept watching me

And of my error you do not hold me innocent;

15 If I am actually in the wrong, too bad for me!

And if I am actually in the right, I may not raise my head,

Glutted with dishonor and saturated with affliction.

16 And if it acts haughtily, like a young lion you will hunt for me,

And you will again show yourself marvelous in my case.

17 You will bring forth new witnesses of yours in front of me,

And you will make your vexation with me greater;

Hardship after hardship is with me.

18 So why from a womb did you bring me out?

Could I have expired, that not even an eye could see me,

19 There as though I had not come to be I should have become;

From the belly to the burial place I should have been brought.’

20 Are not my days few? Let him leave off,

Let him turn his gaze from me, that I may brighten up a little

21 Before I go away—and I shall not come back—

To the land of darkness and deep shadow,

22 To the land of obscurity like gloom, of deep shadow

And disorder, where it beams no more than gloom does.”

Job

11 And Zo′phar the Na′a·ma·thite proceeded to answer and say:

2 “Will a multitude of words go unanswered,

Or will a mere boaster be in the right?

3 Will your empty talk itself put men to silence,

And will you keep deriding without having anyone rebuke you?

4 Also, you say, ‘My instruction is pure,

And I have proved really clean in your eyes.’

5 Yet O if only God himself would speak

And open his lips with you!

6 Then he would tell you the secrets of wisdom,

For the things of practical wisdom are manifold.

Also, you would know that God allows some of your error to be forgotten for you.

7 Can you find out the deep things of God,

Or can you find out to the very limit of the Almighty?

8 It is higher than heaven. What can you accomplish?

It is deeper than She′ol. What can you know?

9 It is longer than the earth in measure,

And broader than the sea.

10 If he moves on and hands someone over

And calls a court, then who can resist him?

11 For he himself well knows men who are untrue.

When he sees what is hurtful, will he not also show himself attentive?

12 Even a hollow-minded man himself will get good motive

As soon as an asinine zebra be born a man.

13 If you yourself will really prepare your heart

And actually spread out your palms to him,

14 If what is hurtful is in your hand, put it far away,

And let no unrighteousness dwell in your tents.

15 For then you will raise your face without defect

And you will certainly become established, and you will not fear.

16 For you—you will forget trouble itself;

As waters that have passed along you will remember it.

17 And brighter than midday will your life’s duration arise;

Darkness will become like the morning itself.

18 And you will be bound to trust because there exists hope;

And you will certainly look carefully around—in security you will lie down.

19 And you will indeed stretch yourself out, with no one to make you tremble.

And many people will certainly put you in a gentle mood;

20 And the very eyes of the wicked will fail;

And a place for flight will certainly perish from them,

And their hope will be an expiring of the soul.”

Job

13 “Look! All this my eye has seen,

My ear has heard and considers it.

2 What YOU men know I myself well know also;

I am not inferior to YOU.

3 However, I, for my part, would speak to the Almighty himself,

And in arguing with God I would find delight.

4 On the other hand, YOU men are smearers of falsehood;

All of YOU are physicians of no value.

5 If only YOU would absolutely keep silent,

That it might prove to be wisdom on YOUR part!

6 Hear, please, my counterarguments,

And to the pleadings of my lips pay attention.

7 Will YOU men speak unrighteousness for God himself,

And for him will YOU speak deceit?

8 Will YOU be treating him with partiality,

Or for the true God will YOU contend at law?

9 Would it be good that he sound YOU out?

Or as one trifles with mortal man will YOU trifle with him?

10 He will positively reprove YOU

If in secrecy YOU try to show partiality;

11 Will not his very dignity make YOU start up with fright,

And the very dread of him fall upon YOU?

12 YOUR memorable sayings are proverbs of ashes;

YOUR shield bosses are as shield bosses of clay.

13 KEEP silent before me, that I myself may speak.

Then let come upon me whatever it may be!

14 Why do I carry my flesh in my teeth

And place my own soul in my palm?

15 Even if he would slay me, would I not wait?

I would only argue to his face for my own ways.

16 He would also be my salvation,

For before him no apostate will come in.

17 HEAR my word clear through,

And let my declaration be in YOUR ears.

18 Look! Please, I have presented a case of justice;

I well know that I myself am in the right.

19 Who is the one that will contend with me?

For now were I to become silent I should simply expire!

20 Only two things do not do to me;

In that case I shall not conceal myself just on your account;

21 Put your own hand far away from upon me,

And the fright of you—may it not terrify me.

22 Either call that I myself may answer;

Or may I speak, and you return me answer.

23 In what way do I have errors and sins?

Make me to know my own revolt and my own sin.

24 Why do you conceal your very face

And regard me as an enemy of yours?

25 Will you make a mere leaf driven about quiver,

Or keep chasing after mere dry stubble?

26 For you keep writing against me bitter things

And you make me possess the consequences of the errors of my youth.

27 You also keep my feet put in the stocks,

And you watch all my paths;

For the soles of my feet you mark your own line.

28 And he is like something rotten that wears out;

Like a garment that a moth actually eats up.

Job

18 And Bil′dad the Shu′hite proceeded to answer and say:

2 “How long will YOU people be at putting an end to words?

YOU should understand, that afterward we may speak.

3 Why should we be reckoned as beasts

And be regarded as unclean in YOUR eyes?

4 He is tearing his soul to pieces in his anger.

For your sake will the earth be abandoned,

Or a rock move away from its place?

5 The light also of wicked ones will be extinguished

And the spark of his fire will not shine.

6 A light itself will certainly grow dark in his tent,

And in it his own lamp will be extinguished.

7 His steps of vigor will become cramped.

Even his counsel will cast him off.

8 For he will indeed be let go into a net by his feet,

And onto a network he will walk.

9 A trap will seize him by the heel;

A snare keeps hold upon him.

10 A cord for him is hidden on the earth,

And a catching device for him on his pathway.

11 Round about, sudden terrors certainly make him start up in fright,

And indeed chase him at his feet.

12 His vigor becomes famished,

And disaster stands ready to make him limp.

13 It will eat the pieces of his skin;

The firstborn of death will eat his limbs.

14 His confidence will be torn away from his own tent

And it will march him to the king of terrors.

15 There will reside in his tent something that is not his;

Sulphur will be strewed upon his own abiding place.

16 Underneath will his very roots dry up,

And, up above, his bough will wither.

17 The very mentioning of him will certainly perish from the earth,

And he will have no name out in the street.

18 They will push him out of the light into the darkness,

And from the productive land they will chase him away.

19 He will have no posterity and no progeny among his people,

And there will be no survivor in his place of alien residence.

20 At his day the people in the West will indeed stare in amazement,

And a shudder will certainly seize even the people in the East.

21 Only these are the tabernacles of a wrongdoer,

And this is the place of one that has not known God.”

Job

19 And Job proceeded to answer and say:

2 “How long will YOU men keep irritating my soul

And keep crushing me with words?

3 These ten times YOU proceeded to rebuke me;

YOU are not ashamed that YOU deal so hard with me.

4 And, granted that I have made a mistake,

It is with me that my mistake will lodge.

5 If for a fact against me YOU men do put on great airs,

And YOU show my reproach to be proper against me,

6 KNOW, then, that God himself has misled me,

And his hunting net he has closed in upon me.

7 Look! I keep crying out, ‘Violence!’ but I get no answer;

I keep crying for help, but there is no justice.

8 My very path he has blocked with a stone wall, and I cannot pass over;

And upon my roadways he puts darkness itself.

9 My own glory he has stripped from me,

And he takes away the crown of my head.

10 He pulls me down on all sides, and I go away;

And he pulls my hope out just like a tree.

11 His anger also grows hot against me,

And he keeps reckoning me as an adversary of his.

12 Unitedly his troops come and cast up their way against me,

And they camp round about my tent.

13 My own brothers he has put far away from me,

And the very ones knowing me have even turned aside from me.

14 My intimate acquaintances have ceased to be,

And those known by me have themselves forgotten me,

15 Those residing as aliens in my house; and my slave girls themselves reckon me as a stranger;

A real foreigner I have become in their eyes.

16 To my servant I have called, but he does not answer.

With my own mouth I keep imploring him for compassion.

17 My breath itself has become loathsome to my wife,

And I have become foul-smelling to the sons of my mother’s belly.

18 Also young boys themselves have rejected me;

Let me but rise up, and they begin to speak against me.

19 All the men of my intimate group detest me,

And those whom I loved have turned against me.

20 To my skin and to my flesh my bones actually cleave,

And I escape with the skin of my teeth.

21 Show me some favor, show me some favor, O YOU my companions,

For God’s own hand has touched me.

22 Why do YOU men keep persecuting me as God does,

And not become satisfied with my very flesh?

23 O that now my words were written down!

O that in a book they were even inscribed!

24 With an iron stylus and with lead,

Forever in the rock O that they were hewn!

25 And I myself well know that my redeemer is alive,

And that, coming after me, he will rise up over the dust.

26 And after my skin, which they have skinned off,—this!

Yet reduced in my flesh I shall behold God,

27 Whom even I shall behold for myself,

And whom my very eyes will certainly see, but not some stranger.

My kidneys have failed deep within me.

28 For YOU men say, ‘Why do we keep persecuting him?’

When the very root of the matter is found in me.

29 Be frightened for yourselves because of a sword,

For the sword means a raging against errors,

In order that YOU men may know there is a judge.”

Job

36 And E·li′hu proceeded to say further:

2 “Have patience with me a little while, and I shall declare to you

That there are yet words to say for God.

3 I shall carry my knowledge from far off,

And to my Fashioner I shall ascribe righteousness.

4 For my words are for a fact no falsehood;

The One perfect in knowledge is with you.

5 Look! God is mighty and will not reject;

He is mighty in power of heart;

6 He will not preserve anyone wicked alive,

But the judgment of the afflicted ones he will give.

7 He will not take away his eyes from anyone righteous;

Even kings on the throne—

He will also seat them forever, and they will be exalted.

8 And if they are bound in fetters,

They are captured with ropes of affliction.

9 Then he will tell them about the way they act

And their transgressions, because they take a superior air.

10 And he will uncover their ear to exhortation,

And he will say that they should turn back from what is hurtful.

11 If they obey and serve,

They will finish their days in what is good

And their years in pleasantness.

12 But if they do not obey, they will pass away even by a missile,

And they will expire without knowledge.

13 And those apostate in heart will themselves lay up anger.

They should not cry for help because he has bound them.

14 Their soul will die in youth itself,

And their life among male temple prostitutes.

15 He will rescue the afflicted one in his affliction,

And he will uncover their ear in the oppression.

16 And he will also certainly allure you from the mouth of distress!

Broader space, not constraint, will be in its place,

And the consolation of your table will be full of fatness.

17 With the judicial sentence upon the wicked one you will certainly be filled;

Judicial sentence and justice will themselves take hold.

18 For take care that rage does not allure you into spiteful handclapping,

And let not a large ransom itself lead you astray.

19 Will your cry for help take effect? No, nor in distress

Even all your powerful efforts.

20 Do not pant for the night,

For peoples to retreat from where they are.

21 Be on your guard that you do not turn to what is hurtful,

For this you have chosen rather than affliction.

22 Look! God himself acts exaltedly with his power;

Who is an instructor like him?

23 Who has called his way to account against him,

And who has said, ‘You have committed unrighteousness’?

24 Remember that you should magnify his activity

Of which men have sung.

25 All mankind themselves have gazed upon it;

Mortal man himself keeps looking from far off.

26 Behold! God is more exalted than we can know;

In number his years are beyond searching.

27 For he draws up the drops of water;

They filter as rain for his mist,

28 So that the clouds trickle,

They drip upon mankind abundantly.

29 Indeed, who can understand the cloud layers,

The crashings from his booth?

30 Look! He has spread out over it his light,

And the roots of the sea he has covered.

31 For by them he pleads the cause of peoples;

He gives food in abundance.

32 In his hands he has covered over the lightning,

And he lays a command upon it against an assailant.

33 His booming tells about him,

The livestock also concerning the one coming up.

Job

40 And Jehovah proceeded to answer Job and say:

2 “Should there be any contending of a faultfinder with the Almighty?

Let the reprover of God himself answer it.”

3 And Job went on to answer Jehovah and say:

4 “Look! I have become of little account.

What shall I reply to you?

My hand I have put over my mouth.

5 Once have I spoken, and I will not answer;

And twice, and I will add nothing.”

6 And Jehovah went on to answer Job out of the windstorm and say:

7 “Gird up your loins, please, like an able-bodied man;

I shall question you, and you inform me.

8 Really, will you invalidate my justice?

Will you pronounce me wicked in order that you may be in the right?

9 Or do you have an arm like that of the true God,

And with a voice like his can you make it thunder?

10 Deck yourself, please, with superiority and highness;

And with dignity and splendor may you clothe yourself.

11 Let flow the furious outbursts of your anger,

And see every one haughty and bring him low.

12 See every one haughty, humble him,

And tread down the wicked right where they are.

13 Hide them together in the dust,

Bind their very faces in the hidden place,

14 And I, even I, shall commend you,

Because your right hand can save you.

15 Here, now, is Be·he′moth that I have made as well as you.

Green grass it eats just as a bull does.

16 Here, now, its power is in its hips,

And its dynamic energy in the tendons of its belly.

17 It bends down its tail like a cedar;

The sinews of its thighs are interwoven.

18 Its bones are tubes of copper;

Its strong bones are like wrought-iron rods.

19 It is the beginning of the ways of God;

Its Maker can bring near his sword.

20 For the mountains themselves bear their produce for it,

And all the wild beasts of the field themselves play there.

21 Under the thorny lotus trees it lies down,

In the concealed place of reeds and the swampy place.

22 The thorny lotus trees keep it blocked off with their shadow;

The poplars of the torrent valley surround it.

23 If the river acts violently, it does not run in panic.

It is confident, although the Jordan should burst forth against its mouth.

24 Before its eyes can anyone take it?

With snares can anyone bore its nose?

Job

42 And Job proceeded to answer Jehovah and say:

2 “I have come to know that you are able to do all things,

And there is no idea that is unattainable for you.

3 ‘Who is this that is obscuring counsel without knowledge?’

Therefore I talked, but I was not understanding

Things too wonderful for me, which I do not know.

4 ‘Hear, please, and I myself shall speak.

I shall question you, and you inform me.’

5 In hearsay I have heard about you,

But now my own eye does see you.

6 That is why I make a retraction,

And I do repent in dust and ashes.”

7 And it came about after Jehovah had spoken these words to Job, that Jehovah proceeded to say to El′i·phaz the Te′man·ite:

“My anger has grown hot against you and your two companions, for YOU men have not spoken concerning me what is truthful as has my servant Job. 8 And now take for yourselves seven bulls and seven rams and go to my servant Job, and YOU men must offer up a burnt sacrifice in YOUR own behalf; and Job my servant will himself pray for YOU. His face only I shall accept so as not to commit disgraceful folly with YOU, for YOU have not spoken concerning me what is truthful, as has my servant Job.”

9 Accordingly El′i·phaz the Te′man·ite and Bil′dad the Shu′hite and Zo′phar the Na′a·ma·thite went and did just as Jehovah had spoken to them; and so Jehovah accepted Job’s face.

10 And Jehovah himself turned back the captive condition of Job when he prayed in behalf of his companions, and Jehovah began to give in addition all that had been Job’s, in double amount. 11 And there kept coming to him all his brothers and all his sisters and all those formerly knowing him, and they began to eat bread with him in his house and to sympathize with him and to comfort him over all the calamity that Jehovah had let come upon him; and they proceeded each one to give him a piece of money and each one a gold ring.

12 As for Jehovah, he blessed the end of Job afterward more than his beginning, so that he came to have fourteen thousand sheep and six thousand camels and a thousand spans of cattle and a thousand she-asses. 13 He also came to have seven sons and three daughters. 14 And he went calling the name of the first Je·mi′mah and the name of the second Ke·zi′ah and the name of the third Ker′en-hap′puch. 15 And no women were found as pretty as Job’s daughters in all the land, and their father proceeded to give them an inheritance in among their brothers.

16 And Job continued living after this a hundred and forty years and came to see his sons and his grandsons—four generations. 17 And gradually Job died, old and satisfied with days.

Psalms

A dirge of David that he sang to Jehovah concerning the words of Cush the Ben′ja·min·ite.

7 O Jehovah my God, in you I have taken refuge.

Save me from all those persecuting me and deliver me,

2 That no one may tear my soul to pieces as a lion does,

Snatching me away when there is no deliverer.

3 O Jehovah my God, if I have done this,

If there exists any injustice in my hands,

4 If I have repaid the one rewarding me with what is bad,

Or if I have despoiled anyone showing hostility to me without success,

5 Let an enemy pursue my soul

And let him overtake and trample my life down to the very earth

And cause my own glory to reside in the dust itself. Se′lah.

6 Do arise, O Jehovah, in your anger;

Lift yourself up at the outbursts of fury of those showing hostility to me,

And do awake for me, since you have given command for judgment itself.

7 And let the very assembly of national groups surround you,

And against it do you return on high.

8 Jehovah himself will pass sentence on the peoples.

Judge me, O Jehovah, according to my righteousness

And according to my integrity in me.

9 Please, may the badness of wicked ones come to an end,

And may you establish the righteous one;

And God as righteous is testing out heart and kidneys.

10 The shield for me is upon God, a Savior of those upright in heart.

11 God is a righteous Judge,

And God is hurling denunciations every day.

12 If anyone will not return, His sword he will sharpen,

His bow he will certainly bend, and he will make it ready for shooting.

13 And for himself he must prepare the instruments of death;

His arrows he will make flaming ones.

14 Look! There is one that is pregnant with what is hurtful,

And he has conceived trouble and is bound to give birth to falsehood.

15 A pit he has excavated, and he proceeded to dig it;

But he will fall into the hole that he went making.

16 His trouble will return upon his own head,

And upon the crown of his head his own violence will descend.

17 I shall laud Jehovah according to his righteousness,

And I will make melody to the name of Jehovah the Most High.

Psalms

To the director upon Muth-lab′ben. A melody of David.

א [ʼA′leph]

9 I will laud you, O Jehovah, with all my heart;

I will declare all your wonderful works.

2 I will rejoice and exult in you,

I will make melody to your name, O Most High.

ב [Behth]

3 When my enemies turn back,

They will stumble and perish from before you.

4 For you have executed my judgment and my cause;

You have sat on the throne judging with righteousness.

ג [Gi′mel]

5 You have rebuked nations, you have destroyed the wicked one.

Their name you have wiped out to time indefinite, even forever.

6 O you enemy, your desolations have come to their perpetual finish,

And the cities that you have uprooted.

The very mention of them will certainly perish.

ה [Heʼ]

7 As for Jehovah, he will sit to time indefinite,

Firmly establishing his throne for judgment itself.

8 And he himself will judge the productive land in righteousness;

He will judicially try national groups in uprightness.

ו [Waw]

9 And Jehovah will become a secure height for anyone crushed,

A secure height in times of distress.

10 And those knowing your name will trust in you,

For you will certainly not leave those looking for you, O Jehovah.

ז [Za′yin]

11 Make melody, YOU people, to Jehovah, who is dwelling in Zion;

Tell among the peoples his deeds.

12 For, when looking for bloodshed, he will certainly remember those very ones;

He is sure not to forget the outcry of the afflicted ones.

ח [Chehth]

13 Show me favor, O Jehovah; see my affliction by those hating me,

O you who are lifting me up from the gates of death,

14 In order that I may declare all your praiseworthy deeds

In the gates of the daughter of Zion,

That I may be joyful in your salvation.

ט [Tehth]

15 The nations have sunk down into the pit that they have made;

In the net that they hid, their own foot has been caught.

16 Jehovah is known by the judgment that he has executed.

By the activity of his own hands the wicked one has been ensnared.

Hig·ga′ion. Se′lah.

י [Yohdh]

17 Wicked people will turn back to She′ol,

Even all the nations forgetting God.

18 For not always will the poor one be forgotten,

Nor will the hope of the meek ones ever perish.

כ [Kaph]

19 Do arise, O Jehovah! Let not mortal man prove superior in strength.

Let the nations be judged before your face.

20 Do put fear into them, O Jehovah,

That the nations may know that they are but mortal men. Se′lah.

Psalms

A prayer of David.

17 Do hear what is righteous, O Jehovah; do pay attention to my entreating cry;

Do give ear to my prayer without lips of deception.

2 From before you may my judgment go forth;

May your own eyes behold uprightness.

3 You have examined my heart, you have made inspection by night,

You have refined me; you will discover that I have not schemed.

My mouth will not transgress.

4 As for the activities of men,

By the word of your lips I myself have watched against the paths of the robber.

5 Let my steps take hold on your tracks,

In which my footsteps will certainly not be made to totter.

6 I myself do call upon you, because you will answer me, O God.

Incline your ear to me. Hear my saying.

7 Make your acts of loving-kindnesses wonderful, O Savior of those seeking refuge

From the revolters against your right hand.

8 Keep me as the pupil of the eyeball,

In the shadow of your wings may you conceal me,

9 Because of the wicked who have despoiled me.

The enemies against my soul themselves keep closing in upon me.

10 They have enclosed themselves with their own fat;

With their mouth they have spoken in haughtiness;

11 As regards our steps, now they have surrounded us;

They fix their eyes to incline to the earth.

12 His likeness is that of a lion that yearns to tear to pieces

And that of a young lion sitting in concealed places.

13 Do rise up, O Jehovah; do confront him to the face;

Make him bow down; do provide escape for my soul from the wicked one with your sword,

14 From men, by your hand, O Jehovah,

From men of this system of things, whose share is in this life,

And whose belly you fill with your concealed treasure,

Who are satisfied with sons

And who do lay up for their children what they leave over.

15 As for me, in righteousness I shall behold your face;

I will be satisfied when awakening to see your form.

Psalms

Of David. A melody.

24 To Jehovah belong the earth and that which fills it,

The productive land and those dwelling in it.

2 For upon the seas he himself has solidly fixed it,

And upon the rivers he keeps it firmly established.

3 Who may ascend into the mountain of Jehovah,

And who may rise up in his holy place?

4 Anyone innocent in his hands and clean in heart,

Who has not carried My soul to sheer worthlessness,

Nor taken an oath deceitfully.

5 He will carry away blessing from Jehovah

And righteousness from his God of salvation.

6 This is the generation of those seeking him,

Of those searching for your face, O God of Jacob. Se′lah.

7 “Raise YOUR heads, O YOU gates,

And raise yourselves up, O YOU long-lasting entrances,

That the glorious King may come in!”

8 “Who, then, is this glorious King?”

“Jehovah strong and mighty,

Jehovah mighty in battle.”

9 “Raise YOUR heads, O YOU gates;

Yes, raise them up, O YOU long-lasting entrances,

That the glorious King may come in!”

10 “Who, then, is he, this glorious King?”

“Jehovah of armies—he is the glorious King.” Se′lah.

Psalms

Of David. Mas′kil.

32 Happy is the one whose revolt is pardoned, whose sin is covered.

2 Happy is the man to whose account Jehovah does not put error,

And in whose spirit there is no deceit.

3 When I kept silent my bones wore out through my groaning all day long.

4 For day and night your hand was heavy upon me.

My life’s moisture has been changed as in the dry heat of summer. Se′lah.

5 My sin I finally confessed to you, and my error I did not cover.

I said: “I shall make confession over my transgressions to Jehovah.”

And you yourself pardoned the error of my sins. Se′lah.

6 On this account every loyal one will pray to you

At such a time only as you may be found.

As for the flood of many waters, they will not touch him himself.

7 You are a place of concealment for me; you will safeguard me from distress itself.

With joyful cries at providing escape you will surround me. Se′lah.

8 “I shall make you have insight and instruct you in the way you should go.

I will give advice with my eye upon you.

9 Do not make yourselves like a horse or mule without understanding,

Whose spiritedness is to be curbed even by bridle or halter

Before they will come near to you.”

10 Many are the pains that the wicked one has;

But as for the one trusting in Jehovah, loving-kindness itself surrounds him.

11 Rejoice in Jehovah and be joyful, YOU righteous ones;

And cry out joyfully, all YOU who are upright in heart.

Psalms

33 Cry out joyfully, O YOU righteous ones, because of Jehovah.

On the part of the upright ones praise is fitting.

2 Give thanks to Jehovah on the harp;

On an instrument of ten strings make melody to him.

3 Sing to him a new song;

Do YOUR best at playing on the strings along with joyful shouting.

4 For the word of Jehovah is upright,

And all his work is in faithfulness.

5 He is a lover of righteousness and justice.

With the loving-kindness of Jehovah the earth is filled.

6 By the word of Jehovah the heavens themselves were made,

And by the spirit of his mouth all their army.

7 He is gathering as by a dam the waters of the sea,

Putting in storehouses the surging waters.

8 Let all those of the earth be in fear of Jehovah.

At him let all the inhabitants of the productive land be frightened.

9 For he himself said, and it came to be;

He himself commanded, and it proceeded to stand so.

10 Jehovah himself has broken up the counsel of the nations;

He has thwarted the thoughts of the peoples.

11 To time indefinite the very counsel of Jehovah will stand;

The thoughts of his heart are to one generation after another generation.

12 Happy is the nation whose God is Jehovah,

The people whom he has chosen as his inheritance.

13 From the heavens Jehovah has looked,

He has seen all the sons of men.

14 From the established place where he dwells

He has gazed at all those dwelling on the earth.

15 He is forming their hearts all together;

He is considering all their works.

16 There is no king saved by the abundance of military forces;

A mighty man himself is not delivered by the abundance of power.

17 The horse is a deception for salvation,

And by the abundance of its vital energy it does not afford escape.

18 Look! The eye of Jehovah is toward those fearing him,

To those waiting for his loving-kindness,

19 To deliver their soul from death itself,

And to preserve them alive in famine.

20 Our very soul has been in expectation of Jehovah.

Our helper and our shield he is.

21 For in him our heart rejoices;

For in his holy name we have put our trust.

22 Let your loving-kindness, O Jehovah, prove to be upon us,

Even as we have kept waiting for you.

Psalms

BOOK TWO

(Psalms 42 – 72)

To the director. Mas′kil for the sons of Ko′rah.

42 As the hind that longs for the water streams,

So my very soul longs for you, O God.

2 My soul indeed thirsts for God, for the living God.

When shall I come and appear before God?

3 To me my tears have become food day and night,

While they say to me all day long: “Where is your God?”

4 These things I will remember, and I will pour out my soul within me.

For I used to pass along with the throng,

I used to walk slowly before them to the house of God,

With the voice of a joyful cry and thanksgiving,

Of a crowd celebrating a festival.

5 Why are you in despair, O my soul,

And why are you boisterous within me?

Wait for God,

For I shall yet laud him as the grand salvation of my person.

6 O my God, within me my very soul is in despair.

That is why I remember you,

From the land of Jordan and the peaks of Her′mon,

From the little mountain.

7 Watery deep to watery deep is calling

At the sound of your waterspouts.

All your breakers and your waves—

Over me they have passed.

8 By day Jehovah will command his loving-kindness,

And by night his song will be with me;

There will be prayer to the God of my life.

9 I will say to God my crag:

“Why have you forgotten me?

Why do I walk sad because of the oppression of the enemy?”

10 With murder against my bones those showing hostility to me have reproached me,

While they say to me all day long: “Where is your God?”

11 Why are you in despair, O my soul,

And why are you boisterous within me?

Wait for God,

For I shall yet laud him as the grand salvation of my person and as my God.

Psalms

To the director upon The Lilies. Of the sons of Ko′rah. Mas′kil. A song of the beloved women.

45 My heart has become astir with a goodly matter.

I am saying: “My works are concerning a king.”

May my tongue be the stylus of a skilled copyist.

2 You are indeed more handsome than the sons of men.

Charm has been poured out upon your lips.

That is why God has blessed you to time indefinite.

3 Gird your sword upon your thigh, O mighty one,

With your dignity and your splendor.

4 And in your splendor go on to success;

Ride in the cause of truth and humility and righteousness,

And your right hand will instruct you in fear-inspiring things.

5 Your arrows are sharp—under you peoples keep falling—

In the heart of the enemies of the king.

6 God is your throne to time indefinite, even forever;

The scepter of your kingship is a scepter of uprightness.

7 You have loved righteousness and you hate wickedness.

That is why God, your God, has anointed you with the oil of exultation more than your partners.

8 All your garments are myrrh and aloeswood and cassia;

Out from the grand ivory palace stringed instruments themselves have made you rejoice.

9 The daughters of kings are among your precious women.

The queenly consort has taken her stand at your right hand in gold of O′phir.

10 Listen, O daughter, and see, and incline your ear;

And forget your people and your father’s house.

11 And the king will long for your prettiness,

For he is your lord,

So bow down to him.

12 The daughter of Tyre also with a gift—

The rich ones of the people will soften your own face.

13 The king’s daughter is all glorious within the house;

Her clothing is with settings of gold.

14 In woven apparel she will be brought to the king.

The virgins in her train as her companions are being brought in to you.

15 They will be brought with rejoicing and joyfulness;

They will enter into the palace of the king.

16 In place of your forefathers there will come to be your sons,

Whom you will appoint as princes in all the earth.

17 I will make mention of your name throughout all generations to come.

That is why peoples themselves will laud you to time indefinite, even forever.

Psalms

A melody of A′saph.

50 The Divine One, God, Jehovah, has himself spoken,

And he proceeds to call the earth,

From the rising of the sun until its setting.

2 Out of Zion, the perfection of prettiness, God himself has beamed forth.

3 Our God will come and cannot possibly keep silent.

Before him there devours a fire,

And all around him it has become exceedingly stormy weather.

4 He calls to the heavens above and to the earth

So as to execute judgment on his people:

5 “Gather to me my loyal ones,

Those concluding my covenant over sacrifice.”

6 And the heavens tell of his righteousness,

For God himself is Judge. Se′lah.

7 “Do listen, O my people, and I will speak,

O Israel, and I will bear witness against you.

I am God, your God.

8 Not concerning your sacrifices do I reprove you,

Nor concerning your whole burnt offerings that are in front of me constantly.

9 I will not take out of your house a bull,

Out of your pens he-goats.

10 For to me belongs every wild animal of the forest,

The beasts upon a thousand mountains.

11 I well know every winged creature of the mountains,

And the animal throngs of the open field are with me.

12 If I were hungry, I would not say it to you;

For to me the productive land and its fullness belong.

13 Shall I eat the flesh of powerful bulls,

And the blood of he-goats shall I drink?

14 Offer thanksgiving as your sacrifice to God,

And pay to the Most High your vows;

15 And call me in the day of distress.

I shall rescue you, and you will glorify me.”

16 But to the wicked one God will have to say:

“What right do you have to enumerate my regulations,

And that you may bear my covenant in your mouth?

17 Why, you—you have hated discipline,

And you keep throwing my words behind you.

18 Whenever you saw a thief, you were even pleased with him;

And your sharing was with adulterers.

19 Your mouth you have let loose to what is bad,

And your tongue you keep attached to deception.

20 You sit and speak against your own brother,

Against the son of your mother you give away a fault.

21 These things you have done, and I kept silent.

You imagined that I would positively become like you.

I am going to reprove you, and I will set things in order before your eyes.

22 Understand this, please, YOU forgetters of God,

That I may not tear YOU to pieces without there being any deliverer.

23 The one offering thanksgiving as his sacrifice is the one that glorifies me;

And as for the one keeping a set way,

I will cause him to see salvation by God.”

Psalms

To the director. A melody of David. When Nathan the prophet came in to him after he had had relations with Bath-she′ba.

51 Show me favor, O God, according to your loving-kindness.

According to the abundance of your mercies wipe out my transgressions.

2 Thoroughly wash me from my error,

And cleanse me even from my sin.

3 For my transgressions I myself know,

And my sin is in front of me constantly.

4 Against you, you alone, I have sinned,

And what is bad in your eyes I have done,

In order that you may prove to be righteous when you speak,

That you may be in the clear when you judge.

5 Look! With error I was brought forth with birth pains,

And in sin my mother conceived me.

6 Look! You have taken delight in truthfulness itself in the inward parts;

And in the secret self may you cause me to know sheer wisdom.

7 May you purify me from sin with hyssop, that I may be clean;

May you wash me, that I may become whiter even than snow.

8 May you cause me to hear exultation and rejoicing,

That the bones that you have crushed may be joyful.

9 Conceal your face from my sins,

And wipe out even all my errors.

10 Create in me even a pure heart, O God,

And put within me a new spirit, a steadfast one.

11 Do not throw me away from before your face;

And your holy spirit O do not take away from me.

12 Do restore to me the exultation of salvation by you,

And may you support me even with a willing spirit.

13 I will teach transgressors your ways,

That sinners themselves may turn right back to you.

14 Deliver me from bloodguiltiness, O God the God of my salvation,

That my tongue may joyfully tell about your righteousness.

15 O Jehovah, may you open these lips of mine,

That my own mouth may tell forth your praise.

16 For you do not take delight in sacrifice—otherwise I would give it;

In whole burnt offering you do not find pleasure.

17 The sacrifices to God are a broken spirit;

A heart broken and crushed, O God, you will not despise.

18 In your goodwill do deal well with Zion;

May you build the walls of Jerusalem.

19 In that case you will be delighted with sacrifices of righteousness,

With burnt sacrifice and whole offering;

In that case bulls will be offered up on your very own altar.

Psalms

To the director on the Silent Dove among those far away. Of David. Mik′tam. When the Phi·lis′tines laid hold of him in Gath.

56 Show me favor, O God, because mortal man has snapped at me.

Warring all day long, he keeps oppressing me.

2 My foes have kept snapping all day long,

For there are many warring against me high-mindedly.

3 Whatever day I get afraid, I, for my part, shall trust even in you.

4 In union with God I shall praise his word.

In God I have put my trust; I shall not be afraid.

What can flesh do to me?

5 All day long they keep hurting my personal affairs;

All their thoughts are against me for bad.

6 They attack, they conceal themselves,

They, for their part, keep observing my very steps,

While they have waited for my soul.

7 On account of their hurtfulness cast them forth.

In anger bring down even the peoples, O God.

8 My being a fugitive you yourself have reported.

Do put my tears in your skin bottle.

Are they not in your book?

9 At that time my enemies will turn back, on the day that I call;

This I well know, that God is for me.

10 In union with God I shall praise his word;

In union with Jehovah I shall praise his word.

11 In God I have put my trust. I shall not be afraid.

What can earthling man do to me?

12 Upon me, O God, there are vows to you.

I shall render expressions of thanksgiving to you.

13 For you have delivered my soul from death—

Have you not delivered my feet from stumbling?—

That I may walk about before God in the light of those alive.

Psalms

To the director on The Lily of Reminder. Mik′tam. Of David. For teaching. When he engaged in a struggle with A′ram-na·ha·ra′im and A′ram-Zo′bah, and Jo′ab proceeded to return and strike down E′dom in the Valley of Salt, even twelve thousand.

60 O God, you have cast us off, you have broken through us,

You have become incensed. You should restore us.

2 You have caused the earth to rock, you have split it open.

Heal its breaches, for it has tottered.

3 You have caused your people to see hardship.

You have made us drink wine sending us reeling.

4 You have given to those fearing you a signal

To flee zigzag on account of the bow. Se′lah.

5 In order that your beloved ones may be rescued,

O do save with your right hand and answer us.

6 God himself has spoken in his holiness:

“I will exult, I will give out She′chem as a portion;

And the low plain of Suc′coth I shall measure off.

7 Gil′e·ad belongs to me and Ma·nas′seh belongs to me,

And E′phra·im is the fortress of my head one;

Judah is my commander’s staff.

8 Mo′ab is my washing pot.

Over E′dom I shall throw my sandal.

Over Phi·lis′ti·a I shall shout in triumph.”

9 Who will bring me to the besieged city?

Who will certainly lead me as far as E′dom?

10 Is it not you, O God, who have cast us off

And who do not go forth with our armies as God?

11 Do give us assistance from distress,

As salvation by earthling man is worthless.

12 By God we shall gain vital energy,

And he himself will tread down our adversaries.

Psalms

71 In you, O Jehovah, I have taken refuge.

O may I never be ashamed.

2 In your righteousness may you deliver me and provide me with escape.

Incline to me your ear and save me.

3 Become to me a rock fortress into which to enter constantly.

You must command to save me,

For you are my crag and my stronghold.

4 O my God, provide me with escape from the hand of the wicked one,

From the palm of the one acting unjustly and oppressively.

5 For you are my hope, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, my confidence from my youth.

6 Upon you I have supported myself from the belly;

You are the One severing me even from the inward parts of my mother.

In you my praise is constantly.

7 I have become just like a miracle to many people;

But you are my strong refuge.

8 My mouth is filled with your praise,

All day long with your beauty.

9 Do not throw me away in the time of old age;

Just when my power is failing, do not leave me.

10 For my enemies have said in regard to me,

And the very ones keeping watch for my soul have jointly exchanged counsel,

11 Saying: “God himself has left him.

Pursue and catch him, for there is no deliverer.”

12 O God, do not keep far away from me.

O my God, do hurry to my assistance.

13 May those be ashamed, may those come to their end, who are resisting my soul.

May those cover themselves with reproach and humiliation who are seeking calamity for me.

14 But as for me, I shall wait constantly,

And I will add to all your praise.

15 My own mouth will recount your righteousness,

All day long your salvation,

For I have not come to know the numbers of them.

16 I shall come in grand mightiness, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah;

I shall mention your righteousness, yours alone.

17 O God, you have taught me from my youth on,

And until now I keep telling about your wonderful works.

18 And even until old age and gray-headedness, O God, do not leave me,

Until I may tell about your arm to the generation,

To all those who are to come, about your mightiness.

19 Your righteousness, O God, is up to the height;

As respects the great things that you have done,

O God, who is like you?

20 Because you have made me see many distresses and calamities,

May you revive me again;

And from the watery deeps of the earth may you again bring me up.

21 May you enlarge my greatness,

And may you surround and comfort me.

22 I too, I shall laud you on an instrument of a stringed sort,

As regards your trueness, O my God.

I will make melody to you on the harp, O Holy One of Israel.

23 My lips will cry out joyfully when I am inclined to make melody to you,

Even my soul that you have redeemed.

24 Also, my own tongue, all day long, will utter in an undertone your righteousness,

For they have become ashamed, for they have become abashed, who are seeking calamity for me.

Psalms

To the director. “Do not bring to ruin.” A melody. Of A′saph. A song.

75 We give thanks to you, O God; we give thanks to you,

And your name is near.

Men have to declare your wondrous works.

2 “For I proceeded to take a set time;

I myself began judging with uprightness.

3 The earth and all its inhabitants being dissolved,

It was I that adjusted its pillars.” Se′lah.

4 I said to the foolish ones: “Do not be foolish,”

And to the wicked ones: “Do not exalt the horn.

5 Do not exalt YOUR horn on high.

Do not speak with an arrogant neck.

6 For neither from the east nor from the west,

Nor from the south is there an exalting.

7 For God is the judge.

This one he abases, and that one he exalts.

8 For there is a cup in the hand of Jehovah,

And the wine is foaming, it is full of mixture.

And he will surely pour out its dregs from it;

All the wicked ones of the earth will drain them out, drink them.”

9 But as for me, I shall tell of it to time indefinite;

I will make melody to the God of Jacob.

10 “And all the horns of the wicked ones I shall cut down.”

The horns of the righteous one will be exalted.

Psalms

To the director upon The Lilies. A reminder. Of A′saph. A melody.

80 O Shepherd of Israel, do give ear,

You who are conducting Joseph just like a flock.

O you who are sitting upon the cherubs, do beam forth.

2 Before E′phra·im and Benjamin and Ma·nas′seh do rouse up your mightiness,

And do come to our salvation.

3 O God, bring us back;

And light up your face, that we may be saved.

4 O Jehovah God of armies, how long must you fume against the prayer of your people?

5 You have made them eat the bread of tears,

And you keep making them drink tears upon tears in great measure.

6 You set us for strife to our neighbors,

And our very enemies keep deriding as they please.

7 O God of armies, bring us back;

And light up your face, that we may be saved.

8 You proceeded to make a vine depart from Egypt.

You kept driving out the nations, that you might plant it.

9 You made a clearing before it, that it might take root and fill the land.

10 The mountains were covered with its shadow,

And the cedars of God with its boughs.

11 It gradually sent forth its boughs as far as the sea,

And to the River its twigs.

12 Why have you broken down its stone walls,

And why have all those passing by on the road plucked at it?

13 A boar out of the woods keeps eating it away,

And the animal throngs of the open field keep feeding upon it.

14 O God of armies, return, please;

Look down from heaven and see and take care of this vine,

15 And the stock that your right hand has planted,

And look upon the son whom you have made strong for yourself.

16 It is burned with fire, cut off.

From the rebuke of your face they perish.

17 Let your hand prove to be upon the man of your right hand,

Upon the son of mankind whom you have made strong for yourself,

18 And we shall not turn back from you.

May you preserve us alive, that we may call upon your own name.

19 O Jehovah God of armies, bring us back;

Light up your face, that we may be saved.

Psalms

96 Sing to Jehovah a new song.

Sing to Jehovah, all YOU people of the earth.

2 Sing to Jehovah, bless his name.

From day to day tell the good news of salvation by him.

3 Declare among the nations his glory,

Among all the peoples his wonderful works.

4 For Jehovah is great and very much to be praised.

He is fear-inspiring above all other gods.

5 For all the gods of the peoples are valueless gods;

But as for Jehovah, he has made the very heavens.

6 Dignity and splendor are before him;

Strength and beauty are in his sanctuary.

7 Ascribe to Jehovah, O YOU families of the peoples,

Ascribe to Jehovah glory and strength.

8 Ascribe to Jehovah the glory belonging to his name;

Carry a gift and come into his courtyards.

9 Bow down to Jehovah in holy adornment;

Be in severe pains because of him, all YOU people of the earth.

10 Say among the nations: “Jehovah himself has become king.

The productive land also becomes firmly established so that it cannot be made to totter.

He will plead the cause of the peoples in uprightness.”

11 Let the heavens rejoice, and let the earth be joyful.

Let the sea thunder and that which fills it.

12 Let the open field exult and all that is in it.

At the same time let all the trees of the forest break out joyfully

13 Before Jehovah. For he has come;

For he has come to judge the earth.

He will judge the productive land with righteousness

And the peoples with his faithfulness.

Psalms

A melody.

98 SING to Jehovah a new song,

For wonderful are the things that he has done.

His right hand, even his holy arm, has gained salvation for him.

2 Jehovah has made his salvation known;

In the eyes of the nations he has revealed his righteousness.

3 He has remembered his loving-kindness and his faithfulness to the house of Israel.

All the ends of the earth have seen the salvation by our God.

4 Shout in triumph to Jehovah, all YOU people of the earth.

Be cheerful and cry out joyfully and make melody.

5 Make melody to Jehovah with the harp,

With the harp and the voice of melody.

6 With the trumpets and the sound of the horn

Shout in triumph before the King, Jehovah.

7 Let the sea thunder and that which fills it,

The productive land and those dwelling in it.

8 Let the rivers themselves clap their hands;

All together let the very mountains cry out joyfully

9 Before Jehovah, for he has come to judge the earth.

He will judge the productive land with righteousness

And the peoples with uprightness.

Psalms

99 Jehovah himself has become king. Let the peoples be agitated.

He is sitting upon the cherubs. Let the earth quiver.

2 Jehovah is great in Zion,

And he is high over all the peoples.

3 Let them laud your name.

Great and fear-inspiring, holy it is.

4 And with the strength of a king judgment he has loved.

You yourself have firmly established uprightness.

Judgment and righteousness in Jacob are what you yourself have effected.

5 Exalt Jehovah our God and bow down yourselves at his footstool;

He is holy.

6 Moses and Aaron were among his priests,

And Samuel was among those calling upon his name.

They were calling to Jehovah, and he himself kept answering them.

7 In the pillar of cloud he continued speaking to them.

They kept his reminders and the regulation that he gave to them.

8 O Jehovah our God, you yourself answered them.

A God granting pardon you proved to be to them,

And executing vengeance against their notorious deeds.

9 Exalt Jehovah our God

And bow down yourselves at his holy mountain.

For Jehovah our God is holy.

Psalms

115 To us belongs nothing, O Jehovah, to us belongs nothing,

But to your name give glory

According to your loving-kindness, according to your trueness.

2 Why should the nations say:

“Where, now, is their God?”

3 But our God is in the heavens;

Everything that he delighted to do he has done.

4 Their idols are silver and gold,

The work of the hands of earthling man.

5 A mouth they have, but they cannot speak;

Eyes they have, but they cannot see;

6 Ears they have, but they cannot hear.

A nose they have, but they cannot smell.

7 Hands are theirs, but they cannot feel.

Feet are theirs, but they cannot walk;

They utter no sound with their throat.

8 Those making them will become just like them,

All those who are trusting in them.

9 O Israel, trust in Jehovah;

He is their help and their shield.

10 O house of Aaron, put YOUR trust in Jehovah;

He is their help and their shield.

11 YOU that fear Jehovah, trust in Jehovah;

He is their help and their shield.

12 Jehovah himself has remembered us; he will bless,

He will bless the house of Israel,

He will bless the house of Aaron.

13 He will bless those fearing Jehovah,

The small ones as well as the great ones.

14 Jehovah will give increase to YOU,

To YOU and to YOUR sons.

15 YOU are the ones blessed by Jehovah,

The Maker of heaven and earth.

16 As regards the heavens, to Jehovah the heavens belong,

But the earth he has given to the sons of men.

17 The dead themselves do not praise Jah,

Nor do any going down into silence.

18 But we ourselves will bless Jah

From now on and to time indefinite.

Praise Jah, YOU people!

Psalms

A praise, of David.

א [ʼA′leph]

145 I will exalt you, O my God the King,

And I will bless your name to time indefinite, even forever.

ב [Behth]

2 All day long I will bless you,

And I will praise your name to time indefinite, even forever.

ג [Gi′mel]

3 Jehovah is great and very much to be praised,

And his greatness is unsearchable.

ד [Da′leth]

4 Generation after generation will commend your works,

And about your mighty acts they will tell.

ה [Heʼ]

5 The glorious splendor of your dignity

And the matters of your wonderful works I will make my concern.

ו [Waw]

6 And they will talk about the strength of your own fear-inspiring things;

And as for your greatness, I will declare it.

ז [Za′yin]

7 With the mention of the abundance of your goodness they will bubble over,

And because of your righteousness they will cry out joyfully.

ח [Chehth]

8 Jehovah is gracious and merciful,

Slow to anger and great in loving-kindness.

ט [Tehth]

9 Jehovah is good to all,

And his mercies are over all his works.

י [Yohdh]

10 All your works will laud you, O Jehovah,

And your loyal ones will bless you.

כ [Kaph]

11 About the glory of your kingship they will talk,

And about your mightiness they will speak,

ל [La′medh]

12 To make known to the sons of men his mighty acts

And the glory of the splendor of his kingship.

מ [Mem]

13 Your kingship is a kingship for all times indefinite,

And your dominion is throughout all successive generations.

ס [Sa′mekh]

14 Jehovah is giving support to all who are falling,

And is raising up all who are bowed down.

ע [ʽA′yin]

15 To you the eyes of all look hopefully,

And you are giving them their food in its season.

פ [Peʼ]

16 You are opening your hand

And satisfying the desire of every living thing.

צ [Tsa·dheh′]

17 Jehovah is righteous in all his ways

And loyal in all his works.

ק [Qohph]

18 Jehovah is near to all those calling upon him,

To all those who call upon him in trueness.

ר [Rehsh]

19 The desire of those fearing him he will perform,

And their cry for help he will hear, and he will save them.

ש [Shin]

20 Jehovah is guarding all those loving him,

But all the wicked ones he will annihilate.

ת [Taw]

21 The praise of Jehovah my mouth will speak;

And let all flesh bless his holy name to time indefinite, even forever.

Psalms

146 Praise Jah, YOU people!

Praise Jehovah, O my soul.

2 I will praise Jehovah during my lifetime.

I will make melody to my God as long as I am.

3 Do not put YOUR trust in nobles,

Nor in the son of earthling man, to whom no salvation belongs.

4 His spirit goes out, he goes back to his ground;

In that day his thoughts do perish.

5 Happy is the one who has the God of Jacob for his help,

Whose hope is in Jehovah his God,

6 The Maker of heaven and earth,

Of the sea, and of all that is in them,

The One keeping trueness to time indefinite,

7 The One executing judgment for the defrauded ones,

The One giving bread to the hungry ones.

Jehovah is releasing those who are bound.

8 Jehovah is opening the eyes of the blind ones;

Jehovah is raising up the ones bowed down;

Jehovah is loving the righteous ones.

9 Jehovah is guarding the alien residents;

The fatherless boy and the widow he relieves,

But the way of the wicked ones he makes crooked.

10 Jehovah will be king to time indefinite,

Your God, O Zion, for generation after generation.

Praise Jah, YOU people!

Proverbs

21 A king’s heart is as streams of water in the hand of Jehovah. Everywhere that he delights to, he turns it.

2 Every way of a man is upright in his own eyes, but Jehovah is making an estimate of hearts.

3 To carry on righteousness and judgment is more preferable to Jehovah than sacrifice.

4 Haughty eyes and an arrogant heart, the lamp of the wicked ones, are sin.

5 The plans of the diligent one surely make for advantage, but everyone that is hasty surely heads for want.

6 The getting of treasures by a false tongue is an exhalation driven away, in the case of those seeking death.

7 The very despoiling by the wicked ones will drag them away, for they have refused to do justice.

8 A man, even a stranger, is crooked in his way; but the pure one is upright in his activity.

9 Better is it to dwell upon a corner of a roof than with a contentious wife, although in a house in common.

10 The very soul of the wicked one has craved what is bad; his fellow will be shown no favor in his eyes.

11 By the laying of a fine on the ridiculer the inexperienced becomes wise; and by one’s giving insight to a wise person he gets knowledge.

12 The Righteous One is giving consideration to the house of the wicked one, subverting the wicked ones to their calamity.

13 As for anyone stopping up his ear from the complaining cry of the lowly one, he himself also will call and not be answered.

14 A gift made in secrecy subdues anger; and a bribe in the bosom, strong rage.

15 It is a rejoicing for the righteous one to do justice, but there is something terrible for those practicing what is hurtful.

16 As for a man wandering from the way of insight, he will rest in the very congregation of those impotent in death.

17 He that is loving merriment will be an individual in want; he that is loving wine and oil will not gain riches.

18 The wicked is a ransom for the righteous one; and the one dealing treacherously takes the place of the upright ones.

19 Better is it to dwell in a wilderness land than with a contentious wife along with vexation.

20 Desirable treasure and oil are in the abode of the wise one, but the man that is stupid will swallow it up.

21 He that is pursuing righteousness and loving-kindness will find life, righteousness and glory.

22 A wise one has scaled even the city of mighty men, that he might bring down the strength of its confidence.

23 He that is keeping his mouth and his tongue is keeping his soul from distresses.

24 Presumptuous, self-assuming braggart is the name of the one who is acting in a fury of presumptuousness.

25 The very craving of the lazy will put him to death, for his hands have refused to work. 26 All the day he has shown himself eagerly craving, but the righteous one gives and holds nothing back.

27 The sacrifice of the wicked ones is something detestable. How much more so when one brings it along with loose conduct.

28 A lying witness will perish, but the man that is listening will speak even forever.

29 A wicked man has put on a bold face, but the upright is the one that will firmly establish his ways.

30 There is no wisdom, nor any discernment, nor any counsel in opposition to Jehovah.

31 The horse is something prepared for the day of battle, but salvation belongs to Jehovah.

Proverbs

31 The words of Lem′u·el the king, the weighty message that his mother gave to him in correction:

2 What am I saying, O son of mine, and what, O son of my belly, and what, O son of my vows?

3 Do not give your vital energy to women, nor your ways to what leads to wiping out kings.

4 It is not for kings, O Lem′u·el, it is not for kings to drink wine or for high officials to say: “Where is intoxicating liquor?” 5 that one may not drink and forget what is decreed and pervert the cause of any of the sons of affliction. 6 Give intoxicating liquor, YOU people, to the one about to perish and wine to those who are bitter of soul. 7 Let one drink and forget one’s poverty, and let one remember one’s own trouble no more.

8 Open your mouth for the speechless one, in the cause of all those passing away. 9 Open your mouth, judge righteously and plead the cause of the afflicted one and the poor one.

א [ʼA′leph]

10 A capable wife who can find? Her value is far more than that of corals.

ב [Behth]

11 In her the heart of her owner has put trust, and there is no gain lacking.

ג [Gi′mel]

12 She has rewarded him with good, and not bad, all the days of her life.

ד [Da′leth]

13 She has sought wool and linen, and she works at whatever is the delight of her hands.

ה [Heʼ]

14 She has proved to be like the ships of a merchant. From far away she brings in her food.

ו [Waw]

15 She also gets up while it is still night, and gives food to her household and the prescribed portion to her young women.

ז [Za′yin]

16 She has considered a field and proceeded to obtain it; from the fruitage of her hands she has planted a vineyard.

ח [Chehth]

17 She has girded her hips with strength, and she invigorates her arms.

ט [Tehth]

18 She has sensed that her trading is good; her lamp does not go out at night.

י [Yohdh]

19 Her hands she has thrust out to the distaff, and her own hands take hold of the spindle.

כ [Kaph]

20 Her palm she has stretched out to the afflicted one, and her hands she has thrust out to the poor one.

ל [La′medh]

21 She does not fear for her household because of the snow, for all her household are clothed with double garments.

מ [Mem]

22 Coverlets she has made for herself. Her clothing is of linen and wool dyed reddish purple.

נ [Nun]

23 Her owner is someone known in the gates, when he sits down with the older men of the land.

ס [Sa′mekh]

24 She has made even undergarments and proceeded to sell them, and belts she has given to the tradesmen.

ע [ʽA′yin]

25 Strength and splendor are her clothing, and she laughs at a future day.

פ [Peʼ]

26 Her mouth she has opened in wisdom, and the law of loving-kindness is upon her tongue.

צ [Tsa·dheh′]

27 She is watching over the goings-on of her household, and the bread of laziness she does not eat.

ק [Qohph]

28 Her sons have risen up and proceeded to pronounce her happy; her owner rises up, and he praises her.

ר [Rehsh]

29 There are many daughters that have shown capableness, but you—you have ascended above them all.

ש [Shin]

30 Charm may be false, and prettiness may be vain; but the woman that fears Jehovah is the one that procures praise for herself.

ת [Taw]

31 GIVE her of the fruitage of her hands, and let her works praise her even in the gates.

Ecclesiastes

5 Guard your feet whenever you go to the house of the true God; and let there be a drawing near to hear, rather than to give a sacrifice as the stupid ones do, for they are not aware of doing what is bad.

2 Do not hurry yourself as regards your mouth; and as for your heart, let it not be hasty to bring forth a word before the true God. For the true God is in the heavens but you are on the earth. That is why your words should prove to be few. 3 For a dream certainly comes in because of abundance of occupation, and the voice of a stupid one because of the abundance of words. 4 Whenever you vow a vow to God, do not hesitate to pay it, for there is no delight in the stupid ones. What you vow, pay. 5 Better is it that you vow not than that you vow and do not pay. 6 Do not allow your mouth to cause your flesh to sin, neither say before the angel that it was a mistake. Why should the true God become indignant on account of your voice and have to wreck the work of your hands? 7 For because of abundance of occupation there are dreams, and there are vanities and words in abundance. But fear the true God himself.

8 If you see any oppression of the one of little means and the violent taking away of judgment and of righteousness in a jurisdictional district, do not be amazed over the affair, for one that is higher than the high one is watching, and there are those who are high above them.

9 Also, the profit of the earth is among them all; for a field the king himself has been served.

10 A mere lover of silver will not be satisfied with silver, neither any lover of wealth with income. This too is vanity.

11 When good things become many, those eating them certainly become many. And what advantage is there to the grand owner of them, except looking at them with his eyes?

12 Sweet is the sleep of the one serving, regardless of whether it is little or much that he eats; but the plenty belonging to the rich one is not permitting him to sleep.

13 There exists a grave calamity that I have seen under the sun: riches being kept for their grand owner to his calamity. 14 And those riches have perished because of a calamitous occupation, and he has become father to a son when there is nothing at all in his hand.

15 Just as one has come forth from his mother’s belly, naked will one go away again, just as one came; and nothing at all can one carry away for his hard work, which he can take along with his hand.

16 And this too is a grave calamity: exactly as one has come, so one will go away; and what profit is there to the one who keeps working hard for the wind? 17 Also, all his days he eats in darkness itself, with a great deal of vexation, with sickness on his part and cause for indignation.

18 Look! The best thing that I myself have seen, which is pretty, is that one should eat and drink and see good for all his hard work with which he works hard under the sun for the number of the days of his life that the true God has given him, for that is his portion. 19 Also every man to whom the true God has given riches and material possessions, he has even empowered him to eat from it and to carry off his portion and to rejoice in his hard work. This is the gift of God. 20 For not often will he remember the days of his life, because the true God is preoccupying him with the rejoicing of his heart.

Ecclesiastes

7 A name is better than good oil, and the day of death than the day of one’s being born. 2 Better is it to go to the house of mourning than to go to the banquet house, because that is the end of all mankind; and the one alive should take it to his heart. 3 Better is vexation than laughter, for by the crossness of the face the heart becomes better. 4 The heart of the wise ones is in the house of mourning, but the heart of the stupid ones is in the house of rejoicing.

5 Better is it to hear the rebuke of someone wise than to be the man hearing the song of the stupid ones. 6 For as the sound of thorns under the pot, so is the laughter of the stupid one; and this too is vanity. 7 For mere oppression may make a wise one act crazy, and a gift can destroy the heart.

8 Better is the end afterward of a matter than its beginning. Better is one who is patient than one who is haughty in spirit. 9 Do not hurry yourself in your spirit to become offended, for the taking of offense is what rests in the bosom of the stupid ones.

10 Do not say: “Why has it happened that the former days proved to be better than these?” for it is not due to wisdom that you have asked about this.

11 Wisdom along with an inheritance is good and is advantageous for those seeing the sun. 12 For wisdom is for a protection the same as money is for a protection; but the advantage of knowledge is that wisdom itself preserves alive its owners.

13 See the work of the true God, for who is able to make straight what he has made crooked? 14 On a good day prove yourself to be in goodness, and on a calamitous day see that the true God has made even this exactly as that, to the intent that mankind may not discover anything at all after them.

15 Everything I have seen during my vain days. There exists the righteous one perishing in his righteousness, and there exists the wicked one continuing long in his badness.

16 Do not become righteous overmuch, nor show yourself excessively wise. Why should you cause desolation to yourself? 17 Do not be wicked overmuch, nor become foolish. Why should you die when it is not your time? 18 It is better that you should take hold of the one, but from the other also do not withdraw your hand; for he that fears God will go forth with them all.

19 Wisdom itself is stronger for the wise one than ten men in power who happened to be in a city. 20 For there is no man righteous in the earth that keeps doing good and does not sin.

21 Also, do not give your heart to all the words that people may speak, that you may not hear your servant calling down evil upon you. 22 For your own heart well knows even many times that you, even you, have called down evil upon others.

23 All this I have tested with wisdom. I said: “I will become wise.” But it was far from me. 24 What has come to be is far off and exceedingly deep. Who can find it out? 25 I myself turned around, even my heart did, to know and to explore and to search for wisdom and the reason of things, and to know about the wickedness of stupidity and the foolishness of madness; 26 and I was finding out: More bitter than death I found the woman who is herself nets for hunting and whose heart is dragnets and whose hands are fetters. One is good before the true God if one escapes from her, but one is sinning if one is captured by her.

27 “See! This I have found,” said the congregator, “one thing taken after another, to find out the sum-up, 28 which my soul has continuously sought, but I have not found. One man out of a thousand I have found, but a woman among all these I have not found. 29 See! This only I have found, that the true God made mankind upright, but they themselves have sought out many plans.”

Ecclesiastes

12 Remember, now, your Grand Creator in the days of your young manhood, before the calamitous days proceed to come, or the years have arrived when you will say: “I have no delight in them”; 2 before the sun and the light and the moon and the stars grow dark, and the clouds have returned, afterward the downpour; 3 in the day when the keepers of the house tremble, and the men of vital energy have bent themselves, and the grinding women have quit working because they have become few, and the ladies seeing at the windows have found it dark; 4 and the doors onto the street have been closed, when the sound of the grinding mill becomes low, and one gets up at the sound of a bird, and all the daughters of song sound low. 5 Also, they have become afraid merely at what is high, and there are terrors in the way. And the almond tree carries blossoms, and the grasshopper drags itself along, and the caper berry bursts, because man is walking to his long-lasting house and the wailers have marched around in the street; 6 before the silver cord is removed, and the golden bowl gets crushed, and the jar at the spring is broken, and the waterwheel for the cistern has been crushed. 7 Then the dust returns to the earth just as it happened to be and the spirit itself returns to the true God who gave it.

8 “The greatest vanity!” said the congregator, “Everything is vanity.”

9 And besides the fact that the congregator had become wise, he also taught the people knowledge continually, and he pondered and made a thorough search, that he might arrange many proverbs in order. 10 The congregator sought to find the delightful words and the writing of correct words of truth.

11 The words of the wise ones are like oxgoads, and just like nails driven in are those indulging in collections of sentences; they have been given from one shepherd. 12 As regards anything besides these, my son, take a warning: To the making of many books there is no end, and much devotion to them is wearisome to the flesh.

13 The conclusion of the matter, everything having been heard, is: Fear the true God and keep his commandments. For this is the whole obligation of man. 14 For the true God himself will bring every sort of work into the judgment in relation to every hidden thing, as to whether it is good or bad.

Song of Solomon

3 “On my bed during the nights I have sought the one whom my soul has loved. I sought him, but I did not find him. 2 Let me rise up, please, and go round about in the city; in the streets and in the public squares let me seek the one whom my soul has loved. I sought him, but I did not find him. 3 The watchmen who were going around in the city found me, ‘The one whom my soul has loved have YOU men seen?’ 4 Hardly had I passed on from them until I found the one whom my soul has loved. I grabbed hold of him, and I would not let go of him, until I had brought him into my mother’s house and into the interior room of her that had been pregnant with me. 5 I have put YOU under oath, O daughters of Jerusalem, by the female gazelles or by the hinds of the field, that YOU try not to awaken or arouse love in me until it feels inclined.”

6 “What is this thing that is coming up from the wilderness like columns of smoke, being perfumed with myrrh and frankincense, even with every sort of scent powder of a trader?”

7 “Look! It is his couch, the one belonging to Sol′o·mon. Sixty mighty men are all around it, from the mighty men of Israel, 8 all of them in possession of a sword, being taught in warfare, each one with his sword upon his thigh because of dread during the nights.”

9 “It is the litter that King Sol′o·mon has made for himself from the trees of Leb′a·non. 10 Its pillars he has made of silver, its supports of gold. Its seat is of wool dyed reddish purple, its interior being fitted out lovingly by the daughters of Jerusalem.”

11 “Go out and look, O YOU daughters of Zion, on King Sol′o·mon with the wreath that his mother wove for him on the day of his marriage and on the day of the rejoicing of his heart.”

Song of Solomon

5 “I have come into my garden, O my sister, my bride. I have plucked my myrrh along with my spice. I have eaten my honeycomb along with my honey; I have drunk my wine along with my milk.”

“Eat, O companions! Drink and become drunk with expressions of endearment!”

2 “I am asleep, but my heart is awake. There is the sound of my dear one knocking!”

“Open to me, O my sister, my girl companion, my dove, my blameless one! For my head is filled with dew, the locks of my hair with the drops of the night.”

3 “‘I have put off my robe. How can I put it back on? I have washed my feet. How can I soil them?’ 4 My dear one himself pulled back his hand from the hole of the door, and my inward parts themselves became boisterous within me. 5 I got up, even I, to open to my dear one, and my own hands dripped with myrrh and my fingers with liquid myrrh, upon the hollows of the lock. 6 I opened, even I, to my dear one, but my dear one himself had turned away, he had passed along. My very soul had gone out of me when he spoke. I sought him, but I did not find him. I called him, but he did not answer me. 7 The watchmen that were going about in the city found me. They struck me, they wounded me. The watchmen of the walls lifted my wide wrap off me.

8 “I have put YOU under oath, O daughters of Jerusalem, that, if YOU find my dear one, YOU should tell him that I am lovesick.”

9 “How is your dear one more than any other dear one, O you most beautiful one among women? How is your dear one more than any other dear one, that you have put us under such an oath as this?”

10 “My dear one is dazzling and ruddy, the most conspicuous of ten thousand. 11 His head is gold, refined gold. The locks of his hair are date clusters. His black hair is like the raven. 12 His eyes are like doves by the channels of water, which are bathing themselves in milk, sitting within the rims. 13 His cheeks are like a garden bed of spice, towers of scented herbs. His lips are lilies, dripping with liquid myrrh. 14 His hands are cylinders of gold, filled with chrys′o·lite. His abdomen is an ivory plate covered with sapphires. 15 His legs are pillars of marble based on socket pedestals of refined gold. His appearance is like Leb′a·non, choice like the cedars. 16 His palate is sheer sweetness, and everything about him is altogether desirable. This is my dear one, and this is my boy companion, O daughters of Jerusalem.”

Song of Solomon

7 “How beautiful your steps have become in your sandals, O willing daughter! The curvings of your thighs are like ornaments, the work of an artisan’s hands. 2 Your navel roll is a round bowl. Let not the mixed wine be lacking from it. Your belly is a heap of wheat, fenced about with lilies. 3 Your two breasts are like two young ones, the twins of a female gazelle. 4 Your neck is like an ivory tower. Your eyes are like the pools in Hesh′bon, by the gate of Bath-rab′bim. Your nose is like the tower of Leb′a·non, which is looking out toward Damascus. 5 Your head upon you is like Car′mel, and the tresses of your head are like wool dyed reddish purple. The king is held bound by the flowings. 6 How beautiful you are, and how pleasant you are, O beloved girl, among exquisite delights! 7 This stature of yours does resemble a palm tree, and your breasts, date clusters. 8 I have said, ‘I shall go up on the palm tree, that I may take hold of its fruit stalks of dates.’ And, please, may your breasts become like clusters of the vine, and the fragrance of your nose like apples, 9 and your palate like the best wine that is going with a slickness for my dear one, softly flowing over the lips of sleeping ones.”

10 “I am my dear one’s, and toward me is his craving. 11 Do come, O my dear one, let us go forth to the field; do let us lodge among the henna plants. 12 Do let us rise early and go to the vineyards, that we may see whether the vine has sprouted, the blossom has burst open, the pomegranate trees have bloomed. There I shall give my expressions of endearment to you. 13 The mandrakes themselves have given their fragrance, and by our entranceways there are all sorts of the choicest fruits. The new ones as well as the old, O my dear one, I have treasured up for you.

Isaiah

1 The vision of Isaiah the son of A′moz that he visioned concerning Judah and Jerusalem in the days of Uz·zi′ah, Jo′tham, A′haz and Hez·e·ki′ah, kings of Judah:

2 Hear, O heavens, and give ear, O earth, for Jehovah himself has spoken: “Sons I have brought up and raised, but they themselves have revolted against me. 3 A bull well knows its buyer, and the ass the manger of its owner; Israel itself has not known, my own people have not behaved understandingly.”

4 Woe to the sinful nation, the people heavy with error, an evildoing seed, ruinous sons! They have left Jehovah, they have treated the Holy One of Israel with disrespect, they have turned backwards. 5 Where else will YOU be struck still more, in that YOU add more revolt? The whole head is in a sick condition, and the whole heart is feeble. 6 From the sole of the foot even to the head there is no sound spot in it. Wounds and bruises and fresh stripes—they have not been squeezed out or bound up, nor has there been a softening with oil. 7 YOUR land is a desolation, YOUR cities are burned with fire; YOUR ground—right in front of YOU strangers are eating it up, and the desolation is like an overthrow by strangers. 8 And the daughter of Zion has been left remaining like a booth in a vineyard, like a lookout hut in a field of cucumbers, like a blockaded city. 9 Unless Jehovah of armies himself had left remaining to us just a few survivors, we should have become just like Sod′om, we should have resembled Go·mor′rah itself.

10 Hear the word of Jehovah, YOU dictators of Sod′om. Give ear to the law of our God, YOU people of Go·mor′rah. 11 “Of what benefit to me is the multitude of YOUR sacrifices?” says Jehovah. “I have had enough of whole burnt offerings of rams and the fat of well-fed animals; and in the blood of young bulls and male lambs and he-goats I have taken no delight. 12 When YOU people keep coming in to see my face, who is it that has required this from YOUR hand, to trample my courtyards? 13 Stop bringing in any more valueless grain offerings. Incense—it is something detestable to me. New moon and sabbath, the calling of a convention—I cannot put up with the use of uncanny power along with the solemn assembly. 14 YOUR new moons and YOUR festal seasons my soul has hated. To me they have become a burden; I have become tired of bearing them. 15 And when YOU spread out YOUR palms, I hide my eyes from YOU. Even though YOU make many prayers, I am not listening; with bloodshed YOUR very hands have become filled. 16 Wash yourselves; make yourselves clean; remove the badness of YOUR dealings from in front of my eyes; cease to do bad. 17 Learn to do good; search for justice; set right the oppressor; render judgment for the fatherless boy; plead the cause of the widow.”

18 “Come, now, YOU people, and let us set matters straight between us,” says Jehovah. “Though the sins of YOU people should prove to be as scarlet, they will be made white just like snow; though they should be red like crimson cloth, they will become even like wool. 19 If YOU people show willingness and do listen, the good of the land YOU will eat. 20 But if YOU people refuse and are actually rebellious, with a sword YOU will be eaten up; for the very mouth of Jehovah has spoken it.”

21 O how the faithful town has become a prostitute! She was full of justice; righteousness itself used to lodge in her, but now murderers. 22 Your silver itself has become scummy dross. Your wheat beer is diluted with water. 23 Your princes are stubborn and partners with thieves. Every one of them is a lover of a bribe and a chaser after gifts. For a fatherless boy they do not render judgment; and even the legal case of a widow does not get admittance to them.

24 Therefore the utterance of the true Lord, Jehovah of armies, the Powerful One of Israel, is: “Aha! I shall relieve myself of my adversaries, and I will avenge myself on my enemies. 25 And I will turn back my hand upon you, and I shall smelt away your scummy dross as with lye, and I will remove all your waste products. 26 And I will bring back again judges for you as at the first, and counselors for you as at the start. After this you will be called City of Righteousness, Faithful Town. 27 With justice Zion herself will be redeemed, and those returning of her, with righteousness. 28 And the crash of revolters and that of sinful ones will be at the same time, and those leaving Jehovah will come to their finish. 29 For they will be ashamed of the mighty trees that YOU people desired, and YOU will be abashed because of the gardens that YOU have chosen. 30 For YOU will become like a big tree the foliage of which is withering, and like a garden that has no water. 31 And the vigorous man will certainly become tow, and the product of his activity a spark; and both of them will certainly go up in flames at the same time, with no one to do the extinguishing.”

Isaiah

6 In the year that King Uz·zi′ah died I, however, got to see Jehovah, sitting on a throne lofty and lifted up, and his skirts were filling the temple. 2 Seraphs were standing above him. Each one had six wings. With two he kept his face covered, and with two he kept his feet covered, and with two he would fly about. 3 And this one called to that one and said: “Holy, holy, holy is Jehovah of armies. The fullness of all the earth is his glory.” 4 And the pivots of the thresholds began to quiver at the voice of the one calling, and the house itself gradually filled with smoke.

5 And I proceeded to say: “Woe to me! For I am as good as brought to silence, because a man unclean in lips I am, and in among a people unclean in lips I am dwelling; for my eyes have seen the King, Jehovah of armies, himself!”

6 At that, one of the seraphs flew to me, and in his hand there was a glowing coal that he had taken with tongs off the altar. 7 And he proceeded to touch my mouth and to say: “Look! This has touched your lips, and your error has departed and your sin itself is atoned for.”

8 And I began to hear the voice of Jehovah saying: “Whom shall I send, and who will go for us?” And I proceeded to say: “Here I am! Send me.” 9 And he went on to say: “Go, and you must say to this people, ‘Hear again and again, O men, but do not understand; and see again and again, but do not get any knowledge.’ 10 Make the heart of this people unreceptive, and make their very ears unresponsive, and paste their very eyes together, that they may not see with their eyes and with their ears they may not hear, and that their own heart may not understand and that they may not actually turn back and get healing for themselves.”

11 At this I said: “How long, O Jehovah?” Then he said: “Until the cities actually crash in ruins, to be without an inhabitant, and the houses be without earthling man, and the ground itself is ruined into a desolation; 12 and Jehovah actually removes earthling men far away, and the deserted condition does become very extensive in the midst of the land. 13 And there will still be in it a tenth, and it must again become something for burning down, like a big tree and like a massive tree in which, when there is a cutting down of them, there is a stump; a holy seed will be the stump of it.”

Isaiah

8 And Jehovah proceeded to say to me: “Take for yourself a large tablet and write upon it with the stylus of mortal man, ‘Ma′her-shal′al-hash-baz.’ 2 And let me have attestation for myself by faithful witnesses, U·ri′ah the priest and Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Je·ber·e·chi′ah.”

3 Then I went near to the prophetess, and she came to be pregnant and in time gave birth to a son. Jehovah now said to me: “Call his name Ma′her-shal′al-hash-baz, 4 for before the boy will know how to call out, ‘My father!’ and ‘My mother!’ one will carry away the resources of Damascus and the spoil of Sa·mar′i·a before the king of As·syr′i·a.”

5 And Jehovah proceeded to speak yet further to me, saying: 6 “For the reason that this people has rejected the waters of the Shi·lo′ah that are going gently, and there is exultation over Re′zin and the son of Rem·a·li′ah; 7 even therefore, look! Jehovah is bringing up against them the mighty and the many waters of the River, the king of As·syr′i·a and all his glory. And he will certainly come up over all his streambeds and go over all his banks 8 and move on through Judah. He will actually flood and pass over. Up to the neck he will reach. And the outspreading of his wings must occur to fill the breadth of your land, O Im·man′u·el!”

9 Be injurious, O YOU peoples, and be shattered to pieces; and give ear, all YOU in distant parts of the earth! Gird yourselves, and be shattered to pieces! Gird yourselves, and be shattered to pieces! 10 Plan out a scheme, and it will be broken up! Speak any word, and it will not stand, for God is with us! 11 For this is what Jehovah has said to me with strongness of the hand, that he may make me turn aside from walking in the way of this people, saying: 12 “YOU men must not say, ‘A conspiracy!’ respecting all that of which this people keep saying, ‘A conspiracy!’ and the object of their fear YOU men must not fear, nor must YOU tremble at it. 13 Jehovah of armies—he is the One whom YOU should treat as holy, and he should be the object of YOUR fear, and he should be the One causing YOU to tremble.”

14 And he must become as a sacred place; but as a stone to strike against and as a rock over which to stumble to both the houses of Israel, as a trap and as a snare to the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 15 And many among them will be certain to stumble and to fall and be broken, and to be snared and caught.

16 Wrap up the attestation, put a seal about the law among my disciples! 17 And I will keep in expectation of Jehovah, who is concealing his face from the house of Jacob, and I will hope in him.

18 Look! I and the children whom Jehovah has given me are as signs and as miracles in Israel from Jehovah of armies, who is residing in Mount Zion.

19 And in case they should say to YOU people: “Apply to the spiritistic mediums or to those having a spirit of prediction who are chirping and making utterances in low tones,” is it not to its God that any people should apply? Should there be application to dead persons in behalf of living persons? 20 To the law and to the attestation!

Surely they will keep saying what is according to this statement that will have no light of dawn. 21 And each one will certainly pass through the land hard pressed and hungry; and it must occur that because he is hungry and has made himself feel indignant, he will actually call down evil upon his king and upon his God and will certainly peer upward. 22 And to the earth he will look, and, lo! distress and darkness, obscurity, hard times and gloominess with no brightness.

Isaiah

22 The pronouncement of the valley of the vision: What is the matter with you, then, that you have gone up in your entirety to the roofs? 2 With turmoil you were full, a boisterous city, an exultant town. Your slain ones are not those slain with the sword, nor those dead in battle. 3 All your dictators themselves have fled at one time. Without need of a bow they have been taken prisoner. All those of you who have been found have been taken prisoner together. Far off they had run away.

4 That is why I have said: “Turn YOUR gaze away from me. I will show bitterness in weeping. Do not YOU people insist on comforting me over the despoiling of the daughter of my people. 5 For it is the day of confusion and of downtreading and of confounding that the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, has in the valley of the vision. There is the demolisher of the wall, and the cry to the mountain. 6 And E′lam itself has taken up the quiver, in the war chariot of earthling man, with steeds; and Kir itself has uncovered the shield. 7 And it will occur that the choicest of your low plains must become full of war chariots, and the very steeds must without fail set themselves in position at the gate, 8 and one will remove the screen of Judah. And you will look in that day toward the armory of the house of the forest, 9 and YOU people will certainly see the very breaches of the City of David, for they will actually be many. And YOU will collect the waters of the lower pool. 10 And the houses of Jerusalem YOU will actually count. YOU will also pull down the houses to make the wall unattainable. 11 And there will be a collecting basin that YOU must make between the two walls for the waters of the old pool. And YOU will certainly not look at the Grand Maker of it, and the one forming it long ago YOU will certainly not see.

12 “And the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, will call in that day for weeping and for mourning and for baldness and for girding on sackcloth. 13 But, look! exultation and rejoicing, the killing of cattle and the slaughtering of sheep, the eating of flesh and the drinking of wine, ‘Let there be eating and drinking, for tomorrow we shall die.’”

14 And in my ears Jehovah of armies has revealed himself: “‘This error will not be atoned for in YOUR behalf until YOU people die,’ the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, has said.”

15 This is what the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, has said: “Go, enter in to this steward, to Sheb′na, who is over the house, 16 ‘What is there of interest to you here, and who is there of interest to you here, that you have hewed out for yourself here a burial place?’ On a height he is hewing out his burial place; in a crag he is cutting out a residence for himself. 17 ‘Look! Jehovah is hurling you down with violent hurling, O able-bodied man, and grasping you forcibly. 18 Without fail he will wrap you up tightly, like a ball for a wide land. There you will die, and there the chariots of your glory will be the dishonor of the house of your master. 19 And I will push you away from your position; and from your official standing one will tear you down.

20 “‘And it must occur in that day that I will call my servant, namely, E·li′a·kim the son of Hil·ki′ah. 21 And I will clothe him with your robe, and your sash I shall firmly bind about him, and your dominion I shall give into his hand; and he must become a father to the inhabitant of Jerusalem and to the house of Judah. 22 And I will put the key of the house of David upon his shoulder, and he must open without anyone’s shutting, and he must shut without anyone’s opening. 23 And I will drive him in as a peg in a lasting place, and he must become as a throne of glory to the house of his father. 24 And they must hang upon him all the glory of the house of his father, the descendants and the offshoots, all the vessels of the small sort, the vessels of the bowl sort as well as all the vessels of the large jars.

25 “‘In that day,’ is the utterance of Jehovah of armies, ‘the peg that is driven in a lasting place will be removed, and it must be hewn down and fall, and the load that is upon it must be cut off, for Jehovah himself has spoken it.’”

Isaiah

24 Look! Jehovah is emptying the land and laying it waste, and he has twisted the face of it and scattered its inhabitants. 2 And it must come to be the same for the people as for the priest; the same for the servant as for his master; the same for the maidservant as for her mistress; the same for the buyer as for the seller; the same for the lender as for the borrower; the same for the interest taker as for the one paying the interest. 3 Without fail the land will be emptied, and without fail it will be plundered, for Jehovah himself has spoken this word. 4 The land has gone to mourning, has faded away. The productive land has withered, has faded away. The high ones of the people of the land have withered. 5 And the very land has been polluted under its inhabitants, for they have bypassed the laws, changed the regulation, broken the indefinitely lasting covenant. 6 That is why the curse itself has eaten up the land, and those inhabiting it are held guilty. That is why the inhabitants of the land have decreased in number, and very few mortal men have remained over.

7 The new wine has gone to mourning, the vine has withered, all those glad at heart have gone to sighing. 8 The exultation of the tambourines has ceased, the noise of the highly elated ones has discontinued, the exultation of the harp has ceased. 9 It is with no song that they drink wine; the intoxicating liquor becomes bitter to those drinking it. 10 The deserted town has been broken down; every house has been shut up from entering. 11 There is an outcry in the streets for want of wine. All rejoicing has passed away; the exultation of the land has departed. 12 In the city an astonishing condition has been left behind; the gate has been crushed to a mere rubble heap.

13 For thus it will become in the midst of the land, in among the peoples, like the beating off of the olive tree, like the gleaning when the grape gathering has come to an end. 14 They themselves will raise their voice, they will cry out joyfully. In the superiority of Jehovah they will certainly cry out shrilly from the sea. 15 That is why in the region of light they must glorify Jehovah, in the islands of the sea the name of Jehovah, the God of Israel. 16 From the extremity of the land there are melodies that we have heard: “Decoration to the Righteous One!”

But I say: “For me there is leanness, for me there is leanness! Woe to me! The treacherous dealers have dealt treacherously. Even with treachery the treacherous dealers have dealt treacherously.”

17 Dread and the hollow and the trap are upon you, you inhabitant of the land. 18 And it must occur that anyone fleeing from the sound of the dreaded thing will fall into the hollow, and anyone coming up from inside the hollow will be caught in the trap. For the very floodgates on high will actually be opened, and the foundations of the land will rock. 19 The land has absolutely burst apart, the land has absolutely been shaken up, the land has absolutely been sent staggering. 20 The land absolutely moves unsteadily like a drunken man, and it has swayed to and fro like a lookout hut. And its transgression has become heavy upon it, and it must fall, so that it will not rise up again.

21 And it must occur in that day that Jehovah will turn his attention upon the army of the height in the height, and upon the kings of the ground upon the ground. 22 And they will certainly be gathered with a gathering as of prisoners into the pit, and be shut up in the dungeon; and after an abundance of days they will be given attention. 23 And the full moon has become abashed, and the glowing sun has become ashamed, for Jehovah of armies has become king in Mount Zion and in Jerusalem and in front of his elderly men with glory.

Isaiah

27 In that day Jehovah, with his hard and great and strong sword, will turn his attention to Le·vi′a·than, the gliding serpent, even to Le·vi′a·than, the crooked serpent, and he will certainly kill the sea monster that is in the sea.

2 In that day sing to her, YOU people: “A vineyard of foaming wine! 3 I, Jehovah, am safeguarding her. Every moment I shall water her. In order that no one may turn his attention against her, I shall safeguard her even night and day. 4 There is no rage that I have. Who will give me thornbushes and weeds in the battle? I will step on such. I will set such on fire at the same time. 5 Otherwise let him take hold of my stronghold, let him make peace with me; peace let him make with me.”

6 In the coming days Jacob will take root, Israel will put forth blossoms and actually sprout; and they will simply fill the surface of the productive land with produce.

7 As with the stroke of one striking him does one have to strike him? Or as with the slaughter of his killed ones does he have to be killed? 8 With a scare cry you will contend with her when sending her forth. He must expel her with his blast, a hard one in the day of the east wind. 9 Therefore by this means the error of Jacob will be atoned for, and this is all the fruit when he takes away his sin, when he makes all the stones of the altar like chalkstones that have been pulverized, so that the sacred poles and the incense stands will not rise up. 10 For the fortified city will be solitary, the pasture ground will be left to itself and abandoned like a wilderness. There the calf will graze, and there it will lie down; and he will actually consume her boughs. 11 When her sprigs have dried up, women coming in will break them off, lighting them up. For it is not a people of keen understanding. That is why its Maker will show it no mercy, and its own Former will show it no favor.

12 And it must occur in that day that Jehovah will beat off the fruit, from the flowing stream of the River to the torrent valley of Egypt, and so YOU yourselves will be picked up one after the other, O sons of Israel. 13 And it must occur in that day that there will be a blowing on a great horn, and those who are perishing in the land of As·syr′i·a and those who are dispersed in the land of Egypt will certainly come and bow down to Jehovah in the holy mountain in Jerusalem.

Isaiah

28 Woe to the eminent crown of the drunkards of E′phra·im, and the fading blossom of its decoration of beauty that is upon the head of the fertile valley of those overpowered by wine! 2 Look! Jehovah has someone strong and vigorous. Like a thunderous storm of hail, a destructive storm, like a thunderous storm of powerful, flooding waters, he will certainly do a casting down to the earth with force. 3 With the feet the eminent crowns of the drunkards of E′phra·im will be trampled down. 4 And the fading flower of its decoration of beauty that is upon the head of the fertile valley must become like the early fig before summer, that, when the seer sees it, while it is yet in his palm, he swallows it down.

5 In that day Jehovah of armies will become as a crown of decoration and as a garland of beauty to the ones remaining over of his people, 6 and as a spirit of justice to the one sitting in the judgment, and as mightiness to those turning away the battle from the gate.

7 And these also—because of wine they have gone astray and because of intoxicating liquor they have wandered about. Priest and prophet—they have gone astray because of intoxicating liquor, they have become confused as a result of the wine, they have wandered about as a result of the intoxicating liquor; they have gone astray in their seeing, they have reeled as to decision. 8 For the tables themselves have all become full of filthy vomit—there is no place without it.

9 Whom will one instruct in knowledge, and whom will one make understand what has been heard? Those who have been weaned from the milk, those moved away from the breasts? 10 For it is “command upon command, command upon command, measuring line upon measuring line, measuring line upon measuring line, here a little, there a little.” 11 For by those stammering with their lips and by a different tongue he will speak to this people, 12 those to whom he has said: “This is the resting-place. GIVE rest to the weary one. And this is the place of ease,” but who were not willing to hear. 13 And to them the word of Jehovah will certainly become “command upon command, command upon command, measuring line upon measuring line, measuring line upon measuring line, here a little, there a little,” in order that they may go and certainly stumble backwards and actually be broken and ensnared and caught.

14 Therefore hear the word of Jehovah, YOU braggarts, YOU rulers of this people who are in Jerusalem: 15 Because YOU men have said: “We have concluded a covenant with Death; and with She′ol we have effected a vision; the overflowing flash flood, in case it should pass through, will not come to us, for we have made a lie our refuge and in falsehood we have concealed ourselves”; 16 therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am laying as a foundation in Zion a stone, a tried stone, the precious corner of a sure foundation. No one exercising faith will get panicky. 17 And I will make justice the measuring line and righteousness the leveling instrument; and the hail must sweep away the refuge of a lie, and the waters themselves will flood out the very place of concealment. 18 And YOUR covenant with Death will certainly be dissolved, and that vision of YOURS with She′ol will not stand. The overflowing flash flood, when it passes through—YOU must also become for it a trampling place. 19 As often as it passes through, it will take YOU men away, because morning by morning it will pass through, during the day and during the night; and it must become nothing but a reason for quaking to make others understand what has been heard.”

20 For the couch has proved too short for stretching oneself on, and the woven sheet itself is too narrow when wrapping oneself up. 21 For Jehovah will rise up just as at Mount Pe·ra′zim, he will be agitated just as in the low plain near Gib′e·on, that he may do his deed—his deed is strange—and that he may work his work—his work is unusual. 22 And now do not show yourselves scoffers, in order that YOUR bands may not grow strong, for there is an extermination, even something decided upon, that I have heard of from the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, for all the land.

23 Give ear, YOU men, and listen to my voice; pay attention and listen to my saying. 24 Is it all day long that the plower plows in order to sow seed, that he loosens and harrows his ground? 25 Does he not, when he has smoothed out its surface, then scatter black cumin and sprinkle the cumin, and must he not put in wheat, millet, and barley in the appointed place, and spelt as his boundary? 26 And one corrects him according to what is right. His own God instructs him. 27 For it is not with a threshing instrument that black cumin is given a treading; and upon cumin no wheel of a wagon is turned. For it is with a rod that black cumin is generally beaten out, and cumin with a staff. 28 Is breadstuff itself generally crushed? For never does one incessantly keep treading it out. And he must set the roller of his wagon in motion, and his own steeds, but he will not crush it. 29 This also is what has come forth from Jehovah of armies himself, who has been wonderful in counsel, who has done greatly in effectual working.

Isaiah

33 Woe to you who are despoiling, without you yourself being despoiled, and to you who are dealing treacherously, without others having dealt treacherously with you! As soon as you have finished as a despoiler, you will be despoiled. As soon as you have done with dealing treacherously, they will deal treacherously with you.

2 O Jehovah, show us favor. In you we have hoped. Become our arm every morning, yes, our salvation in the time of distress. 3 At the sound of turmoil peoples have fled. At your arising nations have been dispersed. 4 And the spoil of YOU people will actually be gathered like the cockroaches when gathering in, like the onrush of locust swarms that is rushing against one. 5 Jehovah will certainly be put on high, for he is residing in the height. He must fill Zion with justice and righteousness. 6 And the trustworthiness of your times must prove to be a wealth of salvations—wisdom and knowledge, the fear of Jehovah, which is his treasure.

7 Look! Their very heroes have cried out in the street; the very messengers of peace will weep bitterly. 8 The highways have been made desolate; the one passing over the path has ceased. He has broken the covenant; he has contemned the cities; he has taken no account of mortal man. 9 The land has gone mourning, has withered away. Leb′a·non has become abashed; it has moldered. Shar′on has become like the desert plain; and Ba′shan and Car′mel are shaking off their leaves.

10 “Now I will rise up,” says Jehovah, “now I will exalt myself; now I will lift myself up. 11 YOU people conceive dried grass; YOU will give birth to stubble. YOUR own spirit, as a fire, will eat YOU up. 12 And peoples must become as the burnings of lime. As thorns cut away, they will be set ablaze even with fire. 13 Hear, YOU men who are far away, what I must do! And know, YOU who are nearby, my mightiness. 14 In Zion the sinners have come to be in dread; shivering has grabbed hold of the apostates: ‘Who of us can reside for any time with a devouring fire? Who of us can reside for any time with long-lasting conflagrations?’

15 “There is one who is walking in continual righteousness and speaking what is upright, who is rejecting the unjust gain from frauds, who is shaking his hands clear from taking hold on a bribe, who is stopping up his ear from listening to bloodshed, and who is closing his eyes so as not to see what is bad. 16 He is the one that will reside on the heights themselves; his secure height will be craggy places difficult to approach. His own bread will certainly be given him; his water supply will be unfailing.”

17 A king in his handsomeness is what your eyes will behold; they will see a land far away. 18 Your own heart will comment in low tones on a frightful thing: “Where is the secretary? Where is the one that does the paying out? Where is the one counting the towers?” 19 No insolent people will you see, a people too deep in language to listen to, of a stammering tongue without your understanding. 20 Behold Zion, the town of our festal occasions! Your own eyes will see Jerusalem an undisturbed abiding place, a tent that no one will pack up. Never will its tent pins be pulled out, and none of its ropes will be torn in two. 21 But there the Majestic One, Jehovah, will be for us a place of rivers, of wide canals. On it no galley fleet will go, and no majestic ship will pass over it. 22 For Jehovah is our Judge, Jehovah is our Statute-giver, Jehovah is our King; he himself will save us.

23 Your ropes must hang loose; their mast they will not hold firmly erect; they have not spread a sail.

At that time even spoil in abundance will have to be divided up; the lame ones themselves will actually take a big plunder. 24 And no resident will say: “I am sick.” The people that are dwelling in the land will be those pardoned for their error.

Isaiah

37 And it came about that as soon as King Hez·e·ki′ah heard, he immediately ripped his garments apart and covered himself with sackcloth and came into the house of Jehovah. 2 Further, he sent E·li′a·kim, who was over the household, and Sheb′na the secretary and the older men of the priests covered with sackcloth to Isaiah the son of A′moz the prophet. 3 And they proceeded to say to him: “This is what Hez·e·ki′ah has said, ‘This day is a day of distress and of rebuke and of scornful insolence, for the sons have come as far as the womb’s mouth, and there is no power to give birth. 4 Perhaps Jehovah your God will hear the words of Rab′sha·keh, whom the king of As·syr′i·a his lord sent to taunt the living God, and he will actually call him to account for the words that Jehovah your God has heard. And you must lift up prayer in behalf of the remnant that are to be found.’”

5 So the servants of King Hez·e·ki′ah came in to Isaiah. 6 Then Isaiah said to them: “This is what YOU should say to YOUR lord, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Do not be afraid because of the words that you have heard with which the attendants of the king of As·syr′i·a spoke abusively of me. 7 Here I am putting a spirit in him, and he must hear a report and return to his own land; and I shall certainly cause him to fall by the sword in his own land.”’”

8 After that Rab′sha·keh returned and found the king of As·syr′i·a fighting against Lib′nah, for he had heard that he had pulled away from La′chish. 9 Now he heard it said concerning Tir·ha′kah the king of E·thi·o′pi·a: “He has come out to fight against you.” When he heard, he at once sent messengers to Hez·e·ki′ah, saying: 10 “This is what YOU men should say to Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah, ‘Do not let your God in whom you are trusting deceive you, saying: “Jerusalem will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a.” 11 Look! You yourself have heard what the kings of As·syr′i·a did to all the lands by devoting them to destruction, and will you yourself be delivered? 12 Have the gods of the nations that my forefathers brought to ruin delivered them, even Go′zan and Ha′ran and Re′zeph and the sons of E′den that were in Tel-as′sar? 13 Where is the king of Ha′math and the king of Ar′pad and the king of the city of Seph·ar·va′im—of He′na and of Iv′vah?’”

14 Then Hez·e·ki′ah took the letters out of the hand of the messengers and read them, after which Hez·e·ki′ah went up to the house of Jehovah and spread it out before Jehovah. 15 And Hez·e·ki′ah began to pray to Jehovah, saying: 16 “O Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, sitting upon the cherubs, you alone are the true God of all the kingdoms of the earth. You yourself have made the heavens and the earth. 17 Incline your ear, O Jehovah, and hear. Open your eyes, O Jehovah, and see, and hear all the words of Sen·nach′er·ib that he has sent to taunt the living God. 18 It is a fact, O Jehovah, that the kings of As·syr′i·a have devastated all the lands, and their own land. 19 And there was a consigning of their gods to the fire, because they were no gods, but the workmanship of man’s hands, wood and stone, so that they destroyed them. 20 And now, O Jehovah our God, save us out of his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you, O Jehovah, are God alone.”

21 And Isaiah the son of A′moz proceeded to send to Hez·e·ki′ah, saying: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘Because you have prayed to me concerning Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a, 22 this is the word that Jehovah has spoken against him:

“The virgin daughter of Zion has despised you, she has held you in derision.

Behind you the daughter of Jerusalem has wagged her head.

23 Whom have you taunted and spoken of abusively?

And against whom have you lifted up your voice

And do you raise your eyes on high?

It is against the Holy One of Israel!

24 By means of your servants you have taunted Jehovah and you say,

‘With the multitude of my war chariots I myself—

I shall certainly ascend the height of mountainous regions,

The remotest parts of Leb′a·non;

And I shall cut down its lofty cedars, its choice juniper trees.

And I shall enter its final height, the forest of its orchard.

25 I myself shall certainly dig and drink waters,

And I shall dry up with the soles of my feet all the Nile canals of Egypt.’

26 Have you not heard? From remote times it is what I will do.

From bygone days I have even formed it. Now I will bring it in.

And you will serve to make fortified cities become desolate as piles of ruins.

27 And their inhabitants will be feeble-handed;

They will simply be terrified and ashamed.

They must become as vegetation of the field and green tender grass,

Grass of the roofs and of the terrace before the east wind.

28 And your sitting quiet and your going out and your coming in I well know,

And your exciting yourself against me,

29 Because your exciting yourself against me and your roaring have come up into my ears.

And I shall certainly put my hook in your nose and my bridle between your lips,

And I shall indeed lead you back by the way by which you have come.”

30 “‘And this will be the sign for you: There will be an eating this year of the growth from spilled kernels, and in the second year grain that shoots up of itself; but in the third year sow seed, YOU people, and reap, and plant vineyards and eat their fruitage. 31 And those who escape of the house of Judah, those who are left remaining, will certainly take root downward and produce fruitage upward. 32 For out of Jerusalem a remnant will go forth and those who escape out of Mount Zion. The very zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.

33 “‘Therefore this is what Jehovah has said concerning the king of As·syr′i·a: “He will not come into this city, nor will he shoot an arrow there, nor confront it with a shield, nor cast up a siege rampart against it.”’

34 “‘By the way by which he came he will return, and into this city he will not come,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. 35 ‘And I shall certainly defend this city to save it for my own sake and for the sake of David my servant.’”

36 And the angel of Jehovah proceeded to go forth and strike down a hundred and eighty-five thousand in the camp of the As·syr′i·ans. When people rose up early in the morning, why, there all of them were dead carcasses. 37 Hence Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a pulled away and went and returned and took up dwelling in Nin′e·veh. 38 And it came about that as he was bowing down at the house of Nis′roch his god, A·dram′me·lech and Shar·e′zer, his own sons, struck him down with the sword, and they themselves escaped to the land of Ar′a·rat. And E′sar-had′don his son began to reign in place of him.

Isaiah

43 And now this is what Jehovah has said, your Creator, O Jacob, and your Former, O Israel: “Do not be afraid, for I have repurchased you. I have called you by your name. You are mine. 2 In case you should pass through the waters, I will be with you; and through the rivers, they will not flood over you. In case you should walk through the fire, you will not be scorched, neither will the flame itself singe you. 3 For I am Jehovah your God, the Holy One of Israel your Savior. I have given Egypt as a ransom for you, E·thi·o′pi·a and Se′ba in place of you. 4 Owing to the fact that you have been precious in my eyes, you have been considered honorable, and I myself have loved you. And I shall give men in place of you, and national groups in place of your soul.

5 “Do not be afraid, for I am with you. From the sunrising I shall bring your seed, and from the sunset I shall collect you together. 6 I shall say to the north, ‘Give up!’ and to the south, ‘Do not keep back. Bring my sons from far off, and my daughters from the extremity of the earth, 7 everyone that is called by my name and that I have created for my own glory, that I have formed, yes, that I have made.’

8 “Bring forth a people blind though eyes themselves exist, and the ones deaf though they have ears. 9 Let the nations all be collected together at one place, and let national groups be gathered together. Who is there among them that can tell this? Or can they cause us to hear even the first things? Let them furnish their witnesses, that they may be declared righteous, or let them hear and say, ‘It is the truth!’”

10 “YOU are my witnesses,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “even my servant whom I have chosen, in order that YOU may know and have faith in me, and that YOU may understand that I am the same One. Before me there was no God formed, and after me there continued to be none. 11 I—I am Jehovah, and besides me there is no savior.”

12 “I myself have told forth and have saved and have caused it to be heard, when there was among YOU no strange god. So YOU are my witnesses,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and I am God. 13 Also, all the time I am the same One; and there is no one effecting deliverance out of my own hand. I shall get active, and who can turn it back?”

14 This is what Jehovah has said, the Repurchaser of YOU people, the Holy One of Israel: “For YOUR sakes I will send to Babylon and cause the bars of the prisons to come down, and the Chal·de′ans in the ships with whining cries on their part. 15 I am Jehovah YOUR Holy One, the Creator of Israel, YOUR King.”

16 This is what Jehovah has said, the One making a way through the sea itself and a roadway even through strong waters, 17 the One bringing forth the war chariot and the horse, the military force and the strong ones at the same time: “They will lie down. They will not get up. They will certainly be extinguished. Like a flaxen wick they must be put out.”

18 “Do not remember the first things, and to the former things do not turn YOUR consideration. 19 Look! I am doing something new. Now it will spring up. YOU people will know it, will YOU not? Really, through the wilderness I shall set a way, through the desert rivers. 20 The wild beast of the field will glorify me, the jackals and the ostriches; because I shall have given water even in the wilderness, rivers in the desert, to cause my people, my chosen one, to drink, 21 the people whom I have formed for myself, that they should recount the praise of me.

22 “But you have not called even me, O Jacob, because you have grown weary of me, O Israel. 23 You have not brought me the sheep of your whole burnt offerings, and with your sacrifices you have not glorified me. I have not compelled you to serve me with a gift, nor have I made you weary with frankincense. 24 For me you have bought no sweet cane with any money; and with the fat of your sacrifices you have not saturated me. In reality you have compelled me to serve because of your sins; you have made me weary with your errors.

25 “I—I am the One that is wiping out your transgressions for my own sake, and your sins I shall not remember. 26 Remind me; let us put ourselves on judgment together; tell your own account of it in order that you may be in the right. 27 Your own father, the first one, has sinned, and your own spokesmen have transgressed against me. 28 So I shall profane the princes of the holy place, and I will give Jacob over as a man devoted to destruction and Israel over to words of abuse.

Isaiah

44 “And now listen, O Jacob my servant, and you, O Israel, whom I have chosen. 2 This is what Jehovah has said, your Maker and your Former, who kept helping you even from the belly, ‘Do not be afraid, O my servant Jacob, and you, Jesh′u·run, whom I have chosen. 3 For I shall pour out water upon the thirsty one, and trickling streams upon the dry place. I shall pour out my spirit upon your seed, and my blessing upon your descendants. 4 And they will certainly spring up as among the green grass, like poplars by the water ditches. 5 This one will say: “I belong to Jehovah.” And that one will call himself by the name of Jacob, and another will write upon his hand: “Belonging to Jehovah.” And by the name of Israel one will betitle himself.’

6 “This is what Jehovah has said, the King of Israel and the Repurchaser of him, Jehovah of armies, ‘I am the first and I am the last, and besides me there is no God. 7 And who is there like me? Let him call out, that he may tell it and present it to me. From when I appointed the people of long ago, both the things coming and the things that will enter in let them tell on their part. 8 Do not be in dread, YOU people, and do not become stupefied. Have I not from that time on caused you individually to hear and told it out? And YOU are my witnesses. Does there exist a God besides me? No, there is no Rock. I have recognized none.’”

9 The formers of the carved image are all of them an unreality, and their darlings themselves will be of no benefit; and as their witnesses they see nothing and know nothing, in order that they may be ashamed. 10 Who has formed a god or cast a mere molten image? Of no benefit at all has it been. 11 Look! All his partners themselves will be ashamed, and the craftsmen are from earthling men. They will all of them collect themselves together. They will stand still. They will be in dread. They will be ashamed at the same time.

12 As for the carver of iron with the billhook, he has been busy at it with the coals; and with the hammers he proceeds to form it, and he keeps busy at it with his powerful arm. Also, he has become hungry, and so without power. He has not drunk water; so he gets tired.

13 As for the wood carver, he has stretched out the measuring line; he traces it out with red chalk; he works it up with a wood scraper; and with a compass he keeps tracing it out, and gradually he makes it like the representation of a man, like the beauty of mankind, to sit in a house.

14 There is one whose business is to cut down cedars; and he takes a certain species of tree, even a massive tree, and he lets it become strong for himself among the trees of the forest. He planted the laurel tree, and the pouring rain itself keeps making it get big. 15 And it has become something for man to keep a fire burning. So he takes part of it that he may warm himself. In fact he builds a fire and actually bakes bread. He also works on a god to which he may bow down. He has made it into a carved image, and he prostrates himself to it. 16 Half of it he actually burns up in a fire. Upon half of it he roasts well the flesh that he eats, and he becomes satisfied. He also warms himself and says: “Aha! I have warmed myself. I have seen the firelight.” 17 But the remainder of it he actually makes into a god itself, into his carved image. He prostrates himself to it and bows down and prays to it and says: “Deliver me, for you are my god.”

18 They have not come to know, nor do they understand, because their eyes have been besmeared so as not to see, their heart so as to have no insight. 19 And no one recalls to his heart or has knowledge or understanding, saying: “The half of it I have burned up in a fire, and upon its coals I have also baked bread; I roast flesh and eat. But the rest of it shall I make into a mere detestable thing? To the dried-out wood of a tree shall I prostrate myself?” 20 He is feeding on ashes. His own heart that has been trifled with has led him astray. And he does not deliver his soul, nor does he say: “Is there not a falsehood in my right hand?”

21 “Remember these things, O Jacob, and you, O Israel, because you are my servant. I have formed you. You are a servant belonging to me. O Israel, you will not be forgotten on my part. 22 I will wipe out your transgressions just as with a cloud, and your sins just as with a cloud mass. Do return to me, for I will repurchase you.

23 “Joyfully cry out, YOU heavens, for Jehovah has taken action! Shout in triumph, YOU lowest parts of the earth! Become cheerful, YOU mountains, with joyful outcry, you forest and all YOU trees in it! For Jehovah has repurchased Jacob, and on Israel he shows his beauty.”

24 This is what Jehovah has said, your Repurchaser and the Former of you from the belly: “I, Jehovah, am doing everything, stretching out the heavens by myself, laying out the earth. Who was with me? 25 I am frustrating the signs of the empty talkers, and I am the One that makes diviners themselves act crazily; the One turning wise men backwards, and the One that turns even their knowledge into foolishness; 26 the One making the word of his servant come true, and the One that carries out completely the counsel of his own messengers; the One saying of Jerusalem, ‘She will be inhabited,’ and of the cities of Judah, ‘They will be rebuilt, and her desolated places I shall raise up’; 27 the One saying to the watery deep, ‘Be evaporated; and all your rivers I shall dry up’; 28 the One saying of Cyrus, ‘He is my shepherd, and all that I delight in he will completely carry out’; even in my saying of Jerusalem, ‘She will be rebuilt,’ and of the temple, ‘You will have your foundation laid.’”

Isaiah

45 This is what Jehovah has said to his anointed one, to Cyrus, whose right hand I have taken hold of, to subdue before him nations, so that I may ungird even the hips of kings; to open before him the two-leaved doors, so that even the gates will not be shut: 2 “Before you I myself shall go, and the swells of land I shall straighten out. The copper doors I shall break in pieces, and the iron bars I shall cut down. 3 And I will give you the treasures in the darkness and the hidden treasures in the concealment places, in order that you may know that I am Jehovah, the One calling you by your name, the God of Israel. 4 For the sake of my servant Jacob and of Israel my chosen one, I even proceeded to call you by your name; I proceeded to give you a name of honor, although you did not know me. 5 I am Jehovah, and there is no one else. With the exception of me there is no God. I shall closely gird you, although you have not known me, 6 in order that people may know from the rising of the sun and from its setting that there is none besides me. I am Jehovah, and there is no one else. 7 Forming light and creating darkness, making peace and creating calamity, I, Jehovah, am doing all these things.

8 “O YOU heavens, cause a dripping from above; and let the cloudy skies themselves trickle with righteousness. Let the earth open up, and let it be fruitful with salvation, and let it cause righteousness itself to spring up at the same time. I myself, Jehovah, have created it.”

9 Woe to the one that has contended with his Former, as an earthenware fragment with the other earthenware fragments of the ground! Should the clay say to its former: “What do you make?” And your achievement say: “He has no hands”? 10 Woe to the one saying to a father: “What do you become father to?” and to the wife: “What are you in birth pains with?”

11 This is what Jehovah has said, the Holy One of Israel and the Former of him: “Ask me even about the things that are coming concerning my sons; and concerning the activity of my hands YOU people should command me. 12 I myself have made the earth and have created even man upon it. I—my own hands have stretched out the heavens, and all the army of them I have commanded.”

13 “I myself have roused up someone in righteousness, and all his ways I shall straighten out. He is the one that will build my city, and those of mine in exile he will let go, not for a price nor for bribery,” Jehovah of armies has said.

14 This is what Jehovah has said: “The unpaid laborers of Egypt and the merchants of E·thi·o′pi·a and the Sa·be′ans, tall men, will themselves come over even to you, and yours they will become. Behind you they will walk; in fetters they will come over, and to you they will bow down. To you they will pray, saying, ‘Indeed God is in union with you, and there is no one else; there is no other God.’”

15 Truly you are a God keeping yourself concealed, the God of Israel, a Savior. 16 They will certainly be ashamed and even be humiliated, all of them. Together in humiliation the manufacturers of idol forms will have to walk. 17 As for Israel, he will certainly be saved in union with Jehovah with a salvation for times indefinite. YOU people will not be ashamed, nor will YOU be humiliated for the indefinite times of eternity.

18 For this is what Jehovah has said, the Creator of the heavens, He the true God, the Former of the earth and the Maker of it, He the One who firmly established it, who did not create it simply for nothing, who formed it even to be inhabited: “I am Jehovah, and there is no one else. 19 In a place of concealment I spoke not, in a dark place of the earth; nor said I to the seed of Jacob, ‘Seek me simply for nothing, YOU people.’ I am Jehovah, speaking what is righteous, telling what is upright.

20 “Collect yourselves and come. Bring yourselves up close together, YOU escapees from the nations. Those carrying the wood of their carved image have not come to any knowledge, neither have those praying to a god that cannot save. 21 Make YOUR report and YOUR presentation. Yes, let them consult together in unity. Who has caused this to be heard from a long time ago? Who has reported it from that very time? Is it not I, Jehovah, besides whom there is no other God; a righteous God and a Savior, there being none excepting me?

22 “Turn to me and be saved, all YOU at the ends of the earth; for I am God, and there is no one else. 23 By my own self I have sworn—out of my own mouth in righteousness the word has gone forth, so that it will not return—that to me every knee will bend down, every tongue will swear, 24 saying, ‘Surely in Jehovah there are full righteousness and strength. All those getting heated up against him will come straight to him and be ashamed. 25 In Jehovah all the seed of Israel will prove to be right and will boast about themselves.’”

Isaiah

48 Hear this, O house of Jacob, YOU who are calling yourselves by the name of Israel and who have come forth from the very waters of Judah, YOU who are swearing by the name of Jehovah and who make mention even of the God of Israel, not in truth and not in righteousness. 2 For they have called themselves as being from the holy city, and upon the God of Israel they have supported themselves, Jehovah of armies being his name.

3 “The first things I have told even from that time, and out of my own mouth they went forth, and I kept making them heard. Suddenly I acted, and the things proceeded to come in. 4 Due to my knowing that you are hard and that your neck is an iron sinew and your forehead is copper, 5 I also kept telling you from that time. Before it could come in, I caused you to hear it, that you might not say, ‘My own idol has done them, and my own carved image and my own molten image have commanded them.’ 6 You have heard. Behold it all. As for YOU people, will YOU not tell it? I have made you hear new things from the present time, even things kept in reserve, that you have not known. 7 At the present time they must be created, and not from that time, even things that before today you have not heard, that you may not say, ‘Look! I have already known them.’

8 “Moreover, you have not heard, neither have you known, nor from that time on has your ear been opened. For I well know that without fail you kept dealing treacherously, and a ‘transgressor from the belly’ you have been called. 9 For the sake of my name I shall check my anger, and for my praise I shall restrain myself toward you that there may be no cutting you off. 10 Look! I have refined you, but not in the form of silver. I have made choice of you in the smelting furnace of affliction. 11 For my own sake, for my own sake I shall act, for how could one let oneself be profaned? And to no one else shall I give my own glory.

12 “Listen to me, O Jacob, and you Israel my called one. I am the same One. I am the first. Moreover, I am the last. 13 Moreover, my own hand laid the foundation of the earth, and my own right hand extended out the heavens. I am calling to them, that they may keep standing together.

14 “Be collected together, all YOU people, and hear. Who among them has told these things? Jehovah himself has loved him. He will do what is his delight upon Babylon, and his own arm will be upon the Chal·de′ans. 15 I—I myself have spoken. Moreover, I have called him. I have brought him in, and there will be a making of his way successful.

16 “Come near to me, YOU people. Hear this. From the start I have spoken in no place of concealment at all. From the time of its occurring I have been there.”

And now the Sovereign Lord Jehovah himself has sent me, even his spirit. 17 This is what Jehovah has said, your Repurchaser, the Holy One of Israel: “I, Jehovah, am your God, the One teaching you to benefit yourself, the One causing you to tread in the way in which you should walk. 18 O if only you would actually pay attention to my commandments! Then your peace would become just like a river, and your righteousness like the waves of the sea. 19 And your offspring would become just like the sand, and the descendants from your inward parts like the grains of it. One’s name would not be cut off or be annihilated from before me.”

20 Go forth, YOU people, out of Babylon! Run away from the Chal·de′ans. Tell forth even with the sound of a joyful cry, cause this to be heard. Make it to go forth to the extremity of the earth. Say: “Jehovah has repurchased his servant Jacob. 21 And they did not get thirsty when he was making them walk even through devastated places. Water out of the rock he caused to flow forth for them, and he proceeded to split a rock that the water might stream forth.”

22 “There is no peace,” Jehovah has said, “for the wicked ones.”

Isaiah

49 Listen to me, O YOU islands, and pay attention, YOU national groups far away. Jehovah himself has called me even from the belly. From the inward parts of my mother he has made mention of my name. 2 And he proceeded to make my mouth like a sharp sword. In the shadow of his hand he has hidden me. And he gradually made me a polished arrow. He concealed me in his own quiver. 3 And he went on to say to me: “You are my servant, O Israel, you the one in whom I shall show my beauty.”

4 But as for me, I said: “It is for nothing that I have toiled. For unreality and vanity I have used up my own power. Truly my judgment is with Jehovah, and my wages with my God.” 5 And now Jehovah, the One forming me from the belly as a servant belonging to him, has said for me to bring back Jacob to him, in order that to him Israel itself may be gathered. And I shall be glorified in the eyes of Jehovah, and my own God will have become my strength. 6 And he proceeded to say: “It has been more than a trivial matter for you to become my servant to raise up the tribes of Jacob and to bring back even the safeguarded ones of Israel; I also have given you for a light of the nations, that my salvation may come to be to the extremity of the earth.”

7 This is what Jehovah, the Repurchaser of Israel, his Holy One, has said to him that is despised in soul, to him that is detested by the nation, to the servant of rulers: “Kings themselves will see and certainly rise up, and princes, and they will bow down, by reason of Jehovah, who is faithful, the Holy One of Israel, who chooses you.”

8 This is what Jehovah has said: “In a time of goodwill I have answered you, and in a day of salvation I have helped you; and I kept safeguarding you that I might give you as a covenant for the people, to rehabilitate the land, to bring about the repossessing of the desolated hereditary possessions, 9 to say to the prisoners, ‘Come out!’ to those who are in the darkness, ‘Reveal yourselves!’ By the ways they will pasture, and on all beaten paths their pasturing will be. 10 They will not go hungry, neither will they go thirsty, nor will parching heat or sun strike them. For the One who is having pity upon them will lead them, and by the springs of water he will conduct them. 11 And I will make all my mountains a way, and my highways themselves will be on an elevation. 12 Look! These will come even from far away, and, look! these from the north and from the west, and these from the land of Si′nim.”

13 Give a glad cry, YOU heavens, and be joyful, you earth. Let the mountains become cheerful with a glad outcry. For Jehovah has comforted his people, and he shows pity upon his own afflicted ones.

14 But Zion kept saying: “Jehovah has left me, and Jehovah himself has forgotten me.” 15 Can a wife forget her suckling so that she should not pity the son of her belly? Even these women can forget, yet I myself shall not forget you. 16 Look! Upon my palms I have engraved you. Your walls are in front of me constantly. 17 Your sons have hurried up. The very ones tearing you down and devastating you will go forth even from you. 18 Raise your eyes all around and see. They have all of them been collected together. They have come to you. “As I am living,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “with all of them you will clothe yourself just as with ornaments, and you will bind them on yourself like a bride. 19 Although there are your devastated places and your desolated places and the land of your ruins, although now you are too cramped to be dwelling, and those swallowing you down have been far away, 20 yet in your own ears the sons of your bereaved state will say, ‘The place has become too cramped for me. Do make room for me, that I may dwell.’ 21 And you will for certain say in your heart, ‘Who has become father to these for me, since I am a woman bereaved of children and sterile, gone into exile and taken prisoner? As for these, who has brought them up? Look! I myself had been left behind alone. These—where have they been?’”

22 This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Look! I shall raise up my hand even to the nations, and to the peoples I shall lift up my signal. And they will bring your sons in the bosom, and upon the shoulder they will carry your own daughters. 23 And kings must become caretakers for you, and their princesses nursing women for you. With faces to the earth they will bow down to you, and the dust of your feet they will lick up; and you will have to know that I am Jehovah, of whom those hoping in me will not be ashamed.”

24 Can those already taken be taken from a mighty man himself, or can the body of captives of the tyrant make their escape? 25 But this is what Jehovah has said: “Even the body of captives of the mighty man will be taken away, and those already taken by the tyrant himself will make their escape. And against anyone contending against you I myself shall contend, and your own sons I myself shall save. 26 And I will make those maltreating you eat their own flesh; and as with the sweet wine they will become drunk with their own blood. And all flesh will have to know that I, Jehovah, am your Savior and your Repurchaser, the Powerful One of Jacob.”

Isaiah

57 The righteous one himself has perished, but there is no one taking it to heart. And men of loving-kindness are being gathered to the dead, while no one discerns that it is because of the calamity that the righteous one has been gathered away. 2 He enters into peace; they take rest upon their beds, each one that is walking straightforwardly.

3 “As for YOU men, come up close here, YOU sons of a soothsaying woman, the seed of an adulterous person and of a woman that commits prostitution: 4 Over whom is it that YOU have a jolly good time? Against whom do YOU keep opening wide the mouth, keep sticking out the tongue? Are YOU not the children of transgression, the seed of falsehood, 5 those who are working up passion among big trees, under every luxuriant tree, slaughtering the children in the torrent valleys under the clefts of the crags?

6 “With the smooth stones of the torrent valley was your portion. They—they were your lot. Moreover, to them you poured out a drink offering, you offered up a gift. For these things shall I comfort myself? 7 Upon a mountain high and lifted up you set your bed. There also you went up to offer sacrifice. 8 And behind the door and the doorpost you set your memorial. For apart from me you uncovered yourself and proceeded to go up; you made your bed spacious. And for yourself you went concluding a covenant with them. You loved a bed with them. The male organ you beheld. 9 And you proceeded to descend toward Mel′ech with oil, and kept making your ointments abundant. And you continued sending your envoys far off, so that you lowered matters to She′ol. 10 In the multitude of your ways you have toiled. You have not said, ‘It is hopeless!’ You have found a revival of your own power. That is why you have not grown sick.

11 “Whom did you become frightened at and begin to fear, so that you took up lying? But I was not the one that you remembered. You took nothing to your heart. Was I not keeping silent and hiding matters? So you were in no fear even of me. 12 I myself shall tell forth your righteousness and your works, that they will not benefit you. 13 When you cry for aid your collection of things will not deliver you, but a wind will carry even all of them away. An exhalation will take them away, but the one taking refuge in me will inherit the land and will take possession of my holy mountain. 14 And one will certainly say, ‘Bank up, YOU people, bank up! Clear the way. Remove any obstacle from the way of my people.’”

15 For this is what the High and Lofty One, who is residing forever and whose name is holy, has said: “In the height and in the holy place is where I reside, also with the one crushed and lowly in spirit, to revive the spirit of the lowly ones and to revive the heart of the ones being crushed. 16 For it will not be to time indefinite that I shall contend, nor perpetually that I shall be indignant; for because of me the spirit itself would grow feeble, even the breathing creatures that I myself have made.

17 “At the erroneousness of his unjust gain I grew indignant, and I proceeded to strike him, concealing my face, while I was indignant. But he kept walking as a renegade in the way of his heart. 18 I have seen his very ways; and I began to heal him and conduct him and make compensation with comfort to him and to his mourning ones.”

19 “I am creating the fruit of the lips. Continuous peace there will be to the one that is far away and to the one that is near,” Jehovah has said, “and I will heal him.”

20 “But the wicked are like the sea that is being tossed, when it is unable to calm down, the waters of which keep tossing up seaweed and mire. 21 There is no peace,” my God has said, “for the wicked ones.”

Isaiah

58 “Call out full-throated; do not hold back. Raise your voice just like a horn, and tell my people their revolt, and the house of Jacob their sins. 2 Yet day after day it was I whom they kept seeking, and it was in the knowledge of my ways that they would express delight, like a nation that carried on righteousness itself and that had not left the very justice of their God, in that they kept asking me for righteous judgments, drawing near to God in whom they had delight,

3 “‘For what reason did we fast and you did not see, and did we afflict our soul and you would take no note?’

“Indeed YOU people were finding delight in the very day of YOUR fasting, when there were all YOUR toilers that YOU kept driving to work. 4 Indeed for quarreling and struggle YOU would fast, and for striking with the fist of wickedness. Did YOU not keep fasting as in the day for making YOUR voice to be heard in the height? 5 Should the fast that I choose become like this, as a day for earthling man to afflict his soul? For bowing down his head just like a rush, and that he should spread out mere sackcloth and ashes as his couch? Is it this that you call a fast and a day acceptable to Jehovah?

6 “Is not this the fast that I choose? To loosen the fetters of wickedness, to release the bands of the yoke bar, and to send away the crushed ones free, and that YOU people should tear in two every yoke bar? 7 Is it not the dividing of your bread out to the hungry one, and that you should bring the afflicted, homeless people into your house? That, in case you should see someone naked, you must cover him, and that you should not hide yourself from your own flesh?

8 “In that case your light would break forth just like the dawn; and speedily would recuperation spring up for you. And before you your righteousness would certainly walk; the very glory of Jehovah would be your rear guard. 9 In that case you would call, and Jehovah himself would answer; you would cry for help, and he would say, ‘Here I am!’

“If you will remove from your midst the yoke bar, the poking out of the finger and the speaking of what is hurtful; 10 and you will grant to the hungry one your own soulful desire, and you will satisfy the soul that is being afflicted, your light also will certainly flash up even in the darkness, and your gloom will be like midday. 11 And Jehovah will be bound to lead you constantly and to satisfy your soul even in a scorched land, and he will invigorate your very bones; and you must become like a well-watered garden, and like the source of water, the waters of which do not lie. 12 And at your instance men will certainly build up the places devastated a long time; you will raise up even the foundations of continuous generations. And you will actually be called the repairer of the gap, the restorer of roadways by which to dwell.

13 “If in view of the sabbath you will turn back your foot as regards doing your own delights on my holy day, and will actually call the sabbath an exquisite delight, a holy day of Jehovah, one being glorified, and will actually glorify it rather than doing your own ways, rather than finding what delights you and speaking a word; 14 you will in that case find your exquisite delight in Jehovah, and I will make you ride upon the high places of the earth; and I will cause you to eat from the hereditary possession of Jacob your forefather, for the mouth of Jehovah itself has spoken it.”

Isaiah

66 This is what Jehovah has said: “The heavens are my throne, and the earth is my footstool. Where, then, is the house that YOU people can build for me, and where, then, is the place as a resting-place for me?”

2 “Now all these things my own hand has made, so that all these came to be,” is the utterance of Jehovah. “To this one, then, I shall look, to the one afflicted and contrite in spirit and trembling at my word.

3 “The one slaughtering the bull is as one striking down a man. The one sacrificing the sheep is as one breaking the neck of a dog. The one offering up a gift—the blood of a pig! The one presenting a memorial of frankincense is as one saying a blessing with uncanny words. They are also the ones that have chosen their own ways, and in their disgusting things their very soul has taken a delight. 4 I myself, in turn, shall choose ways of ill-treating them; and the things frightful to them I shall bring upon them; for the reason that I called, but there was no one answering; I spoke, but there were none that listened; and they kept on doing what was bad in my eyes, and the thing in which I took no delight they chose.”

5 Hear the word of Jehovah, YOU men who are trembling at his word: “YOUR brothers that are hating YOU, that are excluding YOU by reason of my name, said, ‘May Jehovah be glorified!’ He must also appear with rejoicing on YOUR part, and they are the ones that will be put to shame.”

6 There is a sound of uproar out of the city, a sound out of the temple! It is the sound of Jehovah repaying what is deserved to his enemies.

7 Before she began to come into labor pains she gave birth. Before birth pangs could come to her, she even gave deliverance to a male child. 8 Who has heard of a thing like this? Who has seen things like these? Will a land be brought forth with labor pains in one day? Or will a nation be born at one time? For Zion has come into labor pains as well as given birth to her sons.

9 “As for me, shall I cause the breaking through and not cause the giving birth?” says Jehovah. “Or am I causing a giving birth and do I actually cause a shutting up?” your God has said.

10 Rejoice with Jerusalem and be joyful with her, all YOU lovers of her. Exult greatly with her, all YOU keeping yourselves in mourning over her; 11 for the reason that YOU will suck and certainly get satisfaction from the breast of full consolation by her; for the reason that YOU will sip and experience exquisite delight from the teat of her glory. 12 For this is what Jehovah has said: “Here I am extending to her peace just like a river and the glory of nations just like a flooding torrent, and YOU will certainly suck. Upon the flank YOU will be carried, and upon the knees YOU will be fondled. 13 Like a man whom his own mother keeps comforting, so I myself shall keep comforting YOU people; and in the case of Jerusalem YOU will be comforted. 14 And YOU will certainly see, and YOUR heart will be bound to exult, and YOUR very bones will sprout just like tender grass. And the hand of Jehovah will certainly be made known to his servants, but he will actually denounce his enemies.”

15 “For here Jehovah himself comes as a very fire, and his chariots are like a storm wind, in order to pay back his anger with sheer rage and his rebuke with flames of fire. 16 For as fire Jehovah himself will for a fact take up the controversy, yes, with his sword, against all flesh; and the slain of Jehovah will certainly become many. 17 Those sanctifying themselves and cleansing themselves for the gardens behind one in the center, eating the flesh of the pig and the loathsome thing, even the jumping rodent, they will all together reach their end,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 18 “And as regards their works and their thoughts, I am coming in order to collect all the nations and tongues together; and they will have to come and see my glory.”

19 “And I will set among them a sign, and I will send some of those who are escaped to the nations, to Tar′shish, Pul, and Lud, those drawing the bow, Tu′bal and Ja′van, the faraway islands, who have not heard a report about me or seen my glory; and they will for certain tell about my glory among the nations. 20 And they will actually bring all YOUR brothers out of all the nations as a gift to Jehovah, on horses and in chariots and in covered wagons and on mules and on swift she-camels, up to my holy mountain, Jerusalem,” Jehovah has said, “just as when the sons of Israel bring the gift in a clean vessel into the house of Jehovah.”

21 “And from them also I shall take some for the priests, for the Levites,” Jehovah has said.

22 “For just as the new heavens and the new earth that I am making are standing before me,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “so the offspring of YOU people and the name of YOU people will keep standing.”

23 “And it will certainly occur that from new moon to new moon and from sabbath to sabbath all flesh will come in to bow down before me,” Jehovah has said. 24 “And they will actually go forth and look upon the carcasses of the men that were transgressing against me; for the very worms upon them will not die and their fire itself will not be extinguished, and they must become something repulsive to all flesh.”

Jeremiah

5 Go roving about in the streets of Jerusalem and see, now, and know, and seek for yourselves in her public squares whether YOU can find a man, whether there exists anyone doing justice, anyone seeking faithfulness, and I shall forgive her. 2 Even if they should say: “As Jehovah is alive!” they would thereby be swearing to sheer falsehood.

3 O Jehovah, are not those eyes of yours toward faithfulness? You have struck them, but they did not become ill. You exterminated them. They refused to take discipline. They made their faces harder than a crag. They refused to turn back. 4 Even I myself had said: “Surely they are of low class. They acted foolishly, for they have ignored the way of Jehovah, the judgment of their God. 5 I will go my way to the great ones and speak with them; for they themselves must have taken note of the way of Jehovah, the judgment of their God. Surely they themselves must have all together broken the yoke; they must have torn apart the bands.”

6 That is why a lion out of the forest has struck them, a wolf itself of the desert plains keeps despoiling them, a leopard is keeping awake at their cities. Everyone going forth from them gets torn to pieces. For their transgressions have become many; their acts of unfaithfulness have become numerous.

7 How can I forgive you for this very thing? Your own sons have left me, and they keep swearing by what is no God. And I kept satisfying them, but they continued committing adultery, and to the house of a prostitute woman they go in troops. 8 Horses seized with sexual heat, having strong testicles, they have become. They neigh each one to the wife of his companion.

9 “Should I not take an accounting because of these very things?” is the utterance of Jehovah. “Or upon a nation that is like this should not my soul avenge itself?”

10 “Come up against her vine rows and cause ruin, but do not YOU men make an actual extermination. Take away her luxuriating shoots, for they do not belong to Jehovah. 11 For the house of Israel and the house of Judah have positively dealt treacherously with me,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 12 “They have denied Jehovah, and they keep saying, ‘He is not. And upon us no calamity will come, and no sword or famine shall we see.’ 13 And the prophets themselves become a wind, and the word is not in them. That is how it will be done to them.”

14 Therefore this is what Jehovah, the God of armies, has said: “For the reason that YOU men are saying this thing, here I am making my words in your mouth a fire, and this people will be pieces of wood, and it will certainly devour them.”

15 “Here I am bringing in upon YOU men a nation from far away, O house of Israel,” is the utterance of Jehovah. “It is an enduring nation. It is a nation of long ago, a nation whose language you do not know, and you cannot hear understandingly what they speak. 16 Their quiver is like an open burial place; all of them are mighty men. 17 They will also certainly eat up your harvest and your bread. The men will eat up your sons and your daughters. They will eat up your flocks and your herds. They will eat up your vine and your fig tree. They will shatter with the sword your fortified cities in which you are trusting.”

18 “And even in those days,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “I shall not carry out an extermination of YOU men. 19 And it must occur that YOU will say, ‘Due to what fact has Jehovah our God done to us all these things?’ And you must say to them, ‘Just as YOU have left me and have gone serving a foreign god in YOUR land, so YOU will serve strangers in a land that is not YOURS.’”

20 TELL this in the house of Jacob, and publish it in Judah, saying: 21 “Hear, now, this, O unwise people that is without heart: They have eyes, but they cannot see; they have ears, but they cannot hear. 22 ‘Do YOU not fear even me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘or are YOU in no severe pains even because of me, who have set the sand as the boundary for the sea, an indefinitely lasting regulation that it cannot pass over? Although its waves toss themselves, still they cannot prevail; and although they do become boisterous, still they cannot pass over it. 23 But this very people has come to have a stubborn and rebellious heart; they have turned aside and keep walking in their course. 24 But they have not said in their heart: “Let us, now, fear Jehovah our God, the One who is giving the downpour and the autumn rain and the spring rain in its season, the One who guards even the prescribed weeks of the harvest for us.” 25 YOUR own errors have turned these things away, and YOUR own sins have held back what is good from YOU people.

26 “‘For among my people there have been found wicked men. They keep peering, as when birdcatchers crouch down. They have set a ruinous trap. It is men that they catch. 27 As a cage is full of flying creatures, so their houses are full of deception. That is why they have become great and they gain riches. 28 They have grown fat; they have become shiny. They have also overflowed with bad things. No legal case have they pleaded, even the legal case of the fatherless boy, that they may gain success; and the judgment of the poor ones they have not taken up.’”

29 “Should I not hold an accounting because of these very things,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “or on a nation that is like this should not my soul avenge itself? 30 An astonishing situation, even a horrible thing, has been brought to be in the land: 31 The prophets themselves actually prophesy in falsehood; and as for the priests, they go subduing according to their powers. And my own people have loved it that way; and what will YOU men do in the finale of it?”

Jeremiah

11 The word that occurred to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying: 2 “Hear the words of this covenant, YOU men!

“And you must speak them to the men of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, 3 and you must say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said: “Cursed is the man that does not listen to the words of this covenant, 4 which I commanded YOUR forefathers in the day of my bringing them out of the land of Egypt, out of the furnace of iron, saying, ‘Obey my voice, and YOU must do things according to all that I command YOU; and YOU will certainly become my people and I myself shall become YOUR God, 5 for the purpose of carrying out the oath that I swore to YOUR forefathers, to give them the land flowing with milk and honey, as in this day.’”’”

And I proceeded to answer and say: “Amen, O Jehovah.”

6 And Jehovah went on to say to me: “Proclaim all these words in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem, saying, ‘Hear, YOU people, the words of this covenant, and YOU must do them. 7 For I solemnly admonished YOUR forefathers in the day of my bringing them up out of the land of Egypt and down to this day, rising up early and admonishing, saying: “Obey my voice.” 8 But they did not listen or incline their ear, but they kept walking each one in the stubbornness of their bad heart; and so I brought upon them all the words of this covenant that I commanded them to do, but that they did not do.’”

9 Furthermore, Jehovah said to me: “Conspiracy has been found among the men of Judah and among the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 10 They have returned to the errors of their forefathers, the first ones, who refused to obey my words, but who themselves have walked after other gods in order to serve them. The house of Israel and the house of Judah have broken my covenant that I concluded with their forefathers. 11 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am bringing upon them a calamity that they will not be able to get out of; and they will certainly call to me for aid, but I shall not listen to them. 12 And the cities of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem will have to go and call for aid to the gods to which they are making sacrificial smoke, but which will positively bring no salvation to them in the time of their calamity. 13 For your gods have become as many as your cities, O Judah; and as many altars as the streets of Jerusalem YOU people have placed for the shameful thing, altars to make sacrificial smoke to Ba′al.’

14 “And as for you, do not pray in behalf of this people, and do not lift up in their behalf an entreating cry or a prayer, for I shall not be listening in the time of their calling out to me in regard to their calamity.

15 “What business does my beloved one have in my house, that many of them should do this thing, the evil device? And with holy flesh will they make it pass over from upon you, when your calamity comes? At that time will you exult? 16 ‘A luxuriant olive tree, pretty with fruit and in form,’ is what Jehovah has called your name. With sound of the great roaring, he has set a fire blazing against her, and they have broken its branches.

17 “And Jehovah of armies himself, the Planter of you, has spoken against you a calamity on account of the badness of the house of Israel and the house of Judah that they have committed on their own part to offend me in making sacrificial smoke to Ba′al.”

18 And Jehovah himself has informed me that I may know. At that time you caused me to see their dealings. 19 And I was like a male lamb, an intimate one, that is brought to slaughter, and I did not know that it was against me that they thought out schemes: “Let us bring to ruin the tree with its food, and let us cut him off from the land of the living ones, that his very name may no more be remembered.” 20 But Jehovah of armies is judging with righteousness; he is examining the kidneys and the heart. O may I see your vengeance on them, for it is to you that I have revealed my case at law.

21 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said against the men of An′a·thoth who are seeking for your soul, saying: “You must not prophesy in the name of Jehovah, that you may not die at our hand”; 22 therefore this is what Jehovah of armies has said: “Here I am turning my attention upon them. The young men themselves will die by the sword. Their sons and their daughters themselves will die by the famine. 23 And not even a remnant will there come to be for them, because I shall bring calamity upon the men of An′a·thoth, the year of their being given attention.”

Jeremiah

12 You are righteous, O Jehovah, when I make my complaint to you, indeed when I speak even about matters of judgment with you. Why is it that the way of wicked ones is what has succeeded, that all those who are committing treachery are the unworried ones? 2 You have planted them; they have also taken root. They keep going ahead; they have also produced fruit. You are near in their mouth, but far away from their kidneys. 3 And you yourself, O Jehovah, know me well; you see me, and you have examined my heart in union with yourself. Single them out like sheep for the slaughtering, and set them apart for the day of killing. 4 How long should the land keep withering away, and the very vegetation of all the field dry up? Because of the badness of those dwelling in it the beasts and the flying creatures have been swept away. For they have said: “He does not see our future.”

5 Because with footmen you have run, and they would tire you out, how, then, can you run a race with horses? And in the land of peace are you confident? So how will you act among the proud thickets along the Jordan? 6 For even your own brothers and the household of your own father, even they themselves have dealt treacherously with you. Even they themselves have called out loudly behind you. Do not put any faith in them, just because they speak to you good things.

7 “I have left my house; I have deserted my inheritance; I have given the beloved one of my soul into the palm of her enemies. 8 My inheritance has become to me like a lion in the forest. She has let loose her voice even against me. That is why I have hated her. 9 My inheritance is as a many-colored bird of prey to me; the birds of prey are round about upon it. Come, gather together, all YOU wild beasts of the field; bring them to eat. 10 Many shepherds themselves have brought my vineyard to ruin; they have stamped down my share. They have turned my desirable share into a wilderness of a desolate waste. 11 One has made it a desolate waste; it has withered away; it is desolated to me. The whole land has been made desolate, because there is no man that has taken it to heart. 12 On all the beaten paths through the wilderness the despoilers have come. For the sword belonging to Jehovah is devouring from one end of the land even to the other end of the land. There is no peace for any flesh. 13 They have sown wheat, but thorns are what they have reaped. They have worked themselves sick; they will be of no benefit. And they will certainly be ashamed of the products of YOU people because of the burning anger of Jehovah.”

14 This is what Jehovah has said against all my bad neighbors, who are touching the hereditary possession that I caused my people, even Israel, to possess: “Here I am uprooting them from off their ground; and the house of Judah I shall uproot from the midst of them. 15 And it must occur that after my uprooting them I shall again certainly have mercy upon them and will bring them back, each one to his hereditary possession and each one to his land.”

16 “And it must occur that if they will without fail learn the ways of my people in swearing by my name, ‘As Jehovah is alive!’ just as they taught my people to swear by Ba′al, they will also be built up in the midst of my people. 17 But if they will not obey, I will also uproot that nation, uprooting and destroying it,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

Jeremiah

13 This is what Jehovah has said to me: “Go, and you must get for yourself a linen belt and put it upon your hips, but you must not bring it into any water.” 2 So I got the belt in accord with the word of Jehovah and put it upon my hips. 3 And the word of Jehovah proceeded to occur to me a second time, saying: 4 “Take the belt that you got, that is upon your hips, and rise up, go to the Eu·phra′tes, and hide it there in a cleft of the crag.” 5 So I went and hid it by the Eu·phra′tes, just as Jehovah had commanded me.

6 But it came about at the end of many days that Jehovah proceeded to say to me: “Rise up, go to the Eu·phra′tes and take from there the belt that I commanded you to hide there.” 7 Accordingly I went to the Eu·phra′tes and dug and took the belt from the place in which I had hid it, and, look! the belt had been ruined; it was not fit for anything.

8 Then the word of Jehovah occurred to me, saying: 9 “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘In the same way I shall bring to ruin the pride of Judah and the abundant pride of Jerusalem. 10 This bad people who are refusing to obey my words, who are walking in the stubbornness of their heart and who keep walking after other gods in order to serve them and to bow down to them, will also become just like this belt that is fit for nothing.’ 11 ‘For just as a belt clings to the hips of a man, so I caused the whole house of Israel and the whole house of Judah to cling even to me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘in order to become to me a people and a name and a praise and something beautiful; but they did not obey.’

12 “And you must say to them this word, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said: “Every large jar is something that gets filled with wine.”’ And they will certainly say to you, ‘Do we not positively know that every large jar is something that gets filled with wine?’ 13 And you must say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Here I am filling all the inhabitants of this land and the kings that are sitting for David upon his throne and the priests and the prophets and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem with drunkenness. 14 And I will dash them one against another, both the fathers and the sons, at the same time,” is the utterance of Jehovah. “I shall show no compassion, nor feel any sorrow, and I shall not have the mercy to keep from bringing them to ruin.”’

15 “Hear, YOU people, and give ear. Do not be haughty, for Jehovah himself has spoken. 16 Give to Jehovah YOUR God glory, before he causes darkness and before YOUR feet strike up against each other on the mountains at dusk. And YOU will certainly hope for the light, and he will actually make it deep shadow; he will turn it into thick gloom. 17 And if YOU will not hear it, in places of concealment my soul will weep because of pride and will positively shed tears; and my eye will run down with tears, because the drove of Jehovah will have been carried captive.

18 “Say to the king and to the lady, ‘Seat yourselves in a lower place, for down from YOUR heads YOUR crown of beauty will certainly come.’ 19 The cities of the south themselves have been shut up, so that there is no one opening them. Judah in its entirety has been taken into exile. It has been taken into exile completely.

20 “Raise your eyes and see those who are coming from the north. Where is the drove that one gave to you, your beautiful flock? 21 What will you say when one turns his attention upon you, when you yourself have taught them as confidential friends right alongside you at the start? Will not birth pangs themselves seize hold of you, like those of a wife giving birth? 22 And when you will say in your heart, ‘Why is it that these things have befallen me?’ because of the abundance of your error your skirts have been taken off as a cover; your heels have been treated violently.

23 “Can a Cush′ite change his skin? or a leopard its spots? YOU yourselves would also be able to do good, who are persons taught to do bad. 24 So I shall scatter them like stubble that is passing along in the wind from the wilderness. 25 This is your lot, your measured portion from me,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “because you have forgotten me and you keep putting your trust in falsehood. 26 And I myself also will lift up your skirts over your face, and your dishonor will certainly be seen, 27 your acts of adultery and your neighings, your loose conduct in prostitution. Upon the hills, in the field, I have seen your disgusting things. Woe to you, O Jerusalem! You cannot be clean—after how much longer?”

Jeremiah

16 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “You must not take for yourself a wife, and you must not come to have sons and daughters in this place. 3 For this is what Jehovah has said concerning the sons and concerning the daughters that are born in this place, and concerning their mothers who are giving them birth and concerning their fathers who are causing their birth in this land, 4 ‘With deaths from maladies they will die. They will not be bewailed, neither will they be buried. As manure upon the surface of the ground they will become; and by the sword and by famine they will come to an end, and their dead bodies will actually serve as food for the flying creatures of the heavens and for the beasts of the earth.’

5 “For this is what Jehovah has said, ‘Do not enter into the house of a mourners’ feast, and do not go to bewail and do not sympathize with them.’

“‘For I have taken away my peace from this people,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘even loving-kindness and mercies. 6 And they will certainly die, the great ones and the small ones, in this land. They will not be buried, neither will people beat themselves for them, nor will anyone make cuts upon himself or make himself bald for them. 7 And they will not deal out to them any bread on account of mourning to comfort someone over the dead; neither will they give them the cup of consolation to drink on account of one’s father and on account of one’s mother. 8 And you must enter no house of banqueting at all to sit down with them to eat and to drink.’

9 “For this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said, ‘Here I am causing to cease out of this place before the eyes of YOU people and in YOUR days the voice of exultation and the voice of rejoicing, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride.’

10 “And it must occur that, when you tell to this people all these words and they actually say to you, ‘On what account has Jehovah spoken against us all this great calamity, and what is our error and what is our sin with which we have sinned against Jehovah our God?’ 11 you must also say to them, ‘“On account of the fact that YOUR fathers left me,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and they kept going after other gods and serving them and bowing down to them. But me they left, and my law they did not keep. 12 And YOU yourselves have acted worse in YOUR doing than YOUR fathers, and here YOU are walking each one after the stubbornness of his bad heart in not obeying me. 13 And I will hurl YOU out from off this land into the land that YOU yourselves have not known, neither YOUR fathers, and there YOU will have to serve other gods day and night, because I shall not give YOU any favor.”’

14 “‘Therefore, look! days are coming,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘when it will no more be said: “As Jehovah is alive who brought the sons of Israel up out of the land of Egypt!” 15 but: “As Jehovah is alive who brought the sons of Israel up out of the land of the north and out of all the lands to which he had dispersed them!” and I shall certainly bring them back to their soil, which I gave to their forefathers.’

16 “‘Here I am sending for many fishers,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘and they will certainly fish for them; and afterward I shall send for many hunters, and they will certainly hunt them from every mountain and from every hill and out of the clefts of the crags. 17 For my eyes are upon all their ways. They have not been concealed from before me, neither has their error been hid from in front of my eyes. 18 And, first of all, I will repay the full amount of their error and of their sin, on account of their profaning my land. With the corpses of their disgusting things and their detestable things they had filled my inheritance.’”

19 O Jehovah my strength and my stronghold, and my place for flight in the day of distress, to you the nations themselves will come from the ends of the earth, and they will say: “Indeed our forefathers came to possess sheer falsehood, vanity and things in which there was nothing beneficial.” 20 Can earthling man make for himself gods when they are no gods?

21 “Therefore here I am causing them to know; at this one time I shall cause them to know my hand and my mightiness, and they will have to know that my name is Jehovah.”

Jeremiah

23 “Woe to the shepherds who are destroying and scattering the sheep of my pasturage!” is the utterance of Jehovah.

2 Therefore this is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said against the shepherds who are shepherding my people: “YOU yourselves have scattered my sheep; and YOU kept dispersing them, and YOU have not turned YOUR attention to them.”

“Here I am turning my attention upon YOU for the badness of YOUR dealings,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

3 “And I myself shall collect together the remnant of my sheep out of all the lands to which I had dispersed them, and I will bring them back to their pasture ground, and they will certainly be fruitful and become many. 4 And I will raise up over them shepherds who will actually shepherd them; and they will be afraid no more, neither will they be struck with any terror, and none will be missing,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

5 “Look! There are days coming,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and I will raise up to David a righteous sprout. And a king will certainly reign and act with discretion and execute justice and righteousness in the land. 6 In his days Judah will be saved, and Israel itself will reside in security. And this is his name with which he will be called, Jehovah Is Our Righteousness.”

7 “Therefore, look! there are days coming,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and they will no more say, ‘Jehovah is alive who brought the sons of Israel up out of the land of Egypt,’ 8 but, ‘Jehovah is alive who brought up and who brought in the offspring of the house of Israel out of the land of the north and out of all the lands to which I have dispersed them,’ and they will certainly dwell on their own ground.”

9 As regards the prophets, my heart has been broken within me. All my bones have begun shaking. I have become like a man that is drunk, and like an able-bodied man whom wine has overcome, because of Jehovah and because of his holy words. 10 For it is with adulterers that the land has become full. For because of the curse the land has gone to mourning, the pasture grounds of the wilderness have dried up; and their course of action proves to be bad, and their mightiness is not right.

11 “For both the prophet and the priest themselves have become polluted. Also in my own house I have found their badness,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 12 “Therefore their way will become for them like slippery places in the gloom, into which they will be pushed and certainly fall.”

“For I shall bring upon them a calamity, the year of their being given attention,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 13 “And in the prophets of Sa·mar′i·a I have seen impropriety. They have acted as prophets incited by Ba′al, and they keep making my people, even Israel, wander about. 14 And in the prophets of Jerusalem I have seen horrible things, committing adultery and walking in falsehood; and they have strengthened the hands of evildoers in order that they should not return, each one from his own badness. To me all of them have become like Sod′om, and the inhabitants of her like Go·mor′rah.”

15 Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies has said against the prophets: “Here I am making them eat wormwood, and I will give them poisoned water to drink. For from the prophets of Jerusalem apostasy has gone forth to all the land.”

16 This is what Jehovah of armies has said: “Do not listen to the words of the prophets who are prophesying to YOU people. They are making YOU become vain. The vision of their own heart is what they speak—not from the mouth of Jehovah. 17 They are saying again and again to those who are disrespectful of me, ‘Jehovah has spoken: “Peace is what YOU people will come to have.”’ And to every one walking in the stubbornness of his heart they have said, ‘No calamity will come upon YOU people.’ 18 For who has stood in the intimate group of Jehovah that he might see and hear his word? Who has given attention to his word that he might hear it? 19 Look! The windstorm of Jehovah, rage itself, will certainly go forth, even a whirling tempest. Upon the head of the wicked ones it will whirl itself. 20 The anger of Jehovah will not turn back until he will have carried out and until he will have made the ideas of his heart come true. In the final part of the days YOU people will give YOUR consideration to it with understanding.

21 “I did not send the prophets, yet they themselves ran. I did not speak to them, yet they themselves prophesied. 22 But if they had stood in my intimate group, then they would have made my people hear my own words, and they would have caused them to turn back from their bad way and from the badness of their dealings.”

23 “Am I a God nearby,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and not a God far away?”

24 “Or can any man be concealed in places of concealment and I myself not see him?” is the utterance of Jehovah.

“Is it not the heavens and the earth that I myself actually fill?” is the utterance of Jehovah. 25 “I have heard what the prophets who are prophesying falsehood in my own name have said, saying, ‘I have had a dream! I have had a dream!’ 26 How long will it exist in the heart of the prophets who are prophesying the falsehood and who are prophets of the trickiness of their own heart? 27 They are thinking of making my people forget my name by means of their dreams that they keep relating each one to the other, just as their fathers forgot my name by means of Ba′al. 28 The prophet with whom there is a dream, let him relate the dream; but the one with whom my own word is, let him speak forth my word truthfully.”

“What does the straw have to do with the grain?” is the utterance of Jehovah.

29 “Is not my word correspondingly like a fire,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and like a forge hammer that smashes the crag?”

30 “Therefore here I am against the prophets,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “the ones who are stealing away my words, each one from his companion.”

31 “Here I am against the prophets,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “the ones who are employing their tongue that they may utter forth, ‘An utterance!’”

32 “Here I am against the prophets of false dreams,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “who relate them and cause my people to wander about because of their falsehoods and because of their boasting.”

“But I myself did not send them or command them. So they will by no means benefit this people,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

33 “And when this people or the prophet or priest asks you, saying, ‘What is the burden of Jehovah?’ you must also say to them, ‘“YOU people are—O what a burden! And I shall certainly abandon YOU,” is the utterance of Jehovah.’ 34 As for the prophet or the priest or the people who say, ‘The burden of Jehovah!’ I will also turn my attention upon that man and upon his household. 35 This is what YOU keep saying each one to his fellow and each one to his brother, ‘What has Jehovah answered? And what has Jehovah spoken?’ 36 But the burden of Jehovah mention no more YOU people, for the burden itself becomes to each one his own word, and YOU have changed the words of the living God, Jehovah of armies, our God.

37 “This is what you will say to the prophet, ‘What answer has Jehovah given you? And what has Jehovah spoken? 38 And if “The burden of Jehovah!” is what YOU keep on saying, therefore this is what Jehovah has said: “By reason of YOUR saying, ‘This word is the very burden of Jehovah,’ when I kept sending to YOU, saying, ‘YOU must not say: “The burden of Jehovah!”’ 39 therefore here I am! And I will give YOU people to neglect, with finality, and I will desert YOU and the city that I gave to YOU and to YOUR forefathers—from before me. 40 And I will put upon YOU reproach to time indefinite and humiliation to time indefinite, which will not be forgotten.”’”

Jeremiah

24 And Jehovah showed me, and, look! two baskets of figs set before the temple of Jehovah, after Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon had carried into exile Jec·o·ni′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·kim, the king of Judah, and the princes of Judah and the craftsmen and the builders of bulwarks, from Jerusalem that he might bring them to Babylon. 2 As for the one basket, the figs were very good, like early figs; and as for the other basket, the figs were very bad, so that they could not be eaten for badness.

3 And Jehovah proceeded to say to me: “What are you seeing, Jeremiah?” So I said: “Figs, the good figs being very good, and the bad ones being very bad, so that they cannot be eaten for badness.”

4 Then the word of Jehovah occurred to me, saying: 5 “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘Like these good figs, so I shall regard the exiles of Judah, whom I will send away from this place to the land of the Chal·de′ans, in a good way. 6 And I will set my eye upon them in a good way, and I shall certainly cause them to return to this land. And I will build them up, and I shall not tear down; and I will plant them, and I shall not uproot. 7 And I will give them a heart to know me, that I am Jehovah; and they must become my people, and I myself shall become their God, for they will return to me with all their heart.

8 “‘And like the bad figs that cannot be eaten for badness, this in fact is what Jehovah has said: “So I shall give Zed·e·ki′ah the king of Judah and his princes and the remnant of Jerusalem who are remaining over in this land and those who are dwelling in the land of Egypt— 9 I will also give them over for quaking, for calamity, in all the kingdoms of the earth, for reproach and for a proverbial saying, for a taunt and for a malediction, in all the places to which I shall disperse them. 10 And I will send against them the sword, the famine and the pestilence, until they come to their finish off the ground that I gave to them and to their forefathers.”’”

Jeremiah

25 The word that occurred to Jeremiah concerning all the people of Judah in the fourth year of Je·hoi′a·kim the son of Jo·si′ah, the king of Judah, that is, the first year of Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon; 2 which Jeremiah the prophet spoke concerning all the people of Judah and concerning all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, saying:

3 “From the thirteenth year of Jo·si′ah the son of A′mon, the king of Judah, and down to this day, these twenty-three years the word of Jehovah has occurred to me, and I kept speaking to YOU people, rising up early and speaking, but YOU did not listen. 4 And Jehovah sent to YOU all his servants the prophets, rising up early and sending them, but YOU did not listen, neither did YOU incline YOUR ear to listen, 5 they saying, ‘Turn back, please, every one from his bad way and from the badness of YOUR dealings, and continue dwelling upon the ground that Jehovah gave to YOU and to YOUR forefathers from long ago and to a long time to come. 6 And do not walk after other gods in order to serve them and to bow down to them, that YOU may not offend me with the work of YOUR hands, and that I may not cause calamity to YOU.’

7 “‘But YOU did not listen to me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘to the intent that YOU might offend me with the work of YOUR hands, for calamity to yourselves.’

8 “Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies has said, ‘“For the reason that YOU did not obey my words, 9 here I am sending and I will take all the families of the north,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “even sending to Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon, my servant, and I will bring them against this land and against its inhabitants and against all these nations round about; and I will devote them to destruction and make them an object of astonishment and something to whistle at and places devastated to time indefinite. 10 And I will destroy out of them the sound of exultation and the sound of rejoicing, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride, the sound of the hand mill and the light of the lamp. 11 And all this land must become a devastated place, an object of astonishment, and these nations will have to serve the king of Babylon seventy years.”’

12 “‘And it must occur that when seventy years have been fulfilled I shall call to account against the king of Babylon and against that nation,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘their error, even against the land of the Chal·de′ans, and I will make it desolate wastes to time indefinite. 13 And I will bring in upon that land all my words that I have spoken against it, even all that is written in this book that Jeremiah has prophesied against all the nations. 14 For even they themselves, many nations and great kings, have exploited them as servants; and I will repay them according to their activity and according to the work of their hands.’”

15 For this is what Jehovah the God of Israel said to me: “Take this cup of the wine of rage out of my hand, and you must make all the nations to whom I am sending you drink it. 16 And they must drink and shake back and forth and act like crazed men because of the sword that I am sending among them.”

17 And I proceeded to take the cup out of the hand of Jehovah and to make all the nations drink to whom Jehovah had sent me: 18 namely, Jerusalem and the cities of Judah and her kings, her princes, to make them a devastated place, an object of astonishment, something to whistle at and a malediction, just as at this day; 19 Phar′aoh the king of Egypt and his servants and his princes and all his people; 20 and all the mixed company, and all the kings of the land of Uz, and all the kings of the land of the Phi·lis′tines and Ash′ke·lon and Ga′za and Ek′ron and the remnant of Ash′dod; 21 E′dom and Mo′ab and the sons of Am′mon; 22 and all the kings of Tyre and all the kings of Si′don and the kings of the island that is in the region of the sea; 23 and De′dan and Te′ma and Buz and all those with hair clipped at the temples; 24 and all the kings of the Arabs and all the kings of the mixed company who are residing in the wilderness; 25 and all the kings of Zim′ri and all the kings of E′lam and all the kings of the Medes; 26 and all the kings of the north who are near and far away, one after the other, and all the other kingdoms of the earth that are on the surface of the ground; and the king of She′shach himself will drink after them.

27 “And you must say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said: “Drink and get drunk and puke and fall so that YOU cannot get up because of the sword that I am sending among YOU.”’ 28 And it must occur that in case they refuse to take the cup out of your hand to drink, you must also say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies has said: “YOU will drink without fail. 29 For, look! it is upon the city upon which my name is called that I am starting off in bringing calamity, and should YOU yourselves in any way go free of punishment?”’

“‘YOU will not go free of punishment, for there is a sword that I am calling against all the inhabitants of the earth,’ is the utterance of Jehovah of armies.

30 “And as for you, you will prophesy to them all these words, and you must say to them, ‘From on high Jehovah himself will roar, and from his holy dwelling he will give forth his voice. Without fail he will roar upon his abiding place. A shout like that of those treading the winepress he will sing out against all the inhabitants of the earth.’

31 “‘A noise will certainly come clear to the farthest part of the earth, for there is a controversy that Jehovah has with the nations. He must personally put himself in judgment with all flesh. As regards the wicked ones, he must give them to the sword,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.

32 “This is what Jehovah of armies has said, ‘Look! A calamity is going forth from nation to nation, and a great tempest itself will be roused up from the remotest parts of the earth. 33 And those slain by Jehovah will certainly come to be in that day from one end of the earth clear to the other end of the earth. They will not be bewailed, neither will they be gathered up or be buried. As manure on the surface of the ground they will become.’

34 “Howl, YOU shepherds, and cry out! And wallow about, YOU majestic ones of the flock, because YOUR days for slaughtering and for YOUR scatterings have been fulfilled, and YOU must fall like a desirable vessel! 35 And a place to flee to has perished from the shepherds, and a means of escape from the majestic ones of the flock. 36 Listen! The outcry of the shepherds, and the howling of the majestic ones of the flock, for Jehovah is despoiling their pasturage. 37 And the peaceful abiding places have been rendered lifeless because of the burning anger of Jehovah. 38 He has left his covert just like a maned young lion, for their land has become an object of astonishment because of the maltreating sword and because of his burning anger.”

Jeremiah

26 In the beginning of the royal rule of Je·hoi′a·kim the son of Jo·si′ah, the king of Judah, this word occurred from Jehovah, saying: 2 “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Stand in the courtyard of the house of Jehovah, and you must speak concerning all the cities of Judah that are coming in to bow down at the house of Jehovah all the words that I will command you to speak to them. Do not take away a word. 3 Perhaps they will listen and return, each one from his bad way, and I shall have to feel regret for the calamity that I am thinking to execute upon them because of the badness of their dealings. 4 And you must say to them: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘If YOU will not listen to me by walking in my law that I have put before YOU, 5 by listening to the words of my servants the prophets, whom I am sending to YOU, even rising up early and sending them, whom YOU have not listened to, 6 I will, in turn, make this house like that in Shi′loh, and this city I shall make a malediction to all the nations of the earth.’”’”

7 And the priests and the prophets and all the people began to hear Jeremiah speaking these words in the house of Jehovah. 8 So it came about that when Jeremiah had completed speaking all that Jehovah had commanded him to speak to all the people, then the priests and the prophets and all the people laid hold of him, saying: “You will positively die. 9 Why is it that you have prophesied in the name of Jehovah, saying, ‘Like that in Shi′loh is how this house will become, and this very city will be devastated so as to be without an inhabitant’?” And all the people kept congregating themselves about Jeremiah in the house of Jehovah.

10 In time the princes of Judah got to hear these words, and they proceeded to come up from the house of the king to the house of Jehovah and to sit down in the entrance of the new gate of Jehovah. 11 And the priests and the prophets began to say to the princes and to all the people: “To this man the judgment of death belongs, because he has prophesied concerning this city just as YOU have heard with YOUR own ears.”

12 At that Jeremiah said to all the princes and to all the people: “It was Jehovah that sent me to prophesy concerning this house and concerning this city all the words that YOU have heard. 13 And now make YOUR ways and YOUR dealings good, and obey the voice of Jehovah YOUR God, and Jehovah will feel regret for the calamity that he has spoken against YOU. 14 And as for me, here I am in YOUR hand. Do to me according to what is good and according to what is right in YOUR eyes. 15 Only YOU should by all means know that, if YOU are putting me to death, it is innocent blood that YOU are putting upon yourselves and upon this city and upon her inhabitants, for in truth Jehovah did send me to YOU to speak in YOUR ears all these words.”

16 Then the princes and all the people said to the priests and to the prophets: “There is no judgment of death belonging to this man, for it was in the name of Jehovah our God that he spoke to us.”

17 Furthermore, certain ones of the older men of the land rose up and began saying to all the congregation of the people: 18 “Mi′cah of Mo′resh·eth himself happened to be prophesying in the days of Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah and went on to say to all the people of Judah, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies has said: “Zion herself will be plowed up as a mere field, and Jerusalem herself will become mere heaps of ruins, and the mountain of the House will be for high places of a forest.”’ 19 Did Hez·e·ki′ah the king of Judah and all those of Judah by any means put him to death? Did he not fear Jehovah and proceed to soften the face of Jehovah, so that Jehovah got to feeling regret for the calamity that he had spoken against them? So we are working up a great calamity against our souls.

20 “And there also happened to be a man prophesying in the name of Jehovah, U·ri′jah the son of She·mai′ah from Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim. And he kept prophesying against this city and against this land in accord with all the words of Jeremiah. 21 And King Je·hoi′a·kim and all his mighty men and all the princes got to hear his words, and the king began seeking to put him to death. When U·ri′jah got to hear of it he at once became afraid and ran away and came into Egypt. 22 But King Je·hoi′a·kim sent men to Egypt, El·na′than the son of Ach′bor and other men with him to Egypt. 23 And they proceeded to bring U·ri′jah out from Egypt and to bring him to King Je·hoi′a·kim, who then struck him down with the sword and cast his dead body into the graveyard of the sons of the people.”

24 Moreover, it was the hand of A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan that proved to be with Jeremiah, in order not to give him into the hand of the people to have him put to death.

Jeremiah

28 Then it came about in that year, in the beginning of the kingdom of Zed·e·ki′ah the king of Judah, in the fourth year, in the fifth month, that Han·a·ni′ah the son of Az′zur, the prophet who was from Gib′e·on, said to me in the house of Jehovah before the eyes of the priests and of all the people: 2 “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said, ‘I will break the yoke of the king of Babylon. 3 Within two full years more I am bringing back to this place all the utensils of the house of Jehovah that Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon took from this place that he might bring them to Babylon.’” 4 “‘And Jec·o·ni′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·kim, the king of Judah, and all the exiles of Judah who have come to Babylon I am bringing back to this place,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘for I shall break the yoke of the king of Babylon.’”

5 And Jeremiah the prophet proceeded to say to Han·a·ni′ah the prophet before the eyes of the priests and before the eyes of all the people who were standing in the house of Jehovah; 6 yes, Jeremiah the prophet proceeded to say: “Amen! Thus may Jehovah do! May Jehovah establish your words that you have prophesied by bringing back the utensils of the house of Jehovah and all the exiled people from Babylon to this place! 7 However, hear, please, this word that I am speaking in your ears and in the ears of all the people. 8 As regards the prophets that happened to be prior to me and prior to you from long ago, they also used to prophesy concerning many lands and concerning great kingdoms, of war and of calamity and of pestilence. 9 As regards the prophet that prophesies of peace, when the word of the prophet comes true the prophet whom Jehovah has sent in truth will become known.”

10 At that Han·a·ni′ah the prophet took the yoke bar from off the neck of Jeremiah the prophet and broke it. 11 And Han·a·ni′ah went on to say before the eyes of all the people: “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Just like this I shall break the yoke of Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon within two full years more from off the neck of all the nations.’” And Jeremiah the prophet proceeded to go his way.

12 Then the word of Jehovah occurred to Jeremiah, after Han·a·ni′ah the prophet had broken the yoke bar from off the neck of Jeremiah the prophet, saying: 13 “Go, and you must say to Han·a·ni′ah, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Yoke bars of wood you have broken, and instead of them you will have to make yoke bars of iron.” 14 For this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said: “A yoke of iron I will put upon the neck of all these nations, to serve Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon; and they must serve him. And even the wild beasts of the field I will give him.”’”

15 And Jeremiah the prophet went on to say to Han·a·ni′ah the prophet: “Listen, please, O Han·a·ni′ah! Jehovah has not sent you, but you yourself have caused this people to trust in a falsehood. 16 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said, ‘Look! I am sending you away from off the surface of the ground. This year you yourself must die, for you have spoken outright revolt against Jehovah.’”

17 So Han·a·ni′ah the prophet died in that year, in the seventh month.

Jeremiah

31 “At that time,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “I shall become God to all the families of Israel; and as for them, they will become my people.”

2 This is what Jehovah has said: “The people made up of survivors from the sword found favor in the wilderness, when Israel was walking to get his repose.” 3 From far away Jehovah himself appeared to me, saying: “And with a love to time indefinite I have loved you. That is why I have drawn you with loving-kindness. 4 Yet shall I rebuild you and you will actually be rebuilt, O virgin of Israel. You will yet deck yourself with your tambourines and actually go forth in the dance of those who are laughing. 5 You will yet plant vineyards in the mountains of Sa·mar′i·a. The planters will certainly plant and start to use them. 6 For there exists a day when the lookouts in the mountainous region of E′phra·im will actually call out, ‘Rise up, O men, and let us go up to Zion, to Jehovah our God.’”

7 For this is what Jehovah has said: “CRY out loudly to Jacob with rejoicing, and CRY shrilly at the head of nations. PUBLISH it. GIVE praise and SAY, ‘Save, O Jehovah, your people, the remnant of Israel.’ 8 Here I am bringing them from the land of the north, and I will collect them together from the remotest parts of the earth. Among them will be the blind and the lame, the pregnant woman and the one giving birth, all together. As a great congregation they will return here. 9 With weeping they will come, and with their entreaties for favor I shall bring them. I shall make them walk to torrent valleys of water, in a right way in which they will not be caused to stumble. For I have become to Israel a Father; and as for E′phra·im, he is my firstborn.”

10 Hear the word of Jehovah, O YOU nations, and tell it among the islands far away, and say: “The One scattering Israel will himself collect him together, and he will certainly keep him as a shepherd does his drove. 11 For Jehovah will actually redeem Jacob and reclaim him out of the hand of the one stronger than he is. 12 And they will certainly come and cry out joyfully on the height of Zion and become radiant over the goodness of Jehovah, over the grain and over the new wine and over the oil and over the young ones of the flock and the cattle. And their soul will simply become like a well-watered garden, and no more will they languish again.”

13 “At that time the virgin will rejoice in the dance, also the young men and the old men, all together. And I will change their mourning into exultation, and I will comfort them and make them rejoice away from their grief. 14 And I will saturate the soul of the priests with fatness, and with my goodness my own people will become satisfied,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

15 “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘In Ra′mah a voice is being heard, lamentation and bitter weeping; Rachel weeping over her sons. She has refused to be comforted over her sons, because they are no more.’”

16 This is what Jehovah has said: “‘Hold back your voice from weeping, and your eyes from tears, for there exists a reward for your activity,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘and they will certainly return from the land of the enemy.’

17 “‘And there exists a hope for your future,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘and the sons will certainly return to their own territory.’”

18 “I have positively heard E′phra·im bemoaning himself, ‘You have corrected me, that I may be corrected, like a calf that has not been trained. Cause me to turn back, and I shall readily turn back, for you are Jehovah my God. 19 For after my turning back I felt regret; and after my being led to know I made a slap upon the thigh. I became ashamed, and I also felt humiliated, for I had carried the reproach of my youth.’”

20 “Is E′phra·im a precious son to me, or a fondly treated child? For to the extent of my speaking against him I shall without fail remember him further. That is why my intestines have become boisterous for him. By all means I shall have pity upon him,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

21 “Set up road marks for yourself. Place signposts for yourself. Fix your heart upon the highway, the way that you will have to go. Come back, O virgin of Israel. Come back to these cities of yours. 22 How long will you turn this way and that, O unfaithful daughter? For Jehovah has created a new thing in the earth: A mere female will press around an able-bodied man.”

23 This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said: “They will yet say this word in the land of Judah and in his cities, when I shall gather their captives, ‘May Jehovah bless you, O righteous dwelling place, O holy mountain.’ 24 And in it Judah and all his cities will certainly dwell all together, farmers and those who have set out with the drove. 25 For I will saturate the tired soul, and every languishing soul I will fill.”

26 At this thing I awoke and began to see; and as for my sleep, it had been pleasurable to me.

27 “Look! There are days coming,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and I will sow the house of Israel and the house of Judah with the seed of man and with the seed of domestic animal.”

28 “And it must occur that just as I had kept alert toward them to uproot and to pull down and to tear down and to destroy and to do damage, so I shall keep alert toward them to build up and to plant,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 29 “In those days they will no more say, ‘The fathers were the ones that ate the unripe grape, but it was the teeth of the sons that got set on edge.’ 30 But it will be each one for his own error that one will die. Any man eating the unripe grape, his will be the teeth that will be set on edge.”

31 “Look! There are days coming,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and I will conclude with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah a new covenant; 32 not one like the covenant that I concluded with their forefathers in the day of my taking hold of their hand to bring them forth out of the land of Egypt, ‘which covenant of mine they themselves broke, although I myself had husbandly ownership of them,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

33 “For this is the covenant that I shall conclude with the house of Israel after those days,” is the utterance of Jehovah. “I will put my law within them, and in their heart I shall write it. And I will become their God, and they themselves will become my people.”

34 “And they will no more teach each one his companion and each one his brother, saying, ‘KNOW Jehovah!’ for they will all of them know me, from the least one of them even to the greatest one of them,” is the utterance of Jehovah. “For I shall forgive their error, and their sin I shall remember no more.”

35 This is what Jehovah, the Giver of the sun for light by day, the statutes of the moon and the stars for light by night, the One stirring up the sea that its waves may become boisterous, the One whose name is Jehovah of armies, has said: 36 “‘If these regulations could be removed from before me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘those who are the seed of Israel could likewise cease from proving to be a nation before me always.’”

37 This is what Jehovah has said: “‘If the heavens up above could be measured and the foundations of the earth below could be searched out, I myself also could reject the entire seed of Israel on account of all that they have done,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

38 “Look! There are days coming,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and the city will certainly be built to Jehovah from the Tower of Ha·nan′el to the Corner Gate. 39 And the line for measurement will yet actually go forth straight ahead to the hill of Ga′reb, and it will certainly go around to Go′ah. 40 And all the low plain of the carcasses and of the fatty ashes, and all the terraces as far as the torrent valley of Kid′ron, clear to the corner of the Horse Gate toward the sunrising, will be something holy to Jehovah. It will not be uprooted, neither will it be torn down anymore to time indefinite.”

Jeremiah

32 The word that occurred to Jeremiah from Jehovah in the tenth year of Zed·e·ki′ah the king of Judah, that is, the eighteenth year of Neb·u·chad·rez′zar. 2 And at that time the military forces of the king of Babylon were laying siege to Jerusalem; and as for Jeremiah the prophet, he happened to be under restraint in the Courtyard of the Guard that is in the house of the king of Judah; 3 because Zed·e·ki′ah the king of Judah had restrained him, saying:

“Why is it that you are prophesying, saying, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Here I am giving this city into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he will certainly capture it; 4 and Zed·e·ki′ah himself, the king of Judah, will not escape from the hand of the Chal·de′ans, for he will without fail be given into the hand of the king of Babylon, and his mouth will actually speak with the mouth of that one, and his own eyes will see even the eyes of that one”’; 5 ‘and to Babylon he will take Zed·e·ki′ah, and there he will continue until I turn my attention to him,’ is the utterance of Jehovah; ‘although YOU men keep warring against the Chal·de′ans, YOU will not succeed’?”

6 And Jeremiah proceeded to say: “The word of Jehovah has occurred to me, saying, 7 ‘Here is Han′a·mel the son of Shal′lum your paternal uncle coming in to you, saying: “Buy for yourself the field of mine that is in An′a·thoth, because the right of repurchase belongs to you for buying it.”’”

8 In time Han′a·mel the son of my paternal uncle came in to me, according to the word of Jehovah, into the Courtyard of the Guard, and proceeded to say to me: “Buy, please, the field of mine that is in An′a·thoth, which is in the land of Benjamin, for the right of hereditary possession is yours, and the repurchasing power is yours. Buy it for yourself.” At that I knew that it had been the word of Jehovah.

9 So I proceeded to buy from Han′a·mel the son of my paternal uncle the field that was in An′a·thoth. And I began to weigh out to him the money, seven shekels and ten silver pieces. 10 Then I wrote in a deed and affixed the seal and took witnesses as I went weighing the money in the scales. 11 After that I took the deed of purchase, the one sealed according to the commandment and the regulations, and the one left open; 12 and I then gave the deed of purchase to Bar′uch the son of Ne·ri′ah the son of Mah·sei′ah before the eyes of Han′a·mel the son of my paternal uncle and before the eyes of the witnesses, those writing in the deed of purchase, before the eyes of all the Jews who were sitting in the Courtyard of the Guard.

13 I now commanded Bar′uch before their eyes, saying: 14 “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said, ‘Taking these deeds, this deed of purchase, even the sealed one, and the other deed left open, you must also put them into an earthenware vessel, in order that they may last for many days.’ 15 For this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said, ‘Houses and fields and vineyards will yet be bought in this land.’”

16 And I began to pray to Jehovah after my having given the deed of purchase to Bar′uch the son of Ne·ri′ah, saying: 17 “Alas, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah! Here you yourself have made the heavens and the earth by your great power and by your outstretched arm. The whole matter is not too wonderful for you yourself, 18 the One exercising loving-kindness toward thousands, and repaying the error of the fathers into the bosom of their sons after them, the true God, the great One, the mighty One, Jehovah of armies being his name, 19 great in counsel and abundant in acts, you whose eyes are opened upon all the ways of the sons of men, in order to give to each one according to his ways and according to the fruitage of his dealings; 20 you who set signs and miracles in the land of Egypt down to this day and in Israel and among men, that you might make a name for your own self, just as at this day. 21 And you proceeded to bring forth your people Israel out of the land of Egypt, with signs and with miracles and with a strong hand and with a stretched-out arm and with great fearsomeness.

22 “In time you gave them this land that you swore to their forefathers to give to them, a land flowing with milk and honey. 23 And they proceeded to come in and take possession of it, but they did not obey your voice, and in your law they did not walk. All the things that you commanded them to do they did not do, so that you caused all this calamity to befall them. 24 Look! With siege ramparts men have come to the city to capture it, and the very city will certainly be given into the hand of the Chal·de′ans who are fighting against it, because of the sword and the famine and the pestilence; and what you have said has happened, and here you are seeing it. 25 Yet you yourself have said to me, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘Buy for yourself the field with money and take witnesses,’ although the city itself must be given into the hand of the Chal·de′ans.”

26 At that the word of Jehovah occurred to Jeremiah, saying: 27 “Here I am, Jehovah, the God of all flesh. For me is there any matter at all too wonderful? 28 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am giving this city into the hand of the Chal·de′ans and into the hand of Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon, and he must capture it. 29 And the Chal·de′ans who are fighting against this city must come in and set this city aflame with fire and must burn it down and the houses upon the roofs of which they have made sacrificial smoke to Ba′al and have poured out drink offerings to other gods for the purpose of offending me.’

30 “‘For the sons of Israel and the sons of Judah have proved to be mere doers of what was bad in my eyes, from their youth on up; for the sons of Israel are even offending me by the work of their hands,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. 31 ‘For this city, from the day that they built it, clear down to this day, has proved to be nothing but a cause of anger in me and a cause of rage in me, in order to remove it from before my face, 32 on account of all the badness of the sons of Israel and of the sons of Judah that they have done to offend me, they, their kings, their princes, their priests and their prophets, and the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 33 And they kept turning to me the back and not the face; though there was a teaching of them, a rising up early and teaching, but there were none of them listening to receive discipline. 34 And they went putting their disgusting things in the house upon which my own name has been called, in order to defile it. 35 Furthermore, they built the high places of Ba′al that are in the valley of the son of Hin′nom, in order to make their sons and their daughters pass through the fire to Mo′lech, a thing that I did not command them, neither did it come up into my heart to do this detestable thing, for the purpose of making Judah sin.’

36 “And now, therefore, this is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said concerning this city which YOU persons are saying will certainly be given into the hand of the king of Babylon by the sword and by the famine and by the pestilence, 37 ‘Here I am collecting them together out of all the lands to which I shall have dispersed them in my anger and in my rage and in great indignation; and I will bring them back to this place and make them dwell in security. 38 And they will certainly become my people, and I myself shall become their God. 39 And I will give them one heart and one way in order to fear me always, for good to them and to their sons after them. 40 And I will conclude with them an indefinitely lasting covenant, that I shall not turn back from behind them, for me to do them good; and the fear of me I shall put in their heart in order not to turn aside from me. 41 And I will exult over them to do them good, and I will plant them in this land in trueness with all my heart and with all my soul.’”

42 “For this is what Jehovah has said, ‘Just as I have brought in upon this people all this great calamity, so I am bringing in upon them all the goodness that I am speaking concerning them. 43 And fields will certainly be bought in this land of which YOU people will be saying: “It is a desolate waste without man and domestic animal. It has been given into the hand of the Chal·de′ans.”’

44 “‘With money people will buy fields themselves, and there will be a recording in the deed and a sealing and a taking of witnesses in the land of Benjamin and in the surroundings of Jerusalem and in the cities of Judah and in the cities of the mountainous region and in the cities of the lowland and in the cities of the south, because I shall bring back their captives,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”